<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-7724-0655-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MYRISTICA (7th edition, volume 15, page 655)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141377">Syrups</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129725">Spices</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t75x">Syrups</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193827724?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MYRISTICA</label>, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Nutmeg
                    Tree..</hi> The seeds or kernels called <hi rend="italic">nutmegs</hi> are well
                    known, as they have long been used both for culinary and medicinal purposes.
                    Distilled with water, they yield a large quantity of essential oil, resembling
                    in flavour the spice itself; after the distillation an insipid sebaceous matter
                    is found swimming on the water; and the decoction inspissated gives an extract
                    of an unctuous, very slightly bitterish taste, and with little or no
                    astringency. Rectified spirit extracts the whole virtue of nutmegs by infusion,
                    and elevates very little of it in distillation; hence the spirituous extract
                    possesses the flavour of the spice in an eminent degree.</p>
                <p>Nutmegs, when heated, yield to the press a considerable quantity of limpid yellow
                    oil, which, on cooling, concretes into a sebaceous consistence. In the shops we
                    meet with three sorts of unctuous substances, called oil of mace, though really
                    expressed from the nutmeg. The best, which is brought from the East Indies in
                    stone jars, is of a thick consistence, of the colour of mace, and has an
                    agreeable fragrant smell; the second sort, which is of a paler colour, and much
                    inferior in quality, comes from Holland in solid masses, generally flat, and of
                    a square figure; the third, which is the worst of all, and usually called common
                    oil of mace, is an artificial composition of sevum, palm oil, and the like,
                    flavoured with a little genuine oil of nutmeg.</p>
                <p>When the fruit is ripe, the natives ascend the trees, and gather it by pulling
                    the branches to them with long hooks. Some are employed in opening them
                    immediately, and in taking off the green shell or first rind, which is laid
                    together in a heap in the woods, where in time it putrefies. As soon as the
                    putrefaction has taken place, there spring up a kind of mushrooms called <hi
                    rend="italic">boleti</hi><hi rend="italic">mosehatyni,</hi> of a blackish
                    colour, and much valued by the natives, who consider them as delicate eating.
                    When the nuts are stripped of their first rind they are carried home, and the
                    mace is carefully taken off with a small knife. The mace, which is of a
                    beautiful red, but afterwards assumes a darkish or reddish colour, is laid to
                    dry in the sun for the space of a day, and is then removed to a place less
                    exposed to his rays, where it remains for eight days, that it may soften a
                    little. It is afterwards moistened with sea water, to prevent it from drying too
                    much, or from losing its oil; but the people are careful not to employ too much
                    water, lest it should become putrid, and be devoured by the worms. It is last of
                    all put into small bags, and squeezed very close.</p>
                <p>The nuts, which are still covered with their ligneous shell, are for three days
                    exposed to the sun, and afterwards dried before a fire till they emit a sound
                    when they are shaken; they then beat them with small sticks, in order to remove
                    their shell, which flies off in pieces. These nuts are distributed into three
                    parcels, the first of which contains the largest and most beautiful, which are
                    destined for Europe; the second contains such as are reserved for the use of the
                    inhabitants; and the third contains the smallest, which are irregular or unripe.
                    These last are burned; and part of the rest is employed for procuring oil by
                    pressure. A pound of them commonly gives three ounces of oil, which has the
                    consistence of tallow, and the taste of nutmeg. Both the nut and mace, when
                    distilled, afford an essential, transparent, and volatile oil, of an excellent
                    flavour.</p>
                <p>The nutmegs which have thus been selected would soon corrupt if they were not
                    watered, or rather pickled, with lime-water made from calcined shell-fish, which
                    is diluted with salt water till it attain the consistence of fluid pap. Into
                    this mixture are plunged the nutmegs, contained in small baskets, two or three
                    times, till they are completely covered over with the liquor. They are
                    afterwards laid in a heap, where they heat, and lose their superfluous moisture
                    by evaporation. When they have sweated sufficiently, they are then properly
                    prepared, and fit for a sea voyage.</p>
                <p>In the island of Banda, the fruit of the nutmeg-tree is preserved entire in the
                    following manner. When ‘it is almost ripe, but previous to its opening, it is
                    boiled in water and pierced with a needle. It is next laid in water to soak for
                    ten days, till it has lost its sour and sharp taste, and then it is boiled
                    gently in a syrup of sugar, to which, if they wish it to be hard, a little lime
                    is added. This operation is repeated for eight days, and each time the syrup is
                    renewed. The fruit, when thus preserved, is put for the last time into a pretty
                    thick syrup, and is kept in earthen pots closely shut.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
