<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-0691-0263-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CONNECTICUT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 263</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g226">Unitarianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="18" ref="fastgeo:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194750691" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CONNECTICUT</label>, one of the United States of North
                    America, is bounded on the north by Massachusetts, on the east by Rhode Island,
                    on the south by Long Island Sound, and on the west by New York. The length of
                    this state from east to west is eighty-five miles; the mean width sixty miles,
                    and the area 5050 square miles. Connecticut is in general hilly, sometimes
                    mountainous, but in no part rises to a great elevation above the level of the
                    sea. The greatest heights are a continuation of the Green Mountains, on the
                    western side of Connecticut river, and even these are of moderate size. The
                    country is healthy, notwithstanding its being exposed to the extremes of heat
                    and cold, and also to sudden changes of temperature. In winter keen north-west
                    winds prevail; but the serenity of the sky during the same season compensates in
                    some degree the severity of the weather. Upon the coast, in particular, the wind
                    is exceedingly variable, but the inland country is less subject to this
                    vicissitude. The soil for the most part is fertile, though at intervals
                    intermixed with patches comparatively thin and barren; the whole, however, is
                    well watered, and in general in a state of good cultivation. The chief
                    productions are Indian corn, rye, wheat, oats, barley, buck-wheat, flax in
                    considerable quantities, some hemp, potatoes, pumpkins, turnips, peas, beans,
                    &amp;c. There are numerous orchards, and cider is made for exportation. Great
                    quantities of cattle, horses, and sheep, are reared upon its fine meadows and
                    pastures, and the country in general is considered as better adapted for grazing
                    than tillage. A great quantity of very excellent cheese is made annually, and
                    beef and pork of a superior quality are also abundant. The farms are for the
                    most part small, consisting of from fifty to three hundred and four hundred
                    acres. This state is intersected by numerous roads, which are generally kept in
                    good condition. The exports consist of beef, pork, cattle, horses, mules,
                    butter, cheese, maize, rye, flax-seed, fish, candles, and soap. Almost all the
                    produce of the western part of the state is conveyed to New York.</p>
                <p>The manufacturing industry of Connecticut is considerable, and greater than that
                    of any other state in the union, with the exception of Rhode Island. The
                    manufactures consist of cotton and woollen goods, tinware, iron, gin, glass,
                    paper, snuff’, leather, powder, clocks, shoes, buttons, fire-arms, carriages,
                    &amp;c. Several mines have been opened in this state, but none of them wrought
                    to any considerable extent, except those of iron ore, abundance of which, of an
                    excellent quality, is found in Kent, Salisbury, and in other places. Copper
                    mines have also been wrought, but the speculation proved unprofitable, and was
                    abandoned. Marble, porcelain clay, cobalt, black lead, and an excellent
                    freestone, are found in various parts of the state.</p>
                <p>Amongst the literary institutions of Connecticut may be mentioned Yale College of
                    New Haven, which is one of the oldest and most respectable colleges in the
                    United <pb break="no" facs="nls:194750704" xml:id="kp-eb0707-0704-0264"/>States.
                    It is furnished with an excellent library, and complete philosophical and
                    chemical apparatus; and the mineralogical museum is probably the finest in the
                    United States. The American asylum for the education of the deaf and dumb was
                    established at Hartford in 1817. It was the first institution of the kind which
                    appeared in America. It received a grant from the congress of the United States
                    of 23,000 acres of land; and the legislatures of several individual states have
                    made appropriations for the support of the pupils. A foreign mission school was
                    established at Cornwall in 1817, for the purpose of educating heathen youth from
                    various parts of the world. A law school was established at Litchfield in 1784,
                    and has long had a great reputation. The Bacon Academy of Colehester, the
                    Episcopal Aeademy of Cheshire, and the Washington College at Hertford, are all
                    flourishing institutions. There are also academies in almost all the principal
                    towns of the state, and common schools are universally established. There is a
                    large school fund, which in 1824 amounted to 1,756,233 dollars. The yearly
                    income, together with 12,000 dollars from the public taxes, goes to the support
                    of common schoolmasters in every town of the state.</p>
                <p>The religious bodies are numerous, consisting of Con-gregationalists (who are the
                    most numerous), Baptists, Episcopalians, Methodists, Universalists, Unitarians,
                    Catholics, Quakers, Shakers, and others. The inhabitants are distinguished for
                    their habits of industry and sobriety.</p>
                <p>There are five incorporated cities in Connecticut, namely, Hartford. New Haven,
                    Middletown, New London, and Norwich. Hartford and New Haven are the seats of the
                    state government, and the sessions are held at each alternately. The principal
                    rivers are the Connecticut, Housatonic, Thames, Farmington, and Naugatuch.</p>
                <p>The present constitution was framed in 1818. The legislature, styled the general
                    assembly, is composed of a senate of twelve members, and a house of
                    representatives, eighty towns sending each two representatives. The other towns
                    founded since the charter of Charles II. in 1662 send one each. The governor,
                    lieutenant-governor, senators, and representatives, are all chosen annually in
                    April. The general assembly has one stated session in each year, on the first
                    Wednesday of May, and such others as they deem necessary. Judges of the supreme
                    and superior courts hold their offices during good behaviour, but are
                    disqualified when they reach seventy years of age. The inhabitants are perfectly
                    free from constraint in matters of religious belief.</p>
                <p>A few Dutch traders∙appear to have been the first who established themselves in
                    Connecticut, and the remains of the settlement are still visible at Hartford. In
                    1634, Lords Say and Seal, who had obtained a grant of Connecticut, sent over a
                    small number of men, who concluded a treaty with the natives for the lands on
                    the river. In 1644 the adventurers purchased the right of the colony for L.1600.
                    Connecticut and New Haven continued two distinct governments for many years; but
                    the royal charter, which was obtained from Charles II., amongst other
                    provisions, constituted the two colonies one body corporate and politic, which
                    they have ever since remained. This charter was framed in the most liberal
                    spirit, and the civil rights granted are nearly the same as those which the
                    state enjoys at present. The revolution, which so sensibly affected the
                    government of most of the other colonies, produced no great alteration in that
                    of Connecticut. This state presents perhaps the most perfect specimen of a
                    republic to be found in the world.</p>
                <p>The population in 1800 amounted to 251,002, in 1810 to 261,942, in 1820 to
                    275,248, and in 1830 to 297,711. Accordingto a recent account, Connecticut
                    contains41,416 houses, 2,607,869 acres of land, 1597 mills, 1827 stores and
                    shops, 402 distilleries, 1211 manufactories, 46 fisheries, 33,358 horses, asses,
                    &amp;c., 219,733 neat cattle, 331,054 sheep, and 5048 carriages.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Connecticut,</hi> an important river of the United States.
                    It rises on the northern border of New Hampshire, which state it separates from
                    Vermont, passes through Massachusetts and Connecticut, and discharges itself
                    into Long Island Sound, between Saybrook and Lime. Its course for the most part
                    is south-west until it reaches Middletown in Connecticut, after which it has a
                    south-south-east course to its mouth. Its whole length is 410 miles. For
                    thirty-six miles from its mouth it is navigable for vessels drawing ten feet of
                    water; for those drawing eight, fourteen miles farther; and, by means of locks
                    and canals, it has been rendered navigable to Bath, in New Flampshire, a
                    distance of 300 miles from its confluence with the sea. The falls which have
                    been rendered passable by artificial means are those at Enfield in Connecticut,
                    the Willemantic Falls, those at South Hadley, Montague, Walpole, Plain-field,
                    and Lebanon. Of these, Bellow Falls, at Walpole, are the most remarkable. The
                    Connecticut flows through a fine country. The land which borders upon it is for
                    the most part of excellent quality, and there are upon its banks many beautiful
                    and flourishing towns. Amongst others are Haverhill, Hanover, Charlestown, and
                    Walpole, in New Hampshire; Newbury, Windsor, and Brattleborough, in Vermont;
                    Greenfield, Hadley, Northampton, and Springfield, in Massachusetts; and
                    Hartford, Middletown, &amp;c. in Connecticut.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
