<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-4149-0529-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CUJAS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 529</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:830788">Berries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj8h">Berries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zx91">Anger</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m471">Nihilism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194754149" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CUJAS</label>, in Latin <hi rend="smallcaps">Cujacius,
                    James,</hi> was born at Toulouse in 1520. His father was a fuller, and his real
                    name Cujaus, but, by way of softening it, he afterwards abridged it into Cujas.
                    But if, when young and poor, he curtailed his name, at a more advanced age, when
                    fortune had become more propitious, he extended it, and then subscribed himself
                    Jacques de Cujas. His happy disposition enabled him to surmount all the
                    difficulties which the obscure condition in which he had been born seemed to
                    throw in the way of his advancement. By his own exertions, and without the
                    assistance of any master, he learned Greek and Latin; and he was instructed in
                    the elements of law by Arnoul Ferrier, then professor at Toulouse, a man who,
                    when called to higher employments, distinguished himself by great talents united
                    to great virtues. Cujas always cherished the most affectionate regard for his
                    master. The knowledge which he had imbibed from Ferrier became, as it were, the
                    germ of that which he himself acquired by the efforts of his own genius, and by
                    his extreme ardour in study. Cujas was employed as tutor to the children of the
                    president Dufaur, who afterwards became a distinguished personage; and for their
                    instruction, as well as that of some other young persons whose education he
                    superintended, he began, in the year 1547, to give lessons on the Institutions
                    of Justinian. Etienne Pasquier, who was present at the first of these, says,
                    that he then discovered a clear and vigorous mind, which gave great promise of
                    future excellence; and Antoine Loiscl, who attended the lessons with the
                    greatest assiduity, declares that Cujas prevented him from abandoning the
                    science of law, with which the other doctors had disgusted him by their
                    barbarism. His merit, however, would not seem to have been fully appreciated in
                    his native place. A chair of law having, it is said, become vacant at Toulouse
                    in 1554, Cujas not only failed in obtaining it, but he had the mortification of
                    seeing the preference given to one Forcadel, a person of very moderate
                    abilities, and in all respects confessedly his inferior. The city of Toulouse,
                    however, conceiving its honour to be interested in contesting a fact founded on
                    a well-accredited tradition, and of which the odium could only attach to the
                    individual protectors of ignorance and intrigue, its chief magistrates, on the
                    occasion of placing the bust of Cuias in their gallery in the year 1674, affixed
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:194754162" xml:id="kp-eb0707-4162-0530"/> to the
                    inscription a solemn and indignant denial of the imputation cast upon their
                    predecessors. And it has also been remarked, that Cujas makes no mention, in any
                    of his numerous writings, of the injustice which he is alleged to have
                    experienced at the hands of his townsmen; but little weight seems to be due to
                    this observation, because it is not improbable that Cujas might have avoided any
                    allusion to a disagreeable subject. Besides, John Robert of Orleans, with whom
                    Cujas had some keen altercations, meanly reproaches him with having been thrice
                    rejected at Toulouse in his applications for a professorship of law; and Cujas
                    is evidently embarrassed in his reply to the insulting allegation. He says,
                    “that Robert lies at least in regard to two of these alleged rejections, and
                    probably even in regard to the third; that, moreover, after he had been called
                    to Cahors, and then to Bourges, the inhabitants of Toulouse had used the most
                    pressing entreaties to induce him to return among them.” The town of Toulouse,
                    however, had the misfortune of not being able to attach to its school a man
                    whose merit, which had for seven years been fully recognised, could not fail to
                    add to the lustre which it had already acquired. But that of Cahors was more
                    fortunate. A chair having become vacant there by the retirement of Govea, in
                    1554, Cujas was appointed to fill it; and he was followed by almost all his
                    pupils. But he only remained about a year at Cahors; patrons worthy of him
                    having stepped forward to withdraw him from the obscure theatre where he had
                    been content to exert his great talents. Margaret of Valois, duchess of Berri,
                    inheriting the love which her father, Francis I., bore to men of letters, had
                    already given proofs of her discernment in choosing as her chancellor Michel de
                    ľHôpital, who afterwards, in the highest dignity of the state, exhibited a
                    character so elevated and a patriotism so pure. Wishing to render the school of
                    Bourges, the chief place of her apanage, the most celebrated of all those which
                    had as yet existed, Margaret intrusted L’Hôpital with the choice of professors;
                    and he was not slow in discerning the merit of Cujas, whom he called to Bourges,
                    where he had already placed Baudouin and Duaren, the latter of whom had taught
                    there since the year 1538. Duaren at first received Cujas favourably; but,
                    either from weakness or senility, he soon became jealous of the young professor,
                    and, unable to endure the popularity which the latter almost immediately
                    acquired, he had recourse to every expedient in order to rid himself of so
                    formidable a rival. With this view he stirred up the students against the new
                    professor, and such was the disorder produced in consequence at Bourges, that
                    Cujas was obliged to yield to the storm, and to retire to Valence. But this
                    persecution became useful to him, by inspiring him with such a degree of
                    emulation, that he applied himself with greater vigour to the study of law,
                    which the levity natural to his age would otherwise perhaps have induced him to
                    abandon. Recalled to Bourges by order of the Duchess of Berri, he remained there
                    till 1567, when he returned to Valence, on the invitation of Bertrand de
                    Simiane, lieutenant-general of the king in Dauphine, and reflected greatlustre
                    to the university of that city, to which young men flocked from all quarters in
                    order to study under him. In 1570 Cujas was elected professor in the university
                    of Avignon; but his first wife, who belonged to that city, having recently
                    before this died, Cujas resolved to remain at Valence. But Margaret of Valois,
                    who had now become Duchess of Savoy, persuaded him to repair to Turin, where,
                    however, he only remained a few months. His scholars and friends at Bourges
                    induced him to return thither towards the end of 1575. But the troubles which
                    threatened that city forced him to seek a retreat elsewhere, and his first
                    intention was to proceed to Angers, where the people were most desirous of
                    having him; but the orders of the king called him to Paris, where, on the
                    requisition of the procureur-general, and the report of Μ. Anjorrant, the
                    parliament passed an arrêt, by which Cujas, who is declared to be a person of
                    great and singular learning and erudition, is permitted “de faire lecture et
                    profession en droit civil en l’université de Paris;" a species of instruction
                    which was then interdicted in the university, and in fact only established there
                    under Louis XIV. Terrasson has supposed that he himself was the first to publish
                    this arrêt; but it is found, together with some other particulars respecting
                    Cujas, in the remarks of Menage on the life of Pierre Ayrault. Cujas remained at
                    Paris only about a year, and returned to Bourges, which he never afterwards
                    quitted, in 1577. In 1584 Gregory XIII. who was himself well skilled in the
                    civil and canon law, wished to draw Cujas to Bologna, thinking that something
                    would be wanting to the glory of that city if it did not reckon among its
                    professors a man of so distinguished merit; and Cujas was on the point of
                    yielding to the pressing solicitations of the pontiff; but his attachment for
                    his pupils prevailed over every other consideration, and retained him in France.
                    At the commencement of his works, in the edition of Fabrot, are some very
                    curious verses, composed at Blois, for the purpose of dissuading him from
                    proceeding to Bologna. Who, then, it may be asked, was this man, whom all the
                    countries of Europe sought after, and who, in an age which produced Du Moulin
                    and so many other celebrated jurisconsults, placed himself foremost in the first
                    rank, and eclipsed all his rivals by the superiority of his knowledge and the
                    lustre of his renown? In order to appreciate his works, we must remember the
                    period at which he appeared. The civilization of Europe had barely commenced;
                    and jurisprudence was regarded as the science most proper to accelerate its
                    progress, by diffusing correct notions of reason and justice. But from want of
                    erudition, and from ignorance of criticism, the first interpreters of the Roman
                    law had only a very imperfect knowledge of the system which they professed to
                    expound; and it is mainly to Cujas that the world is indebted for the
                    advancement which the study of this great body of written wisdom has made since
                    his time. The old interpreters had only' been able to deduce some general
                    maxims, and some rules of private law, which they applied to the manners, still
                    rude, of the times in which they lived. The minds of men were not as yet
                    prepared for any thing more perfect. They wanted that degree of maturity
                    necessary to receive the light in all its purity. The same thing is observable
                    in the history of ancient Rome. There is as great a distance between the law of
                    the twelve tables and that system which, in the first two or three centuries of
                    our era, the Papinians, the Ulpians, and other geniuses of the first order,
                    created, as between the manners of a semibarbarous people and those of a nation
                    arrived at the highest degree of civilization. It may be said of legislation,
                    indeed, with still greater truth than even of literature, that it is the
                    reflected image of society. In proportion as the civilization of Europe
                    improved, jurisprudence advanced towards perfection; and Cujas came, at a
                    seasonable moment, to lay open its true sources. He had read the works of the
                    old interpreters; but he had derived nothing but disgust from the perusal.
                    Repelled by the barbarism of their language as much as by the vicious method
                    which they had followed, Cujas resolved to apply himself solely to the text of
                    the Roman laws, to illustrate whatever was obscure in them, to restore passages
                    which had been altered by time or the ignorance of copyists, and to fix the true
                    signification of the words which were there employed. In prosecution of this
                    design, the knowledge which he possessed of the ancient languages, and the vast
                    erudition which he had acquired by means <pb break="no" facs="nls:194754175"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-4175-0531"/>of them, were of admirable service to him. Not
                    only did he consult books; he made a still greater use of manuscripts, of which
                    he had collected more than five hundred in his own library. The corrections
                    which he made, not only in books of law, but in a great number of ancient Greek
                    and Latin authors, are immense. He in part collected these, under the’title of
                    <hi rend="italic">Observations and Corrections;</hi> and this work is still a
                    fertile mine, which philologers continually explore with advantage. Nor did he
                    confine his researches to the books compiled by order of Justinian, but extended
                    them to every thing which had the smallest relation to the subject, or which
                    entered into the jurisprudence of modern times. He recovered and gave to the
                    world a part of the Theodosian code, with explanations; and he procured the
                    manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Basilica</hi> (a species of abridgment in
                    Greek, which the successors of Justinian had made of his laws), from which
                    manuscript they were afterwards published by Fabrot. Besides, he composed a
                    learned commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Consuetudines</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Feudorum,</hi> and on some books of the Decretals. In fact, Cujas was not only
                    a learned man; he was what is far better, a man of profound sagacity. It is by
                    no means uncommon to find writers who, in all sciences, have been able to master
                    some isolated parts; but to embrace the whole in one comprehensive view, to
                    ascend to the fundamental principles from which all the others are derived, and
                    to condense in brief maxims the kernel of all the consequences which flow from
                    them, is a power which has only been given to a small number of privileged men
                    of genius, distinguished from the common herd, who are wholly incapable of such
                    a concentration. This was preeminently the talent of Cujas. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">Paratitla,</hi> or summaries which he made of the Digest, and
                    particularly of the Code of Justinian, he condensed into short axioms the
                    elementary principles of law, and gave definitions remarkable for their
                    admirable clearness and precision. Hottoman, a distinguished jurisconsult, the
                    rival and the enemy of Cujas, earnestly recommends to his son to take along with
                    him in his journeys these <hi rend="italic">Paratitla</hi> or summaries, and to
                    study them with indefatigable assiduity. Instead of the semibarbarous
                    jurisprudence of the early interpreters, Cujas substituted that of the most
                    polished ages of Rome; and those who succeeded him have been able to do little
                    more than to confirm his views. All the jurisconsults of Europe indeed are
                    agreed in considering him as the first and greatest of the interpreters of law,
                    one whom none can equal, much less surpass, in the art of teaching and
                    expounding it “Cujas,” said D’Aguesseau, “has spoken the language of law better
                    than any modern, and perhaps as well as any ancient.” His lessons, which he
                    never dictated, were continuous discourses, for which he made no other
                    preparation than that of profound meditation on the subjects to be discussed.
                    His scholars, particularly the Germans, wrote down at the moment his discourses,
                    as well as the rapidity of utterance would permit; and afterwards, by comparing
                    their notes together, they suffered but little of what fell from him to escape
                    them. He was impatient of interruption, and upon the least noise he would
                    instantly quit the chair and retire. The use of theses, which has been continued
                    in the modern schools, had already been introduced; but these exercises, so
                    common and so useless at present, entered not into the ordinary plan of the
                    lessons of Cujas. The honour of supporting a thesis under him was the reward of
                    the highest merit, and it was but rarely conferred. Loisel has preserved that
                    which Pierre Pithou composed on quitting the school of Cujas; and it is
                    certainly a very masterly production of its kind. Cujas was strongly attached to
                    his pupils; and Scaliger affirms that he lost more than four thousand livres by
                    lending money to such of them as were in want. During the thirty years he
                    taught, their number was immense, for pupils flocked from all parts of Europe to
                    his school; and many of them, like Scaliger and the brothers Pithou, afterwards
                    became his most intimate friends. None of them who showed distinguished talents
                    escaped his observation; and he advanced the fortunes of several by making known
                    their merits. From his school there issued magistrates of the first rank, and
                    able ministers and negociators, whose talents proved highly serviceable to their
                    country; whilst others carried to the bar and the bench the lights which they
                    had there acquired, and contributed essentially to the great progress which
                    jurisprudence made in the century which followed. Such were the fruits of a life
                    entirely devoted to the public good, and of which no species of ambition ever
                    disturbed the tranquil tenor. Indeed it appears that Cujas never even solicited
                    the honours which lie enjoyed. In 1573, during his residence at Valence, Charles
                    XI. appointed him honorary counsellor to the parliament of Grenoble; Henry III.,
                    by letters patent, dated at Lyons in 1574, also conferred upon him a small
                    pension, with the titular reversion of the first vacant office; and, by other
                    letters dated the year following, Cujas was permitted to continue his
                    instructions at Valence, and to draw the emoluments of his office of counsellor
                    without discharging its duties. In the year 1582, however, Cujas resigned his
                    office in favour of Charles de Dorne, advocate to the parliament of Grenoble;
                    but this court, annoyed at his quitting Valence, repeatedly refused to accept
                    his resignation, and only received it in consequence of a positive order to that
                    effect. Merit so eminent as his could scarcely fail to excite envy; and he had
                    detractors, whom, however, he crushed by the weight of his reputation. His
                    sentiments and opinions were irreproachable, and, in an age of civil discord, he
                    never varied nor changed. Cujas was sincerely attached to the religion of his
                    fathers; but he steadily refused to take any part in the theological
                    controversies which so greatly agitated the times in which he lived. <hi
                    rend="italic">Nihil hoc ad</hi><hi rend="italic">edictum praetoris,</hi> “this
                    has nothing to do with the edict of the praetor,” was his usual answer to those
                    who spoke to him on the subject. He was far, indeed, from participating in the
                    fury engendered by the league; and his fidelity to Henry IV. remained unshaken,
                    a circumstance which frequently exposed him to danger at Bourges, where the
                    leaguers predominated. But vexation on account of the evils which preyed upon
                    France is supposed to have hastened his death, which happened at Bourges the 4th
                    of October 1590. His library, which was of very considerable extent, containing
                    manuscripts as well as printed books of all kinds, a great number of which were
                    enriched with remarks by his own hand, he ordered by his will to be sold in
                    detail, from an apprehension lest, if it fell into the hands a single
                    individual, advantage might be taken of his notes by persons who did not
                    understand them, to compose works injurious to his reputation. His wishes were
                    complied with to an extent he had never contemplated; for the booksellers of
                    Lyons, who purchased his manuscripts, employed them to cover rudiments for the
                    schools. In his lifetime he published an edition of his works, printed at
                    Nivelle in 1577. It is beautiful and exact, but now very scarce, and contains
                    only a part of his works. The same observation applies to the edition of
                    Colombet, published in 1634. Fabrot, however, collected the whole in the edition
                    which he published at Paris, 1658, in 10 vols. folio, and which was reprinted at
                    Naples, 1722, 1727, in 11 vols. folio, and thereafter at Naples and at Venice,
                    1758, in 10 vols. folio, with an index forming an eleventh volume. In the
                    editions of Naples and Venice there are some additions, not to be found in that
                    of Fabrot, particularly a general table, which will be <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194754188" xml:id="kp-eb0707-4188-0532"/>found very useful, and
                    interpretations of all the Greek words used by Cujas. (Terrasson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Jurispru-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> ι</hi><hi rend="italic">deuce Romaine,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Mélanges d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire, de Littérature, et</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Jurisprudence</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Bernardi, <hi rend="italic">Eloge de
                    Cujas;</hi> Hugo, <hi rend="italic">Civ-listisches</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Magazin;</hi> Berriat St Prit, <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de Cujas,</hi>
                    appended to his <hi rend="italic">Histoire du Droit Romain; Biographie
                    Universelle,</hi> art. Cujas.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
