<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-0028-0212-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CONFUCIUS, or Cong-fu-tse, or Koung-tsee</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 212</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn10">Loo</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62820">Lungs</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4nk3680j">Eras</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:852051">Change</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1176240">Wisdom</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1152520">Tongs</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194750028" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CONFUCIUS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cong-fu-tse</hi>, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Koung-tsee</hi></label>, the most eminent and venerated of all
                    the philosophers of China, and a descendant of the imperial family of the
                    dynasty of Chang, was born in the kingdom of Loo, now called the province of
                    Chang-tong, about 550 years before the commencement of the Christian era, which
                    makes him contemporary with Pythagoras and Solon, and prior to the days of
                    Socrates. At an early period of life, he gave striking proofs of uncommon
                    talents, and these were cultivated and improved with great assiduity under the
                    tuition of the ablest masters. Scarcely had he attained to the years of
                    maturity, when he showed himself acquainted with all the literature of that
                    period, and, in particular, possessed of a comprehensive knowledge of the
                    canonical and classical books, ascribed to the legislators Yao and Chun, which
                    the Chinese emphatically denominate the Five Volumes, as containing the essence
                    of all their sciences and morality. Nature had bestowed upon him a most amiable
                    temper, and his moral deportment was altogether unexceptionable. He acquired a
                    distinguished reputation for humility, sincerity, the government of his
                    appetites, a disinterested heart, and a sovereign contempt of wealth; qualities
                    which pointed him out as a proper person to fill offices of importance and trust
                    in the government of his country, which lie did with honour to himself and
                    advantage to the empire. These public stations afforded him excellent
                    opportunities of estimating with accuracy the true state of morals among his
                    countrymen, which at this time were dissolute and vicious in the extreme. He
                    conceived the idea of attempting a general reformation both in morals and in
                    politics, and his efforts for some time were attended with such effect, that he
                    inspired his countrymen with a veneration for his character, and gratitude for
                    his exertions. He was raised to a station of high importance in the province of
                    Loo. His counsels and advice were productive of the mostbeneficial consequences
                    in establishing good order, the due exercise of justice, concord, and decorum
                    throughout the whole kingdom. As the province thus became an object of
                    admiration, so, likewise, neighbouring princes beheld with envy its growing
                    happiness and prosperity, to destroy which they contrived a fatal and effectual
                    expedient. The king of Tsi being apprehensive that if the king of Loo continued
                    to be directed by the wisdom and sound policy of Confucius, he would soon become
                    by far too powerful, sent him and his nobility a present of the most beautiful
                    young women, trained up from infancy in all the arts of seduction, and who were
                    but too successful in plunging the whole court into voluptuousness and
                    dissipation. This in a short time demolished the whole of that beautiful fabric
                    which had been erected by Confucius; and finding it a hopeless attempt to stem
                    the universal torrent of corruption and depravity, he resolved to exert his
                    talents in some distant kingdom, in the philanthropic cause of moral
                    reformation, with better hopes of success. But he had the mortification to
                    discover that vice was everywhere triumphant, while virtue was compelled to hide
                    her head. This induced him to adopt the more humble, although not the less
                    interesting employment of a teacher of youth, in which he made great and rapid
                    progress. About six hundred of his scholars were sent into different parts of
                    the empire to carry on his favourite work of moral reformation. Among his
                    disciples, seventy-two were remarkably distinguished above the rest for their
                    mental acquisitions, and ten others were deemed superior even to these, as
                    having a thorough comprehension of their master’s whole system. These were
                    divided by him into four classes; the first being destined to the study of the
                    moral virtues; the second to the arts of logic and of public speaking; the third
                    class studied jurisprudence and the duties of the civil magistrate; and public
                    speaking, or the delivery of popular discourses on moral topics, occupied the
                    fourth. Indefatigable, however, as his labours were, the task was too mighty to
                    be acomplished by human exertions. During his last illness, he declared to his
                    pupils, that the grief of his mind occasioned by the profligacy of human nature
                    had become insupportable; and with a melancholy voice he exclaimed, “Immense
                    mountain, how art thou fallen! The grand machine is demolished, and the wise and
                    the virtuous are no more. The kings will not follow my maxims: I am no longer
                    useful on earth; it is, therefore, time that I should quit it.” On uttering
                    these words he was seized with a lethargy, which brought him to the grave. He
                    finished his honourable career in the seventy-second year of his age, in his
                    native kingdom, to which he had returned in company with his disciples. It is
                    frequently the fate of illustrious characters never to be properly valued till
                    after they are cut off by death. This was the case with Confucius. The whole
                    empire of China bewailed the loss of him, and erected innumerable edifices to
                    perpetuate his memory, adorned with such honourable inscriptions as the
                    following: “To the great master “To the chief doctor “To the saint ;” “To the
                    wise king of literature ;” “To the instructor of emperors and kings.” All his
                    descendants, even to the present day, enjoy the honourable title and office of
                    mandarins, and are exempted from the payment of taxes to the emperor, as well as
                    to the princes of the blood. The man who applies for the title of doctor must
                    previously have made a present to a mandarin descended in a direct line from
                    Confucius. The writings of this great man are esteemed by the Chinese as of the
                    highest authority, next to the Five Volumes, to which he modestly acknowledges
                    himself to have been much indebted. His works arc, 1. The <hi rend="italic">Taynio,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> The Grand Science, or School of Adults,”
                    chiefly intended for the information of princes and magistrates, recommending
                    the duties of self-government and uniform obedience to the laws of right reason;
                    2. The <hi rend="italic">Chong-yong</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> or
                    “Immutable Medium,” in which he shows its importance in the government of the
                    passions by a variety of examples, and points out the method of arriving at
                    perfection in virtue; 3. <hi rend="italic">Lung-yu,</hi> or moral and
                    sententious discourses, which exhibit a lively picture of the opinions, conduct,
                    and maxims of Confucius and his followers; 4. <hi rend="italic">Meng-tsi,</hi>
                    the book of Mencius, which derived its name from one of that great philosopher’s
                    disciples. These are all deservedly esteemed by the Chinese, being held next in
                    importance to the Five Volumes. 5. The <hi rend="italic">Hyau-king,</hi> or
                    dissertation on the duty and respect which children owe their parents; and, 6.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Syan-hyo,</hi> or science for children, being a judicious
                    collection of moral sentences from various writers.</p><p>If a fair and impartial estimate of the religion of Confucius be made, it cannot
                    be viewed in any other light than as uncorrupted deism, although he has
                    sometimes been accused of befriending and secretly propagating atheistical
                    sentiments; but such an accusation is as cruel as it is unjust, since the purity
                    of his moral precepts, and the acknowledged rectitude of his whole deportment,
                    are utterly incompatible with such a supposition. He considered the <hi rend="italic">Tien</hi> or Deity as the purest and most perfect essence,
                    principle, and source of all things in the boundless universe; as a being who is
                    absolutely independent, omnipotent, the governor and guardian of every thing;
                    possessed of infinite wisdom, which nothing can deceive; holy, without
                    partiality, of unlimited goodness and inflexible justice. We are at a loss to
                    form any adequate opinion of his sentiments relative to the soul of man and the
                    doctrine of futurity, <pb break="no" facs="nls:194750041" xml:id="kp-eb0707-0041-0213"/>having no well authenticated data on which to
                    proceed. But his morality is in many respects superior to that of Greece and
                    Rome, and yields to none upon earth, except to that of divine revelation. The
                    religion of Confucius, notwithstanding the estimation in which he is held, is
                    adopted as a model by none of his countrymen, the literati excepted. Their
                    prevailing system is a medley of pagan idolatry, and the fabulous superstition
                    of the Indians, introduced into China by Fo in the first century of the
                    Christian era.</p></div></body></text></TEI>