<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-0041-0213-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CONFUSION</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 213</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:892462">Dialectic</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1202511">Buildering</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950737">Ham</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104504">Samaritans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25g11">Dialects</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w849">Dialectics</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7n383">Understanding</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8ds25">Ham</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194750041" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CONFUSION</label>, in a general sense, is opposed to <hi rend="italic">order,</hi> in the disturbance of which confusion consists; as
                    when things prior in nature do not precede, or posterior do not follow.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Confusion</hi><hi rend="italic">of Tongues,</hi> in
                    the history of mankind, is a memorable event, which, according to the Hebrew
                    chronology, happened in the one hundred and first year, and according to the
                    Samaritan, in the four hundred and first year after the flood, at the overthrow
                    of Babel; and which was providentially brought about in order to facilitate the
                    dispersion of mankind and the population of the earth. Until this period there
                    had been but one common language, which formed a bond of union that prevented
                    the separation of mankind into distinct nations; and some have supposed that the
                    tower of Babel was erected as a kind of fortress, by which the people intended
                    to defend themselves against that separation which Noah had projected.</p><p>There has been considerable difference of opinion as to the nature of this
                    confusion, and the manner in which it was effected. Some learned men,
                    prepossessed with the notion that all the different idioms now in the world at
                    first arose from one original language to which they may be reduced, and that
                    the variety which exists among them is no more than must naturally have happened
                    in a long course of time by the mere separation of the builders of Babel, have
                    maintained that there were no new languages formed at the confusion, but that
                    this event was accomplished by creating a misunderstanding and variance among
                    the builders, without any immediate influence on their languages. But this
                    opinion, which was advanced by Le Clerc, seems to be directly contrary to the
                    obvious meaning of the word <hi rend="smallcaps">γct,</hi><hi rend="italic">shctpha,</hi> “lip,” used by the sacred historian. Others have imagined that
                    the separation was brought about by a temporary confusion of their speech, or
                    rather of their apprehensions, which caused them, whilst they continued together
                    and spoke the same language, to understand the words differently. Scaliger is of
                    the same opinion. Others, again, account for this event by the privation of all
                    language, and by supposing that mankind were under a necessity of associating
                    together, and of imposing new names on things by common consent. Another opinion
                    ascribes the confusion to such an indistinct remembrance of the original
                    language which they spoke before, as made them speak it differently; so that, by
                    the various inflexions, terminations, and pronunciations of different dialects,
                    they could no more understand one another than they who understand Latin can
                    understand those who speak French, Italian, or Spanish, though all these
                    languages arise out of it. This opinion is adopted by Casaubon, and by Bishop
                    Patrick in his Commentary, and is certainly much more probable than either of
                    the former. Mr Shuckford, however, maintains that the confusion arose from small
                    beginnings, by the invention of new words in any of the three families of Shem,
                    Ham, and Japhet, which might contribute to separate them from one another; and
                    that in each family new differences of speech might gradually arise, so that
                    they went on to divide and subdivide among themselves. Others, again, as Mr Mede
                    and Dr Wotton, not satisfied with either of the foregoing methods of accounting
                    for the diversity of languages among mankind, have recourse to an extraordinary
                    interposition of divine power, by which new languages were framed and
                    communicated to different families, through a supernatural infusion or
                    inspiration; which languages have been the roots and originals from which the
                    several dialects that are, or have been, or will be spoken as long as this earth
                    shall last, have arisen or will arise, and to which they may with ease be
                    reduced. As to the number of languages thus introduced, many opinions have been
                    adopted. If there were no more than there were nations or heads of nations, then
                    the number would be seven for Japhet, four for Ham, and five for Shem; but if
                    there were as many as there were families, which is the more probable opinion,
                    their number cannot be certainly assigned. However, the Hebrews fancy they were
                    seventy, because the descendants from the sons of Noah, enumerated in Genesis,
                    were just so many. Allowing, then, the languages of the chief families to have
                    been fundamentally different from each other, the sub-languages and dialects
                    within each branch would probably have had a mutual affinity, greater or less as
                    these families settled nearer or farther from each other. But whichsoever of
                    these hypotheses is adopted, the primary object of the confusion at Babel was
                    the separation and dispersion of mankind.</p><p>Dr Bryant, in the third volume of his <hi rend="italic">Analysis of Ancient
                    Mythology,</hi> has advanced a singular hypothesis, both with respect to the
                    confusion of tongues and the dispersion of mankind. He supposes that the
                    confusion of language was local and partial, and limited to Babel only. By
                    jπκn⅛□ (Gen. xi. 1 and 8), which our translators render <hi rend="italic">the
                    whole earth,</hi> he understands <hi rend="italic">every region</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and by the same words (in verse 9), <hi rend="italic">the
                    whole region</hi> or province. This confusion was occasioned, as he supposes, by
                    a labial failure; so that the people could not articulate. Thus their speech was
                    confounded, but not altered; for as soon as they separated, they recovered the
                    true tenor of pronunciation, and the language of the earth continued for some
                    ages nearly the same. The interviews between the Hebrews and other nations
                    recorded in Scripture were conducted without an interpreter; and he further
                    observes, that the various languages which subsist at this day retain sufficient
                    relation to show that they were once dialects from the same matrix, and that
                    their variety was the effect of time.</p></div></body></text></TEI>