<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-9768-0192-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COMPOSITION</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 192</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1353199">Grammar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194749768" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COMPOSITION</label>, in a general sense, the uniting or <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194749781" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9781-0193"/> putting together
                    several things, so as to iorm a whole or compound.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Composition</hi><hi rend="italic">of Ideas,</hi> an
                    act of the mind, by which it unites several simple ideas into one conception or
                    complex idea.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Composition,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Grammar,</hi> the
                    joining of two words together; or prefixing a particle to another word, to
                    augment, diminish, or change its signification.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Composition,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Literature,</hi> the
                    art of forming and arranging sentiments, and clothing them with language
                    suitable to the nature of the subject or discourse.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Composition,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Logic,</hi> a method
                    of reasoning, by which we proceed from some general self-evident truth to other
                    particular and singular ones.</p>
                <p>In disposing and putting together our thoughts, there are two modes of proceeding
                    equally within our choice; for we may arrange the truths relating to any part of
                    knowledge as they presented themselves to the mind in the course of
                    investigation, carrying on the series of proofs in a reverse order, till at last
                    they terminate in first principles; or, beginning with these principles, we may
                    take the contrary mode, and from them deduce, by a direct train of reasoning,
                    the several propositions we want to establish.</p>
                <p>This diversity in the manner of arranging our thoughts gives rise to the twofold
                    division of method established among logicians. The first is the <hi
                    rend="italic">analytic</hi> method, or the method of <hi rend="italic"
                    >resolution,</hi> inasmuch as it traces things back to their source, and
                    resolves knowledge into its first and original principles. And this stands in
                    contradistinction to the method of composition, or, as it is otherwise called,
                    the <hi rend="italic">synthetic</hi> method; for here we proceed by gathering
                    together the several scattered parts of knowledge, and combining them into one
                    system, in such a manner as that the understanding is enabled distinctly to
                    follow truth through all the different stages of gradation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Composition,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> is the
                    art of composing airs, which, being either singly or in parts combined together,
                    and accompanied with appropriate harmony, form a complete piece of music.</p>
                <p>Compositions have been generally divided into two capital species; the <hi
                    rend="italic">sacred</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">secular.</hi></p>
                <p>Sacred compositions are usually written in strict observance of the rules of
                    harmony, in order to produce a solemn and imposing effect; and to this end also
                    all the parts are conducted in studied and regular progressions. Hence this
                    species has been called rigorous or severe. Albrechtsberger limits the severe
                    style to compositions for voices only, without instrumental accompaniments; but
                    he remarks, at the same time, that they are frequently executed along with the
                    organ and other instruments. The severe style has been accurately observed by
                    the greatest ancient and modern writers, in fugues and other movements of a
                    measured and uniform character; but the species <hi rend="italic">sacred</hi>
                    must not be understood to comprehend the whole range of compositions commonly so
                    called, many of which abound in free and fanciful melodies, with full and rich
                    instrumentation.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">secular</hi> species affords a wider range to genius, and
                    subsists in greater variety than the <hi rend="italic">sacred.</hi> The composer
                    in this style is completely unfettered. He may exert all us inventive powers to
                    heighten the effect of his music. He is tied down to no rules save those which
                    are dictated by taste and judgment, without which no composition can give real
                    satisfaction. The <hi rend="italic">secular</hi> style is subdivided into two
                    kinds, <hi rend="italic">theatrical</hi> and <hi rend="italic">chamber</hi>
                    music. The former is that employed in operas; the latter includes solos,
                    concertos, airs, cappricios, fantasias, vocal and instrumental pieces, and, in
                    general, all sorts of composition which do not fall under the sacred or severe
                    style, or belong to the regular stage opera.</p>
                <p>An intimate acquaintance with musical science and the capabilities of
                    instruments, although essential as a foundation, will not of itself confer the
                    power and ability to compose. Conversant with mere mechanical rules, one is no
                    more qualified to understand the art, and operate in the practice of
                    composition, than to form himself for eloquence upon the rules of grammar. The
                    acquisition of such knowledge is only the preparative for composition, “The
                    composer must find in his own genius,” as Rousseau observes, “the sources of
                    beautiful melody, of sublime harmony, the picturesque and the expressive in
                    music; he must, in short, be capable of perceiving and of forming the order of
                    the whole piece; to follow the relations.and aptitudes of which it is
                    susceptible in every kind; to inflame his soul with the spirit and enthusiasm of
                    the poet, instead of being carried away with the mere sound of the words.”</p>
                <p>Every composition is either vocal or instrumental, and has a determined number of
                    parts. In vocal music the compass of the human voice must be particularly
                    attended to. In instrumental music the extension of the parts is regulated by
                    the compass of the instruments, and the harmony ought always to be subservient
                    to the expression of the melody.</p>
                <p>The great aim in all kinds of musical composition is to produce iimŵ/and <hi
                    rend="italic">variety,</hi> because without these two qualities no work can be
                    essentially pleasing. Their employment must be mutual, and, above all,
                    judicious. A piece of music having unity without variety is poor and monotonous;
                    but possessing variety without unity, it maybe compared to the dress of a
                    harlequin, made up of patches and colours, which, in point of effect, appears
                    altogether ridiculous. Every piece of music must, therefore, have at the same
                    time both <hi rend="italic">unity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">variety.</hi> It is
                    then a genuine production of art, the result of well-directed talent, and a
                    model for artists. <hi rend="italic">Variety</hi> is attained by avoiding
                    monotony; <hi rend="italic">unity</hi> by connecting ideas in a free and
                    perspicuous manner, attending to just proportion, and keeping clear of
                    heterogeneous construction.</p>
                <p>It is easy to define what is termed unity in the other fine arts, because they
                    are chiefly addressed to the understanding, which judges for itself. Thus, for
                    instance, there is no difficulty in observing the unities of time, place, and
                    action in dramatic poetry, in which there are fixed principles to guide an
                    author with the utmost certainty. But in music, which is an art in which the
                    understanding cannot competently judge, and where every thing is dictated and
                    created by feeling only, it is impossible to indicate in what <hi rend="italic"
                    >variety,</hi> and particularly <hi rend="italic">unity,</hi> in music actually
                    consist. Clear perception, well-regulated taste, and genius, are all essential
                    to enable a composer to attain facility in composition. Incalculable benefit
                    will be reaped by carefully analyzing the best models of art, such as the works
                    of Handel, Jomelli, Cimarosa, Mozart, Haydn, and Beethoven. The monotony of
                    sounds, progressions, and cadences, is relieved by pleasing and natural
                    modulations, which do not affect unity. A happy mixture of diapasons, pianos,
                    and fortes, different rhythms, long and short phrases, and periods symmetrically
                    distributed, together with notes of different length, and well proportioned
                    intervals, all tend to produce <hi rend="italic">variety</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> whilst, on the other hand, whatever is confused, either in modulation or
                    ideas, is oflensive to feeling, and consequently detrimental to <hi
                    rend="italic">unity.</hi></p>
                <p>It has been observed that a multiplicity of different ideas, crowded together in
                    one piece, is reprehensible. It is for that reason desirable that the composer
                    should revert to his primarily-divulged ideas, and continue to develope, modify,
                    and vary them. The best works of Haydn are constructed on two or three leading
                    ideas. That celebrated composer used to say, “When I found a happy idea, I
                    obliged myself to conduct it according to the rules of art. <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749794" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9794-0194"/>It is by neglecting tłiis
                    that so many composers have erred. Their ideas are no sooner given out than they
                    are discussed. Thus their compositions leave no permanent impression on the
                    hearer."</p>
                <p>The composer must be thoroughly versed in all kinds of counterpoint, and
                    generally in the whole theoretical and practical mechanism of his art. For such
                    instruction we refer to Music, and other articles relating to musical science,
                    in this work. In conclusion, we may remark, that nothing conduces so
                    beneficially in forming an accomplished composer, as a careful and diligent
                    study and practice of the <hi rend="italic">fugue,</hi> which, as remarked by
                    Reicha in his <hi rend="italic">Traité de Mélodie,</hi> will teach him, <hi
                    rend="italic">first,</hi> to give every possible variety to passages; <hi
                    rend="italic">secondly,</hi> to modulate with accuracy; <hi rend="italic"
                    >thirdly,</hi> to develope his ideas in every beautiful form; and, <hi
                    rend="italic">lastly,</hi> to preserve the strictest unity in his compositions.
                    It was by a profound conception of the genius of the fugue that Handel and Haydn
                    acquired such distinguished proficiency in music; and it is to it that we are
                    consequently indebted for a great proportion of the most sublime productions of
                    these two illustrious composers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Composition,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Painting,</hi>
                    includes the invention as well as disposition of the figures, the choice of
                    attitudes, and so forth. Composition, therefore, consists of two parts; one of
                    which finds out, by means of history, proper objects for a picture; and the
                    other disposes them to advantage. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Painting.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Composition,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Printing,</hi> commonly
                    termed <hi rend="italic">composing,</hi> the arranging of several types or
                    letters in the composing stick, in order to form a line; and of several lines
                    placed in order in the galley, to make a page; and of several pages to make a
                    form. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Printing.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
