<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-3395-0471-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">CRIMEA, or Crim Tartary</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 471</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term><term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1109953">Scythians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:804065">Alani</term><term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1056939">Peninsulas</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194753395" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">CRIMEA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Crim Tartary</hi></label>,
                    anciently the <hi rend="italic">Chersonesus</hi><hi rend="italic">Taurica,</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi> peninsula situated directly to the south of St
                    Petersburg, between the 44th and 46 th degrees of north latitude, and in 34
                    degrees of east longitude. Its southern and western coasts are on the Euxine,
                    its northern and eastern on the Putrid Sea and the Sea of Azof. It is joined to
                    the continent on the north by a small neck of land not more than six miles in
                    breadth. This peninsula has been known for more than three thousand years, since
                    the first naval expedition of the Argonauts; a story which, though mixed with
                    fable, is yet well founded in its principal facts. The mountainous parts were
                    inhabited by the Tauri, probably a colony of Scythians; while its coasts on the
                    west, the east, and the south, were occupied by Greeks. The Scythians were
                    driven out by Mithridates; the Greeks by the Sarmatians; and these again by the
                    Alani and Goths, a northern horde of Scythians. The Hungarians, the Cossacks,
                    and Tartars, succeeded in their turn; and the Genoese, in the twelfth century,
                    held a temporary and precarious possession of the sea-ports, which they were
                    obliged to yield to the Turks in 1475. At the peace of 1774, the Tartars of the
                    Crimea were declared independent; and in 1783, this peninsula was definitively
                    united to the Russian empire. ,</p><p>From the isthmus, on which is built the fortress of Or-kapi or Pcrecop, to the
                    first elevation of the hill at Karasubasar, the country is one continued flat;
                    then it rises by an easy gradation to the summit of the hill, which forms the
                    southern side of the peninsula and the shore of the Euxine Sea. The surface of
                    the soil is almost all of one kind, namely, a reddish-gray loam; on digging, it
                    is found more or less mixed with a black earth, and the hills abound with marl.
                    The whole flat country from Perecop to the river Salgir, an extent of about
                    eighty miles, is full of saline marshes and lakes, whence the neighbóuring
                    Russian governments, as well as the Crimea itself, Anatolia, and Bessarabia, are
                    supplied with salt. The most remarkable of these lakes are five in number;
                    Koslof and Caffa, both very large, and so called after the towns near which they
                    lie; the Tusla, about fifteen versts<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The verst, a Kussian measure of length, is equal to 3520
                    English feet; consequently three versts are equal to two English
                    miles.</p></note> from Perecop, on the road from Caffa; the Red Lake, not far
                    from that last mentioned; and the Black Lake. Besides these, there are many
                    other swamps and lakes, whence the inhabitants obtain salt for their own
                    consumption.</p><p>The greater part of the peninsula is so level that a man may travel over the half
                    of it without meeting with a river, or even the smallest brook; the inhabitants
                    of the villages, therefore, make a pit in the yard of every house, for receiving
                    and containing the rain water. The whole tract is destitute of every kind of
                    tree. Not a bush or a bramble is to be seen, and the herbage is extremely
                    scanty. This, however, does not proceed so much from the unfruitfulness of the
                    soil, as from the vast herds of cattle which rove from place to place, during
                    the whole year, by which means the grass in spring, summer, or autumn, no sooner
                    appears through the long drought which succeeds the rainy season, than it is
                    immediately devoured or trodden down. The universal prevalence of this custom of
                    keeping cattle to wander up and down, joined to the slothfulness of the Tartars,
                    together with their inaptitude and aversion to agriculture, is the reason of the
                    total neglect of cultivation in the Crimea. Were the land divided into portions
                    and properly managed, there would be a sufficiency for the cattle, and the rest
                    would be fruitful in corn and grain.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:194753408" xml:id="kp-eb0707-3408-0472"/><p>This peninsula is indeed but a little district, yet from the many advantages
                    conferred upon it by nature it may be considered as peculiarly rich. It is
                    divided into the hill country and the flat. The latter, which extends from
                    Perecop to Koslof and the river Bulganap, to Karasubasar, Caffa, and Yenicali,
                    is diversified here and there with little Tartar villages, maintained by cattle
                    and the produce of the salt lakes. The highlands or hill country forms the
                    southern part of the Crimea, along the straight coast of the Black Sea, and
                    stretching westward in a right line from Cafla to the vicinity of Belbek. These
                    hills are composed of layers of chalk, which, in the headlands and promontories,
                    are soft, but more inland quite hard. The strata of the high hills are like
                    those of the promontories, and take a direction from north to south. These
                    qualities of the strata prevail not throughout the whole hills, but only in the
                    large and lofty ones; such as the two which rise near Karasubasar, and a very
                    high one near Akmetchet, which bears the name of Aktau. The other smaller hills
                    lie scattered and dispersed, but take the names of the greater ones, to which
                    they seem to belong, and are called <hi rend="italic">Palkans.</hi></p><p>Nature has favoured these highland countries with great advantages, and blessed
                    them with abundance of all things. A number of springs which flow from the
                    mountains form the two considerable rivers Salgir and Karasu, which run into the
                    Putrid Sea. The former, which takes its rise from a cavern in a high hill near
                    Akmctchet, falls straight into the plain below, and waters a great part of the
                    Crimea; the other, commencing behind Karasubasar, falls likewise into the plain,
                    and mingles with the Salgir. There are many other little rivers and streams
                    which run eastward, and either join the two above mentioned or fall immediately
                    into the Putrid Sea. All the streams which begin at Cafla flow to the north or
                    the north-east, excepting the one behind Akmetchet, which falls on the other
                    side. This river, rising on the northern side of the mountain, flows, as was
                    before observed, towards the northeast, to the Salgir and the Putrid Sca; and
                    those which spring on the western side also take their course westward to the
                    Bulganak, and thence straight to the Black Sca, which receives all the other
                    little rivers which rise from these hills, as the Amma, the Katscha, the Belbek,
                    the Kasulkioi, and some others.</p><p>The mountains arc covered with wood fit for the purpose of ship-building, and
                    abound in wild beasts. The valleys consist of fine arable land; whilst on the
                    sides of the hills grow corn and vines in great abundance, and the earth is rich
                    in mines. But the mountaineers are as careless and negligent as the inhabitants
                    of the deserts they slight all the advantages we have mentioned, and, like their
                    brethren of the lowlands, think themselves sufficiently happy if they are in
                    possession of a fat sheep and a small portion of bread.</p><p>The houses in the towns as well as the villages are for the most part built of
                    square timbers, having the interstices filled with brick work, if the possessor
                    can afford it, and those of the poorer sort with turf. The chinks and crannies
                    are made tight with clay, and then plastered both within and without. The
                    covering commonly consists either of bricks or of turfs. Only the medscheds,
                    minarets, and baths are of stone, and a few, extremely handsome, of marble. They
                    have chimneys in the chambers, at which they likewise dress their victuals, but
                    no stoves in the Russian manner. In extreme frosts a great iron pan of charcoal
                    is brought into the room. Their custom is to sit upon low sofas, with Turkish
                    coverings and cushions, or upon a clay seat, somewhat raised above the ground
                    and covered with a carpet. In these rooms arc cupboards and chests, often
                    covered with cushions to serve as scats, and in these they keep their gold,
                    silver, and valuables. Such are the inner apartments or harams in which the
                    women generally live; the others are not so fine, and contain only a sofa, or a
                    bank of clay covered with a carpet, as in the chimney rooms.</p><p>The rich Tartars, and their nobility or murzas, commonly reside all the year
                    round in the country, coming only to town when they have business there. There
                    are but few towns in the Crimea, at least in comparison of its former
                    population. The Krimskoi Tartars have no tribunals of justice, controversies and
                    quarrels being seldom heard of amongst them; and, if a dispute should arise, it
                    is immediately settled by an appeal to the Koran. Little differences which occur
                    in the villages about property, or other matters not taken notice of in that
                    code, are amicably adjusted by the eldermen and abeses; but in the towns all
                    weighty concerns, excepting the single case of murder or homicide, arc brought
                    before the kaimakan, or commandant, who settles them absolutely without
                    appeal.</p><p>The residence of the khans of the Crimea was formerly Baktchi-serai, in which
                    city they held their seat for upwards of two centuries. They went thither from
                    Eski-Crim, or Old Crim, the capital city of the Genoese, upon Bengli Ghirei
                    Khan’s plundering the sea-ports, and expelling all the Genoese from their
                    stations. Before Eski-Crim became the capital, and indeed upon the Tartars first
                    coming into this peninsula, the sovereign residence was at Koslof; but here it
                    did not long continue. Under the khan Shagin Ghirei it was held at Caffa, the
                    ancient Theodosia, which is ten miles distant from Eski-Crim, said to be the <hi rend="italic">Cimmerium</hi> of the ancients.</p><p>The principal cities or towns of the Crimea shall now be enumerated. Perccop is a
                    fortified place, consisting only of three houses. The suburbs arc three versts
                    or two English miles distant, peopled by a thousand individuals, who carry on a
                    trade in salt; but they are very ill built. The towns arc chiefly situated in
                    the district watered by the Salgir. That part of the country in which Akmetchet,
                    or the capital, stands, is unfruitful, and ill provided with water, and the
                    inhabitants are exposed to endemi-cal fevers. This town has been called
                    Sympheropol by the Russians, since they became masters of the peninsula; but it
                    is only known in the country by the name which it received from the Tartars. The
                    population is not less than 20,000 souls. The inhabitants are indolent, and the
                    place is without commerce. The distance from Akmetchet to Baktchi-serai is not
                    more than thirty versts, or twenty English miles. It was once the residence of
                    the khan, and the Tartar capital of the Crimea. It is built on the craggy side
                    of a large natural moat or ravine between two mountains, and surrounded with
                    fountains, streams, terraces, hanging vineyards, and groves of black poplars
                    near rocks and precipices. The vast palace of the khans still remains, but many
                    other edifices have been destroyed by the victorious Russians. The number of
                    inhabitants is now reduced to seven or eight thousand; their principal trade
                    consists in cutlery and morocco leather. Tchufut-Kali, an ancient fortress
                    erected by the Genoese on a lofty precipice, is not more than five versts from
                    the last-mentioned town. It is now a place of refuge for 1200 Jews, of the sect
                    Karai. The character of the Karaites is very different from that of their
                    brethren in other countries; they live without reproach, their honesty is
                    proverbial in the Crimea, and the word of a Karaite is said to be as good as
                    another man’s bond. They still adhere to the law of Moses; they have rejected
                    the Talmud, every Rabbinical doctrine, and all interpolations of scriptural
                    texts. Koslof, which was for a short time distinguished by the name of
                    Eupatoria, is situated on the western coast; its port is the most commercial of
                    any in the peninsula, and its population amounts to 12,000 inhabitants, <pb break="no" facs="nls:194753421" xml:id="kp-eb0707-3421-0473"/>
                    many of whom are brewers of <hi rend="italic">bouza,</hi> the Mussulman ale,
                    which is drunk on the banks of the Sennaar. Akhtiar or Sebastopol, a large naval
                    arsenal, and a temporary station of the Russian Black Sea flcct, from which it
                    can sail in twenty-four hours to the Bosphorus, is built on the southern
                    extremity of the same coast. This was one of the chief mercantile towns of the
                    ancient kingdom of Colchis: it now contains about 3000 inhabitants. The harbour
                    is excellent; the principal bay, which runs up between four and five miles into
                    the land, is from six to eight hundred fathoms in width, and from ten to eleven
                    fathoms deep, is perfectly sheltered, and without a single shoal. After having
                    doubled the capes of the Chersonesus and St George, the voyager observes the
                    narrow entrance of the port Balaklava, where two thousand Greeks gain a
                    subsistence by trade and the produce of their mackarel fisheries'. All the rocky
                    and steep coast from Cape Aia to Cape Aitodoro is probably theŷrowí <hi rend="italic">of the ram,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Criou-Metopon,</hi> of
                    the ancients. Travellers remark at the base of the mountains, or the Byzantine
                    Klimata, the romantic towns of Nikita, Aloutchti, Sou-dak, with its small
                    harbour, and Ioursof, with a castle belonging to the governors of Taurida. Caffa
                    or the ancient Theodosia is situated at the extremity of the mountains on the
                    bay of Caffa. It covers the southern side of the gulf, and rises like a vast
                    theatre of mosques and minarets near the hills which inclose that part of the
                    bay. It merited and obtained in past times the appellation of the Lesser
                    Constantinople. It contained 36,000 houses within its walls, and not fewer than
                    8000 in the suburbs. It must be confessed, however, that the ruins do not
                    indicate a space proportionate to so great a number. Mahommed II. having made
                    himself master of the Bosphorus, took the town in 1475. It continued to flourish
                    under the Tartars; but its inhabitants, like those throughout the Crimea,
                    abandoned their possessions at the approach of the Russians, and the Genoese and
                    Tartar monuments were destroyed by the barbarous troops of the czar. ∖The
                    present population is less than 400. Kertsh, once t’ņe residence of Mithridates,
                    and the capital of the Bosplmrian kings, and Yenikali, a small fortress which
                    commands?Rıe strait, are situated on the eastern peninsula. Near the former is
                    the tomb of Mithridates; and a magnificent sarcophagus at Yenikali is now
                    converted into a reservoir. The Altyn Obo, or highest hill in that part of the
                    Crimea, is about four versts distant from Kertsh.</p><p>The neck of land which joins the peninsula with the continent is at least six
                    miles broad, and is intersected by a wide and deep ditch lined with stone, which
                    reaches from the Black Sea to the Putrid Sea. This was formerly kept without
                    water, but it is now filled from both seas. On the Crimean side a high wall of
                    earth runs across from one sea to the other. The people pass over the ditch by
                    means of a drawbridge, and through the wall by a gateway. The walls of the
                    fortress are some fathoms from the road side, but the ruins are only now
                    discernible, namely, large brick houses, with a number of bomb-shells and
                    cannon-balls lying about them, which were formerly kept in the fortress. About
                    two miles from this is a pretty populous but miserable place, being probably the
                    town to which this fort belonged. Near the gate is a customhouse, where all
                    imports and exports pay duty.</p><p>The Crimea was heretofore divided into twenty-four ka-duliks or districts,
                    namely, Yenikali, Kertsh, Arabat, Eski-Crim, Caffa, Karasubasar, Sudak,
                    Akmetchet, Yalof, Baktchi-serai, Balaklava, Mangup, Inkerman, Koslof, Or,
                    Mansur, Tarkan, Sivasch, Tischongar, Sarubulat, Barun, Argun, Sidschugut, and
                    Schirin. Several of these districts are named after the town or village in which
                    the governor resides.</p></div></body></text></TEI>