<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-3135-0451-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRAYON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 451</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jt0c">Tinting</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b49882v44">Stucco</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:833576">Black</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1024112">Mixing</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:834915">Blue</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194753135" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRAYON</label> is a sort of soft pencil made of any kind of
                    coloured substance used for drawing in what is called pastil. It is a name which
                    may also with propriety be applied to primitive substances or chalks.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Crayon</hi><hi rend="italic">Painting.</hi> This method of
                    painting, or more properly drawing, with coloured substances or chalks in a dry
                    form, was first practised by the French painters in the time of Louis XIV., and
                    then, and for some considerable time subsequently, was much in use in the
                    painting of portraits. But the liability of crayon pictures to injuries by
                    exposure to the light and the decomposition of their colours, with the
                    consequent defect of their original lustre, and by their proneness to collect
                    damp and dust, has rendered this art less in reputation than it was half a
                    century ago. At the present time we are not aware of any artist of reputation in
                    this country who practises it. The American naturalist Audubon has lately shown,
                    however, by his drawings of ornithological subjects, that crayons, together with
                    a judicious admixture of water-colour paints and black-lead hatchings, are
                    admirably adapted for giving the peculiar appearance to the feathers and the
                    brilliant lustre of the beautiful birds of his native forests. But unless it be
                    this accomplished foreigner, we do not know of any other individual who has made
                    much use of these means for the production of works of art. But we would not on
                    this account be warranted in omitting to detail a few particulars as to the
                    management of the art of crayon painting.</p>
                <p>Crayon paper is of a peculiar quality, and is manufactured with colour in its
                    fabric. It is well known, and may be had in all the stationers’ shops. It should
                    be pasted upon linen or cotton cloth stretched tight upon a wooden frame in the
                    same manner as canvass to be painted upon. When completely dry, the outline of
                    the object is first to be drawn, afterwards the shadows laid in with the crayons
                    in a broad manner, and then the colours of the draperies and the tints
                    added.</p>
                <p>It is not the proper place here to enumerate the various modes of mixing colours
                    so as to produce certain tints or shades. This will be detailed at length under
                    the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Painting</hi>; and it is by practice alone that
                    any approximation to excellence can be attained in this as in every department
                    of art. All we think requisite to mention is, that too many mixtures of various
                    crayons are carefully to be avoided, as they tend greatly to injure the
                    brilliancy of the colours.</p>
                <p>Crayons are to be procured in sets; but if prepared, care must be taken not to
                    admit any of the white leads into the composition of the various tints of which
                    the sets are made up. The white should be prepared chalk, or zinc white, or any
                    other white substance not liable to deterioration by age or exposure to the
                    light. All the pigments made use of in painting, properly ground up with water,
                    and reduced to the necessary tints by the proper admixtures with one another, or
                    with whiting prepared in the manner afterwards explained, may be used for making
                    the <pb break="no" facs="nls:194753148" xml:id="kp-eb0707-3148-0452"/>pencils or
                    crayons, and which are applied to the surface of the paper in the same way as
                    chalks, and these may be blended into one another with the finger, or left pure,
                    just as occasion requires.</p>
                <p>Generally speaking, to keep the colours and shades broad and clear of each other,
                    is the practice to be preferred here, as well as in oil painting. Too much
                    tinting and blending at first will be sure to produce heaviness and want of
                    brilliancy in the end. Therefore, the purer the tints are laid in at the
                    beginning, the better will be the result; for if the nostrils or the lips, for
                    example, be done with pure carmine at the commencement, it will be easy to tone
                    them down with other shading colours, and thus produce and preserve the greater
                    clearness.</p>
                <p>After the whole subject is laid in in a broad manner with carmine, black, and
                    white, and with such colours as the draperies or back-ground may be composed of,
                    but without attention to minutiae, or, as the process is termed by artists,
                    after the picture is “dead coloured,” the whole must be softened and blended
                    together with the finger, or with an instrument called a <hi rend="italic"
                    >stump,</hi> which is a piece of chamois leather rolled up in a cylindrical
                    form, and shaped to a point.</p>
                <p>In performing this process, care must be taken not to mix the colours improperly,
                    and on this account the finger or stump should be wiped often on a towel; and
                    care must be taken not to soften and rub in the tints too much or too often,
                    which will deteriorate that richness of effect which the dry pigments produce
                    when the crayons are laid on in a rough manner.</p>
                <p>When the picture is thus laid in with the dead colour, it will have the
                    appearance of being composed, (if the subject be a portrait) of three colours,
                    carmine, black, and white, which is the best preparation for the reception of
                    the tints of which the painting should consist when finished. The back-ground
                    and the hair should next be completed, or nearly so, as the chalk dust in the
                    progress of painting these would otherwise injure the face and the lighter
                    parts.</p>
                <p>In every case the highest lights are to be left out till the last. In painting
                    over the forehead for the last time, begin the highest light with the faintest
                    vermilion tint, in the same place where the faint carmine was first laid,
                    keeping it broad in the same manner. In the next shade which succeeds the
                    highest lights some light-blue colours must be worked in, intermixing them with
                    richer tints of vermilion, softening them carefully together, and at same time
                    adding some warmer yellow colours very sparingly. Strong verditer tints
                    intermixed with greens will be serviceable in the shadow at the roots of the
                    hair, and in other places where necessary; and cool-coloured crayons composed of
                    black and white should succeed these, and blend with the hair.</p>
                <p>In finishing the cheeks, or any other parts where pure colour obtains, this
                    should be amongst the last of the touches; and it should be done with lakes and
                    bright vermilion intermixed with a little orange-coloured crayon, all with great
                    delicacy, and sweetened and softened with the finger cautiously, to avoid
                    producing that heaviness incident to over much mixing of the one colour with the
                    other, as the beauty and excellence of crayon painting consists in one colour
                    showing itself through, or rather between the other.</p>
                <p>When a very smart touch is required to be made, such as the spark of light on the
                    eye, or the light on the point of the nose, a small piece of the crayon should
                    be chipped off, and the touch effected with the fragmented angle.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Drapery.</hi> Dark blue, purple, black, pink, and all shades of
                    red draperies, should be first laid in slightly with carmine, which, in the end,
                    will produce much more brilliant colours than can be done by any other mode.
                    Over this preparation should be laid the middle tint, which is the medium colour
                    between the light and dark shades, and which should extend over the spaces
                    occupied by the lights and middle tints. The shadows should be kept clear of all
                    these lighter mixtures from the commencement, as they will have most clearness
                    if not allowed to partake of them, and the whole are to be softened together
                    with the finger in the manner already described, and the highest lights
                    superinduced upon the middle tints at the last Reflected lights should partake,
                    of course, of the colour of the reflecting medium, whatever it may happen to be
                    composed of. &lt; <hi rend="italic">Materials.</hi> The excellence of crayons
                    consists in a great measure in their softness. To obviate the tendency of crayon
                    pictures to change their colour, great pains and care should be used in
                    preparing the whiting with which the shades of the colours are made up. This
                    should be done as follows: Take a vessel of water, put the whiting into it, and
                    mix them well together. Let this stand for half a minute, then pour off the top
                    into another vessel, and throw the gritty sediment away; let what is prepared
                    rest about a minute, and then pour it off as before, which will purify the
                    whiting, and render it smooth and free of gritty particles. When this is done,
                    let the whiting settle, and then pour the water off, after which lay it upon a
                    plate of stucco to dry, and iţ will answer either for pure white, or for mixing
                    up with all the other colours; and the whiting thus purified may be used to mix
                    with all the colours, either while in the wet or dry state. The crayons are made
                    by rolling them out into convenient lengths upon a marble slab, or piece of
                    plate glass, while the paste is in a wet state.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reds</hi> —It is rather difficult to procure either good
                    carmine or good lake.· Good carmine is inclined to the vermilion tint, and good
                    lake to the carmine tint. The carmine crayons are prepared in the following
                    manner. ,</p>
                <p>1. Carmine. As their texture is inclinable to hardness, instead of grinding and
                    rolling them, take a sufficient quantity of carmine, lay it upon the
                    grinding-stone, mix it by means of a levigating knife with spirit of wine till
                    it becomes smooth and even. The stucco stone being ready, lay the colour upon it
                    to absorb the spirit; but be careful that it is laid on in a proper state for
                    painting. If it is levigated too thin, the crayons will be too flat; and if too
                    thick, it will occasion a waste of colour, by their adhering to the
                    pallet-knife; but practice will render the proper degree of consistency
                    familiar. The simple colour being prepared, the next step is to compose the
                    different tints by a mixture with whiting; and the proportion to be observed,
                    consisting of twenty gradations to one, may be clearly understood by the
                    following directions: Take some of the simple colour, and levigate it with
                    spirit of wine, adding about one part of washed whiting to three parts of
                    carmine, of which, when properly incorporated, make two parcels. The next
                    gradation should be composed of equal quantities of carmine and whiting, of
                    which four crayons may be made. The third composition should have one fourth
                    carmine and three fourths whiting: of this make six crayons, which will be a
                    good proportion for the rest. The last tint should be made of whiting, very
                    faintly tinged with carmine, of which make about eight crayons, which will
                    complete the above-mentioned proportion. As these compound tints are levigated,
                    they are to be laid immediately upon the stucco, that the moisture may be
                    absorbed to the proper degree of dryness for forming into crayons, which may be
                    known by its losing the greater part of its adhesive quality when taken into the
                    hand; if the consistence is^found to be right, it may be then laid upon the
                    glass, which, having no pores, will <pb break="no" facs="nls:194753161"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-3161-0453"/>prevent the moisture from being carried off before
                    it is convenient to form it into crayons, otherwise the crayons ’ would be full
                    of cracks and very brittle, which will be a great inconvenience when they are
                    used in painting.</p>
                <p>2. Lake. This is a colour very apt to be hard; to prevent which the following
                    particulars must be observed: Take about half the quantity of lake intended for
                    the crayons, and grind it very fine with spirit of wine; let it dry, and then
                    pulverize it, which is easily done if the lake is good; then take the other
                    half, and grind it with spirits, after which mix it with the pulverized lake,
                    and lay it out directly in crayons on the stucco. This colour will not bear
                    rolling. The simple colour being thus prepared, proceed with the compound
                    crayons as before directed, and in the same degrees of gradation as the carmine
                    tints. ∣</p>
                <p>3. Vermilion. The best is inclined to the carmine tint. Nothing more is required
                    to prepare this colour than to mix it on the stone with soft water or spirits,
                    after'which it may be rolled into crayons. The different tints are produced by a
                    mixture of the simple colour with whiting, according to the proportion already
                    given.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Blues.</hi> —1. Prussian blue is a colour very apt to bind,
                    and is rendered soft with more difficulty than carmine and lake. The same method
                    of preparation is to be followed with this as is directed with respect to lake,
                    only it is necessary to grind a larger quantity of the pure colour, as it is
                    chiefly used for painting draperies. The different tints may be made according
                    to necessity; or the fancy of the painter. 2. Blue verditer is a colour
                    naturally gritty, and therefore it is necessary to wash it well. Its particles
                    are so coarse as to require some binding matter to unite them, otherwise the
                    crayons will never adhere together. To accomplish this, take a quantity
                    sufficient to form two or three crayons, to which add a piece of slaked plaster
                    of Paris about the size of a pea; mix these well together, and form the crayons
                    upon the stucco. This blue is extremely brilliant, and will be of great use in
                    heightening draperies, &amp;c. The tints must be formed with whiting as directed
                    in the former instances, and are highly serviceable for painting flesh,
                    particularly to produce those pearly tints so beautiful in crayon pictures. It
                    is not necessary to mix the compounds with spirits, as clear water will be
                    sufficient.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Greens.</hi> —Brilliant greens are produced with great
                    difficulty. We usually take yellow ochre, and after grinding it with spirits,
                    mix it with the powder of Prussian blue, then temper it with a knife, and lay
                    the crayons on the stucco, without rolling them. Instead of this some use king’s
                    yellow mixed with Prussian blue, and others brown ochre and Prussian blue. The
                    crayons made of the two last may be rolled. Various tints may be produced by
                    these colours, according to fancy or necessity; some partaking more of the blue,
                    and others of the yellow. Of late many beautiful greens have been invented, such
                    as olympian, emerald, and mineral greens, all which may be used in this art if
                    mixed properly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Yellows.</hi> —1. King’s yellow is the most useful and the
                    most brilliant, levigated with spirits of wine, to com-i pose the different
                    tints as before directed. 2. Yellow ochre, and Naples yellow ground with
                    spirits, will make useful crayons. 3. Orange is produced with king’s yellow and
                    vermilion ground together with spirits, and the tints formed as in other cases;
                    but no great quantity of them is required.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Browns.</hi> —1. Cullen’s earth is a fine dark brown. After
                    six or eight of the simple crayons are prepared, scI veral rich compound tints
                    may be produced from it by a mixture with carmine in various degrees. Black,
                    carmine, and this colour, mi∖cd together, make useful tints for painting hair;
                    several gradations may be produced from each of these by a mixture with whiting.
                    Roman or brown ochre is an excellent colour, either simple or compounded with
                    carmine. Whiting tinged in several degrees with either of these, will prove very
                    serviceable in painting. 2. Umber may be treated in just the same manner, only
                    it is necessary to levigate it with spirit of wine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Purples.</hi> —Prussian blue ground with spirits' and mixed
                    with pulverized lake, will produce a good purple. ' Carmine thus mixed with
                    Prussian blue will produce a purple something different from the former. Various
                    tints may be made from either of these compounds by a mixture with whiting. ∙.
                    .∣ -</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Black.</hi> —1. Lamp-black is the only black that can be
                    used with safety, as all others are subject to mildew; but as good lamp-black is
                    very scarce, the student will perhaps find it most expedient to make it himself.
                    The process is as follows: Provide a tin cone, fix it over a lamp at such a
                    height that the flame may just reach the cone for the soot to gather within it.
                    When a sufficient quantity is collected, take it out, and burn all the grease
                    from it in a crucible. It must then be ground with spirits, and laid on the
                    chalk to absorb the moisture. Various gray tints may be formed from this by a
                    mixture with whiting, as mentioned in former instances. 2. Vermilion mixed with
                    carmine. This is a composition of great use, and tints made from it with whiting
                    will be found to be very serviceable.</p>
                <p>3. Carmine and black is another good compound, of which five or six gradations
                    may be made, some partaking more of the black, and others having the carmine
                    most predominant, besides several tints by a mixture with whiting.</p>
                <p>4. Vermilion and black is also a very useful compound, from which several
                    different tints may be made. 5. Prussian blue and black is another good
                    compound, which will be found of singular service in painting draperies.</p>
                <p>It is impossible to lay down rules for forming every tint necessary in composing
                    a set of crayons, there being many accidental compositions, entirely dependent
                    on fancy and opinion. The student should make it a rule to preserve the leavings
                    of his colours; for of these he may form various tints, which will occasionally
                    be useful.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Of Polling the Crayons, and disposing them for painting.</hi>
                    The: different compositions of colours must be cut into a proper magnitude,
                    after they are prepared, in order to be rolled into pastils, for the convenience
                    of using them. Each crayon should be formed in the left hand with the ball of
                    the right, first formed cylindrically, and then tapering at each end. If the
                    composition is too dry, dip the finger in water; if too wet, the composition
                    must be laid upon the stucco again to absorb more of the moisture. The crayons
                    should be rolled as quick as possible; and when finished, laid upon the stucco
                    again, to absorb all remaining moisture. After the gradation of tints from one
                    colour is formed, the stone should be well scraped and cleansed with water
                    before it is used for another colour.</p>
                <p>When the set of crayons is completed according to the rules prescribed, they
                    should be arranged in classes for the convenience of painting with them. Some
                    thin drawers, divided into a number of partitions, is the most convenient method
                    of disposing them properly. The crayons should be deposited according to the
                    several gradations of light. The bottom of the partitions must be covered with
                    bran, as a bed for the colours; because it not only preserves them clean, but
                    prevents their breaking.</p>
                <p>The box made use of when the student paints should be about a foot square, with
                    nine partitions. In the upper corner on the left hand, supposing the box to be
                    in the lap when he paints, let him place the black and gray crayons, those being
                    the most seldom used; in the second partition the blues; in the third the greens
                    and browns; <pb break="no" facs="nls:194753174" xml:id="kp-eb0707-3174-0454"/>in
                    the first partition on the left hand of the second row the carmines, lakes,
                    vermilions, and all deep reds; the yellows and orange in the middle, and the
                    pearly tints next; and as these last arc of a very delicate nature, they must be
                    kept very clean, that the gradations of colour may be easily distinguished. In
                    the lower row let the first partition contain a piece of fine linen rag to wipe
                    the crayons with while they are using; let the second contain all the pure lake
                    and vermilion tints; and the other partition may include those tints which, from
                    their complex nature, cannot be classed with any of the former, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(g.g.g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
