<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-7298-0004-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COACH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 4</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cc21">Coaches</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b47659g8k">Coaching</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4p84454w">Wheels</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1174522">Wheels</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1130935">Springs</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:919892">Fairs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194747298" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COACH</label>. Few things have been more often or more
                    unsuccessfully defined than this well-known and useful vehicle. Of the
                    descriptions which have been given of it, many might with as much propriety be
                    applied to various other machines of conveyance, which it would be a violation
                    of language to dignify with the name of coach. The nearest approximation to a
                    definition appears to be, that it is a vehicle for commodious travelling, the
                    body of which is covered in, and suspended by means of springs upon the
                    frame-work to which the wheels are attached, the latter being sometimes two, and
                    sometimes four in number. It does not appear that the ancients were acquainted
                    with carriages of this description, although chariots and waggons, both open and
                    covered, were employed in very remote ages.</p>
                <p>In Britain, and throughout Europe, coaches are drawn by horses, except in Spain,
                    where mules are used for the purpose. In a part of the East, especially the
                    dominions of the Great Mogul, coaches are commonly drawn by oxen. In Denmark,
                    rein-deer are sometimes harnessed in coaches, though rather for curiosity than
                    use. The coachman is ordinarily placed on a seat raised before the body of the
                    coach; but in Spain policy displaced him from that position by a royal
                    ordinance,, on occasion when the Duke d’Olivares discovered that a very
                    important secret, respecting which he had conferred in his coach, had been
                    overheard and revealed by his coachman. Since that time the place of the Spanish
                    coachman is the same with that of the French stage coachman and our postilion,
                    namely, on the first horse on the left.</p>
                <p>According to Professor Beckmann <hi rend="italic">(History of Inventions and
                    Discoveries'),</hi> coaches of some kind were known <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194747311" xml:id="kp-eb0707-7311-0005"/>about the beginning of the
                    sixteenth century; but the use of them was limited to women of the highest rank,
                    it being accounted disgraceful in men to ride in them. It appears, from the
                    history of that period, that the electors and princes of the empire, when they
                    did not choose to attend the meetings of the states, excused themselves to the
                    emperor by informing him that their health would not permit them to travel on
                    horseback; and it was considered as unbecoming to ride in carriages like women.
                    But it seems also pretty certain that, about the end of the fifteenth century,
                    the emperor, kings, and some princes, travelled in covered carriages, and also
                    employed them in public solemnities.</p>
                <p>The nuptial carriage of the first wife of Leopold, a Spanish princess, cost,
                    including the harness, 38,000 florins. The coaches used by that emperor are thus
                    described :— In the imperial coaches no great magnificence was to be seen, being
                    covered over with red cloth and black nails. The harness was black, and no gold
                    was to be seen in the whole work. They had glass panneis, for which reason they
                    were called <hi rend="italic">imperial coaches.</hi> The harness was ornamented
                    with fringes of red silk on days of festivity. The imperial coaches were only
                    distinguished by having leather traces, whilst the ladies in the emperor’s suite
                    were contented with traces made of ropes. Fifty gilt coaches, having six horses
                    each, were to be seen, in 1681, at the court of Ernest Augustus of Hanover. The
                    first time that plenipotentiaries appeared in coaches was at the imperial
                    commission held at Erfurt in 1613.</p>
                <p>We meet with ample proof in the history of France, that in the fourteenth,
                    fifteenth, and even sixteenth centuries, the monarchs rode on horses, the
                    servants on mules, and ladies of distinction occasionally on asses. Yet
                    carriages of some kind seem to have been used in France at an early period,
                    since there is still preserved a statute of Philip the Fair, issued in 1294, for
                    the suppression of luxury, in which the wives of citizens are prohibited the use
                    of carriages.</p>
                <p>The oldest coaches used by the ladies of England were denominated <hi
                    rend="italic">whirlicotes,</hi> a name which has now sunk into oblivion. About
                    the end of the fourteenth century, when Richard II. was forced to fly before his
                    rebellious subjects, he and all his.attendants travelled on horseback, his
                    mother alone riding in a coach, because she was indisposed. But this became
                    afterwards unfashionable, the daughter of Charles IV. having showed the ladies
                    of England how conveniently she could ride on a side-saddle.</p>
                <p>According to Stowe, coaches first came to be used in England about the middle of
                    the sixteenth century, having been introduced from Germany by the Earl of
                    Arundel. The English plenipotentiary travelled to Scotland in a coach in the
                    year 1598, and these vehicles were generally used about the year 1605.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Duties on Carriages.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> It is long
                    since duties were imposed on carriages, and these have varied considerably at
                    different periods. The following table exhibits the number of four-wheeled and
                    other carriages, exclusive of hackney coaches, upon which duty was charged in
                    1828; the rates of duty on each kind of carriage; and the produce of the
                    duties.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Four-wheeled
                            Carriages.</hi><hi rend="italic">Carriages charged at progressive
                            rates.</hi></p><p>Pprsons keppino 1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Number of Carriages.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Rates of</p><p>Duty.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Amount of Duty.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>21,876</p><p>5,017</p><p>924</p><p>244</p><p>96</p><p>36</p><p>14</p><p>8</p><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">£ s.
                            d.</hi></p><p>6 0 0</p><p>6 10 0</p><p>7 0 0</p><p>7 10 0</p><p>7 17
                            6</p><p>8 4 0</p><p>8 10 0</p><p>8 16 0</p><p>9 1 6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">£ s.
                            d.</hi></p><p>131,256 0 0</p><p>32,610 10 0</p><p>6,468 0 0</p><p>1,830
                            0 0</p><p>756 0 0</p><p>295 4 0</p><p>119 0 0</p><p>70 8 0</p><p>108 18
                            0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8...„</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9 and upwards</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28,227</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p/></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>173,514 0 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Additional bodies</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>55</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3 3 0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>173 5 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Carriages let to hire without
                            horses</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>472</p><p>6,596</p><p>2,996</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6 0 0</p><p>5 5 0</p><p>5 5
                            0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,832 0 0</p><p>34,629 0
                            0</p><p>15,729 0 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Post chaises and other carriages let
                            to hire with ļ horses J</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Public stage coaches</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9,647</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p/></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53,190 0 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Two-wheeled
                            Carriages.</hi></p><p>Drawn by one horse</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48,318</p><p>425</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3 5 0</p><p>4 10 0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>157,033 10 0</p><p>1,912 10
                            0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Drawn by two or more
                            horses</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48,743</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p/></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>158,946 0 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Additional bodies</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>in r,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>99 1 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>By 1 Will. IV. c. 35, it is enacted, that for every carriage with four wheels,
                    each being of less diameter than thirty inches, drawn by a pony or ponies, mule
                    or mules, above twelve but not exceeding thirteen hands high, an annual duty of
                    L.3. 5s. shall be charged. Carriages with four wheels, drawn by one horse,
                    &amp;c. and no more, are to pay L.4. 10s. Every carriage with four wheels used
                    by any common carrier in the carriage of goods, where such carriage is only
                    occasionally used for the conveyance of passengers for hire, and in such manner
                    that the stamp-office duty, or any composition for the same, is not payable
                    under any license from the commissioners of stamps, is charged <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194747324" xml:id="kp-eb0707-7324-0006"/>L.2. 1 Os. per annum; and
                    where such carriage has less than four wheels, it is only charged L.l. 5s. per
                    annum. Any carriage with less than four wheels, each of which is of less
                    diameter than thirty inches, and not let for hire, drawn by a pony or mule not
                    exceeding twelve hands high, is exempt from duty.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hackney</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Coaches</hi> are
                    coaches stationed in the streets or other public places, and bound to carry
                    those who require them at certain fixed rates of hire, according to the distance
                    travelled. Vehicles of this description were first established in London in
                    1625, and in Edinburgh in 1773. The number of hackney coaches, chariots, and
                    cabriolets licensed in the metropolis on the 1st of January 1830 was 1265. The
                    rates of duty were L.2 per lunar month for each .carriage; and the produce of
                    the duties, including fines, was L.32,908. 18s. 6d. The fares, &amp;c. are
                    regulated conformably to the act 48 Geo. III. c. 87.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stage</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Coaches,</hi> as defined
                    in the act of parliament, 3 Geo. IV. c∙ 95, sect. 6, are carriages or vehicles
                    used, employed, or let out for the purpose of carrying passengers for hire, and
                    travelling at the rate of three or more miles in the hour, without regard to the
                    number of wheels, horses, or passengers, or whether the same be open or close,
                    provided each passenger be charged a separate and distinct fare. The above
                    definition applies to carriages either drawn by horseè or propelled by steam.
                    The latter species of vehicles are as yet exempt from taxation, but the
                    following duties have been imposed upon the former :—Any carriage or vehicle,
                    with two or more wheels, without springs, and drawn by one horse only, for every
                    mile which it shall be licensed to travel, one penny. Any carriage, &amp;c.
                    without springs, and drawn by two horses only, for every mile, &amp;c. two
                    pence. Any carriage, &amp;c. having springs, and .drawn by one horse only, for
                    every mile three half pence. Any carriage, &amp;c. drawn by two horses only,
                    having springs, not distinguishing between inside and outside passengers, per
                    mile three pence. And any carriage, &amp;c. as last mentioned, drawn by three or
                    more horses, for every mile four pence half-penny. A duty of L.5. 5s. a year is
                    also imposed upon every stage coach. For various statutes and regulations
                    relating both to stage and hackney coaches, and which make provision for the
                    safety and convenience of the passenger, see M‘Culloch’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commercial Dictionary,</hi> p. 264-5.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mail</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Coaches</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">are</hi> stage-coaches of a particular construction, which, for a
                    certain consideration, carry his majesty’s mails, are protected by a guard, and
                    subject to the regulations of the post-office.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Coach-making</hi> is a combination of crafts, such as are
                    very rarely united in one calling or trade. The technical names of those
                    composing the different branches are, body-makers, carriage-makers, wheelers,
                    spring-makers, axle-makers, smiths, trimmers, &amp;c. Painting is an important
                    part of the business; and those professing it are divided into body, carriage,
                    and heraldry or ornamental painters. These classes of workmen have each their
                    own department in the construction of a coach, and none of them can be dispensed
                    with. Under the general head of coachmaking a great variety of different kinds
                    of vehicles are produced, such as close coaches, landaus, landaulets, chariots,
                    phaetons, briskeys, gigs, &amp;c.; of the three kinds last named, there are
                    almost infinite varieties, both with regard to construction and the manner of
                    finishing. The fashion with respect to these is about as fluctuating and mutable
                    as that of dress. One thing is certain, however, that in neatness and general
                    utility the vehicles of the present day are superior to those of any former
                    period.</p>
                <p>Within the last ten years or so a great revolution has taken place in regard to
                    coach-making. For a few years before that period, coach-makers could not get
                    their coaches made short enough in the carriage, nor small enough in the body,
                    from the false notion, that being lighter, and easier drawn, they would answer
                    the purpose better. There can be no doubt that they were lighter, and probably
                    easier drawn, but it has been proved that shortness in the carriage not only
                    makes them harder to ride in, but also harder on the axles and springs, thus
                    rendering them more apt to break down.</p>
                <p>Noblemen’s and gentlemen’s carriages are now, however, made a great deal larger
                    in the body; the carriages themselves are also longer, and the wheels not so
                    high as those in use formerly. Coaches may be divided into two classes, namely,
                    gentlemen’s carriages, to which the above remarks refer, and road coaches. If a
                    revolution has taken place in regard to the former, much more has it done so in
                    regard to the latter. A few years ago road-coaches were made to weigh at least
                    twenty or twenty-five cwts., and often more, and were then constantly breaking
                    down. They were generally drawn by four horses, and carried, we believe, sixteen
                    passengers, besides driver and guard, the driver changing every stage. Now they
                    are constructed so as not to exceed twelve or fourteen cwts., and are drawn by
                    two horses, carry thirteen passengers, and travel in about one third less time
                    without changing the driver, unless the coach travels more than four or five
                    stages. A broken down road-coach is now a thing rarely heard of; and, except the
                    mail, they in general have no guard. Nay, more; while under the old system, they
                    were not only high set upon their carriages, but the outside passengers and
                    luggage were almost exclusively placed upon the top, and consequently they were
                    easily overset; while on the present system the bodies are placed low, and the
                    luggage deposited in large masses before and behind the vehicle. Above these sit
                    the outside passengers; so that the whole load, instead of top weight as before,
                    acts as ballast to prevent the carriage from oversetting, and hence the few
                    coach accidents of late, in comparison with those which used to occur under the
                    old system. It is proper to observe, however, that the great improvement in
                    road-making has in no small degree contributed to the safety and convenience of
                    travelling.</p>
                <p>The principal part of the coach-making business depends chiefly on the selection
                    of the materials for the construction of the work; and the first, and not the
                    least in importance, is the stock of wood. It requires a good deal of experience
                    to apportion this article so as to apply the different kinds of it to that part
                    of the work for which it is the best adapted. Ash is the kind of wood commonly
                    used in the frame-work both of body and carriage; and the quality best suited
                    for body wood is that of a mild and free nature, while for the carriage the wood
                    cannot be too strong or robust. Full-grown wood is best suited for both
                    purposes, because young wood, although of a tough nature, is found from
                    experience to fail sooner, and not to last so long as full-grown timber. But in
                    all cases it must be cut into planks before the log gets into a state of decay
                    after being felled. The planks must also be allowed to lie until they are
                    properly seasoned.</p>
                <p>After the frame-work is made, the lower part of the body is pannelled up with bay
                    mahogany of the softest kind. As the panneis have to be bent into peculiar
                    shapes, hard mahogany will not answer the purpose. Close coaches or chariots are
                    covered on the roof and upper quarters with leather dressed without grease, so
                    as to receive the painting; whilst the roof and upper quarters of landaus and
                    landaulets are, in order to afford facilities for opening, covered with leather
                    properly dressed in oil, and blackened by the currier upon the grain side, so as
                    not to require the help of the painter; but to keep it in this pliable state it
                    requires the constant care of the coachman. The kinds <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194747337" xml:id="kp-eb0707-7337-0007"/>of wood generally applied to
                    coach-wheel making are elm for the naves, oak for the spokes, and ash for the
                    felloes; but beech felloes are often used; and it is the opinion of the writer,
                    formed upon experience, that beech, when cut into felloes from the log shortly
                    after it is felled, and kept until these become dry before being put upon
                    wheels, is decidedly the best. Indeed nothing but properly seasoned wood can be
                    applied to any purpose in the construction of a coach.</p>
                <p>A great improvement has of late years been introduced into the making of
                    coach-springs, from the quality of steel used in their construction. Formerly
                    nothing was used but German steel, which from its hardness was more apt to snap
                    than the English steel now employed for that purpose. The latter, with superior
                    elasticity, combines a strength that enables, the spring-maker to fabricate his
                    springs at least one third lighter than formerly, while they stand equal
                    fatigue, with less risk of breaking. Although axles are at present in a high
                    state of perfection, yet no material improvements have been made upon, them for
                    these twenty or twenty-five years. The kinds of axles now chiefly used are the
                    common or plain axle, the mail-coach patent, and the Collinge patent, which
                    last, when properly executed, is found to be the best for retaining the oil, as
                    they are generally found to be in good order in this respect after having
                    performed a journey of 500 or 600 miles. The iron mounting of coach-work
                    requires the skill of most experienced smiths; for, besides the solidity
                    required, a considerable degree of taste to form the shapes and sets of the
                    different parts is necessary. No branch of the coach-making business contributes
                    more to the elegance of the vehicle than that of the painter. His colours must
                    be of the best quality, and unadulterated, as they have to stand exposure in all
                    weathers. The varnish used is made from gum, and is called copal varnish, of
                    which there are two kinds, the finest being used for finishing the body, and the
                    second for finishing the carriage. Heraldry painting is a very fine art, and
                    requires a knowledge of heraldry, combined with considerable practice, before
                    perfection can be attained. The business of the trimmer is to make and put in
                    the linings, mount the coachman’s seat, steps, &amp;c., and put on the leather
                    work, bead-fing, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Coaches built in London are
                    reputed the most perfect of their kind <hi rend="italic">of any</hi> in the
                    world.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Coach,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Couch,</hi> is also a
                    sort of chamber or apart- • ment in a large ship of war near the stern. The
                    floor of it is formed by the aftmost part of the quarter-deck, and the roof of
                    it by the poop. It is generally the habitation of the captain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
