<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0021-0014-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">URUGUAY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 14</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="25" ref="fastgeo:1202667">Uruguay</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204928">California</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205150">Florida</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1066737">Plate</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1066824">Plating</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1939238">Negroes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn8h">Plate</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n21/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">URUGUAY</label>. The republic of Uruguay, officially known as
                    the <hi rend="smallcaps">Oriental Republic of the Uruguay,</hi> and long locally
                    called the <hi rend="smallcaps">Banda Oriental</hi> (meaning the land on the
                    eastern side of the large river from which the country takes its modern name),
                    is the smallest independent state in South America. It runs conterminous with
                    the southern border of the empire of Brazil and lies between 30°</p>
                <p>and 35° S. lat. and 53° 25' and 57° 42' W. long.; its area is 73,185 square
                    miles. The country is in some sense a peninsula, having a seaboard on the
                    Atlantic Ocean of 120 miles, a shore line to the south on the river Plate of 235
                    miles, and another of 270 miles along the Uruguay on the west. The boundaries
                    separating it from Rio Grande do Sul, a province of Brazil, are Lake Mirim, the
                    rivers Chuy, Yaguaron, and Cuareim, and a <hi rend="italic">cuchilla</hi> or low
                    range of hills called Santa Ana. The extent of the northern frontier from the
                    Cuareim to the bar of the Chuy on the coast of the Atlantic is 450 miles.
                    Uruguay is intersected nearly from west to north-east by the river Negro and its
                    affluent the Yi. The Uruguay (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate River,</hi> vol.
                    xix. p. 187) is navigable all the year by steamers from the island of Martin
                    Garcia at the mouth to Salto (200 miles). Above this place the navigation is
                    interrupted by rapids. The ordinary volume of water in the Uruguay averages 11
                    millions of cubic feet per minute. The Negro, of which the principal port is the
                    city of Mercedes, is the only important and to any practical extent navigable
                    inland river. Others are navigable for short distances and by steamers of light
                    draught. Besides the rivers mentioned, the chief streams are the Santa Lucia,
                    which falls into the Plate a little west of Montevideo; the Queguay in Paysandú;
                    and the Cebollati, rising in the sierras in Minas and flowing into Lake Mirim.
                    These rivers as well as the Uruguay are fed by innumerable smaller streams or
                    “arroyos,” many of which have the importance and sometimes the names of rivers,
                    such as the Arapey in Salto, the Dayman in Pay-sandú, the Yaguary (an affluent
                    of the Negro) in Tacua-rembó, the Arroyo Grande between the departments of
                    Soriano and San José, and the San José (an affluent of the Santa Lucia). None of
                    the sierras or mountains in Uruguay exceed (or perhaps even attain) a height of
                    2000 feet; but, contrasting in their tawny colour with the grassy undulating
                    plains, they loom up high and are often picturesque. They are ramifications of a
                    range which, breaking away from the Andes in about 20° S. lat., reaches the
                    frontier of Uruguay in 32°. Here the chain divides, forming the Cuchilla de
                    Haedo on the north and west and the Cuchilla Grande on the south and east. In
                    the departments of Minas and Maldonado the second range takes the name of the
                    Ghost Mountains. No accurate geological survey has yet been made, but it is
                    known that the hills in the north are chiefly gneiss and granite and in other
                    parts porphyry and sandstone. The hilly districts in the north and east contain
                    minerals of many kinds, including gold, lead, copper, agate, amethyst,
                    alabaster, and marble. The limestone, granite, and marble quarries have some
                    commercial value; but so far little progress has been made in the working of
                    metallic veins. For the gold mines, see below.</p>
                <p>The seat of government is the city of <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> at the entrance of the river Plate. The harbour and
                    roadstead of that port form the only good natural refuge for shipping for
                    hundreds of miles south of Rio de Janeiro.</p>
                <p>Uruguay has a healthy climate. Endemic diseases are unknown and epidemics are
                    rare. According to the tables of mortality for 1882, out of a total of 9640
                    deaths 45 were of persons over 100 years of age. In the interior, away from the
                    sea and the shores of the great rivers, the temperature frequently rises in
                    summer as high as 86° Fahr. and in winter falls as low as 35° ∙6 Fahr. In the
                    districts bordering on the coast the thermometer seldom falls below 37°; and
                    only for a few moments and at long intervals has it been known to rise as high
                    as 105°. The annual rainfall is stated to be more than twice that of Paris (19
                    68 inches). This arises not from the frequency of rain but from the greater
                    quantity which falls in a given time. Observations made during the years 1842 to
                    1852 inclusive showed that there were in Montevideo in the summer
                    season—November, December, and January—701 fine days, 14∙1 cloudy, and 6∙1 wet;
                    in winter—May, June, and July—there were 54∙3 fine, 27∙1 cloudy, and 10∙6 wet
                    days.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n24/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0024-0015"/>
                <p>The pastoral wealth of Uruguay as of the neighbouring Argentine Republic is due
                    to the fertilizing constituents of “pampa mud,” geologically associated with
                    gigantic antediluvian animals, whose fossil remains are found abundantly in
                    those regions. The country is rich in hard woods, suitable for cabinet work and
                    certain building purposes. The principal trees are the alder, aloe, palm,
                    poplar, acacia, willow, and eucalyptus (recently introduced). The “montes,” by
                    which are understood plantations as well as native thickets, produce amongst
                    other woods the algarrobo, a poor imitation of oak; the guayabo, a substitute
                    for boxwood; the quebracho, of which the red kind is compared to sandalwood; and
                    the urunday, black and white, not unlike rosewood. Indigenous palms grow in the
                    valleys of the Sierra José Ignacio, also to some extent in the departments of
                    Minas, Maldonado, and Paysandú. The myrtle, rosemary, mimosa, and the
                    scarlet-flowered ceibo are amongst the plants commonly seen. The valleys within
                    the hill ranges are fragrant with aromatic shrubs. In the plains below the
                    swards are gay with the scarlet and white verbena and other wild flowers of
                    brilliant hues. The country abounds in medicinal plants. The sarsaparilla even
                    colours the water of the Rio Negro and gives to it its name—the “black
                    river.”</p>
                <p>Amongst the wild animals the tiger or ounce—called in the Guarani language the
                    “ja-gua” or “big dog”—and the puma are found on the frontier of Brazil and on
                    the wooded islets and banks of the larger rivers. The tapir, fox, deer, wild
                    cat, wild dog, carpincho or water hog, and a few small rodents nearly complete
                    the list of quadrupeds. A little armadillo, the mulita, must be mentioned as the
                    living representative of the antediluvian giants, the mylodon, mastodon,
                    megatherium, &amp;c. The ostrich— <hi rend="italic">Rhea americana—</hi> roams
                    everywhere in the plains; and there are a few specimens of the vulture tribe, a
                    native crow (lean, tall, and ruffed), partridges, and quails. Parakeets are
                    plentiful in the “montes,” and the lagoons swarm with waterfowl of all
                    descriptions. The most esteemed is the “pato real,” a large duck. Of the birds
                    of bright plumage the humming bird and the cardinal—the scarlet, the yellow, and
                    the white—are the most attractive. The fish of the lagoons and streams are
                    coarse, and some of them primitive in type; but two or three kinds, found
                    generally in the large rivers, are much prized. The varieties of fish on the sea
                    coast are many and excellent; 130 species are known. More than 2000 species of
                    insects have been classified. The scorpion is rarely seen; but large and
                    venomous spiders are common. The principal reptiles are a lizard, a tortoise,
                    the “vivora de la cruz,” a dangerous viper, so called from marks like a cross on
                    its head, and the rattlesnake, this last in Maldonado and the stony lands of Las
                    Minas.</p>
                <p>At the commencement of the 19th century the population of Montevideo and the
                    surrounding territory was estimated by Azara at 30,000, one-half of these being
                    given to the city of Montevideo. This total seems not to have included what
                    remained of the indigenous inhabitants in the north and west, though the Indian
                    population of the Jesuit missions before these were destroyed, about the year
                    1767, was known to be very numerous. But the aborigines have now completely
                    disappeared. They have been supplanted by half-breeds, from whom the class known
                    as gauchos are mostly recruited. The gauchos are now being supplanted by
                    European immigrants and their progeny. In 1829, the epoch of the declaration of
                    independence, the population is stated to have numbered 74,000, and in 1852,
                    after the great war, 131,969. In 1860 the number had risen to 221,300 and in
                    1873 to 450,000. Comparatively recent estimates place it between 450,000 and
                    700,000, the latest official estimate being 551,768; but no formal census has
                    yet been taken. In the eighteen departments of the state the proportion of
                    foreigners is 25∙41 per cent. of the population (in the department of Montevideo
                    42∙29 per cent. and in the others 24∙66 per cent.), consisting of 39,780
                    Spaniards, 36,303 Italians, 20,178 Brazilians, 15,546 Argentinians, 14,375
                    French (principally Basques), 2772 English, 2125 Germans, and 9143 of other
                    nations. The density of the population in the metropolitan department is 365
                    inhabitants per square mile; in the whole republic it is 4∙83, in the
                    agricultural department of Canelones 27∙37, and in the remote departments of
                    Tacuarembó and Rivera about 1∙6. In respect of numbers the males have a slight
                    preponderance over the females. Of the children 20∙23 per cent. are
                    illegitimate, in the metropolitan department 7∙73 and in the rural departments
                    23∙24. Illegitimate births have recently decreased, a fact which may be
                    explained by the institution of civil marriage and by the appointment of
                    registrars in the remote country districts. Marriages take place at the rate of
                    6∙8 per 1000. The death-rate is only 16∙5 per 1000.</p>
                <p>The country is divided into eighteen departments, of which that of Montevideo is
                    the smallest, although it contains one-fourth of the total population. Adjoining
                    this is Canelones; and in a northerly direction are those of Florida, Durazno,
                    Tacuarembó, and Rivera, the last-named bordering on Brazil. To the eastward on
                    the Atlantic are Maldonado and Rocha, and north and west of these Minas, Treinta
                    y Tres, and Cerro Largo. To the west, along the Plate and Uruguay, are San José,
                    Colonia, Soriano, Rio Negro, and Paysandú; and farther north towards the
                    Brazilian frontier are Salto and Artigas. The principal inland town is San José.
                    The chief ports, besides Montevideo, are Salto, Paysandú, Fray Bentos, Mercedes,
                    Colonia, and Maldonado.</p>
                <p>More than two centuries ago the Banda Oriental was looked upon by the Spanish
                    colonies on the opposite banks of the Plate and Uruguay as a station for the
                    breeding of live stock and the cutting of timber and firewood. And at this day,
                    in spite of the thriving foreign trade of Montevideo, it still partakes largely
                    of this character. It boasts of 20,000,000 sheep—perhaps 14,000,000 would be
                    nearer the mark—and 8,000,000 head of cattle. The country being in general
                    pastoral, sheep and cattle grazing is the main occupation of the people; the
                    sheep flourish best in the southern and western departments, whilst the
                    principal cattle districts are towards the north and east. More than two-thirds
                    of the public wealth, estimated variously between £80,000,000 and £120,000,000,
                    consist of land, live stock, and rural properties. Ninety-six per cent. of the
                    exports of the country consists of live stock and their produce—wool, hides,
                    horns, hair, sheepskins, tallow, grease, bones, bone-ash, and jerked beef. More
                    than half the fixed property and commercial capital is in the hands of
                    foreigners. At Fray Bentos, in the department of Rio Negro, is the Liebig
                    factory of extract of meat; at Colonia there is a branch of the River Plate
                    Frozen Meat Company. But, apart from these, and some breweries, flour-mills,
                    tanneries, establishments in Montevideo for the making of boots and shoes and
                    clothing, and a few local industries, unnaturally fostered by high import
                    duties, there are no manufactures to speak of. Agriculture is still in a
                    promising infancy. Latterly it has made great strides; yet the export of
                    agricultural produce appears to be relatively insignificant. At intervals during
                    the last twenty years agricultural settlements (colonies) have been established
                    with great success in different departments, but principally in Colonia, where
                    the settlers are mostly Italians and Swiss. These prosperous colonies have
                    already in Colonia outgrown the space originally allotted; but owing to the
                    irregular and illegal appropriation of the public lands there is no more land to
                    bestow on settlers, native or foreign, except at the exorbitant rates demanded
                    by private owners and speculators.</p>
                <p>At Cuñapirú in Tacuarembó gold was accidentally discovered in 1842. The mines
                    have been worked at intervals since 1867, but, partly owing to difficulties of
                    communication, with indifferent success. But gold-mining seems to have lately
                    assumed a more hopeful aspect, owing to the employment of improved and
                    economical machinery introduced by a French company. The metals of Uruguay are
                    found in two quite distinct systems of hills. The Cuñapirú mines are in the
                    Santa Ana range, the auriferous quartz being found in thin layers embedded in
                    rocks of red porphyry. The formation of the system in general resembles that of
                    the gold-producing regions in Brazil, California, and Australia. The Pan de
                    Azucar (Sugar-Loaf Mountain), near the south coast of Maldonado, forms the
                    extremity of a second system, which has its origin as far north as Pernambuco in
                    Brazil; as developed in Uruguay it is Huronian, limestone and slate being
                    superposed on the gneiss and granite. The metals of this system are principally
                    silver, lead, copper, and an argentiferous lead, which in earlier times the
                    Spaniards mistook for silver. Two copper mines at the foot of the Pan de Azucar
                    are now in active operation.</p>
                <p>Since the beginning of the 19th century the value of the exports and imports has
                    increased twenty-fold, and with some relapses has more than doubled in the last
                    twenty years. In 1881 the total value was £8,116,680, and in 1885 £10,750,747.
                    The value of the exports is always a little in excess of that of the imports.
                    Within the last ten years the number of vessels entering the port of Montevideo
                    has increased only about 10 per cent., whereas the total tonnage has increased
                    100 per cent., owing to the large ocean steamers which trade with the port or
                    make it a place of call. A few years ago the imports from Great Britain amounted
                    to about a third of the whole, and the exports to the same country to about
                    one-fourth of the whole. But much of the produce from the river Plate countries
                    in general which formerly was shipped to England or to Antwerp now goes direct
                    to France or to Hamburg and Bremen.</p>
                <p>Telegraph lines, with a total length of 661 miles, exist in most of the
                    departments. Submarine cables communicate with Buenos Ayres and the ports of
                    Brazil, and thence with Europe. The railways are comprehended in three main
                    systems, the central, northwestern, and eastern; their combined length barely
                    reaches 300 miles. There are no public roads in the country; but communication
                    in the more inhabited parts is easily effected over the nearly level grassy
                    plains.</p>
                <p>The system of national education is gratuitous and compulsory. The number of
                    school children is over 30,000, about 5∙4 per cent. of the total population. The
                    teaching at the national schools is irrespective of religious creed or
                    denomination. In higher education much has yet to be accomplished. There is a
                    school of arts and trades in the capital. The university of Montevideo, founded
                    in 1838, numbers about 1300 students. The state religion is Roman Catholic; but
                    all sects enjoy complete toleration, unless a decided non-toleration of the
                    Jesuits be regarded as an exception to the rule.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n25/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0025-0016"/>
                <p>The legislative power of the state rests with the general assembly, consisting of
                    two chambers, one of senators (18) and one of representatives (51). The deputies
                    of the lower house are elected annually and directly by the people, one deputy
                    for every 3000 of the population, or any fraction not less than 2000. One
                    senator is named for each department. The executive power is exercised by the
                    president of the republic, who is elected by the general assembly. The judicial
                    power is vested in a superior court, composed of two courts of appeal, which
                    temporarily supply the place of a supreme court of justice, not yet created.</p>
                <p>The permanent army on a peace footing consists of 3260 men. The national guard
                    numbers about 20,000. On an emergency the Government could put into the field
                    30,000 men. The regular troops are well armed and accoutred after the European
                    fashion. The navy consists of a few small steamers and gunboats.</p>
                <p>The estimated revenue for 1886-87 was £2,775,362 (about two-thirds from custom
                    dues, the rest from taxes on property and from stamps, trade licences, &amp;c.
                    ). Of the estimated expenditure about two-fifths are devoted to the payment of
                    the interest on the public debt, which in 1883 amounted to £11,127,000. On 1st
                    July 1886 the debt was officially stated to be £14,718,089.</p>
                <p>The history of Uruguay dates from 1512, when Juan Diaz de Solis entered the
                    Paraná-guazú or “sealike” estuary of the Plate and landed about 70 miles east of
                    the present city of Montevideo. Uruguay at that time was inhabited by Indians,
                    of whom the dominant tribe was called Charrúas, a people described as physically
                    strong and well-formed, and endowed with a natural nobility of character. Their
                    habits were simple, and they were disfigured neither by the worst crimes nor by
                    the primitive superstitions of savages. They are said to have revealed no
                    vestiges of religion. The Charrúas are generally classified as a yellow-skinned
                    race, of the same family as the Pampa Indians; but they are also represented as
                    tanned almost black by the sun and air, without any admixture of red or yellow
                    in their complexions. Almost beardless, and with thin eyebrows, they had on
                    their heads thick, black, lustrous hair, which neither fell off nor turned grey
                    until the possessors reached the age of eighty. They lived principally upon
                    fish, venison, and honey. In the Guarani language “Charrúa” means turbulent, and
                    by their enemies the Charmas were accounted as such, and even ferocious,
                    although admitted to be generous to their captives. They were a curiously
                    taciturn and reticent race. Their weapons were the bow and arrow and stones.</p>
                <p>Solis, on his second visit, 1515-16, was slain by the Charmas in Colonia. Eleven
                    years later Ramon, the lieutenant of Sebastian Cabot, was defeated by the same
                    tribe. In 1603 they destroyed in a pitched battle a veteran force of Spaniards
                    under Saavedra. During the next fifty years three unsuccessful attempts were
                    made by the Spaniards to subdue this courageous people. The real conquest of
                    Uruguay was commenced under Philip III. by the Jesuit missions. It was gradually
                    consummated by the military and commercial settlements of the Portuguese, and
                    subsequently by the Spaniards, who established themselves formally in Montevideo
                    under General Zavala in 1729, and finally demolished the rival Portuguese
                    settlement in Colonia in 1777. From 1750 Montevideo enjoyed a provincial
                    government independent of that of Buenos Ayres. The American rebellion, the
                    French Revolution, and the British invasions of Montevideo and Buenos Ayres
                    (1806-7) under Generals Auchmuty and Whitelock all contributed to the final
                    extinction of the Spanish power on the river Plate. During the war of
                    independence Montevideo was taken in 1814 by the Buenos-Ayrean general Alvear. A
                    long straggle for dominion in Uruguay between Brazil and the revolutionary
                    Government of Buenos Ayres was concluded in 1828, through the mediation of Great
                    Britain, Uruguay being declared a free and independent state. The republic was
                    formally constituted in 1830. Subsequently Juan Manuel Rosas, dictator of Buenos
                    Ayres, interfered in the intestine quarrels of Uruguay; and Montevideo was
                    besieged by his forces, allied with the native partizans of General Oribe, for
                    nine years (1842-51). From the era of its independence to about 1870 the history
                    of Uruguay is a long record of foreign invasions and intrigues, financial rain,
                    and political folly and crime.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Album de la Reρublica oriental del Uruguay,</hi> by F. A.
                    Berro, A. de Vedia, and Μ. de Pena (Montevideo, 1882); <hi rend="italic">Anuariο
                    Estadistico</hi> for 1885 and preceding years, official documents and reports
                    published by the Government of Uruguay; Bauza, <hi rend="italic">La Dominacion
                    Española en el Uruguay</hi> (Montevideo, 1880); G. E. Bordoni, <hi rend="italic"
                    >La Repubblica dell' Uruguay</hi> (Milan, 1885); Μ. G. and E. T. Mulhall, <hi
                    rend="italic">Handbook of the River Plate</hi> (London, 1885); <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Republic of Uruguay</hi> (London, 1883); an official and statistical
                    pamphlet by Lomba; <hi rend="italic">Reports</hi> by W. Gifford Palgrave (1885
                    and 1887). (J. GR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
