<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0018-0011-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">URI (9th edition, volume 24, page 11)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03xx31">Shields</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n18/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">URI</label>,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>The name is probably connected with the same obscure
                            root as Urseren and Reuss, and is popularly derived from <hi
                                rend="italic">Urochs,</hi> “wild bull,” a bull’s head having been
                            for ages borne on the cantonal shield.</p></note> one of the Forest
                    Cantons of Switzerland, ranks as fourth in the Confederation. It comprises the
                    upper basin of the Reuss from its source to the Lake of Lucerne, the southern
                    arm of which is also within the canton. Its total area is 415∙4 square miles; of
                    these 184∙4 are classed as productive, 40∙3 are covered with forests, 44∙3
                    consist of glaciers, and 7∙7 of the lake. The highest point in the canton is the
                    Galenstock (11,802 feet). The population in 1880 amounted to 23,694 (men having
                    a majority of 3000 over women), showing an increase of 7649, or 39∙4 per cent.,
                    since 1870, owing to the St Gotthard Railway. German is the native tongue of
                    18,024 persons, Italian of 5313. The canton has always been very strongly Roman
                    Catholic (23,149 in 1880). It was included up to 1814 in the diocese of
                    Constance (except the valley of Urseren, which was in that of Chur), and since
                    then has formed part of no diocese, but is provisionally administered by the
                    bishop of Chur. In Uri the limits of the ecclesiastical parishes are the same as
                    those of the civil communes. The capital is Altdorf (2901 inhabitants).
                    Göschenen (2990) and Wasen (2744) have increased since the opening of the St
                    Gotthard Railway (1880), which runs through the greater part of the canton. The
                    inhabitants are occupied in agricultural and pastoral pursuits, and are very
                    saving and industrious. The main valley is fertile, but the side glens are very
                    wild. Education is still very backward and largely in the hands of the priests;
                    but an improvement was made in 1885. The main characteristics of the people are
                    extreme conservatism and a passionate attachment to their religion.</p>
                <p>Uri is first mentioned in history in 732 as the place to which Eto, abbot of
                    Reichenau, was banished. For the early history of the canton, see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Switzerland,</hi> vol. xxii. pp. 783-787. In 1410 a
                    perpetual alliance was made with the upper valley of Urseren or Val Orsera, the
                    latter being allowed its own headman and assembly, and courts under those of
                    Uri, with which it was not fully incorporated till 1803. In 1440 Uri alone won
                    the Val Leventina for good, the title being confirmed by a treaty of 1466 with
                    the duke of Milan and by the bloody fight of Giornico (1478). At the
                    Reformation, Uri clung to the old faith (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Switzerland,</hi> vol. xxii. pp. 790-791). In 1798 on the formation of the
                    Helvetic republic Uri lost all its Italian possessions. In September 1799
                    Suwaroff and the Russian army, having crossed the St Gotthard to Altdorf, were
                    forced by the French to pass over into Schwyz, instead of sailing down the lake
                    to Lucerne. In 1803 Uri became an independent canton again, with Urseren, but
                    without the Val Leventina. It tried hard to bring back the old state of things
                    in 1814-15, and opposed all attempts at reform, joining the League of Sarnen in
                    1832 to maintain the pact of 1815, opposing the proposed revision of the pact,
                    and being one of the members of the Sonderbund in 1843. Despite defeat in the
                    war of 1847, Uri voted against the federal constitution of 1848, and by a
                    crushing majority against that of 1874. The existing constitution of Uri is that
                    framed in 1850 and amended in 1851, 1872, 1879, and 1881. The “landesgemeinde,”
                    composed of all male citizens of twenty years of age, meets annually on 1st May,
                    and is the supreme legislative assembly. There is a subordinate legislative
                    assembly (landrath), consisting of the landammann or headman and his deputy, 4
                    of the members of the executive, and 70 elected members (1 for every 300 of the
                    population), which drafts bills and passes laws provisionally in case of
                    necessity. The executive consists of 9 members—the landammann, his deputy, and
                    the treasurer, with 6 elected members. By an immemorial custom 7 men of 7
                    different families, bearing different names, can cause an extraordinary meeting
                    of the assembly of their “gemeinde” to be summoned, or call on the landrath to
                    do the same in the case of the “landesgemeinde.”</p>
                <p>See K. F. Lusser’s <hi rend="italic">Gesch. des Kantοns Uri</hi> (1862).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
