<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0448-0433-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HYDROGEN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 12, page 433</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:964990">Hydrogen</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:965072">Hydrogenation</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1049655">Oxygenators</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1049616">Oxygen</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b41j97c0n">Hydrogen</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wr3t">Oxygen</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55q5x">Liquids</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr4v">Box</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n448/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HYDROGEN</label> (from ΰδ <hi rend="italic">ωp,</hi> water,
                    and <hi rend="italic">γεννάω,</hi> to generate) is a chemical element which in
                    the free state occurs in volcanic gases, but exists for the most part in
                    combination with oxygen as water. As its elemental characteristics and the chief
                    compounds of hydrogen have already been described in the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. pp. 478, 483, 491, 499, 544, &amp;c.,
                    it is here only necessary to refer to the liquefaction of gaseous hydrogen.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The statement in the article
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. p. 479, that hydrogen has never
                    been liquefied, was true at the date of publication.</p></note></p>
                <p>At the close of 1877 and in the beginning of 1878, not only hydrogen, but all the
                    so-called permanent gases, were reduced to the liquid state, an achievement the
                    more remarkable as it was the result of the simultaneous but entirely
                    independent labours of two distinguished physicists, M. Cailletet of
                    C⅛a∣illon-sur-Seine and M. Pictet of Geneva. The experiments of the former, who
                    clearly demonstrated the possibility of liquefying acetylene, carbonic oxide,
                    hydrogen, methane, nitric oxide, nitrogen, and oxygen, are described in detail
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Chimie et</hi><hi rend="italic">de Physique,</hi> ser. 5, vol. xv. p. 132;
                    those of M. Pictet, who operated only upon oxygen and hydrogen, are detailed in
                    the same journal, ser. 5, vol. xiii. p. 145. The instrumental means employed by
                    them were very different, as will be evident from the following description.</p>
                <p>Μ. Cailletet’s apparatus is represented in the annexed sketch (fig. 1). The gas
                    under experiment is contained in a stout glass tube of narrow bore of the form
                    shown in fig. 2.</p>
                <p>To fill this tube with gas, both ends being open, a globule of mercury is first
                    introduced at the lower curved extremity; the tube is then placed in a nearly
                    horizontal position, the curved extremity is connected with the holder
                    containing the gas, or with the apparatus in which the gas is being evolved, by
                    means of caoutchouc tubing, and a current of the pure dry gas is passed through
                    the tube until the air is entirely expelled; this being effected, the point
                    opposite to the curved extremity is sealed in the blowpipe flame; the tube is
                    then brought into a vertical position, so that the globule of mercury closes the
                    lower extremity, the caoutchouc tube is withdrawn, and the tube AA thus filled
                    is screwed into its place in the cylinder B. The lower part of the cylinder
                    contains mercury, the upper part water. The pressure is exerted by forcing a
                    plunger into a massive steel cylinder· filled with water by means of the screw
                    and wheel seen on the left in fig. 1, the water being forced from this cylinder
                    through the fine coiled tube into the upper part of the cylinder in which the
                    glass tube is fixed; by rapidly turning the wheel seen on the right of the
                    figure, a valve may be opened, allowing of the escape of the water, and thus the
                    pressure on the gas may be suddenly withdrawn. The pressure to which the gas is
                    submitted is measured by means of either of the manometers seen on the right.
                    The gas may be cooled by surrounding the tube A with liquid sulphur dioxide,
                    carbon dioxide, or nitrous oxide, and the deposition of ice on the outside of
                    the cylinder containing the refrigerating liquid is prevented by covering it
                    with a glass cylinder or bell jar, under which is placed some desiccating
                    material. By strongly compressing a gas in this apparatus, and then suddenly
                    relieving it from pressure, an enormous reduction in its temperature is
                    effected, owing to the sudden expansion of the gas, and it is under these
                    circumstances that liquefaction takes place in cases where pressure alone is
                    ineffective. On submitting hydrogen to a pressure of nearly 300 atmospheres, and
                    then suddenly withdrawing the pressure, Μ. Cailletet observed the formation of a
                    fine mist in the interior of the tube; the experiments of Andrews and his own
                    previous observations had shown that this result afforded incontestable proof of
                    the presence of liquid, if not of solid, particles.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n449/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0449-0434"/>
                <p>The general disposition of Μ. Pictet’s apparatus is seen in fig. 3. It is o' a
                    much more complex character, but permits of the experiment being made on a
                    comparatively very large scale. The condensation of the gas is effected in a
                    copper tube of narrow bore, connected at the one end with a manometer capable of
                    indicating pressures up to 800 atmospheres, and with a fine steel stop-cock, and
                    at the other with a very strong wrought-iron vessel in which the hydrogen is
                    generated by heating a perfectly dry mixture of potassium formate with potassium
                    hydroxide; these two substances enter into reaction in accordance with the
                    equation HCOOK + H0K= K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> CO <hi rend="subscript">
                    3</hi> + H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, the hydrogen being evolved in a
                    perfectly regular manner when the temperature is maintained at 225°. The
                    dimensions of the condensation tube are—internal diameter <hi rend="superscript"
                    > ,</hi> 001 metre, external diameter Ό15 metre, length 4 <hi rend="superscript"
                    > ,</hi> 16 metres; and the retort has a capacity of 1659 cubic centimetres. The
                    charge introduced consisted of 500 grammes potassium hydroxide and 1251 grammes
                    potassium formate. The condensation tube is surrounded with a wider tube
                    containing condensed carbon dioxide or nitrous oxide; these tubes are enclosed
                    in the lower box seen in the sketch. The upper box contains a tubular
                    arrangement in which carbon dioxide or nitrous oxide from the gasholder is
                    reduced to the liquid state. The pumps are such as are used in ice-making
                    machines, one of each pair being an exhausting, the other a condensing pump; one
                    pair of these pumpsis employed in condensing and volatilizing the sulphur
                    dioxide, and the other in condensing and volatilizing the carbon dioxide or
                    nitrous oxide. Figs. 4 and 5 show the apparatus in vertical section and in
                    plan.</p>
                <p>In working the apparatus, in the first place liquid sulphur dioxide from the
                    reservoir seen between the first pair of pumps is charged into the outer tube of
                    the condenser in the upper box, and is caused rapidly to evaporate by the action
                    of the exhausting pump in connexion with the tube, while the other pump serves
                    to recondense it in the reservoir, which is a kind of tubular boiler provided
                    with a cold water circulation. The temperature of the liquid sulphur dioxide is
                    thus reduced to - 65° C.; on allowing the carbon dioxide or nitrous oxide to
                    enter the inner tube of the condenser thus cooled, it begins to liquefy under a
                    pressure of about 4 atmospheres, and the condensation of the whole of the gas is
                    effected at a pressure of from 4 to 7 atmospheres, the temperature of the liquid
                    sulphur dioxide fluctuating between - 65° and - 50°. The liquid carbon
                    dioxide</p>
                <p>(or nitrous oxide) thus obtained is then allowed to pass into the tube
                    surrounding the condensation tube, and by the action of the second exhausting
                    pump it is caused to evaporate so quickly that it solidifies. The temperature
                    may thus be reduced to - 120° or even - 140°.</p>
                <p>In describing his first experiment with hydrogen with this apparatus, Μ. Pictet
                    states that the pressure, having risen gradually during about 40 minutes, became
                    stationary at about 650 atmospheres; on then opening the stop-cock, the orifice
                    being illuminated by a powerful electric light, an opaque jet of a highly
                    characteristic steel-blue tint was seen to issue forth. At the same moment, a
                    sharp hissing noise like that produced on plunging a red-hot bar of iron into
                    water was heard, and simultaneously a highly characteristic rustling noise on
                    the ground, recalling the sound of small seed falling. Moreover, the jet was not
                    continuous as in the case of oxygen, but intermittent, each projection of matter
                    being attended with the peculiar πιstling noise alluded to; in fact, owing to
                    the great reduction in temperature, due to the sudden volatilization of the
                    liquid, portions became solidified in the tube. On closing the stop-cock after
                    several seconds, the pressure being still 370 atmo spheres, the pressure fell to
                    320 atmospheres, then slowly rose to 330 atmospheres, and remained constant for
                    several minutes; on now opening the stop-cock again, a jet issued of extremely
                    short duration, accompanied with the violent projection of solid particles, but
                    then nothing escaped although the pressure was 315 atmospheres, an indication
                    that the hydrogen had solidified in the interior of the tube. On ceasing to
                    aspirate from the tube surrounding the condensation tube, and thus allowing the
                    temperature of the latter to rise somewhat, discharges took place with
                    increasing frequency, until after about a quarter of an hour the pressure fell
                    to zero.</p>
                <p>Pictet thus succeeded in liquefying and solidifying hydrogen on January 10th,
                    1878, Cailletet having demonstrated its liquefaction on December 30th
                    previously.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n450/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0450-0435"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
