<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0581-0566-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HYGIENE (9th edition, volume 12, page 566)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c21">Mosaics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026687">Mosaics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026685">Mosaicism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n581/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HYGIENE</label> is the science, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Practical Hygiene</hi> the art, of preserving health. The name has been
                    adopted from the French, from which language it has also been introduced into
                    most other tongues; it is derived from the Greek vyι∈ια or vy«a, health.
                    Writings on health are among the oldest in the world, for the subject has
                    engaged the attention of the profoundest thinkers and the most renowned leaders
                    of men. We have only to point to the elaborate directions in the Mosaic laws for
                    the preservation of health through scrupulous attention to cleanliness, the
                    isolation of the sick, and extreme care in the use of wholesome articles of food
                    and drink. Throughout the whole of their history the Jews enjoyed a remarkable
                    immunity from epidemic disease, the most of the instances in which such disease
                    occurred being represented as those in which they departed from the law and
                    doubtless relaxed the wholesome vigilance enjoined by it. In mediaeval and
                    modern history they have often, even down to our own time, been spared the
                    ravages of epidemics, when their Christian neighbours were perishing around
                    them. Ignorant superstition often gave rise to the idea that they had poisoned
                    the wells, and they fell victims to the fanaticism of the times. It is highly
                    probable that the periodical cleansing of their dwellings, involved in the
                    thorough search for the leaven which preceded the yearly passover <hi
                        rend="italic">{Mishna,</hi> Pesachim, i. 11), had a notable influence in
                    preventing that continuous deposition of organic matter, which is no doubt one
                    most powerful factor in the production of zymotic disease. On the other hand,
                    the filthy habits of the Christian populations offered a premium to plagues of
                    every kind; for there is no parallel in ancient history to the terrible
                    invasions of disease which from time to time ravaged Europe down to quite recent
                    times.</p>
                <p>It is the province of hygiene to seek out and determine the causes of disease,
                    and to formulate rules for their prevention and removal. It may thus be called
                    also preventive medicine, although this term does not quite express all that
                    must be included. The progress of hygiene, such as it was, rested for many ages
                    upon an empirical basis, and indeed to a large extent this is still the case.
                    The subject has, however, in later times at least, been studied to considerable
                    advantage, although much remains to be done. Two centuries ago the mortality of
                    London was 80 per 1000—at the present day it is under 23. A century ago ships
                    could barely keep the sea for scurvy, whilst jails and hospitals were in many
                    cases the hotbeds of fatal disease; now those conditions are rectified, or at
                    least the means of rectifying them are known. Thirty years ago the English
                    troops at home died at the rate of 20 per 1000— now their death-rate is less
                    than one-half of this. A knowledge of the causes and modes of propagation of
                    disease being necessary in order to provide rules for its prevention, it is
                    obvious that hygiene must be largely dependent upon the advances made in
                    pathology and aetiology; hence the impossibility of any very marked progress in
                    former times, by reason of the imperfection of the collateral sciences, and the
                    want of the appliances more recently made available for inquiries of such a
                    difficult and recondite character. Within this century, however, and especially
                    within the last forty or fifty years, it has been possible to follow out the
                    subject on a more strictly scientific basis, and so to lay a foundation, at
                    least, on which to build a structure, which may one day entitle hygiene to a
                    place among the more exact sciences.</p>
                <p>The special subjects which hygiene embraces are the following:—I. Those which
                    concern the surroundings of man; such as meteorological conditions, roughly
                    included under the head of climate; the site or soil on which his dwelling is
                    placed; the character, materials, and arrangement of his dwelling; the air he
                    breathes; the cleansing of his dwelling, and the arrangements for the removal
                    therefrom of excreta and other effete matters.</p>
                <p>II. Those which concern the personal care of health; such as the food he eats and
                    the water and other beverages he drinks; clothing; work and exercise; personal
                    cleanliness; special habits, such as the use of tobacco, narcotics, &amp;c.;
                    control of sexual and other passions.</p>
                <p>III. Certain points not directly included in the above; such as the management of
                    infancy; the prevention of disease; the hygiene of the sick-chamber; and the
                    disposal of the dead.</p>
                <p>It is obvious that it is impossible to draw any hard and fast line in these
                    divisions, and that they must constantly run into and overlap each other. Such a
                    division, however, gives a general idea of the scope of the science, and a brief
                    consideration of the different sections will enable us to furnish a slight
                    sketch of the nature of the subject.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Meteorological</hi> or (so-called) <hi rend="italic"
                        >climatic</hi> conditions. Here, temperature and humidity are the two points
                    that obviously present themselves for consideration, but it is very difficult
                    indeed to separate their influence from those of soil or site. It is also
                    certain that much that has been attributed to climate is really due to other
                    causes. It may be laid down as a general principle that, if moderate care be
                    taken, man may preserve his health in almost any part of the world, although it
                    must be admitted that in some places, such as hot and moist climates, disease
                    causes appear to be more easily called into action than under colder or drier
                    conditions. Some diseases, such as yellow fever, appear to require a certain
                    temperature for their development and propagation; others, such as enteric
                    (commonly called “typhoid”) fever, appear to exist indiscriminately under any
                    meteorological conditions; others, such as cholera, although undoubtedly
                    originating in hot and moist countries, appear capable of being propagated in
                    most parts of the world. In some cases great heat and dryness arrest disease, as
                    used to be observed in Egypt, where the plague was commonly said to cease after
                    St John’s day. During the hot harmattan wind of the west coast of Africa
                    small-pox is arrested, and successful vaccination becomes impossible. To the
                    sick or delicate, meteorological conditions are of great importance, but this
                    part of the subject belongs more to the treatment of disease than to general
                    hygiene. To the healthy, meteorological conditions, however much they may affect
                    personal comfort, are of comparatively little moment as <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n582/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0582-0567"/> regards health, so long as reasonable care is
                    observed. In a healthy body an adaptation to circumstances rapidly takes place,
                    and an equilibrium is soon established. Thus, it used to be supposed that great
                    heat increased the temperature of the body, but later observations have shown
                    this to be erroneous, and that the balance is soon re-established by the process
                    of transpiration;—should this, however, be arrested, then a rise of temperature
                    may take place, and disease of a febrile character be established.</p>
                <p>2. The <hi rend="italic">soil</hi> or <hi rend="italic">site</hi> of the dwelling
                    is, however, of greater moment, and much that has been attributed to climate has
                    been more truly due to locality. Soils are generally divided into moist and dry,
                    permeable and impermeable, and again subdivided according to formation,
                    composition, slope, &amp;c. Healthy soils are those which are dry and permeable,
                    or which have such a slope as renders drainage easy; on the other hand, soils
                    which are flat, moist, and impermeable are generally unhealthy. Soils containing
                    much organic matter are to be avoided, such as alluvial soils generally, as well
                    as all marshy districts. The air in soils is generally more or less impure,
                    hence the unadvisability of occupying dwellings below the ground level or
                    situated immediately on its surface. The water in the soil is a question of
                    great importance, apart from the mere moisture. At varying distances from the
                    surface, but everywhere, there exists a great subterranean lake or sea, known as
                    the <hi rend="italic">ground-water</hi> or <hi rend="italic">water-table,</hi>
                    which is constantly in motion, both vertically and horizontally. Its horizontal
                    movement is towards the nearest water-course or towards the sea; its vertical
                    movement is determined by rainfall chiefly. Much importance has been attached to
                    it, and the following points may be considered as accepted by most hygienists
                    :—(1) a permanently high ground-water, that is, within 5 feet of the surface, is
                    bad, while a permanently low ground-water, that is, more than 15 feet from the
                    surface, is good; and (2) violent fluctuations are bad, even with an average low
                    ground-water; a comparatively high ground-water with moderate and slow
                    fluctuations may be healthy. According to the school of Pettenkofer, it is the
                    ground-water which determines the spread of certain forms of disease, such as
                    cholera and enteric fever. A previously high level, succeeded by a fall, with a
                    certain height of temperature in the soil-air, is the condition believed by them
                    to be the one most favourable for disease production. Healthy soils are the
                    granites, metamorphic rocks, clay-slate, limestone, sandstone, chalk, gravel,
                    and sand; unhealthy are—clay, sand and gravel with clay subsoil, alluvial soil,
                    and marsh-lands, with the exception of peatlands. Among the unhealthy soils
                    ought also to be included all “made” soils, particularly those that are formed
                    so often in towns from rubbish of all sorts. Such soils ought not to be occupied
                    as building sites for at least two years.</p>
                <p>3. The sanitation of <hi rend="italic">dwellings</hi> involves numerous points.
                    The site has been considered in the previous section, but the importance of
                    excluding soil emanations must be insisted upon. The placing of a dwelling in
                    any spot of ground tends to exert an extractive force upon the soil, because the
                    air of the dwelling is almost always warmer than the external air, and there is
                    therefore a constant danger of sucking up the more or less impure soil-air into
                    the dwelling. Not only is this a recognized source of disease, but fatal cases
                    of direct poisoning have sometimes resulted, as when coal-gas has -escaped into
                    the soil below or near a dwelling. An impervious foundation is therefore
                    necessary, although this precaution is too often neglected, even in high-class
                    dwellings. Houses ought to be so arranged that they may receive plenty of light,
                    not merely for work or convenience, but as a matter of health. Sunlight, for
                    full health, is as necessary as air, and this is now so strongly recognized in
                    America that in many of the hospitals in that country rooms are provided where
                    patients may take a “sun-bath.”</p>
                <p>The materials of which houses are built are various. Wooden dwellings have
                    advantages, but there is always the danger of fire. Brick or stone is most
                    commonly used, but very good dwellings may be made of concrete or even of mud.
                    Probably the best material is good, sound, well-burnt brick. Dryness must be
                    secured by means of damp-proof courses along the foundations, hollow walls, and
                    cementing or slate-hanging externally. Non-absorbent surfaces internally are
                    important, although some writers, such as Pettenkofer, &amp;c., have been
                    inclined to attribute the unhealthiness of dwellings to the impermeability of
                    the walls obstructing air change. But where air can pass, organic matter can
                    lodge and become a source of danger. It is better, therefore, to have
                    non-absorbent surfaces as much as possible, and to provide for ventilation in
                    other ways. Paint that can be washed is therefore better than paper; if the
                    latter is used it had better be glazed. Care should be taken to scrape off all
                    old papers beneath, as they and the paste used with them tend to decompose and
                    become injurious to health. Ceilings ought to be impervious as well as walls,
                    and floors ought to be made of well-fitting seasoned wood, caulked, and oiled or
                    varnished so as to make them water-tight.</p>
                <p>Proper cubic space is a matter of great importance, for upon it depends the
                    renewal of air. The air of an air-space can seldom be changed oftener than three
                    times an hour, hence the space ought to be large enough to allow of such rate of
                    change providing enough of air for respiratory purposes. The furniture of rooms,
                    especially sleeping rooms, ought not to be too massive; whilst curtains and
                    hangings too often form traps for dust and organic matter.</p>
                <p>The warming of houses is important, and is generally badly and wastefully done.
                    The open fire-place has great advantages, but it is in many cases insufficient.
                    Where any general system is employed it is better to warm the air in the room
                    itself, as by pipes conveying hot water or steam, than to warm it before
                    delivery. Overheated rooms are a source of ill-health. For sitting-rooms 60° to
                    65° is quite enough; for a study or work-room 60° is sufficient, even in some
                    cases less than this. A sleeping-room need never be above 60°, often with
                    advantage below it. Fresh air ought not to be sacrificed to temperature, except
                    under extreme circumstances. Dwellings should not be occupied for some time
                    after building, till they are thoroughly dry. Rheumatism, chest diseases,
                    &amp;c., are very apt to arise from neglect of this precaution.</p>
                <p>Scrupulous attention to cleanliness is necessary in dwellings, and there is
                    wisdom in their periodical vacation for a certain time, so as to let them lie
                    fallow, as it were, and interrupt the continuity of deposit of organic matter.
                    Dwellings ought to be scattered over as wide an area as possible, for statistics
                    show that sickness and death-rate are often inversely proportional to the amount
                    of area per head occupied by a community. The area per head in London is
                    estimated at double that of Paris and many other cities, whilst at the same time
                    its death-rate is smaller than that of any other large city in Europe.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Air</hi> is the prime necessity of life. Food or water may
                    be abstained from for a considerable time, and we may thus have an opportunity
                    of replacing either should we doubt its purity or wholesomeness, but the
                    atmosphere around us we must breathe or die. Hence the paramount necessity for
                    having it pure. But, although this is apparently so obvious, attention to its
                    importance has been very generally omitted. Air consists of a mechanical mixture
                    of oxygen and nitrogen, in the proportion of nearly 21 per cent, of the former
                    to 79 of the latter, with small quantities in addition of carbonic acid,
                    moisture, organic matter, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n583/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0583-0568"/> &lt;fcc. By respiration and combustion air
                    becomes vitiated, the oxygen diminishing and the carbonic acid and organic and
                    suspended matter increasing. Within certain limits the amount of carbonic acid
                    is in itself immaterial to health, but it is important as a measure of the
                    amount of organic matter, which is really the dangerous impurity. Air vitiated
                    by respiration is also much more dangerous than when the carbonic acid is partly
                    the result of combustion. It is now pretty generally admitted that air cannot be
                    con- -sidered as really good and fit for respiration in which the respiratory
                    impurity reckoned as carbonic acid much exceeds two parts in 10,000 by volume.
                    On the other hand, if air can be kept down to this point, the condition may be
                    looked upon as satisfactory. The amount of impurity given off by living beings
                    varies of course with size, weight, age, sex, and work, but it may be allowed
                    that under ordinary circumstances it amounts to about six cubic feet of carbonic
                    acid per head in ten hours during repose. This requires an hourly supply per
                    head of 3000 cubic feet of fresh air for its dilution, and this amount should be
                    largely increased during work or in sickness (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Hospital).</hi> The diseases which have been shown to arise from the
                    effects of vitiated air are widely prevalent, including such as consumption and
                    other forms of scrofulous disorders, bronchitis and pneumonia, sore throat,
                    &amp;c. Crowded and ill-ventilated places also tend to increase the virulence
                    and the rapidity of spread of the various communicable diseases.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Cleansing,</hi> including the removal of slops, excreta,
                    &amp;c., forms one of the most important and also most difficult of questions.
                    The main principle is that all should be immediately and effectually removed
                    from the house and its neighbourhood, and that there should be no possibility of
                    reflux of foul air from drain or cesspool. The system of water-carriage is
                    certainly the cleanest and most convenient, especially among large communities,
                    but other systems find advocates. In villages and isolated houses the earth
                    system and other dry methods have many advantages. The question of the disposal
                    of sewage is a very large one, into which it is impossible to enter here.
                    Hitherto all or almost all thé material has been wasted by being poured into
                    rivers or the sea, the streams being thus polluted and the shores rendered
                    offensive. The object to be aimed at is to utilize a product of undoubted
                    fertilizing influence, without endangering the health of the community. The
                    diseases to be apprehended from imperfect methods of sewage removal are enteric
                    fever, cholera, diphtheria, sore throat, and an aggravation of most other
                    diseases, especially those of an eruptive character. Ashpits ought to be
                    especially attended to, their neglect being attended with much danger.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Water-supply,</hi> although included under the head of food
                    and beverages, merits special consideration, so important is its relation to
                    health, both directly as a drink and indirectly with reference to its many other
                    uses. It is required for drinking, cooking, the cleansing of person, clothes,
                    and dwelling, and the flushing of closets, sewers, and drains. The hygienic
                    requirements are that water should be good in quality and sufficient in
                    quantity. Good water should be clear, colourless, quite free from suspended
                    matter, of a good lustre, and should have a pleasant sparkling taste, the latter
                    qualities being due to the carbonic acid and atmospheric air dissolved in it. In
                    its chemical composition it ought to be as free as possible from organic matter.
                    The evidence in favour of communication of disease by means of drinking water is
                    now very extensive, and we may cite diarrhoea, dysentery, ague, enteric fever,
                    and cholera as among the diseases which may be conveyed through this channel.
                    Numerous parasites also find their way into the human body by this means. Hard
                    water is objectionable for cooking and washing, nor can it be recommended for
                    drinking, although some insist upon a certain amount of hardness being
                    essential. In the case of water being impure, boiling, distilling, or filtering
                    may be resorted to. The two former are the most efficacious, but the last has
                    advantages of convenience if properly carried out. Charcoal filters, if properly
                    cleansed, or renewed sufficiently often, are useful, but it is better to have a
                    material that purifies without risking any deterioration of the water itself.
                    Such filters as the spongy iron and the carierai effect this. All filters,
                    however, require the medium to be cleansed or renewed periodically. In a house
                    the chief dangers are from dirty cisterns and from pipes being connected with
                    drains and closets. All supply should be on the constant system, and no pipe
                    supplying a closet should be resorted to for drinking purposes. All overflow
                    pipes should deliver in the open air. The quantity of water required per head
                    may be stated at a minimum of 12 to 16 gallons per diem where there is no
                    general system of drainage, and about 25 gallons with drainage. In towns more
                    than this is necessary, and from 30 to 50 gallons are desirable. In sickness
                    generally double the amount is necessary that is required in health. The source
                    of the water ought to be pure,— springs, deep wells, and upland surface water
                    being the best. Shallow wells and rivers to which sewage gains access are most
                    to be avoided.</p>
                <p>7. For <hi rend="italic">food</hi> and <hi rend="italic">beverages</hi> the
                    reader is referred to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Dietetics.</hi></p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Work and Exercise.—</hi> The kinds of work performed by man
                    are of course very various, but they may be reduced more or less to a uniform
                    standard, which is usually reckoned as so many tons (or pounds) raised through
                    one foot, or, tersely, as foot-tons or ton-feet. A fair day’s work is generally
                    taken at 300 foot-tons, a laborious day’s work at 450, and the maximum to be
                    expected, except under very special conditions, at 600. For this work a certain
                    time should be allowed, as the strain increases (almost in a geometrical ratio)
                    with the velocity. Usually speaking 50 foot-tons an hour is a fair amount, and
                    this ratio is equal to a walk of three miles for an average man. The amount for
                    mental work has not been accurately calculated, but it may be safely assumed
                    that a man of sedentary occupation ought to take exercise of a physical kind
                    varying from 50 to 100 foot-tons per diem. In all cases his food ought to be
                    proportioned to his work, for it is now recognized that man is a machine, whose
                    work depends upon the energy derived from the food he eats.</p>
                <p>9. <hi rend="italic">Clothing and Personal Cleanliness.—</hi> Clothing should
                    fulfil the functions of preserving warmth in cold weather, providing covering
                    without being too oppressive in hot weather, keeping out wet in wet weather, and
                    yet allowing sufficient transpiration for health. At the same time it ought to
                    admit of frequent change and cleansing. Dr Parkes has pointed out that it is
                    probably due in some measure to cleaner habits with reference to clothing that
                    the diminution of typhus fever should have been so marked in recent times.
                    Personal cleanliness is also a matter of great importance, a daily general bath
                    being advisable for every one. For animals as well as human beings it has been
                    shown that cleanliness is conducive to improved appetite and general health.
                    Filth is one of the prime factors in the production and propagation of most of
                    the devastating plagues known to mankind.</p>
                <p>10. <hi rend="italic">Prevention of Disease.—</hi> This is a large question, on
                    which we can only briefly touch. Much depends upon our knowledge of aetiology or
                    the remote causes of disease. The best rule for preventing disease is to follow
                    out carefully the principles of general hygiene, laid down with reference to
                    pure air, pure water, proper food, cleanliness, &amp;c. Some diseases may be
                    more specially provided against, such as paroxysmal fevers by the use of
                    quinine, and smallpox by vaccination, but for the great majority of diseases <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n584/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0584-0569"/> no such special preventive is known. Some
                    diseases, such as typhus fever and plague, are successfully combated by
                    scattering the population over a large area and inducing the freest ventilation,
                    and to all diseases this plan may be applied with more or less effect. In those
                    diseases which are known to be communicable, such as scarlet fever, isolation of
                    the patients is an effectual means of arresting the spread; but the poisons of
                    others, such as measles and hooping-cough, are so subtle that isolation can only
                    be looked upon as a measure of doubtful success. Much stress has been laid upon
                        <hi rend="italic">disinfection</hi> as a means of preventing disease, and if
                    properly carried out it has some efficacy. But it is a mistake to place too
                    implicit reliance upon it as ordinarily practised. In dealing with clothing,
                    bedding, &amp;c., the best method is the application of heat, at or above the
                    boiling-point of water, which may be done by means of dry heat, superheated
                    steam, or boiling water. In fumigating places, burning sulphur or the vapour of
                    chlorine or nitrous acid is used, but to be effectual the air must be rendered
                    for the time irrespirable. The solid and liquid disinfectants (so-called) are
                    chloride of lime, the permanganates, carbolic acid, and a great many similar
                    substances, many of which have been made the subjects of patents. A large number
                    of them are merely deodorants. It may be stated generally that disinfectants are
                    useful as adjuncts to other hygienic measures, but that they cannot replace
                    them, except to a small extent, and in a very imperfect way.</p>
                <p>11. <hi rend="italic">Disposal of the Dead.—</hi> The most frequent plan is
                    interment in the earth, but it may well be a question if this be the best plan;
                    it has certainly led to much evil when carried out near habitations. Two other
                    plans have been suggested, viz., burial at sea (suggested by the late Dr Parkes)
                    and cremation. The former is hardly likely to be resorted to, but the latter
                    would be effectual in preventing the evil consequences of ordinary interment. At
                    the same time the danger that it might too effectually conceal much secret crime
                    has to be taken into account.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> E. A. Parkes, <hi rend="italic">Manual of
                        Practical Hygiene,</hi> edited, by F. de Chaumont; G. Wilson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Handbook of Hygiene·, A.</hi> Wynter Blyth, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dictionary of Hygiene</hi> (after Tardieu); F. de Chaumont, <hi
                        rend="italic">Lectures on State Medicine·,</hi> A. H. Buck, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hygiene and Public Health,</hi> New York; Michel Lévy, <hi
                        rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">d'</hi><hi rend="italic">Hygiène
                        Publique et Privée·,</hi> Von Pappenheim, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
                        Sanitäts-Polizei</hi>; Roth and Lex, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
                        Militärische Gesundheitspflege·,</hi> and numerous works and monographs on
                    special departments. (F. <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
