<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0155-0144-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOOCH, Pieter de (9th edition, volume 12, page
                    144)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx73x6t">Beer</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881890">Courtyards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998642">Lighting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n155/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOOCH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pieter de</hi></label>, a Dutch
                    painter of note, was born it is thought about 1632, and died it is supposed in
                    1681 at Haarlem. Public records testify that he was a native of Rotterdam, and
                    wandered early to Delft, where he married in 1654 and practised till 1657. From
                    that time onward his life is obscure; and the only proofs of his existence to
                    which we can point are the dates on his pictures, which range from 1658 to 1670.
                    The registry of “Pieter de Hooge’s” death at Haarlem on the 28th of February
                    1681 is believed to refer to our artist. Though neglected by his contemporaries,
                    De Hooch is one of the kindliest and most charming painters of homely subjects
                    that Holland has produced. He seems to have been born at the same time and
                    taught in the same school as Van der Meer and Maes, but his works are more
                    harmoniously coloured than those of Maes, and more boldly touched than those of
                    Meer. In one respect all three are alike, being disciples of the school of
                    Rembrandt. De Hooch only once painted a canvas of any size, and that
                    unfortunately perished in a fire at Rotterdam in 1864, But his small pieces
                    display perfect finish and great dexterity of hand, combined with that power of
                    discrimination which accomplishes detail whilst avoiding rapidity and
                    smoothness. Though he sometimes paints open-air scenes, these are not his
                    favourite subjects. He is most at home in interiors, and his delight is to
                    contrast in one picture the different atmospheres of rooms illuminated by
                    different lights with the radiance of day as seen through doors and windows. He
                    thus brings together the most delicate varieties of tone, and produces chords
                    that vibrate with harmony. The themes which he illustrates are thoroughly suited
                    to his purpose. Sometimes he chooses the drawing-room where dames and cavaliers
                    dance, or dine, or sing; sometimes—mostly indeed—he likes cottages or
                    courtyards, where housewives tend their children or superintend the labours of
                    the cook. Satin and gold are as familiar to him as camlet and fur, but the
                    latter are his favourites; and there is no article of furniture in a Dutch house
                    of the middle class that he does not paint with pleasure. What distinguishes him
                    most besides subtle suggestiveuess is the serenity of his pictures, whether in
                    the open or in confined spaces. One of his most charming arrangements is a
                    canvas in the Ashburton collection, where an old lady with a dish of apples
                    walks with a child along a street bounded by a high wall, above which gables and
                    a church steeple are seen. The dame is busied with the child, whilst a gentleman
                    in a hat and cloak shows his back in the distance. The sun radiates and glitters
                    joyfully over the whole. Fine in another way is the Mug of Beer in the Amsterdam
                    museum, an interior where a woman is seen coming out of a pantry and giving a
                    measure of beer to a little girl. The light flows in here from a small closed
                    window. But through the door to the right we look into a drawing-room, and
                    through the open sash of that room we see the open air. The three lights are
                    managed with supreme cunning. In such masterpieces as these we discern the
                    models familiar to later artists such as Boursse and Koedijk, and a delicate
                    gradation of tints which Maes and Meer might have envied. Beautiful for its
                    lighting again is the Mother peeling Apples, whilst her child looks on supported
                    in leading strings by a nurse, the sun shining through the casement to the left,
                    a gem in the Speck collection at Lütschena near Leipsic. More subtly suggestive,
                    in the museum of Berlin, is the Mother seated near a Cradle, whilst a child
                    totters away into a lobby on the right. The mother looks into the depths of the
                    cradle with a smile, thus betraying to us the presence of the baby which we
                    cannot see. A Card Party, dated 1658, at Buckingham Palace is a good example of
                    De Hooch’s drawing-room scenes, counterpart as to date and value of a Woman and
                    Child in the National Gallery, and a Smoking Party belonging to Lord Enfield.
                    Other pictures later onward in the master’s career are—the Lady and Child in a
                    Courtyard, of 1665, in the National Gallery, and the Lady receiving a Letter, of
                    1670, in the Van der Hoop collection at Amsterdam. It is possible to bring
                    together between fifty and sixty examples of De Hooch, but not more. There are
                    eight at St Petersburg alone, three in Buckingham Palace, three in the National
                    Gallery, five, or at least four of undoubted genuineness, in the Hoop collection
                    at Amsterdam, some in the Louvre, at Munich, and Darmstadt; the rest are chiefly
                    in private galleries in England. For England was the first to recognize the
                    merit of De Hooch, who only began to be valued in Holland in the middle of last
                    century. A celebrated picture at Amsterdam, sold for 450 florins in 1765,
                    fetched 4000 in 1817, and now even that price is thought a bagatelle, since the
                    Berlin museum gave £6000 for a De Hooch at the Schneider sale in 1876.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
