<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0337-0326-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HROSVITHA (9th edition, volume 12, page 326)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:877187">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1041386">Nuns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz4b">Conventions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n337/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HROSVITHA</label> (frequently <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Roswitha,</hi> and properly <hi rend="smallcaps">Hbotsuit),</hi> early
                    mediaeval dramatist and chronicler, occupies a very notable position in the
                    history of modern European literature. Her endeavours formed part of the
                    literary activity by which the age of the emperor Otto the Great sought to
                    emulate that of Charles the Great. The famous nun of Gandersheim has
                    occasionally been confounded with her namesake, a learned abbess of the same
                    convent, who must have died at least half a century earlier. The younger
                    Hrosvitha was born in all probability about the year 935; and, if the statement
                    be correct that she sang the praises of the three Ottos, she must have lived to
                    near the close of the century. Some time before the year 959 she entered the
                    Benedictine nunnery of Gandersheim, a foundation which was confined to ladies of
                    German birth, and was highly favoured by the Saxon dynasty. In 959 Gerberga,
                    daughter of Duke Henry of Bavaria, and therefore niece of the emperor Otto I.,
                    was consecrated abbess of Gandersheim, and the earlier literary efforts of the
                    youthful Hrosvitha (whose own connexion with the royal family appears to be an
                    unauthenticated tradition) were encouraged by the still more youthful abbess,
                    and by a nun of the name of Richarda.</p>
                <p>The literary works of Hrosvitha, all of which were as a matter of course in
                    Latin, divide themselves into three groups. Of these the first and least
                    important comprises eight narrative religious poems, in leonine hexameters or
                    distichs. Their subjects are the Nativity of the Virgin (from the apocryphal
                    gospel of St James, the brother of our Lord), the Ascension, and a series of
                    legends of saints (Gandυlph, Pelagius, Theophilus, Basil, Denis, Agnes). Like
                    these narrative poems, the dramas to which above all Hrosvitha owes her fame
                    seem to have been designed for reading aloud or recitation by sisters of the
                    convent. For though there are indications that the idea of their representation
                    was at least present to the mind of the authoress^ the fact of such a
                    representation appears to be an unwarrantable assumption. The comedies of
                    Hrosvitha are six in number, being doubtless in this respect also intended to
                    recall their nominal model, the comedies of Terence. They were devised on the
                    simple principle that the world, the flesh, and the devil should not have all
                    the good plays to· themselves. The experiment upon which the young Christian
                    dramatist ventured was accordingly, although not absolutely novel, audacious
                    enough. In form the-dramas<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n338/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0338-0327"/> of “the strong voice of Gandersheim,” as
                    Hrosvitha (possibly alluding to a supposed etymology of her name) calls herself,
                    are by no means Terentian. They are written in prose, with an element of
                    something like rhythm, and an occasional admixture of rhyme. In their themes,
                    and in the treatment of these, they are what they were intended to be, the
                    direct opposites of the lightsome adapter of Menander. They are founded upon
                    legends of the saints, selected with a view to a glorification of religion in
                    its supremest efforts and most transcendental aspects. The emperor Constantine’s
                    daughter, for example, Constantia, gives her hand in marriage to <hi
                        rend="italic">Gallicanus,</hi> just before he starts on a Scythian campaign,
                    though she has already taken a vow of perpetual maidenhood. In the hour of
                    battle he is himself converted, and, having on his return like his virgin bride
                    chosen the more blessed unmarried state, dies as a Christian martyr in exile.
                    The three holy maidens Agape, Chionia, and Irene are preserved by a humorous
                    miracle from the evil designs of <hi rend="italic">Dulcitius,</hi> to offer up
                    their pure lives as a sacrifice under Diocletian’s persecutions. <hi
                        rend="italic">Callimachus,</hi> who has Romeo-like carried his earthly
                    passion for the saintly Drusiana into her tomb, and among its horrors has met
                    with his own death, is by the mediation of St John raised with her from the dead
                    to a Christian life. All these themes are treated with both spirit and skill,
                    often with instinctive knowledge of dramatic effect—often with genuine touches
                    of pathos and undeniable felicities of expression. In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dulcitius</hi> there is also an element of comedy, or rather of farce. How
                    far Hrosvitha’s comedies were an isolated phenomenon of their age in Germany
                    must remain undecided; in the general history of the drama they form the visible
                    bridge between the few earlier attempts at utilizing the forms of the classical
                    drama for Christian purposes and the miracle plays. They are in any case the
                    productions of genius; nor has Hrosvitha missed the usual tribute of the
                    supposition that Shakespeare has borrowed from her writings.</p>
                <p>The third and last group of the writings of Hrosvitha is that of her versified
                    historical chronicles. At the request of the abbess Gerberga she composed her
                        <hi rend="italic">Carmen de</hi><hi rend="italic">Gestis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Oddonis,</hi> an epic attempting in some degree to follow the
                    great Roman model. It was completed by the year 968, and presented by the
                    authoress to both the old emperor and his son (then already crowned as) Otto II.
                    This poem so closely adheres to the materials supplied to the authoress by
                    members of the imperial family that, notwithstanding its courtly omissions, it
                    is regarded as an historical authority. Unfortunately only half of it remains;
                    the part treating of the period from 953 to 962 is lost with the exception of a
                    few fragments, and the period from 962 to 967is summarized only. Subsequently,
                    in a poem (of 837 hexameters) <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Primordiis Coenobii</hi><hi rend="italic">Gandersheimensis,</hi> Hrosvitha
                    narrated the beginnings of her own convent, and its history up to the year
                    919.</p>
                <p>The Munich MS., which contains all the works enumerated above except the <hi
                        rend="italic">Chronicle of</hi><hi rend="italic">Gandersheim,</hi> was
                    edited by the great Vienna humanist Celtes in 1501, and re-edited by the learned
                    H. L. Schurzfleisch in 1707. The comedies have been translated into German by
                    Ben∣iixen (Lübeck, 1858), and into French by A. Magnin (Paris, 1845), whose
                    introduction gives a full account of the authoress and her works. A copious
                    analysis of these plays will be found in Klein, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">des Dramas,</hi> iii. 665-754. Gustav
                    Freytag is the author of a treatise <hi rend="italic">De Rosuitha</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">poetria</hi> (Breslau, 1839); and at the beginning of Cohn’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Shakspcare in Germany,</hi> Shakespearean parallels are
                    suggested to certain passages in Hrosvitha’s dramas. Her two historical
                    chronicles were edited by Pertz among the <hi rend="italic">Monumenta
                        Germanice</hi> (vol. iv.); for an appreciation of them see Wattenbach, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichtsquellen,</hi> 214-216, and Giesebrecht, <hi
                        rend="italic">Deutsche Kaiserzeit,</hi> i. 780, who mentions a German
                    translation by Pfund. There is a complete edition of the works of Hrosvitha by
                    K. A. Barack (Nuremberg, 1858). J. Aschbach (1867) attempted to prove that
                    Celtes had forged the productions which he published under the name of
                    Hrosvitha, but he was refuted by R. Köpke (Berlin, 1869). (A. W. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
