<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0319-0308-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOTMAN, or Hottoman</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 12, page 308</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15t8m">Eucharist</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n319/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOTMAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Hottoman</hi></label>, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">François</hi> (1524-1590), one of the most learned of French
                    civilians, and a brilliant publicist, was born at Paris in 1524, of a family
                    which had come, in the days of his grandfather, from Silesia. His father a <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n320/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0320-0309"/> counsellor of the parliament of Paris, naturally
                    hoped to see his eldest son his successor, and gave him a legal education at
                    Orleans. After three years’ study he was made a doctor of laws, and immediately
                    began to practise at the Paris bar. But the quibbles of pleading soon disgusted
                    him, and to his father’s annoyance he turned to the calmer study of
                    jurisprudence. At the age of twenty-two he was named public lecturer with
                    Baudouin at Paris, and at once gained high repute. The fortitude of Anne Dubourg
                    under torture roused his latent enthusiasm for the Reformed opinions; he at once
                    gave up his career, and went in 1547 to Lyons, the outpost of Genevan theology,
                    and thence to Geneva and Lausanne. At Lausanne he became professor of
                    belles-lettres and history, and married a French refugee from Orleans; in 1550
                    we find him in high repute as a teacher at Strasburg, where he lectured for
                    several years to large crowds of students. In 1560, in the beginning of the
                    civil troubles, he attached himself to Antony of Navarre, and was trusted with
                    delicate missions from the Huguenot chiefs to German princes; he even at one
                    time carried credentials from Catherine de’ Medici, and his speech at the
                    Frankfort diet, which is extant, is “a model of eloquence and political
                    shrewdness.” After a while we find him professor at Valence, expounding the
                    civil law with such success as to restore the failing credit of that university.
                    Three years later he succeeded Cujas at Bourges; but the civil war drove him to
                    Orleans for refuge, whence he was sent down to Blois to negotiate the peace of
                    1568. He returned to Bourges only to encounter another outbreak of war and
                    another flight, this time to Sancerre, where in the tedium of the obstinate
                    siege he composed his <hi rend="italic">Consolatio,</hi> a striking work drawn
                    from the Bible and St Augustine. The peace of 1570 restored him once more; but
                    the St Bartholomew drove him away again; and with wife and family he fled to
                    Geneva, turning his back for ever on his country. As he went he shot at Charles
                    IX. a Parthian shaft in his celebrated <hi rend="italic">Franco-Gallia,</hi> a
                    treatise much censured by Catholics and Huguenots alike. It breathed the true
                    spirit of research and of Huguenot independence and even republicanism; for it
                    boldly appealed, in the very citadel of hereditary succession, from rights of
                    blood to popular election, and declared that the French monarchy rested on that
                    foundation; the use soon made of the book by the Jesuits in their pamphlet war
                    against Henry IV. added to its unpopularity. At Geneva Hotman was appointed
                    professor of Roman law, and taught in peace for six years; in 1579, however, the
                    threatening approach of the duke of Savoy frightened him away to Basel. Thence
                    the plague sent him to Montbéliard in 1582, where he lost his faithful wife.
                    After making trial of Geneva once more, he again in 1589 fled to Basel, where he
                    died in 1590, and was buried in the cathedral.</p>
                <p>Hotman was a man of unfeigned piety, nor were his firm and lofty ideas on
                    religion ever shaken; the purity of his home-life, his devotion to wife and
                    family, his courageous endurance of poverty and trouble, made him one of the
                    finer characters of his age. His very timidity and restlessness were but the
                    results of a parent’s anxiety for the safety of his children; the infinite
                    horrors of unbridled war filled him with fears for them. It was his quick
                    intelligence and passionate temperament that made him a wanderer, and even laid
                    him open to the suspicion of cowardice. As an author, if not original, he
                    certainly was not Scaliger’s “vulgare ingenium.” His criticism is sound and
                    acute, his learning beyond question scholarly and legal, his Latinity admirable,
                    even eloquent; he is one of the best writers of his age; and it is not to be
                    urged severely against him that he cheated himself with that snare of clever and
                    needy men, alchemy, and sought to achieve the transmutation of metals.</p>
                <p>∏is chief works were—the <hi rend="italic">Anti-T</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∙ibonien</hi> (1567), a treatise to show that French law could not
                    be based on Justinian; the <hi rend="italic">Franco-Gallia</hi> (1573), with the
                    pamphlets in its defence; his <hi rend="italic">Controversia patrui et
                    nepoti»</hi> (1585); his <hi rend="italic">Brutum Fulmen</hi> (1585), against
                    the bull of Pope Sixtus; the <hi rend="italic">Consolatio</hi> (published in
                    1593); <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on the Eucharist</hi> (156C&gt;); <hi
                    rend="italic">A Life of Coligny</hi> (1575), with many other works on law,
                    history, politics, or classical scholarship. These are mostly forgotten; but in
                    their day they placed Francis Hotman in the first rank among the learned and
                    accomplished authors of France. A collection of his letters was published at
                    Amsterdam in 1700.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
