<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0357-0346-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HUMBOLDT, Karl Wilhelm von (9th edition, volume 12,
                    page 346)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966473">Iberians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830652">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93g2m">Friendship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nk3693f">Iberians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882n4f">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n357/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HUMBOLDT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karl Wilhelm von</hi></label>
                    (1767-1835), the elder brother of the more celebrated Alexander von Humboldt,
                    was born at Potsdam, on the 22d of June 1767. After being educated at Berlin,
                    Göttingen, and Jena, in the last of which places he formed a close and lifelong
                    friendship with Schiller, he married Fräulein von Dacherode, a lady of birth and
                    fortune, and in 1802 was appointed by the Prussian Government first resident and
                    then minister plenipotentiary at Rome. While there he published a poem entitled
                        <hi rend="italic">Rom,</hi> which was reprinted in 1824. This was not,
                    however, the first of his literary productions; his critical essay on Goethe’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Hermann and Dorothea,</hi> published in 1800, had already
                    placed him in the first rank of authorities on aesthetics, and, together with
                    his family connexions, had much to do with his appointment at Rome; while in the
                    years 1795 and 1797 he had brought out translations of several of the odes of
                    Pindar, which were held in high esteem. On quitting his post at Rome he was made
                    councillor of state and minister of public instruction. He soon, however,
                    retired to his estate at Tegel, near Berlin, but was recalled and sent as
                    ambassador to Vienna in 1812 during the exciting period which witnessed the
                    closing struggles of the French empire. In the following year, as Prussian
                    plenipotentiary at the congress of Prague, he was mainly instrumental in
                    inducing Austria to unite with Prussia and Russia against France; in 1815 he was
                    one of the signatories of the capitulation of Paris, and the same year was
                    occupied in drawing up the treaty between Prussia and Saxony, by which the
                    territory of the former was largely increased at the expense of the latter. The
                    next year he was at Frankfort settling the future condition of Germany, but was
                    summoned to London in the midst of his work, and in 1818 had to attend the
                    congress at Aix-la-Chapelle. The reactionary policy of the Prussian Government
                    made him resign his office of privy councillor and give up political life in
                    1819; and from that time forward he devoted himself solely to literature and
                    study.</p>
                <p>During the busiest portion of his political career, however, he had found time
                    for literary work. Thus in 1816 he had published a translation of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Agamemnon</hi> of Aeschylus, and in 1817 corrections and
                    additions to Adelung’s <hi rend="italic">Mithridates,</hi> that famous
                    collection of specimens of the various languages and dialects of the world.
                    Among these additions that on the Basque language is the longest and most
                    important, Basque having for some time specially attracted his attention. In
                    fact, Wilhelm von Humboldt may be said to have been the first who brought Basque
                    before the notice of European philologists, and made a scientific study of it
                    possible. In order to gain a practical knowledge of the hnguage and complete his
                    investigations into it, he visited the Basque country itself, the result of his
                    visit being the valuable “Researches into the Early Inhabitants of Spain by the
                    help of the Basque language” <hi rend="italic">{Prüfung der Untersuchungen über
                        die Urbewohner His-paniens vermittelst der vaskischen Sprache'),</hi>
                    published in 1821. In this work he endeavoured to sh(&gt;w, by an examination of
                    geographical names, that a race or races speaking dialects allied to modern
                    Bisque once extended through the whole of Spain, the southern coast of France,
                    and the Balearic Islands, and suggested that these people, whom he identified
                    with the Iberians of classical writers, had come from Northern Africa, where the
                    name of Berber still perhaps perpetuates their old designation. Another work on
                    what has sometimes been termed the metaphysics of language appeared from his pen
                    in 1828, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Ueber</hi><hi rend="italic">den
                        Dualis</hi>; but the great work of his life, on the ancient Kawi language of
                    Java, was unfortunately interrupted by his death on the 8th of April 1835. The
                    imperfect fragment was edited by his brother and Dr</p>
                <p>Buschmann in 1836, and contains the remarkable introduction on “The Heterogeneity
                    of Language and its Influence on the Intellectual Development of Mankind” <hi
                        rend="italic">{Ueber die</hi><hi rend="italic">Verschiedenheit des
                        menschlichen Sprachbaues und ihren Einfluss auf die geistige Entwickelung
                        des Menschengeschlechts),</hi> which has been since edited and defended
                    against SteinthaΓs criticisms by Professor Pott (2 vols., 1876). This essay,
                    which has been called the text-book of the philosophy of speech, first clearly
                    laid down that the character and structure of a language expresses the inner
                    life and knowledge of its speakers, and that languages must differ from one
                    another in the same way and to the same degree as those who use them. Sounds do
                    not become words until a meaning has been put into them, and this meaning
                    embodies the thought of a community. What Humboldt terms the inner form of a
                    language is just that mode of denoting the relations between the parts of a
                    sentence which reflects the manner in which a particular body of men regards the
                    world about them. It is the task of the morphology of speech to distinguish the
                    various ways in which languages differ from each other as regards their inner
                    form, and to classify and arrange them accordingly. Other linguistic
                    publications of Humboldt, which had appeared in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Transactions</hi> of the Berlin Academy, the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>
                    of the Royal Asiatic Society, or elsewhere, were republished by his brother in
                    the seven volumes of Wilhelm von Humboldt’s <hi rend="italic">Gesammelte
                        Werke</hi> (1841-52). These volumes also contain poems, essays on
                    aesthetical subjects, and other creations of his prolific mind. Perhaps,
                    however, the most generally interesting of his works, outside those which deal
                    with language, is his correspondence with Schiller, published in 1830. Both poet
                    and philosopher come before us in it in their most genial mood. For, though
                    Humboldt was primarily a philosopher, he was a philosopher rendered practical by
                    his knowledge of statesmanship and wide experience of life, and endowed with
                    keen sympathies, warm imagination, and active interest in the method of
                    scientific inquiry. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. h. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
