<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0061-0052-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOLBACH, Paul Heinrich Dietrich, Baron d’ (9th edition,
                    volume 12, page 52)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mg3z">Socialism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1123768">Socialization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1123637">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n61/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOLBACH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul Heinrich Dietrich, Baron
                            d’</hi></label> (1723-1789), <hi rend="italic">philosophe</hi> of the
                    Parisian school of the 18th century, was born at Heidelsheim in the palatinate
                    in 1723. Of his family little is known; according to J. J. Rousseau, his father
                    was a rich parvenu, who brought his son at an early age to Paris, where the
                    latter spent most of his life. Much of Holbach’s fame is due to his intimate
                    connexion with the brilliant coterie of bold thinkers and polished wits whose
                    creed, the new philosophy, is concentrated in the famous <hi rend="italic"
                        >Encyclopédie.</hi> Possessed of easy means and being of hospitable
                    disposition, he kept open house for such men as Helvetius, D’Alembert, Diderot,
                    Condillac, Turgot, Buffon, Grimm, Hume, Garrick, Wilkes, Sterne, and for a time
                    Rousseau, who, while enjoying the intellectual pleasure of their host’s
                    conversation, were not insensible to the material charms of his excellent
                    cuisine and costly wines.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n62/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0062-0053"/>
                <p>Although an atheist, or at least a materialist of the most material school,
                    Holbach seems to have been endowed with a more than average share of virtue,
                    and, whether by his courtesy, gentleness, or benevolence, inspired a warm
                    affection in all he met. Even bis failings, of which his simple credulity was
                    perhaps the most prominent, were amiable. He was one of the best informed men of
                    his day, and his excellent memory placed at his immediate disposal all the
                    learning he had amassed. He visited England on one occasion, but the solemn
                    stiffness of the British, even while amusing themselves, and the peculiar
                    relatione of society, disgusted as much as they surprised him. For the <hi
                        rend="italic">Encyclopédie</hi> Holbach compiled and translated a large
                    number of articles on chemistry and mineralogy, chiefly from German sources. He
                    attracted more attention, however, in the department of philosophy. In 1767 <hi
                        rend="italic">Christianisme</hi><hi rend="italic">Devoile</hi> appeared, in
                    which he attacked Christianity and religion as the source of all human evils.
                    Regarding religion as a blind superstitious bondage, maintained on men’s minds
                    bj <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> the self-interest of the priests, he tried to
                    prove it not only unnecessary but absolutely prejudicial to human morality. This
                    was followed up in 1770 by a still more open attack in his most famous book, <hi
                        rend="italic">Le Système de la Nature,</hi> in which it is probable he was
                    assisted by Diderot. Denying the existence of a deity, and refusing to admit as
                    evidence all <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> arguments, Holbach saw in the
                    universe nothing save matter in spontaneous movement. What men call their souls
                    become extinct when the body dies. Happiness is the end of mankind. “It would be
                    useless and almost unjust to insist upon a man’s being virtuous if he cannot be
                    so without being unhappy. So long as vice renders him happy, he should love
                    vice.” Not less direct and trenchant are his attacks on political government,
                    which, interpreted by the light of after events, sound like the first distant
                    mutterings of the tempest that shortly after his death broke over the capital of
                    France. The <hi rend="italic">Système</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Nature</hi>
                    struck horror into the minds of even the most “enlightened” of the Parisian
                    philosophers. Charmed by the novelty of their own opinions, and dazzled by the
                    glittering wit and argument with which they had supported them, they had never
                    realized into what extremities they had hurried till this lurid torch revealed
                    the hideous abyss from which they were so little removed. Voltaire hastily
                    seized his pen to refute the philosophy of the <hi rend="italic">Système,</hi>
                    in the article “Dieu” in his <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Philosophique,</hi>
                    while Frederick the Great also drew up an answer to it. Though vigorous in
                    thought and in some passages clear and eloquent, the style of the book is
                    diffuse and declamatory, and asserts rather than proves its statements. Its
                    principles are summed up in a more popular form in <hi rend="italic">Bon</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Sens,</hi><hi rend="italic">ou Idées naturelles opposées aux
                        idées surnaturelles,</hi> published at Amsterdam in 1772. In the <hi
                        rend="italic">Système</hi><hi rend="italic">Social</hi> (1773), the <hi
                        rend="italic">Politique</hi><hi rend="italic">Naturelle</hi> (1773-74), and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Morale</hi><hi rend="italic">Universelle</hi> (1776),
                    Holbach attempts to rear a system of morality in place of the one he had so
                    fiercely attacked, but these later writings had not a tithe of the popularity
                    and influence of his earlier and more pernicious work. He published his books
                    either anonymously or under a borrowed name, and was forced to have them printed
                    out of France. He died in 1789. On the death of his first wife he obtained a
                    papal dispensation to marry her sister, who survived him till 1814.</p>
                <p>Holbach is also the author of the following and other works:— <hi rend="italic"
                        >Esprit du Clergé,</hi> 1767; <hi rend="italic">De Γ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Imposture sacerdotale,</hi> 1767; <hi rend="italic">Prêtres Démasqués,</hi>
                    1768; <hi rend="italic">Examen Critique de la vie et des ouvrages de St
                        Paul,</hi> 1770; <hi rend="italic">Histoire Critique de Jésus Christ,</hi>
                    1770; and <hi rend="italic">Etho-cratie,</hi> 1776. For further particulare as
                    to his life and doctrines see Grimm’s <hi rend="italic">Correspondance
                        Littéraire,</hi> &amp;c., 1813; Rousseau’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Confessions</hi>; Morellet’s <hi rend="italic">Mémoires,</hi> 1821; Madame
                    de Genlis, <hi rend="italic">Les Diners</hi><hi rend="italic">du Baron
                        Holbach</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> Madame d’Épinay’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mémoires</hi>; Avezac-Lavigne., <hi rend="italic">Diderot</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et la Société du Baron d'Holbach,</hi> 1875; and Morley’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Diderot,</hi> 1878.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
