<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0557-0542-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HYDROPATHY (9th edition, volume 12, page 542)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41834445">Cold</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885283">Curing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866956">Cold</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964151">Hunters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n557/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HYDROPATHY</label> is the treatment of disease by water, used
                    outwardly and inwardly. Like many descriptive names, the word “hydropathy” is
                    defective and even misleading, the active agents in the treatment being heat and
                    cold, of which water is little more than the vehicle, and not the only one.
                    Thermo-therapeutics (or thermotherapy) is a term less open to objection. The
                    name “hydropathy,” however, as being itself an advance on an earlier and less
                    happy designation, “the water cure,” as having obtained general currency, is
                    here employed.</p>
                <p>Hydropathy, as a system, or mode of treatment complete in itself, dates from
                    about 1829, when Vincenz Priessnitz (1801-51), a farmer of Gräfenberg in
                    Silesia, Austria, began his public career in the paternal homestead, extended so
                    as to accommodate the increasing numbers attracted by the fame of his cures. Two
                    English works, however, on the medical uses of water had been translated into
                    German in the century preceding the rise of the movement under Priessnitz. One
                    of these was by Sir John Floyer, a physician of Lichfield, who, struck by the
                    remedial use of certain springs by the neighbouring peasantry, investigated the
                    history of cold bathing, and published in 1702 his “Ψυχρολουσία, <hi
                        rend="italic">or the History of Cold Bathing, both Ancient and Modern."</hi>
                    The book ran through six editions within a few years, and the translation was
                    largely drawn upon by Dr J. S. Hahn of Silesia, in a work published in 1738, <hi
                        rend="italic">On the Healing Virtues of Cold Water, Inwardly and Outwardly
                        applied, as proved by Experience.</hi> The other work was that of Dr Currie
                    of Liverpool, entitled <hi rend="italic">Medical Reports on the Effects of
                        Water, Cold and Warm, as a Remedy in Fevers and other Diseases,</hi>
                    published in 1797, and soon after translated into German by Michaeb’s (1801) and
                    Hegewisch (1807). It was highly popular, and first placed the subject on a
                    scientific basis. Hahn’s writings had meanwhile created much enthusiasm among
                    his countrymen, societies having been everywhere formed to promote the medicinal
                    and dietetic use of water; and in 1804 Professor Oertel of Ansbach republished
                    them and quickened the popular movement by unqualified commendation of water
                    drinking as a remedy for all diseases. In him the rising Priessnitz found a
                    zealous advocate, and doubtless an instructor also. The origin of hydropathy is
                    thus to be traced to an English source and to the medical profession. The broad
                    conception that water had curative relations to the whole realm of disease seems
                    to have been first grasped by a Capuchin monk of Sicily, Father Bernardo, who,
                    at Malta, in 1724, obtained results by iced water alone, which, according to
                    Hahn, caused a great stir throughout Europe; but, owing to the excesses of his
                    imitators, it was of no long duration. With this exception there is, as regards
                    the remedial use of water, nothing in the history <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n558/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0558-0543"/> of medicine that approaches in completeness
                    the system of Priessnitz, though much leading up to it can be discovered. Among
                    most primitive peoples, indeed, both in the Old and in the New World, the
                    existence of one kind or another of hydropathic practice can be traced; and the
                    fathers of medicine made frequent reference in their writings to the employment
                    of water. The warm bath came into use at an early period (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Baths,</hi> vol. iii. p. 434); and the clyster, shower
                    bath, douche, plunge, wet compress, drop bath, head and foot baths, are
                    mentioned from time to time, as also combinations of heat and cold and primitive
                    modes of sweating, until, before the end of the 17 th century, all the processes
                    of modern hydropathy, the wet sheet pack and induced cutaneous crisis alone
                    excepted, had become known and were in a measure practised. Prominent in the
                    roll of names associated more or less with the advocacy of water in earlier
                    times are those of Asclepiades of Prusa (90 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi>
                    surnamed <hi rend="italic">Ψυχρολοντης</hi> (“cold bather”), Antoninus Musa (30
                    B.c.), famed for his cure of Augustus by cold water (comp. Hoc., <hi
                        rend="italic">Epist.</hi> i. 15, 3-5), Galen (130 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.),</hi> Rhazes (923), Avicenna (1036), Cardan, and Van der Heyden.
                    Raymond of Marseilles (1755) gained a prize for the best treatise on the
                    applications of cold water in disease, and another prize essay by Marteau shows
                    what knowledge of the subject prevailed in his time.</p>
                <p>At Gräfenberg, to which the fame of Priessnitz drew people of every rank and many
                    countries, medical men were conspicuous by their numbers, some being attracted
                    by curiosity, others by the desire of knowledge, but the majority by the hope of
                    cure for ailments which had as yet proved incurable. Many records of experiences
                    at Gräfenberg were published, all more or less favourable to the claims of
                    Priessnitz, and some enthusiastic in their estimate of his genius and
                    penetration; and from these alone can a knowledge of his practice and views be
                    obtained, not a line having ever been written by this singular man. To Captain
                    Claridge was due the introduction in 1840 of hydropathy to England, his writings
                    and lectures, and later those of Drs Wilson, Gully, and Edward Johnson, making
                    numerous converts, and filling the establishments opened soon after at Malvern
                    and elsewhere. In Germany, France, and America hydropathic establishments
                    multiplied with great rapidity. Antagonism ran high between the old practice and
                    the new. Unsparing condemnation was heaped by each on the other; and a legal
                    prosecution, leading to a royal commission of inquiry, served but to make
                    Priessnitz and his system stand higher in public estimation.</p>
                <p>But increasing popularity diminished before long that timidity which hitherto had
                    in great measure prevented trial of the new method from being made on the weaker
                    and more serious class of cases, and had caused hydropathists to occupy
                    themselves mainly with a sturdy order of chronic invalids well able to bear a
                    rigorous regimen and the severities of unrestricted crisis. The need of a
                    radical adaptation to the former class was first adequately recognized by John
                    Smedley, a manufacturer of Derbyshire, who, impressed in his own person with the
                    severities as well as the benefits of “the cold water cure,” practised among his
                    workpeople a milder form of hydropathy, and began about 1852 a new era in its
                    history, founding at Matlock a counterpart of the establishment,at
                    Gräfenberg.</p>
                <p>Whilst hydropathy as a system has been gaining favour with the people, and
                    receiving ample acknowledgment from the more liberal members of the medical
                    profession, individual measures have from time to time been advocated in the
                    medical journals and adopted more or less widely in particular diseases. Brand
                    of Berlin, Räljen and Jürgensen of Kiel, and Liebermeister of Basel, between
                    1860 and 1870, employed the cooling bath in abdominal typhus with results which,
                    after every deduction on the score of defective classification had been made,
                    were striking enough, and led to its introduction to England by Dr Wilson Fox,
                    whose able monograph commanded general acceptance. In the Franco-German war the
                    cooling bath was largely employed, in conjunction frequently with quinine; and
                    it now holds a recognized position in the treatment of hyperpyrexia. The wet
                    sheet pack has of late been much used in fevers of all kinds both in private and
                    hospital practice; and the Turkish bath, introduced about twenty-four years ago
                    by Mr David Urquhart on his return from the East, and ardently adopted by Mr
                    Barter of Cork, has become a public institution, and, with the “morning tub” and
                    the general practice of water drinking, is the most noteworthy of the many
                    contributions by hydropathy to public health.</p>
                <p>The theoretical basis of hydropathy is wide and fundamental enough to include
                    within its scope all disease« Each individual cell of the mass constituting in
                    various forms and combinations the human body being in its growth and function
                    dependent on and regulated by the nervous and vascular systems, themselves
                    cellular, and every derangement of these cells originating in or being.attended
                    with a derangement of their nervous and vascular supply, and that supply being
                    powerfully and in quite diverse ways influenced by heat and cold,—all morbid
                    conditions of the economy may be influenced materially by the regulated
                    employment of heat and cold, which are entitled therefore to rank as powerful
                    factors in therapeutics.</p>
                <p>Hydropathy insists in quite a special way on the necessity of regarding disease
                    first in relation to its cause. It next requires that whatever assistance may be
                    afforded to the <hi rend="italic">vis medicatrix</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >naturoe</hi> should in the first place be similar in kind (⅛'.e., should be
                    natural or physiological), rather than alien to it and drawn from sources remote
                    and strange; and, while proceeding on lines which have been common to all
                    medical practice from an early period, it does so by agents hitherto strangely
                    neglected, though not unknown, and effects its purpose in ways less open to
                    objection than those it would displace. For example, when local depletion is
                    required, as of the lung in pneumonia, or the brain in haemorrhagic apoplexy,
                    the final withdrawal from the general circulation of a quantity of blood is
                    deprecated as unnecessary for the attainment of the object in view, and
                    prejudicial in the after period of convalescence. Hydropathy substitutes a
                    diversion to parts indifferent, as the extremities and general cutaneous
                    surface, and so material and sustained as tobe much more effectual; while at the
                    same time it holds in reserve the abstracted blood to perform its part in the
                    restoration of strength. Where purgation is employed to derive blood from the
                    brain, liver, or kidneys, a highly sensitive and vital membrane is more or less
                    injured thereby, and convalescence proportionately imperilled. Hydropathy
                    selects the skin as more accessible than the mucous membrane of the alimentary
                    tract, more serviceable also, and less, if at all, susceptible of injury, either
                    temporary or permanent. The skin can with safety be used for counter-irritation,
                    and is a reservoir of capacity almost unlimited, into which to divert the excess
                    of blood from the brain or other part, while for purposes of excretion it is not
                    inferior to the bowels themselves, and, unlike the latter, is left even more
                    efficient than before. In the febrile state, a reduction of pulse and
                    temperature, and relief from pain and sleeplessness, were commonly attempted, at
                    the period when hydropathy was introduced, by depressants, as antimony,
                    ipecacuanha, and perhaps large doses of alcohol, in combination with sedatives,
                    as opium and chloral. Impaired digestion and depressed vitality were results in
                    some measure inevitable, and always of moment, especially in the more protracted
                    fevers, where recovery becomes a question often of simple physical endurance. By
                    means of the wet <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n559/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0559-0544"/> sheet pack, cooling compresses, spongings,
                    and allied measures, these ends are attained with comparative ease, certainty,
                    and simplicity, and with entire freedom from objectionable secondary
                    effects.</p>
                <p>The agents of hydropathy are at once simple and complex,—simple in their
                    elements, and complex in their combinations and modifications. They afford the
                    physician a series of effects almost infinite in variety, both in kind and in
                    degree, both immediate and remote. According as heat and cold<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Roughly, and for
                            practical purposes, temperature lower than 60° may be called cold; from
                            60° to 90°, temperate or tepid; from 90° to 100°, warm; and above 100°,
                            hot (compare vol. iii. ρ. 440).</p></note> are used in their extreme or
                    their intermediate degrees, singly or in combination, successively or
                    alternately, momentarily or continuously, dry or moist, and according as the
                    primary action is utilized or the secondary, do their effects differ. The direct
                    or primary effect of cold is to depress, cool, and deplete the part concerned.
                    If its exhibition is brief, reaction (an important factor in hydropathic
                    practice) quickly establishes an opposite condition, stimulating the part, and
                    determining an increased flow of blood to it, with increase of its temperature
                    and vital activity. If it is continuous, the primary depression is maintained,
                    and the revulsive or secondary effect delayed or averted. The direct effect of
                    heat is to increase the amount of blood present; but if the exhibition is brief,
                    and evaporation is permitted, the contrary effect is produced, viz., depression,
                    coolness, and depletion; if it is continuous, the primary effect is preserved.
                    Thus with truth it may be said that cold heats and heat cools, while the
                    converse holds good, and that by simple variations of detail. From the
                    intermediate temperatures (80° to 100°) simple sedative effects are obtained,
                    with absence of secondary or revulsive effects in proportion as the temperature
                    of the part is approximated to. Results vary also according to the heat of the
                    subject. In local inflammations, continuous cold benumbs and contracts,
                    continuous heat soothes and relaxes. Momentary cold excites, heats by reaction,
                    and intensifies inflammation; while momentary heat soothes and ultimately cools
                    the inflamed part by the after evaporation. In the earlier stages and acute
                    varieties of inflammation, therefore, continuous cold or transient hot
                    applications are appropriate, and brief applications of cold in the later,
                    congestive, and chronic forms. But where the local inflammation coexists with
                    general feverishness, continuous cold as the local application is preferable,
                    helping, as it does, to reduce the general exaltation of temperature. In
                    collapse the low general temperature makes heat the best local application. On
                    internal parts the application of heat and cold externally has definite
                    therapeutic effects either identical or opposite (as remarked by John Hunter)
                    through reflex or sympathetic nervous action. Through the vascular system also
                    remote effects are produced, as in heating the lower extremities to derive blood
                    from the brain. The counter relation also of the entire cutaneous surface to the
                    internal organs, as the kidneys and alimentary mucous membrane, is, in
                    hydropathy, largely utilized for remedial purposes. This sympathy is familiar
                    enough in the etiology of disease, which may be said likewise of all the
                    physiological laws applied to curative purposes in hydropathy.</p>
                <p>The appliances and arrangements by means of which heat and cold are brought to
                    bear on the economy are—(a) Packings, hot and cold, general and local, sweating
                    and cooling; (δ) hot air and steam baths; (c) general baths, of hot water and
                    cold; (d) sitz, spinal, head, and foot baths; (e) bandages (or compresses), wet
                    and dry; also (∕) fomentations and poultices, hot and cold, sinapisms, stupes,
                    rubbings, and water potations, hot and cold.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">(a.</hi>) Packings. —The full pack consists of a wet sheet
                    enveloping the body, with a number of dry blankets packed tightly over it,
                    including a macintosh covering or not. In an hour or less these are removed and
                    ageneralbath administered. The pack is a derivative, sedative, sudorific, and
                    stimulator of cutaneous excretion. There are numerous modifications of it,
                    notably the cooling pack, where the wrappings are loose and scanty, permitting
                    evaporation, and the application of indefinite duration, the sheet being
                    rewetted as it dries; this is of great value in protracted febrile conditions.
                    There are also local packs, to trunk, limbs, or head separately, which are
                    derivative, soothing, or stimulating, according to circumstance and detail.</p>
                <p>(δ.) Hot air baths, the chief of which is the Turkish (properly, the Roman) bath,
                    consisting of two or more chambers ranging in temperature from 120° to 212° or
                    higher, but mainly used at 150° for curative purposes. Exposure is from twenty
                    minutes up to two hours according to the effect sought, and is followed by a
                    general bath, and occasionally by soaping and shampooing. 11 is stimulating,
                    derivative, depurative, sudorific, and alterative, powerfully promoting tissue
                    change by increase of the natural waste and repair. It determines the blood to
                    the surface, reducing internal congestions, is a potent diaphoretic, and,
                    through the extremes of heat and cold, is an effective nervous and vascular
                    stimulant and tonic. Morbid growths and secretions, as also the uraemic, gouty,
                    and rheumatic diathesis, are beneficially influenced by it. The full pack and
                    Turkish bath have between them usurped the place and bettered the function of
                    the once familiar hot bath. The Russian or steam bath and the lamp bath are
                    primitive and inferior varieties of the modern Turkish bath, the atmosphere of
                    which cannot be too dry and pure.</p>
                <p>(c.) General baths comprise the rain (or needle), spray (or rose), shower,
                    shallow, plunge, douche, wave, and common morning sponge baths, with the
                    dripping sheet, and hot and cold spongings, and are combinations, as a rule, of
                    hot and cold water. They are stimulating, tonic, derivative, and detergent.</p>
                <p>(&lt;Z.) Local baths comprise the sitz (or sitting), douche (or spouting),
                    spinal, foot, and head baths, of hot or cold water, singly or in combination,
                    successive or alternate. The sitz, head, and foot baths are used “flowing” on
                    occasion. Rapid alternations of hot and cold water have a powerful effect in
                    vascular stasis and lethargy of the nervous system and absorbents, yielding
                    valuable results in local congestions and chronic inflammations.</p>
                <p>(e.) Bandages (or compresses) are of two kinds,— <hi rend="italic">cooling,</hi>
                    of wet material left exposed for evaporation, used in local inflammations and
                    fevers; and <hi rend="italic">heating,</hi> of the same, covered with waterproof
                    material, used in congestion, external or internal, for short or long periods.
                    Poultices, warm, of bread, linseed, bran, &amp;c., changed but twice in
                    twenty-four hours, are identical in action with the heating bandage, and
                    superior only in the greater warmth and consequent vital activity their closer
                    application to the skin ensures.</p>
                <p>(∕.) Fomentations and poultices, hot or cold, sinapisms, stupes, rubefacients,
                    irritants, frictions, kneadings, calisthenics, gymnastics, electricity, &amp;c.,
                    are adjuncts largely employed in hydropathic practice. Water drinking, while
                    still an important factor in hydropathy, has declined somewhat since the early
                    times of the system.</p>
                <p>But that which has from the first distinguished modern hydropathy, and still
                    makes its strict practice a thing apart, is the “crisis” so called. It is
                    related of Priessnitz that, when a boy'of fourteen, and treating a sprain, as
                    was the native custom, with wet cloths, he observed an eruption appear beneath
                    them, with immediate recovery of the part. Gradually the significance and wider
                    application of this eruption dawned upon him, until it came to hold so prominent
                    a place in his practice as to be regarded by many as his greatest discovery. The
                    eruption coinciding in point of time with recovery as a rule, it was called the
                    crisis, involving doubtless a reference to the term as used by Hippocrates and
                    his successors. But with Priessnitz crisis attained a higher rank, a wider
                    application, and a more definite character. He first showed it to be producible
                    at will under given conditions of the patient, and amenable to direction and
                    control. This eruption, it is claimed, appears only in morbid states of the
                    blood (cachexia) resulting from derangement or defect in the organs of
                    assimilation or excretion or both <hi rend="italic">{p.g.,</hi> gout,
                    rheumatism), or from the presence of a specific poison <hi rend="italic"
                        >(e.g.,</hi> syphilis). The continuous application to a given tract of skin
                    of the heating bandage or poultice (mediums merely for the exhibition of warmth
                    and moisture) stimulates, in a cumulative way, its vascular and nervous
                    activity, and leads, it may be in a few days or weeks (in some cases hours, in
                    others months), to an eruption, papular, then pustular, and ultimately resolving
                    itself into a suppurating surface commensurate with the area covered by the
                    bandage. There is, in the latter stage, a copious discharge of yellowish-green
                    pus, usually foetid, varied occasionally with patches of brown, blue, or
                    metallic green, and accompanied with itching, sometimes intense. The general
                    temperature is not, as a rule, disturbed; the pulse, except perhaps for the
                    first day or two, falls, if previously quick, to a natural rate; the weight and
                    strength, in the most favourable cases from the outset, and in the rest later
                    on, increase, and it is not uncommon to find the anomaly of a patient exulting
                    in freedom from suffering and a return of the impulses of health simultaneously
                    with the appearance of an extensive inflammation of the skin. The applications,
                    continued without intermission and unaltered (save as cleanliness requires) for
                    weeks or months, according to the nature of the case, are at last no more
                    stained with pus but with serum <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n560/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0560-0545"/> simply; and finally, still without change of
                    application, the skin will heal, or, at most, show a little psoriasis,
                    pityriasis, or eczema, or, it may be, but a faint tinge of red. The bandages are
                    then withdrawn. The original symptoms meanwhile have disappeared with more or
                    less celerity and completeness; and with the eruption has departed the disease
                    that called for it and made it possible. Strength grows apace, no longer taxed
                    by disease or crisis, until recovery in appropriate cases is absolute and
                    secure.</p>
                <p>Occasionally the cutaneous inflammation extends in the form of psoriasis, eczema,
                    sudamina, a papular rash, or a succession of boils, invading parts untouched by
                    the wet compress. This is called a general crisis; it usually occurs in the last
                    stage of the local one, sometimes after it has ceased, and is advantageous and
                    transient. Debility, whether pre-existing or consequent on the crisis, may call
                    for some modification of its severity and duration, whether by instalments at
                    proper intervals, or curtailment in the later stages, the natural emunctories
                    being relied on to complete the work of Surification at greater leisure. A
                    residuum of incurable organic egeneration, as of the kidneys or liver, may
                    likewise put limits to recovery, and provide perpetual material for crisis until
                    the patient is worn out in a vain and ignorant attempt at cure. It was the
                    failure of the earlier hydropathists—through inexperience, default of medical
                    education, or inordinate enthusiasm—to recognize these limitations, that brought
                    crisis into its present discredit and comparative desuetude. Where it is
                    necessary from these or other causes to relieve the patient of the eruption, the
                    substitution of simple ointment, unsalted lard, or other oleaginous or viscid
                    material for the stimulating bandages or poultices, permits the excitement to
                    subside, and, with occasional exceptions, the skin, in a few days, it may be
                    hours, bears little trace of the eruption.</p>
                <p>In the course of hydropathic treatment there occur, though rarely, attacks of
                    diarrhoea, sickness, diuresis, or diaphoresis, which, having been observed
                    frequently to mark the turning point in the history of the case, are held to be
                    varieties of crisis, disturbances attendant on the expulsion of the materies
                    morbi from the system.</p>
                <p>The theory of crisis may be stated thus. The digestive and assimilative organs
                    are, as is well known, involved, whether primarily or secondarily, in by far the
                    majority of morbid conditions. Theirproduct, the blood, undergoing constant
                    renewal, becomesneces-sarily more or less impaired,—deprived of the blandness
                    that pertains alone to a pure and perfect condition, with what may be termed an
                    inflammatory disposition as the result. The most familiar, because pronounced,
                    forms are the gouty, rheumatic, tubercular, and strumous diatheses. Later the
                    excretory organs, in common with the whole economy, must more or less become
                    deranged, with additions, in consequence, to the sum of morbid elements in the
                    blood, such as uraemic and biliary matters. A vicious circle of action and
                    reaction is established from which escape is difficult, if not impossible, in
                    its more pronounced developments. The digestive disorder begets imperfect and
                    impure blood, and the morbid blood keeps up, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >coeteris</hi><hi rend="italic">paribus</hi> increases, the initial and
                    originating digestive disorder. In all but its most advanced stages ordinary
                    measures, hydropathic or other, may suffice to break this chain,'and, by
                    eliminating one or more of its links, render recovery possible, or accomplish
                    it. It is when the complication is beyond their reach that the domain peculiar
                    to crisis begins. The superior vascularity and vitality of the digestive
                    organs—the alimentary tract of mucous membrane, the pancreas, and the liver—is
                    what makes them (in addition to their susceptibility to injury through errors in
                    diet) so commonly the seat of diseased action. The highly nervous and vascular
                    structure of the skin makes easy its elevation to at least an equality in vital
                    activity with the mucous membrane. Warmth and moisture continuously applied to a
                    given portion will, in time, effect this, aided doubtless by maceration and
                    denudation of the cuticle and exposure of the sensitive cutis vera. It thus
                    becomes the seat of greatest vital activity; pre-eminence in morbid activity
                    naturally follows, and a genuine metastasis is effected, such as the natural
                    history of disease is rich in examples of. There is a decline, <hi rend="italic"
                        >pro</hi><hi rend="italic">tanto,</hi> of the primary internal disorder
                    under this combined pressure, first by the diversion of morbific elements, and
                    then by the diversion of an appreciable quantity of the blood itself, and by
                    counter-irritation, when the site of the vicarious inflammation has been
                    selected with that in view. The aid of a sustained derivation to the entire
                    cutaneous surface and the extremities is at the same time secured by means of
                    the Turkish bath, full packs, and other stimulating agents, while, at the same
                    time, due care is taken to eliminate and negative the original causes of
                    disease. The sum of morbid activity is for the time being increased and
                    intensified; but, in the new location, no longer self-supporting and
                    self-perpetuating, it is sooner or later exhausted. The change in the relation
                    of the matenes morbi to the digestive system puts an end at one and the same
                    time to the originating and sustaining conditions. The failure ot simple,
                    counter-irritation (where, as by sinapisms, vesicatories, <hi rend="italic">.
                        c∙</hi>, ^ <hi rend="superscript"> ιe</hi> irritant is derived from without)
                    to effect the same result m many of the cases afterwards cured by crisis
                    negatives of itself the view that the results of the latter are to be attributed
                    to the element in it of counter-irritation alone.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> Arnott, <hi rend="italic">Indigestion and
                        its Treatment by the Local Application of Heat and Moisture,</hi> 1847;
                    Balbirnie, <hi rend="italic">Water Cure in Consumption,</hi> 1847, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hydropathic Aphorisms,</hi> 1856, and <hi rend="italic">A Plea
                        for the Turkish Bath,</hi> 1862; Baynard, <hi rend="italic">Hot and Cold
                        Baths,</hi> 1715; Beni-Barde, <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >&lt;T</hi><hi rend="italic">Hydrothérapie,</hi> 1874; Bushnan, <hi
                        rend="italic">observations on Hydropathy,</hi> 1846; Clari&lt;lge, <hi
                        rend="italic">Cold Water Cure, or Hydropathy</hi> (passed through nineteen
                    editions in 18 months), 1841, <hi rend="italic">Facts and Evidence in Support of
                        Hydropathy,</hi> 1843, and <hi rend="italic">Cold Water, Tepid Water, and
                        Friction Cure,</hi> 1849; Cohn, <hi rend="italic">Kaltwasser-Heilkunde,</hi>
                    Leipsic; Crescenzo, <hi rend="italic">Ragionamenti intorno alia nuova</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Medicina</hi><hi rend="italic">dell'</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Acqua,</hi> 1727; Currie, <hi rend="italic">Medical Reports on the Effects
                        of Water,</hi> &lt;tc., 1797; Dunlop, <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of the
                        Bath,</hi> 1873; East, <hi rend="italic">Principles and Practice of the
                        Water Cure,</hi> 1850, and <hi rend="italic">Hydropathy in the Diseases of
                        Women,</hi> 1850; Floyer, <hi rend="italic">Psychrolousia, or the History of
                        Cold-Bathing,</hi> &lt;fcc., 1702; Fyfe, <hi rend="italic">Manual of the
                        Turkish Bath,</hi> 1856; Gibbs, <hi rend="italic">Letters from
                        Greifenberg,</hi> 1847; R. H. Graham, <hi rend="italic">Gräfenberg,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">or a True Account of the Water Cure,</hi> 1844; T. J. Graham,
                        <hi rend="italic">Cold Water System,</hi> 1843; Gully, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Simple Treatment of Disease,</hi> 1842, <hi rend="italic">Exposition of the
                        Symptoms, &lt;kc., of Neuropathy,</hi> 1842, <hi rend="italic">Water Cure in
                        Chronic Disease,</hi> 1847, and <hi rend="italic">Water Cure in Acute
                        Disease,</hi> 1863; J. G. Hahn (Breslau), <hi rend="italic">Cold Affusion in
                        Fevers,</hi> 1737, and <hi rend="italic">Cold Sponging in Fever</hi> (in <hi
                        rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Germanica),</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >1736; J.</hi> S. Hahn (Schweidnitz), <hi rend="italic">Observations on the
                        Healing Virtues of Cold Water,</hi> 1738; S. Hahn, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Psychrolusia Veterum Renovata,</hi> 1738; Hancocke, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Febrifugum Magnum, or Common Water the Cure of Fevers,</hi> 1700;
                    Henderson, <hi rend="italic">Treatment of Disease by means of Water,</hi> 1859;
                    Hunter, <hi rend="italic">Hydropathy for Home Use,</hi> 1879; Jackson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Exposition of Practice of Cold Affusion in Fevers,</hi> 1808;
                    E. Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Hydropathy, its Theory, Principles, and
                        Practice,</hi> 1843, <hi rend="italic">Theory and Principles of the Water
                        Cure,</hi> 1852, <hi rend="italic">Domestic Practice of Hydropathy,</hi>
                    1849, and <hi rend="italic">Hydropathic Treatment of Diseases of Women,</hi>
                    1849; H. F. Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Researches into the Effects of Cold
                        Water,</hi> 1850; Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Results of Hydropathy,</hi>
                    1846; W. Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Hydropathic Treatment of Children,</hi>
                    1846, and <hi rend="italic">Journal of Health,</hi> 1852; King, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hot and Cold Bathing,</hi> 1738; E. W. Lane, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hydropathy, or the Natural System of Medical Treatment,</hi> 1857; R. J.
                    Lane, <hi rend="italic">Life at the Water Cure,</hi> 1851; Sir E. B. Lytton, <hi
                        rend="italic">Confessions of a Water Patient,</hi> 1851; Macleod, <hi
                        rend="italic">Theory of the Treatment of Disease,</hi> 1868; Mayo, <hi
                        rend="italic">Cold Water Cure, its Use and Misuse Examined,</hi> 1845;
                    Richardson, <hi rend="italic">Fourteen Years' Experience of Cold Water,</hi>
                    1857; Rumford, <hi rend="italic">Salubrity of Warm Bathing,</hi> 1802; Shew, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hydropathic Family Physician,</hi> 1857; Short, ths <hi
                        rend="italic">the Inward Use of Cold· Water;</hi> Schwertner, <hi
                        rend="italic">Medicina</hi><hi rend="italic">Vera Universalis;</hi> Simpson,
                        <hi rend="italic">observations on Cold Bathing;</hi> Smedley, <hi
                        rend="italic">Practical Hydropathy, 1679;</hi> Smethurst, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hydrotherapia, or. The Water Cure,</hi> 1843; Smith, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Curiosities of Common Water;</hi> Spence, <hi rend="italic">Constipation
                        Cured by Cold Water,</hi> 1784; Todaro, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Aequa Frigida;</hi> Trail, <hi rend="italic">Hydropathic
                        Encyclopedia;</hi> Van der Heyden, <hi rend="italic">Arthritifugum
                        Magnum,</hi> Ghent, 1649; Wainwright, <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the
                        Nature and Use of Baths,</hi> 1737; weiss. <hi rend="italic">Handbook of
                        Hydropathy,</hi> 1844; Wilmot, <hi rend="italic">Tribute to the Cold Water
                        Cure,</hi> 1843; wilson, <hi rend="italic">Principles and Practice of the
                        Cold Water Cure,</hi> 1854, <hi rend="italic">and The Water Cure,</hi> 1859;
                    Wright, <hi rend="italic">Memoir on Cold Affusion in Fevers,</hi> 1786. (W. B.
                    H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
