<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0056-0047-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOGARTH, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 12, page 47</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1089641">Rakes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:817559">Artists</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1243607">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x362">Printing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n76n">Prints</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n56/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOGARTH, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>
                    (1697-1764). Apart from the story of his works, the life of the greatest English
                    pictorial sa^tirist, when divested of doubtful tradition, is singularly devoid
                    of incident. It is mainly to be found in the autobiographical <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoranda</hi> published by John Ireland in 1798, and the successive <hi
                    rend="italic">Anecdotes</hi> of the antiquary, John Nichols, Hogarth was born in
                    London on the 10th day of November 1697, and baptized on the 28th in the church
                    of St Bartholomew the Great. His father was a schoolmaster and literary hack,
                    who had come to the metropolis to seek that fortune which had been denied to him
                    in his native Westmoreland. His son seems to have been early distinguished
                    rather by a talent for drawing and an active perceptive faculty than by any
                    close attention to the learning which he was soon shrewd enough to see had not
                    male his parent prosper. “Shows of all sorts gave me uncommon pleasure when an
                    infant,” lie says, “and mimicry, common to all children, was remarkable in me. .
                    . . My exercises when at school were more remarkable for the ornaments which
                    adorned them than for the exercise itself.” This being the case, it is no wonder
                    that, by his own desire, he was apprenticed to a silver-plate engraver, Mr Ellis
                    Gamble, at the sign of the “Golden Angel” in Cranbourne Street or Alley,
                    Leicester Fields. For this master he engraved a shop-card which is still extant.
                    When his apprenticeship began is not recorded; but it must have been concluded
                    before the beginning of 1720, for in April of that year he appears to have set
                    up as engraver on his own account. His desires, however, were not limited to
                    silver-plate engraving. “Engraving on copper was, at twenty years of age, my
                    utmost ambition.” For this he lacked the needful skill as a draughtsman; and his
                    account of the means which he took to supply this want, without too much
                    interfering with his pleasure, is thoroughly characteristic, though it can
                    scarcely be recommended as an example. “Laying it down,” he says, “first as an
                    axiom, that he who could by any means acquire and retain in his memory perfect
                    ideas of the subjects he meant to draw would have as clear a knowledge of the
                    figure as a man who can write freely hath of the twenty-four letters of the
                    alphabet and their infinite combinations (each of these being composed of
                    lines), and would consequently be an accurate designer, . . . I therefore
                    endeavoured to habituate myself to the exercise of a sort of technical memory,
                    and by repeating in my own mind the parts of which objects were composed I could
                    by degrees combine and put them down with my pencil.” This account, it is
                    possible, has something of the complacency of the old age in which it was
                    written; but there is little doubt that his marvellous power of seizing
                    expression owed less to patient academical study than to his unexampled
                    eye-memory and tenacity of minor detail. But he was not entirely without
                    technical training, as, by his own showing, he occasionally “took the life” to
                    correct his memories, and is known to have studied at Sir James Thornhill’s then
                    recently opened art school.</p>
                <p>“His first employment” <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> after he set up for himself)
                    “seems,” says Nichols, “to have been the engraving of arms and shop bills.”
                    After this he was employed in designing “plates for booksellers.” Of these early
                    and mostly insignificant works we may pass over The Lottery, an Emblematic Print
                    on the South Sea, and some book illustrations, to pause at Masquerades and
                    Operas, 1724, the first plate he published on his own account. This is a clever
                    little satire on contemporary follies, such as the masquerades of the Swiss
                    adventurer Heidegger, the popular Italian opera singers, Rich’s pantomimes at
                    Lincoln’s Inn Fields, and last, but by no means least, the exaggerated
                    popularity of Lord Burlington’s <hi rend="italic">frrotege,</hi> the architect
                    painter William Kent, who is here represented on the summit cf Burlington Gate,
                    with Raphael and Michelangelo for supporters. This worthy Hogarth had doubtless
                    not learned to despise less in the school of his rival Sir James Thornhill.
                    Indeed almost ’ the next of Hogarth’s important prints was aimed at Kent alone,
                    being that memorable burlesque of the unfortunate altarpiece designed by the
                    latter for St Clement’s Danes, and which, in deference to the ridicule of the
                    parishioners, Bishop Gibson took down in 1725, Hogarth’s squib, which appeared
                    subsequently, exhibits it as a very masterpiece of confusion and bad drawing. In
                    1726 he prepared twelve large engravings for Butler’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hudibras.</hi> These he himself valued highly, and they are the best of his
                    book illustrations. But he was far too individual to be the patient interpreter
                    of other men’s thoughts, and it is not in this direction that his successes are
                    to be sought.</p>
                <p>To 1727-28 belongs one of those rare occurrences which have survived as
                    contributions to his biography. He was engaged by a certain Morris, a tapestry
                    worker, to prepare a design for the Element of Earth. Morris, however, having
                    heard that he was “an engraver and no painter,” declined the work when
                    completed, and Hogarth accordingly sued him for the money in the Westminster
                    Court, where, on the 28th of May 1728, the case was decided in his (Hogarth’s)
                    favour. It may have been the aspersion thus early cast on his skill as a painter
                    (coupled perhaps with the unsatisfactory state of print-selling, owing to the
                    uncontrolled circulation of piratical copies) that induced him about this time
                    to turn his attention to the production of “small conversation pieces” (7.e.,
                    groups in oil of full-length portraits from 12 to 15 inches high), many of which
                    are still preserved in different collections. “This,” he says, “having novelty,
                    succeeded for a few years.” Among his other efforts in oil between 1728 and 1732
                    were The Wanstead Assembly, The House of Commons examining Barnbridge, an
                    infamous warden of the Fleet, and numerous pictuιe&gt; of the chief actors in
                    Gay’s popular <hi rend="italic">Beggar's Opera.</hi></p>
                <p>On the 23d of March 1729 he was married at old Paddington church to Jane
                    Thornhill, the only daughter of Kent’s rival above-mentioned. The match was a
                    clandestine one, although Lady Thornhill appears to have favoured it. We next
                    hear of him in “lodgings at South Lambeth,” where he rendered some assistance to
                    the then well-known Jonathan Tyers, who opened Vauxhall in 1732 with an
                    entertainment styled a <hi rend="italic">ridotto al fresco.</hi> For these
                    gardens Hogarth painted a poor picture of Henry VIII. and Anna Bullen, and for
                    them he also made some designs of the Four Times of the Day, which he afterwards
                    elaborated into a finished series. The only engravings between 1726 and 1732
                    which need be referred to are the Large Masquerade Ticket (1727), another satire
                    on masquerades, and the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n57/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0057-0048"/> print of Burlington Gate, 1731, evoked by Pope’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Epistle to Lord Burlington,</hi> and defending Lord Chandos,
                    who is therein satirized. This print gave great offence, and was, it is said,
                    suppressed. To 1732 belongs that genial journey from London to Sheerness, of
                    which the original record still survives at the British Museum in an oblong MS.
                    volume, entitled <hi rend="italic">An Account of ιvhat seem'd most Remarkable in
                    the Five Days' Peregrination of the Five Folloιving Persons, Vizt., Messieurs
                    Tothall. Scott, Hogarth, Thornhill and Forrest. Begun on Saturday May 21th</hi>
                    1732 <hi rend="italic">and Finish'd On the</hi> 31si <hi rend="italic">of the
                    Same Month.</hi><hi rend="italic">Abi tu</hi><hi rend="italic">et fac</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">similiter.—Inscription on Dulwich Colledge Porch.</hi> The
                    journal, which is written by Forrest, the father of Garrick’s friend Theodosius
                    Forrest, gives a good idea of what a “frisk ”—as Johnson called it—was in those
                    days, while the illustrations were by Hogarth and Samuel Scott the landscape
                    painter. John Thornhill, Sir James’s son, made the map. This version (in prose)
                    was subsequently run into rhyme by one of Hogarth’s friends, the Rev. Mr
                    Gostling of Canterbury, and after the artist’s death both versions were
                    published. In the absence of other biographical detail, they are of considerable
                    interest to the student of Hogarth.</p>
                <p>In 1733 Hogarth moved into the “Golden Head” in Leicester Fields, which, with
                    occasional absences at Chiswick, he continued to occupy until his death. By this
                    date he must have completed the earliest of those great series of moral
                    paintings which first gave him his position as a great and original genius. This
                    was A Harlot’s Progress, the paintings for which, if we may trust the date in
                    the last of the pictures, were finished in 1731. The engravings, by the artist
                    himself, were published in 1734. We have no record of the particular train of
                    thought which prompted these story-pictures; but it may perhaps be fairly
                    assumed that the necessity for creating some link of interest between the
                    personages of the little “conversation pieces” above referred to led to the
                    further idea of connecting several groups or scenes so as to form a sequent
                    narrative. “I wished,” says Hogarth, “to compose pictures on canvas, similar to
                    representations on the stage.” “I have endeavoured,” he says again, “to treat my
                    subject as a dramatic writer; my picture is my stage, and men and women my
                    players, who by means of certain actions and gestures are to exhibit <hi
                    rend="italic">a dumb show."</hi> There was never a more eloquent dumb show than
                    this of the Harlot’s Progress. In six scenes the miserable career of a woman of
                    the town is traced out remorselessly from its first facile beginning to its
                    shameful and degraded end. Nothing of the detail is softened or abated; the
                    whole is acted out <hi rend="italic">coram ρopulo,</hi> with the hard,
                    uncompassionate morality of the age the painter lived in, while the introduction
                    here and there of one or two well-known characters like Colonel Chatteris and
                    Justice Gonson give a vivid reality to the satire. It had an immediate success.
                    To say nothing of the fact that the talent of the paintings completely
                    reconciled Sir James Thornhill to the son-in law he had hitherto refused to
                    acknowledge, more than twelve hundred names of subscribers to the engravings
                    were entered in the artist’s book. On the appearance of plate iii. the lords of
                    the treasury trooped to Leicester Fields for Sir John Gonson’s portrait which it
                    contained. Theophilus Cibber made the story into a pantomime, and some one else
                    into a ballad opera; and it gave rise to numerous pamphlets and poems. It was
                    painted on fan-mounts and transferred to cups and saucers. Lastly, it was freely
                    pirated. There could be no surer testimony to its popularity.</p>
                <p>The favourable reception given to A Harlot’s Progress prompted A Rake’s Progress,
                    which speedily followed, although it had not a like success. It was in eight
                    plates in lieu of six. The story is unequal; but there is nothing finer than the
                    figure of the desperate rake in the Covent Garden gaming-house, or the admirable
                    scenes in the Fleet prison and Bedlam, where at last his headlong career comes
                    to its tragic termination. The plates abound with allusive suggestion and covert
                    humour; but it is impossible to attempt any detailed-description of them
                    here.</p>
                <p>A Rake’s Progress was dated June 25, 1735, and the engravings bear the words
                    “according to Act of Parliament.” This was an Act (8 Geo. II. cap. 13) which
                    Hogarth had been instrumental in obtaining from the legislature, being stirred
                    thereto by the shameless piracies of rival printsellers. Although loosely drawn,
                    it served its purpose; and the painter commemorated his success by a long
                    inscription on the plate entitled Crowns, Mitres, &amp;c., afterwards used as a
                    subscription ticket to the Election series. These subscription tickets to his
                    engravings, let us add, are among the brightest and most vivacious of the
                    artist’s productions. That to the Harlot’s Progress was entitled Boys peeping at
                    Nature, while the Rake’s Progress was heralded by the delighful etching known as
                    A Pleased Audience at a Play, or The Laughing Audience.</p>
                <p>We must pass more briefly over the prints which followed the two Progresses,
                    noting first A Midnight Modern Conversation, an admirable drinking scene which
                    comes between them in 1734, and the bright little plate of Southwark Fair,
                    which, though dated 1733, was published with A Rake’s Progress in 1735. Between
                    these and Marriage <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mode,</hi> upon
                    the pictures of which the painter must have been not long after at work, come
                    the small prints of the Consultation of Physicians, Scholars at a Lecture, and
                    Sleeping Congregation, 1736; the Four Times of the Day, 1738, a series of
                    pictures of everyday 18th century life, the earlier designs for which have been
                    already referred to; the Strolling Actresses dressing in a Barn, 1738, which
                    Walpole held to be, “for wit and imagination, without any other end, the best of
                    all the painter’s works;” and finally the admirable plates of the Distrest Poet,
                    painfully composing a poem on “Riches” in a garret, and the Enraged Musician
                    fulminating from his parlour window upon a discordant orchestra of
                    knife-grinders, milk-girls, ballad-singers, and the rest upon the pavement
                    outside. These are dated respectively 1736 and 1741. To this period also <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the period preceding the production of the plates of
                    Marriage <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mode)</hi> belong two of
                    those history pictures to which, in emulation of the Haymans and Thornhills, the
                    artist was continually attracted. The Pool of Bethesda and the Good Samaritan,
                    “with figures seven feet high,” were painted <hi rend="italic">circa</hi> 1736,
                    and presented by the artist to St Bartholomew’s Hospital, where they remain.
                    They were not masterpieces; and it is pleasanter to think of his connexion with
                    Captain Coram’s recently established Foundling Hospital (1739), which he aided
                    with his money, his graver, and his brush, and for which he painted that
                    admirable portrait of the good old philanthropist which is still, and
                    deservedly, one of its chief ornaments.</p>
                <p>In A Harlot’s Progress Hogarth had not strayed much beyond the lower walks of
                    society, and although, in /V Rake’s Progress, his hero was taken from the middle
                    classes, he can scarcely be said to have quitted those fields of observation
                    which are common to every spectator. It is therefore more remarkable, looking to
                    his education and antecedents, that his masterpiece, Marriage <hi rend="italic"
                    >à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mode,</hi> should successfully depict, as the
                    advertisement has it, “a variety of modern occurrences in high life.” Yet, as an
                    accurate delineation of the surroundings of upper class 18th century society,
                    his Marriage <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mode</hi> has never,
                    we believe, been seriously assailed. The countess’s bedroom, the earl’s
                    apartment with its lavish coronets and old masters, the grand saloon with its
                    marble pillars and grotesque ornaments, are fully as true to nature as the
                    frowsy chamber in the “Turk’s <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n58/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0058-0049"/> Head Bagnio,” the quack-doctor’s museum in St
                    Martin’s Lane, or the mean opulence of the merchant’s house in the city. And
                    what story could be more vividly, more perspicuously, more powerfully told than
                    this godless alliance of <hi rend="italic">sacs</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                    parchemins</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> this miserable tragedy of an
                    ill-assorted marriage? There is no defect of invention, no superfluity of
                    detail, no purposeless stroke. It has the merit of a work by a great master of
                    fiction, with the additional advantages which result from the pictorial fashion
                    of the narrative; and it is matter for congratulation that it is still to be
                    seen by all the world in the National Gallery, where it can tell its own tale
                    better than pages of commentary.</p>
                <p>The engravings of Marriage <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mode</hi>
                    were dated April 1745. Although the painter by this time found a ready market
                    for his engravings, he does not appear to have been equally successful in
                    selling his pictures. The people bought his prints; but the more opulent and not
                    numerous connoisseurs who purchased pictures were wholly in the hands of the
                    importers and manufacturers of “old masters.” In February 1745 the original oil
                    paintings of the two Progresses, the Four Times of the Day, and the Strolling
                    Actresses were still unsold. On the last day of that month Hogarth disposed of
                    them by an ill-devised kind of auction, the details of which may be read in
                    Nichols’s <hi rend="italic">Anecdotes,</hi> for the paltry sum of £427, 7s. No
                    better fate attended Marriage <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">la
                    Mode,</hi> which five years later became the property of Mr Lane of Hillingdon
                    for 120 guineas, being then in Carlo Maratti frames which had cost the artist
                    four guineas a piece. Something of this was no doubt due to Hogarth’s
                    impracticable arrangements, but the fact shows conclusively how completely blind
                    his contemporaries were to his merits as a painter, and how hopelessly in
                    bondage to the all-powerful picture-dealers. Of these latter the painter himself
                    gave a graphic picture in a letter addressed by him under the pseudonym of
                    “Britophil” to the <hi rend="italic">St James's Evening Post,</hi> in 1737.</p>
                <p>But, if Hogarth was not successful with his dramas on canvas, he occasionally
                    shared with his contemporaries in the popularity of portrait painting. For a
                    picture, executed in 1746, of Garrick as Richard III. he was paid £200, “which
                    was more,” says he, “than any English artist ever received for a single
                    portrait.” In the same year a sketch of Simon Fraser, Lord Lovat, afterwards
                    beheaded on Tower Hill, had an exceptional success. Our limits do not, however,
                    enable us to refer to his remaining works in detail, and we must content
                    ourselves with a brief enumeration of the most important. These are The Stage
                    Coach or Country Inn Yard, 1747; the series of twelve plates entitled Industry
                    and Idleness, 1747, depicting the career of two London apprentices; the Gate of
                    Calais, 1749, which had its origin in a rather unfortunate visit paid to France
                    by the painter after the peace of Aix-la-Chapelle; the March to Finchley, 1750;
                    Beer Street, Gin Lane, and the Four Stages of Cruelty, 1751; the admirable
                    representations of election humours in the days of Sir Robert Walpole, entitled
                    Four Prints of an Election, 1755-8; and the plate of Credulity, Superstition,
                    and Fanaticism, a Medley, 1762, adapted from an earlier unpublished design
                    called Enthusiasm Delineated. Besides these must be chronicled three more essays
                    in the “great style of history painting,” viz., 1’aul before Felix, Moses
                    brought to Pharaoh’s Daughter, and the Altarpiece for St Mary Redcliff at
                    Bristol. The first two were engraved in 1751-2, the last in 1794. A subscription
                    ticket to the earlier pictures, entitled Paul before Felix Burlesqued, had a
                    popularity far greater than that of the prints themselves.</p>
                <p>In 1745 Hogarth painted that admirable portrait of himself with his pug-dog
                    Trump, which is now in the National Gallery. In a corner of this he had drawn on
                    a palette a serpentine line with the words “The Line of Beauty and Grace.” Much
                    inquiry ensued as to “the meaning of this hieroglyphic;” and in an unpropitious
                    hour the painter resolved to explain his meaning in writing. The result was the
                    well-known <hi rend="italic">Analysis of Beauty,</hi> 1753, a treatise “to fix
                    the fluctuating ideas of Taste,” otherwise a desultory essay having for pretext
                    the precept attributed to Michelangelo that a figure should be always
                    “Pyramidali, Serpent-like, and multiplied by one two and three.” The fate of the
                    book was what might have been expected. By the painter’s adherents it was
                    praised as a final deliverance upon aesthetics; by his enemies and professional
                    rivals, its obscurities, and the minor errors which, notwithstanding the
                    benevolent efforts of literary friends, the work had not escaped, were made the
                    subject of endless ridicule and caricature. It added little to its author’s
                    fame, and it is perhaps to be regretted that he ever undertook it. Moreover,
                    there were further humiliations in store for him. In 1759 the success of a
                    little picture called The Lady’s Last Stake, painted for Lord Charlemont,
                    procured him a commission from Sir Richard Grosvenor to paint another picture
                    “upon the same terms.” Unhappily on this occasion he deserted his own field of
                    <hi rend="italic">genre</hi> and social satire, to select the story from
                    Boccaccio (or rather Dryden) of Sigismonda weeping over the heart of her
                    murdered lover Guiscardo, being the subject of a picture by Furini in Sir Luke
                    Schaub’s collection which had recently been sold for £400. The picture, over
                    which he spent much time and patience, was not regarded as a success; and Sir
                    Richard rather meanly shuffled out of his bargain upon the plea that “the
                    constantly having it before one’s eyes would be too often occasioning melancholy
                    thoughts to arise in one’s mind.” Sigismonda, therefore, much to the artist’s
                    mortification, and the delight of the malicious, remained upon his hands. As, by
                    her husband’s desire, his widow valued it at £500, it found no purchaser until
                    after her death, when the Boydells bought it for 56 guineas. It was exhibited,
                    with others of Hogarth’s pictures, at the Spring Gardens exhibition of 1761, for
                    the catalogue of which Hogarth engraved a Head-piece and a Tail-piece which are
                    still the delight of collectors; and finally, by the bequest of the late Mr J.
                    H. Anderdon, it passed in 1879 to the National Gallery, where, in spite of
                    theatrical treatment and a repulsive theme, it still commands admiration for its
                    colour, drawing, and expression.</p>
                <p>In 1761 he was sixty-five years of age, and he had but three years more to live.
                    These three years were embittered by that unhappy quarrel with Wilkes and
                    Churchill, over which most of his biographers are contented to pass rapidly,
                    Having succeeded John Thornhill in 1757 as serjeant painter (to which post he
                    was reappointed at the accession of George HL), an evil genius prompted him in
                    1762 to do some “timed” thing in the ministerial interest, and he accordingly
                    published the indifferent satire of The Times, plate i. This at once brought him
                    into collision with his quondam friends, John Wilkes and Churchill the poet; and
                    the immediate result was a violent attack upon him, both as a man and an artist
                    in the opposition <hi rend="italic">North Briton,</hi> No. 17. The alleged decay
                    of his powers, the miscarriage of Sigismonda, the cobbled composition of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Analysis,</hi> were all discussed with scurrilous malignity by
                    those who had known his domestic life and learned his weaknesses. The old artist
                    was deeply wounded, and his health was failing. Early in the next year, however,
                    he replied by that squinting portrait of Wilkes which will for ever carry his
                    features to posterity. Churchill retaliated in July by a savage <hi
                    rend="italic">Epistle to William Hogarth,</hi> to which the artist rejoined by a
                    print of Churchill as a bear, in torn bands and ruffles, not the most successful
                    of his works. “The pleasure, and pecuniary advantage,” writes Hogarth, <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n59/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0059-0050"/><hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> which I derived
                    from these two engravings (of Wilkes and Churchill), “together with occasionally
                    riding on horseback, restored me to as much health as can be expected at my time
                    of life.” He produced but one more print, that of Finis, or The Bathos, March
                    1764, a strange jumble of “fag ends,” intended as a tail-piece to his collected
                    prints; and on the 26th October of the same year he died of an aneurism at his
                    house in Leicester Square. His wife, to whom he left his plates as a chief
                    source of income, survived him until 1789. He was buried in Chiswick churchyard,
                    where a tomb was erected to him by his friends in 1771, with a well-known
                    epitaph by Garrick. Not far off, on the road to Chiswick Gardens, is the now
                    tumble-down house in which, for many years of his life, he spent the summer
                    seasons.</p>
                <p>From such records of him as survive, Hogarth appears to have been much what from
                    his portrait one might suppose him to have been—a blue-eyed, honest, combative,
                    little man, thoroughly national in his prejudices and antipathies, fond of
                    flattery, sensitive like most satirists, a good friend, an intractable enemy,
                    ambitious, as he somewhere says, in all things to be singular, and not always
                    accurately estimating the extent of his powers. With the art connoisseurship of
                    his day he was wholly at war, because, as he believed, it favoured foreign
                    mediocrity at the expense of native talent; and in the heat of argument he would
                    probably, as he admits, often come “to utter blasphemous expressions against the
                    divinity even of Raphael Urbino, Correggio, and Michelangelo.” But it was rather
                    against the third-rate copies of third-rate artists—the “ship-loads of
                    manufactured Dead Christs, Holy Families, and Madonnas ”—that his indignation
                    was directed; and in speaking of his attitude with regard to the great masters
                    of art, it is well .to remember his words to Mrs Piozzi :—“The connoisseurs and
                    I are at war you know; and because I hate <hi rend="italic">them,</hi> they
                    think I hate <hi rend="italic">Titian—</hi> and let them !”</p>
                <p>But no doubt it was in a measure owing to this hostile attitude of his towards
                    the all-powerful picture-brokers that his contemporaries failed to adequately
                    recognize his merits as a painter, and persisted in regarding him as an
                    ingenious humorist alone. Time has reversed that unjust sentence. He is now held
                    to have been an excellent painter, pure and harmonious in his colouring,
                    wonderfully dexterous and direct in his handling, and in his composition leaving
                    little or nothing to be desired. As an engraver his work is more conspicuous for
                    its vigour, spirit, and intelligibility than for finish and beauty of line. He
                    desired that it should tell its own tale plainly, and bear the distinct impress
                    of his individuality, and in this he thoroughly succeeded. As a draughtsman his
                    skill has sometimes been debated, and his work at times undoubtedly bears marks
                    of haste, and even carelessness. If, however, he is judged by his best instead
                    of his worst, his work will not be found to be wanting in this respect. But it
                    is not after all as a draughtsman, an engraver, or a painter that he claims his
                    pre-eminence among English artists—it is as a wit, a humorist, a satirist upon
                    canvas. Regarded in this light he has never been equalled, whether for his
                    vigour of realism and dramatic power, his fancy and invention in the decoration
                    of his story, or his merciless anatomy and exposure of folly and wickedness. If
                    we regard him—as he loved to regard himself—as “author” rather than “artist,”
                    his place is with the great masters of literature,—with the Thackerays and
                    Fieldings, the Cervantes and Molières.</p>
                <p>Additions to Hogarth literature have not been numerous of late years. In 1860 Mr
                    G. A. Sala contributed some picturesque pages to the <hi rend="italic">Cornhill
                    Magazine,</hi> which were afterwards republished in book form. Much minute
                    information has also been collected in Mr F. G. Stephens’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catalogue of the Satirical Prints and Drawings in the British Museum,</hi> now
                    in course of issue. Pictures by Hogarth from private collections are constantly
                    to be found at the annual exhibitions of the Old Masters in the Royal Academy;
                    but most of the best known works have permanent homes in public galleries.
                    Marriage <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mode,</hi> Sigismonda, and
                    his own portrait are in the National Gallery; the Rake’s Progress and the
                    Election Series in thé Sloane Museum; and the March to Finchley and Captain
                    Coram at the Foundling Hospital. There are also notable pictures in the
                    Fitzwilliam Museum at Cambridge, and the National Portrait Gallery at South
                    Kensington. The Lady’s Last Stake, to which reference has been made, is at
                    present (1880) in the possession of Mr Louis Huth. (A. D. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
