<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0348-0337-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HUGUENOTS, The</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 12, page 337</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="fasttopic:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:844591">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv79x75">Coras</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n348/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HUGUENOTS, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label>. The word
                    Huguenot first appears in France about the middle of the 16th century, and there
                    is historical proof that it was imported from Geneva, where it had existed for
                    some time as a political nickname in a form which connects it directly with the
                    German-Swiss <hi rend="italic">Eidgenossen,</hi> oath-comrades, confederates. In
                    France it was used as a term of reproach for those who aimed at a reform of
                    religion according to the pattern displayed by Calvin in his famous <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutio</hi><hi rend="italic">Christianoe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Religionis.</hi> The name attached itself to the Reformers when, having shaken
                    off all connexion with Lutheranism, they were beginning to organize themselves
                    both as a church and as a political body. The Lutheran ideas, which had early
                    come into northern France by way of Metz and Meaux, had for a short time seemed
                    likely to prevail at the court of Francis I., where the king’s love of culture
                    welcomed whatever came from the land of the learned; the genius of Erasmus, or
                    the sharp satire of Hutten, or Luther’s weighty tractates, all seemed to him at
                    first to be so many protests against the darkness of a monkish past; the hymns
                    of Marot, the bright poetry of Margaret of Valois, the king’s sister, harmonized
                    not ill with the desire for a humanist reform which prevailed at the French
                    court. But when the destructive enthusiasm of the artisans who embraced the new
                    opinions, breaking out in attacks on the art-treasures of the churches,
                    alienated the royal moderates, the simpler and more marked theology of the
                    “Sacramentarians” of Geneva quietly replaced the Lutheranism of the first
                    Reformers; and by the middle of the 16th century the new Huguenots were an
                    unpopular party, drawing their inspiration from Calvin, and bitterly disliked by
                    the court and the bulk of the people of France. The persecutions, varied by
                    protection, of the reign of Francis I. had given place to a vehement desire to
                    crush the rising heresy; the character of Henry II. and his chief advisers led
                    them towards a thorough persecution.</p>
                <p>Influenced by these repressive measures, and taught by Calvin’s book and his
                    frequent letters, the French Reformers now began to organize their infant
                    churches. Hitherto they had been content to meet in quiet, to sing Marot’s
                    psalms, to listen to earnest prayer and practical discourse in some lowly
                    chamber, deferring questions as to church government; now their ecclesiastical
                    system began to develop itself. In 1555 the first Protestant French church was
                    established at Paris, and almost immediately there sprang up fifteen
                    communities, the largest being at Meaux, Poitiers, and Angers, each having its
                    pastor, elders, and deacons, each ruling itself, and recognizing no common bond
                    of union save that of charity and suffering. These were the heroic days of the
                    Huguenot movement in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n349/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0349-0338"/> France, each little church striving only to
                    fulfil the simplest ideal of Christian faith and practice, happiest when least
                    observed, purest when least developed. Three influences had hitherto acted on
                    French religious feeling :—that of the Lutherans, that of the ancient Vaudois
                    churches of southeastern France, represented by Faber, and lastly that of Calvin
                    of Noyon, the Picard exile settled at Geneva. Now a fourth element came in:
                    resistance had elicited organization, organization demanded leadership; and,
                    unhappily for France and the Huguenots, the movement fell too much into the
                    hands of secular chiefs, great lords who used it for their own political and
                    selfish purposes.</p>
                <p>In 1559 the churches of the Huguenots met in a first synod at Paris, eleven
                    sending representatives. This body drew up a confession of faith, which bears
                    throughout the mark of Calvin’s hand, in its scrupulous orthodoxy, strong
                    statements as to God’s election of some to eternal life, and careful definitions
                    of the nature and structure of the church; the synod also issued a scheme of
                    discipline to which the churches were all to conform. No church should take
                    lordship over any other (a church being a single community under one pastor).
                    Each “colloque” or synod should have a freely-elected president; every pastor
                    should come to the colloque, bringing each at least one elder or deacon from his
                    church; this body was to meet at least twice a year; new pastors were to be
                    appointed by it to vacant churches, on presentation by the elders and deacons;
                    minute rules were laid down for church discipline; it was ordered that
                    provincial synods should be held in each province, and finally that there should
                    be from time to time a general or national synod of representatives of the whole
                    body.</p>
                <p>Two years later the civil war broke out (see <hi rend="smallcaps">France,</hi>
                    vol. ix. pp. 560-564), and lasted over thirty years. At the beginning of this
                    period we have some data as to the Huguenot strength: Beza tells us that in 1558
                    there were 400,000 of them; a list presented by Condé to Catherine de’ Medici is
                    said to have contained the names of 2150 (some say 2500) churches; and it is
                    probable that the number of their open adherents had increased rapidly. John
                    Correro, Venetiah envoy in 1569, says that only one-thirtieth of the common
                    folk, but one-third of the nobles, were Huguenots, for the strength of the
                    movement had undoubtedly come to lie in the noblesse. The list of the Huguenot
                    churches given by Haag <hi rend="italic">(La France</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Protestante,</hi> voL i., "‘Pièces justificatives,” No. xviii. p. 52) provides
                    us with data as to their distribution in France. The two centres were Languedoc
                    in the south, and the Orléanais in the middle of the country; and a line drawn
                    north-west to south-east through a point halfway between Paris and Orleans would
                    nearly give the northern limit of Huguenot success. Normandy, thanks to the
                    Châtillon influence, had many churches; in Orleans and Burgundy they were well
                    represented. In Guyenne and throughout western France they had numerous
                    communities. The little independent principality of Béarn, through the influence
                    of Jeanne d’Albret, Henry IV.’s mother, was entirely Huguenot. On the other
                    hand, though there were some churches in the île de France and Champagne, they
                    had little hold there; and Picardy was from the first profoundly hostile to
                    them, while Paris became the headquarters of the Catholic League. Their churches
                    sprang up with wonderful quickness at this time; thus we see that all the 76
                    congregations in Languedoc named by Haag were established between 1558 and 1562.
                    All were characterized by a like aptitude for organization; their constitution,
                    simple and popular, is a proof that under better auspices the French people
                    might have well exercised the privileges of constitutional liberty; the
                    Huguenots had a popular representation and frequent deliberative assemblies.
                    Between 1559 and 1598 they held fifteen general church synods, and from 1573 to
                    1622 many political assemblies, in which all questions bearing on the interests
                    of the “cause” were debated and decided.</p>
                <p>The subordination of the religious to the political interests of the Huguenots
                    became inevitable after the massacre of St Bartholomew’s day, 1572; while at the
                    same time their organization assumed a more decidedly republican tone. The
                    horror they felt at the violent action of Charles IX. seemed to free them from
                    all allegiance to him; they looked to England and Germany for help, to
                    Switzerland and the United Provinces for encouragement and political example.
                    They at once drew up an independent constitution, democratic and federative,
                    framed chiefly after the Swiss pattern. Like all other attempts at a republican
                    form of government, it had an aristocratic and a democratic side, the latter for
                    the time seeming to be the stronger. For the centre of their power was now
                    passing from the aristocracy to the burghers, from country chateaux to
                    provincial towns. In the towns the only distinction recognized was that of
                    pastor and elders, and these might be, and mostly were, men of the people,
                    chosen by the people. The great nobles who sided with them, the “Politique”
                    princes, like Alençon or Damville-Montmorency, winked for a time at this new
                    “state within the state,” the germ of that Huguenot organization which later on
                    hampered Richelieu’s path. Their system was based on the towns in their hands.
                    In each an independent government was elected by popular suffrage, and was
                    composed of a mayor, a council of twenty-four, and an elective chamber of
                    seventy-five citizens, making up in all a hundred rulers. This body was a court
                    of justice, with some amount of sovereignty. Thus, the twenty-four with the
                    mayor had control over war, police, and “things of highest importance,” though
                    without the seventy-five they could neither pass nor abrogate laws, as to coin,
                    taxation, truces, or terms of peace. The mayors and privy councils of the
                    confederate towns were charged with the election of a general, a kind of Roman
                    dictator, who was to have both a council to advise him and also five lieutenants
                    to help and succeed him, if need were. Lastly, provision was made for a strict
                    moral discipline.</p>
                <p>Soon after this the Huguenots established a system of “generalities” or
                    districts, each with its own local estates, and over these provincial councils
                    and a states-general, thus materially strengthening their independent
                    organization. This system continued throughout the Leaguewars (1574-1589),
                    during which the religious movement was controlled by a knot of selfish
                    political leaders, and in the course of which their point of view completely
                    changed: for, while in the beginning they had passionately called for popular
                    institutions and the convocation of the states-general of France, in the end
                    they became the followers of Henry of Navarre, as heir to the French crown,
                    representative throughout of the anti-popular temper of the Bourbon house. Under
                    him the discontented Huguenots again reorganized themselves into nine great
                    circles, over each of which was a council of from five to seven members, elected
                    by delegates from the churches, and having the duty of laying their independent
                    taxation, of levying, commanding, and paying their own troops. There was also a
                    general assembly for all the circles (after the pattern of the United Provinces)
                    sitting in three estates— pastors, nobles, burghers; the whole polity being
                    representative as an aristocratic republic. This general assembly sat
                    frequently, sent embassies to foreign powers, sometimes acting as an independent
                    body politic.</p>
                <p>The discontent of the Huguenots at last extorted from Henry IV. the famous edict
                    of Nantes (2d May 1598), a document which in the main only reproduced the more
                    favourable of the earlier edicts. Its provisions were at least as helpful for
                    Catholics as for Protestants; it was always <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n350/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0350-0339"/> being so modified as to show less and less favour
                    to the Calvinists, who were little satisfied with it. They had dreamed of
                    dominance, had hoped for equality, and were now put off with tolerance. For
                    whatever Henry IV. might feel about their faith, he was determined, as he once
                    told Sully, “to reduce to nothing the Huguenot faction,” to destroy their
                    political independence, and by closing up the civil strife to secure the solid
                    establishment of the central monarchy. The edict allows public exercise of the
                    Huguenot faith in the houses of nobles and gentry, and in a few named towns; it
                    gave the sectaries full civil rights, and made them eligible to all civil
                    offices; in several parliaments mixed chambers were established; the education
                    of their children was left in their own hands.</p>
                <p>We find that about 1590 the Huguenots had exercise of their worship in about 3500
                    chateaux, and in about 200 towns oι bourgs, chiefly in the south and west. In
                    most parts of the north, except Paris and round Rouen and Amiens, they had one
                    place for worship in each bailliage or sénéchaussée. In 1598 we have a list of
                    about 150 places granted by Henry IV. to the Huguenots for their safety, the
                    chief groups being in the generalities of Bordeaux and Montpellier, and in
                    Poitou; these were either free towns, like La Rochelle, Nîmes, Montauban, or
                    towns belonging to private gentlemen, or towns belonging to the king, which had
                    fallen into Huguenot hands during the wars.</p>
                <p>Throughout the next quarter of a century we trace their history in a series of
                    outbursts, indicating noble impatience and Calvinistic dissatisfaction. The
                    siege and fall of La Rochelle (1627-1628) brought this period to an end. During
                    this time their number seems to have increased; at the accession of Louis XIII.
                    they had about 500 churches; in 1622 and 1628 we have lists of 688; in 1637 no
                    less than 720 are enumerated, though of these 49 were either vacant or
                    suspended. Richelieu and Mazarin treated them with statesman-like prudence;
                    their synods were discouraged, their grumblings ceased; they grew in piety and
                    purity as the political arena was closed to them, and the noble houses one by
                    one deserted them. This was the time of their material prosperity, and of their
                    important contribution to the welfare of France which Louis XIV. so rudely cast
                    away.</p>
                <p>As that king got hold of his power, the tranquillity of the Huguenots waned. In
                    1657 they were forbidden to hold colloquies, lest perchance they should take to
                    politics; in 1659 they were practically told to hold no more synods. Soon the
                    court went further: conversions were undertaken. Wherever a pastor could be
                    bribed, won over, or got rid of, his “temple” was at once torn down; the
                    Huguenot worship became almost impossible in towns, and lingered on in a few
                    castles, whereby it fell still more under the royal displeasure. As his
                    conscience grew morbid, under Madame de Maintenon’s direction, Louis XIV. became
                    more eager to expiate his own crimes by punishing the heretics. Between 1657 and
                    1685 520 churches were rooted up; Anquetil declares that 700 had been destroyed
                    before 1685. All through this period, while thousands yielded to oppression or
                    bribery, thousands also fled the land; the emigration began in 1666 and went on
                    for fifty years. It is probable that in 1660 there were over two millions of
                    Huguenots, the best and thriftiest citizens in the land; it is said, though no
                    figures can be trusted, that in all fully a million of French subjects escaped
                    from their inhospitable fatherland. At last in 1685, thinking that the Huguenots
                    were as good as suppressed, Louis XIV. revoked the edict of Nantes (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">France,</hi> vol. ix. p. 579). The revocation was the sentence
                    of civil death on all Huguenots; it crushed more than half the commercial and
                    manufacturing industry of the kingdom. It is said that at the time of it there
                    were 1000 Huguenot pastors; of these over 600 escaped from France, 100 were
                    slain or sent to the galleys, the remainder conformed or disappeared.</p>
                <p>The war of 1689 called attention away from the persecuted remnant of the
                    Huguenots, and they had a breathing space in Languedoc, the Cevennes, and
                    Dauphiné; but directly the peace of Ryswick was signed, repression began again,
                    and consequently, when the Spanish succession war commenced, the Huguenots of
                    the “Desert,” that is, of the country about Nîmes, broke out after endless
                    provocations into open war, which lasted two years, and for a while defied all
                    the efforts of the court. Marshal Villars was at last sent down, and by mingled
                    gentleness and severity he both secured the submission of the gallant Cavalier,
                    the chief leader of the Huguenots, and the defeat of the more determined of the
                    mountaineers. Throughout the rest of the century the down-trodden Protestantism
                    of France was kept alive chiefly by the exertions of Antoine Court, the apostle
                    of the Desert, who never lost faith in the cause, and who reorganized the dying
                    churches, breathing into them fresh life. Though under the influence of
                    oppιession and excitement, the Huguenot story is here and there disfigured by
                    fanatical outbursts of the “prophets” and “prophetesses,” still on the whole the
                    account of their endurance is among the most remarkable and heroic records of
                    religious history.</p>
                <p>After the interference of Voltaire in behalf of Calas, their sufferings came
                    almost to an end; the general change of opinion, the steady weakening of the
                    Catholics, the indolence or good nature of the sovereign, forbade the scandals
                    of the past, until at last in 1787, under Necker’s influence, Louis XVI. signed
                    a memorable edict which restored, after 102 years’ deprivation, their civil
                    status to the Huguenots. The Revolution of 1789 carried justice a stage further;
                    among the many titles of the Revolution to the gratitude of posterity none is
                    more marked than the complete restoration of the non-Catholic elements of French
                    society to their rights. From that moment to the present time the descendants of
                    the Huguenots have had peace.</p>
                <p>There are now about half a million Calvinists in France; by the census of 1872
                    they numbered 467,531 souls, of whom about 100,000 were in the north, and the
                    rest mostly in their old quarters in the south; in the Gard, the ancient Desert,
                    nearly a quarter of the whole body still abide. Of late years the Protestant
                    Church in Fiance has shown a tendency to division into two parties, that of the
                    more rigid Calvinistic opinions, and that of a more liberal and less orthodox
                    theology. In either case they form a group of loyal citizens, on whom French
                    politicians now look with favour. The old reproach that “the Huguenots are all
                    republicans” has at last turned to their credit.</p>
                <p>The persecutions which checked all wholesome developments at home, whether
                    religious, literary, or commercial, were favourable to their growth abroad; and
                    we consequently find that in literary and artistic excellence the Huguenots have
                    taken their full share. Their first attention was naturally called to theology,
                    in which the names of Calvin and Farel, Beza, Daillé, the Drélincourts, the
                    learned S. Desmarets, Jortin, P. Jurieu, Labadie the mystic, the Leclercs, the
                    great Hebraist Mercier, Mestrezat the preacher, the old hero Duplessis Mornay,
                    Salmasius, J. Saurin, first of Protestant orators, and a crowd of lesser men
                    testify to their activity in this branch. Add to these the dictionary of Bayle,
                    the works of the Basnages, Morin the Orientalist, Pithou, the Daciers, Etienne
                    Dolet, Ramus, Le Févre of Etaples, above all Scaliger, as leaders in learning;
                    in history, Bénoît, Bongars, Palma Cayet, Hubert Languet, Béroalde, and
                    Rapin-Thoyras; and with them the political writer Hotman. Of lawyers they claim
                    Baudouin, Cujas, Coras, Doneau, Hérault, and Godefroy, famed, as the most <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n351/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0351-0340"/> learned of jurisconsults. In science they have
                    the Cuviers, Desmaizeaux, Dubois the chemist, Paré, father of modern surgery,
                    Papin, herald of the steam-engine, the physician Joubert, L’Ecluse the botanist,
                    and the Hubers. In art they lay claim to Crispin, J. Cousin, Pallissy, Simon the
                    engraver, the Picarts, and Goujon the architect. Their poets are Marot and
                    Margaret of Valois. The general effect of this activity is hard to gauge: from
                    Amsterdam and Berlin, Geneva and London, issued sermon, political pamphlet,
                    controversial polemic; but these efforts had no settled audience, they failed to
                    win the ear of France. The same is true of their religious heroism; though it
                    seemed to be exactly what was wanted to strengthen the national character, the
                    confessors were scattered, like the Jews, among the nations, and ceased to
                    affect the progress of their fatherland. In the Revolution we can see traces of
                    their mental and moral activity; it may be that their day of influence is not
                    yet over. For their history is a standing marvel, illustrating the abiding power
                    of strong religious convictions, narrow in theory, pure in practice; they have
                    stood as much ill-usage as has befallen any branch of Christ’s church. It
                    remains for their descendants to show to France that their creed goes well with
                    freedom and advance,—that the religious instinct, so deeply implanted in man, is
                    a true friend of orderly and rational national life. Religion which does not
                    abuse its power, a freedom from divided allegiances, an aptitude for
                    constitutional institutions, and an intelligent belief in the sovereignty of the
                    people—these are the elements which the Huguenots of to-day can bring to the
                    service of the republic under which they dwell safely, none making them
                    afraid.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Calvin, <hi rend="italic">Institutio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Christianos</hi><hi rend="italic">Religionis,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Lettres,</hi> ed. J. Bonnet, 1854; Haag, <hi rend="italic"
                    >France</hi><hi rend="italic">Protestante,</hi> 1846; Meaux, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Luttes réligieuses au</hi><hi rend="italic">XVI.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >siècle,</hi> 1879; Arquez, <hi rend="italic">Assemblées politiques des
                    Réformés,</hi> 1859; E. Hugues, <hi rend="italic">Restauration de Protestantisme
                    en France,</hi> 1875; Mignet, <hi rend="italic">Établissement ... du Calvinisme
                    à Genève;</hi> G. de Félice, <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Protestants en France;</hi> E. Benoît, <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de VÉdit de Nantes;</hi> C. Coquerel, <hi rend="italic">Églises du
                    Désert;</hi> A. Court, <hi rend="italic">Troubles des Cévennes</hi>; Bonnemère,
                    <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">des Camisards;</hi> Guizot, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">de France,</hi> 1872; Merle d’Aubigné,
                    <hi rend="italic">Réformation au XVI. siècle;</hi> Professor H. Μ. Baird, <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Rise of the Huguenots, 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >vols.,</hi> 1880. (G. W. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
