<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0432-0417-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HUYGENS, Sir (9th edition, volume 12, page 417)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94j3d">Lute</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w66">Cat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1003956">Lute</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n432/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HUYGENS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi></label><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Constantijn</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Constantin</hi>
                    (1596- 1687), Dutch poet and diplomatist, was born at the Hague on the 4th of
                    September 1596. His father, Christiaan Huygens, was secretary to the state
                    council, and a man of great political importance. At the baptism of the child,
                    the city of Breda was one of his sponsors, and the famous admiral Justinus van
                    Nassau the other. From his earliest childhood he was trained in every polite
                    accomplishment, and before he was seven he could speak French with fluency. He
                    was taught Latin by Johannes Dedelus, and soon became a master of classic
                    versification. As he grew up, he developed not only extraordinary intellectual
                    gifts but great physical beauty and strength, and was one of the most
                    accomplished athletes and gymnasts οΐ his age; his skill in playing the lute and
                    in the arts of painting and engraving attracted general attention before he
                    began to develop his genius as a writer. In 1616 he proceeded, with his elder
                    brother, to the university of Leyden. He stayed there only one year, and in 1618
                    proceeded to London with the English ambassador Carleton; he remained in London
                    for some months, and then went to Oxford, where he studied for some time in the
                    Bodleian Library,and to Woodstock,Windsor, and Cambridge; he was introduced at
                    the English court, and played the lute before James I. The most interesting
                    feature of this visit was the intimacy which sprang up between the young Dutch
                    poet and the famous Dr Donne, for whose genius Huygens preserved through life an
                    unbounded admiration. He returned to Holland in company with the English
                    contingent of the synod of Dort, and in 1620 he proceeded to Venice in the
                    diplomatic service of his country; on his return he nearly lost his life by a
                    foolhardy exploit, namely, the scaling of the topmost spire of Strasburg
                    cathedral. In 1621 he published one of his most weighty and popular poems, his
                        <hi rend="italic">Batava</hi><hi rend="italic">Tempe,</hi> and in the same
                    year he proceeded again to London, as secretary to the ambassador, Wijngaerdan,
                    but returned in three months. His third diplomatic visit to England lasted
                    longer, from the 5th of December 1621 to the 1st of March 1623. During his
                    absence, his volume of satires, <hi rend="italic">Costelick Mai,</hi> dedicated
                    to Jacob Cats, appeared at the Hague. In the autumn of 1622 he was knighted by
                    James I. He published a large volume of miscellaneous poems in 1625 under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Otiorum libri</hi><hi rend="italic">sex</hi>; and in
                    the same year he was appointed private secretary to the stadholder. In 1627
                    Huygens married Suzanna van Baerle, and the young couple settled in a handsome
                    house in the best part of the Hague; four sons and a daughter were born to them.
                    In 1630 Huygens was called to a seat in the privy council, and he continued to
                    exercise political power with wisdom and vigour for many years, under the title
                    of the lord of Zuylichem. In 1634 he completed his long-talked-of version of the
                    poems of Donne. In 1637 he had the misfortune to lose his admirable wife, and he
                    immediately began to celebrate the virtues and pleasures of their married life
                    in the remarkable didactic poem called <hi rend="italic">Daywerck,</hi> which
                    was not published till long afterwards. From 1639 to 1641 he occupied himself by
                    building a magnificent house and garden outside the Hague, and by celebrating
                    their beauties in a poem entitled <hi rend="italic">Hofwijck,</hi> which saw the
                    light in 1654. In 1647 he wrote his beautiful poem of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Oogentroost</hi> or “Eye Consolation,” to gratify his blind friend Lucretia
                    van Trollo. He made his solitary effort in the dramatic line in 1659, when he
                    brought out his comedy of <hi rend="italic">Trijntje</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Cornelis,</hi> which deals, in rather broad humour, with the adventures of
                    the wife of a ship’s captain at Zaandam. In 1658 he rearranged his poems, and
                    issued them with many additions, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Corn
                        Flowers.</hi> He proposed to the Government that the present highway from
                    the Hague to the sea at Scheveningen should be constructed, and during his
                    absence on a diplomatic mission to the French court in 1666 the road was made as
                    a compliment to the venerable statesman, who expressed his gratitude in a
                    descriptive poem entitled <hi rend="italic">Zeestraet.</hi> Huygens edited his
                    poems for the last time in 1672, and died in his ninety-first year, on the 28th
                    of March 1687. His second son, Christiaan, the eminent astronomer, is noticed
                    above.</p>
                <p>Constantijn Huygens is the most brilliant figure in Dutch literary history. Other
                    statesmen surpassed him in political influence, and at least two other poets
                    surpassed him in the value and originality of their writings. But his figure was
                    more dignified and splendid, his talents were more varied, and his general
                    accomplishments more remarkable than those of any other person of his age, the
                    greatest age in the history of the Netherlands. Huygens is the <hi rend="italic"
                        >grand seigneur</hi> of the republic, the type of aristocratic oligarchy,
                    the jewel and ornament of Dutch liberty. When we consider his imposing character
                    and the positive value of his writings, we may well be surprised that he has not
                    found a modern editor. It is a disgrace to Dutch scholarship that no complete
                    collection of the writings of Huygens exists. His autobiography, <hi
                        rend="italic">Be vita propria</hi><hi rend="italic">sermones,</hi> did not
                    see the light until 1827, and his remarkable poem, <hi rend="italic">Cluys∙
                        werck,</hi> was not printed until 1842. As a poet Huygens shows a finer
                    sense of form than any other Dutch writer; the language, in his hands, becomes
                    as flexible as Italian. His epistles and lighter pieces, in particular, display
                    his metrical ease and facility to perfection. (E. W. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
