<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0054-0045-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOFFMANN, Ernst Theodor Wilhelm (9th edition, volume
                    12, page 45)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1029870">Murres</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n54/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOFFMANN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernst Theodor
                        Wilhelm</hi></label> (1776-1822), German romance writer (for whose name
                    Wilhelm his own substitute, in homage to Mozart, was Amadeus), was born at
                    Königsberg, January 24, 1776. His parents, who lived unhappily together,
                    separating a year or two after his birth, he was brought up in his grandmother’s
                    house, under the care of a bachelor uncle. His relations seem to have been
                    fairly puzzled at the waywardness, cunning, and precocity of the boy, who
                    neglected his school lessons and hated routine, but applied himself with
                    passionate zest to the study of music and painting, extemporized marvellously on
                    the harpsichord, and with his pencil caricatured friend and foe alike with
                    terrible facility. Incited by his friend Hippel, Hoffmann on leaving school
                    turned to the hereditary profession of the law; but, as no immediate post
                    offered itself, he gave lessons in music and painting, and wrote two novels, for
                    which he could not find a publisher. A discreditable love episode with one of
                    his pupils drove him at this time from Königsberg, and he went to act as
                    assistant to another lawyer uncle at Gross-Glogau in Silesia. In 1798 he became
                    referendary in the supreme court at Berlin, and iu 1800 passed his final
                    examination and was appointed assessor to the court of Posen. Here he seems to
                    have led a dissipated life, and to have contracted the habit of excessive
                    drinking which marred his whole career. He subsequently made enemies in Posen by
                    sending a series of scandalous caricatures for distribution at a masquerade
                    ball, and his appointment was on this account changed to a councillorship at
                    Plozk, where, having married ere this time, he spent two years in retirement,
                    studying in his leisure hours the theory of music, translating Italian poetry,
                    and sketching plans for future literary work; but in 1804, again in favour at
                    headquarters, he was transferred as councillor to Warsaw. There he found a true
                    friend in Hitzig, his colleague, and made the acquaintance of Werner, at whose
                    request he set music to some parts of the <hi rend="italic">Kreuz an</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">der Ostsee.</hi> He soon became the centre of musical society
                    in Warsaw, helped to institute a concert-house or “Ressource,” found leisure not
                    only to paint its saloons but to compose music for its orchestra, and was
                    actually conducting this orchestra before enthusiastic audiences when Warsaw was
                    taken by the French in 1806. For some time he lingered in Warsaw; but in the
                    spring of 1807, having recovered from a fever to find himself almost penniless,
                    he returned to Berlin to seek some means of livelihood. His only child died in
                    Posen while he was in Berlin; and, though he succeeded in obtaining the post of
                    music-director to the Bamberg theatre, the theatre soon after became bankrupt,
                    and Hoffmann was once more destitute. He now found occasional employment as a
                    composer of operatic music, and, as a last resource, attempted authorship. The
                    editor of the <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musikalische Zeitung</hi> enlisted
                    his services, and in that paper appeared a series, afterwards published, with a
                    preface by Jean Paul Richter, as <hi rend="italic">Fantasiestücke</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">in Callots</hi><hi rend="italic">Manier</hi> (1814; 4th ed.,
                    1864). He composed at this time, among other things, a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Miserere</hi> by order of the grand-duke of Würzburg, and, for the
                    proprietors of the Bamberg theatre, music to Kotzebue’s opera <hi rend="italic"
                        >Das Gespenst</hi>; and he also gave lessons in music and drawing, decorated
                    saloons, and painted portraits to order. The misery of his condition was
                    enhanced by his wife’s illness and his own light-hearted recklessness. The money
                    which he inherited at the death of his uncle did not suffice to pay his debts;
                    and he had been reduced to selling his last coat for food when his friends
                    obtained for him the post of music-director to another theatrical company,
                    performing alternately at Dresden and Leipsic. Hoffmann was writing romances in
                    a garret in Dresden, or, bedridden by gout, was drawing caricatures of the
                    “verwünschte Franzosen” while Napoleon and the allied armies were struggling
                    round its walls. In 1814 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Vision</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">auf der Schlachtfelde von</hi><hi rend="italic">Dresden;</hi>
                    and in the same year, on the fall of Napoleon, he returned to Berlin, and was
                    reinstated in the legal profession. Two years later he was appointed councillor
                    in the supreme court, and from that time enjoyed a good income, a dignified
                    position, and the society of his best friends. He was already, in virtue of his
                        <hi rend="italic">Fantasiestücke,</hi> regarded as one of the most notable
                    romance writers of his day, but most of his works were yet to come. These
                    followed each other in quick succession. <hi rend="italic">Die Elixire</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">des Teufels</hi> appeared in 1816; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nachtstücke</hi> in 1817; <hi rend="italic">Seltsame</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Leiden</hi><hi rend="italic">eines Theaterdirektors</hi> in 1818; <hi
                        rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Serapionsbrüder,</hi> a collection
                    of tales, in 1819-24; <hi rend="italic">Klein</hi><hi rend="italic">Zaches,
                        genannt Zinnober,</hi> in 1819; <hi rend="italic">Prinzessin</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Brambilla</hi> in 1821; <hi rend="italic">Meister</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Floh</hi> in 1822; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lebensansichten</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic">Katers
                        Murr</hi> in 1821-22. He also composed the opera <hi rend="italic"
                        >Undine,</hi> the libretto of which was prepared by Fouqué himself. It was
                    performed with success in Berlin; but the music was lost in the subsequent
                    destruction of the opera-house by fire. Hoffmann’s prospects in Berlin were
                    ruined by the old habit of intemperance, which had grown upon him during the
                    years of his poverty. We are told that his legal duties were scrupulously
                    performed, and that the remainder of his day was spent in literary work, but
                    that, when this was over, he avoided refined society, and his nights became a
                    series of wild pothouse revels. His health soon gave way; and, after intense
                    suffering from spinal paralysis, he died at Berlin, July 24, 1822. <hi
                        rend="italic">Der Feind,</hi> lιis last work, remained unfinished.</p>
                <p>Versatility is the chief characteristic of Hoffmann’s genius, and it is also its
                    greatest weakness. He is admitted to have been an excellent jurist. His
                    paintings were clever, though fantastic. He was a popular composer and a
                    brilliant romance-writer. But this very versatility prevented his rising to
                    eminence in any one vocation; and, even as a romance-writer, in which capacity
                    he will be longest remembered, he was deficient in some of the highest
                    attributes. His imagination was unbounded, his wit light and acrid, his dialogue
                    stirring. His descriptive passages, in their minute vividness, have been
                    compared to those of Sir Walter Scott, and his romances abound in the
                    superstitious and mythical, that daemonic element which is so peculiarly German,
                    and which in Hoffmann amounted almost to a frenzy. But, with all this, a perusal
                    of his writings leaves a disagreeable impression on the mind, a feeling
                    ofdi≡satisfaction and unrest. They are the production of a misdeveloped nature,
                    of a man full of feverish impulses, oddities, and weakness, not devoid of
                    tenderness, but whose temper was unforgiving and malicious, whose prevailing
                    mood was the sarcastic, and whose only religious creed was a blind, headlong
                    fatalism. There is also a strong element in his writings which Carlyle in his
                    biography of Hoffmann has called “playerlike,” a glitter which is of tinsel, a
                    something “false, brawling, and tawdry.” His writings, like his character, are a
                    curious mixture of what is really beautiful and rare with much that is petty and
                    sordid. Their cleverness is irresistible; but the dignity of true greatness is
                    not there.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Die Elixire</hi><hi rend="italic">der Teufels,</hi> his longest
                    completed work, contains in a narrative form some of his own wildest and most
                    revolting delusions; and the derisive <hi rend="italic">Kater Murr,</hi> of
                    which the third volume is wanting, is not less characteristic. Some of his
                    smaller pieces have justly been thought the most pleasing and perfect of his
                    works. Among these are <hi rend="italic">Der goldene Topf Das Fräulein von
                        Scudery, Doge und Dogaresse,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Meister Martin und
                        seine Gesellen.</hi> The delicacy and finish of the last, slight though it
                    is, have stamped it as Hoffmann’s masterpiece, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n55/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0055-0046"/> A life of Hoffmann has been written by
                    Hitzig, his colleague first in Warsaw and afterwards in Berlin, under the title
                    of <hi rend="italic">Hoffmanns</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben und Nachlass.</hi> A
                    selection of his writings was published in Berlin, 1827-28, and five more
                    volumes (including Hitzig’s life) were added by his widow in 1839. A selection
                    of his writings by Kurz appeared in 1870, and an edition of his collected works,
                    in 12 vols., in 1871—73. Most of his romances are to be obtained separately in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Universal-Bibliothek,</hi> a cheap edition of standard
                    authors published at Leipsic. <hi rend="italic">Die Blixire des Teufelshas</hi>
                    been translated into English (Edin., 1824), and Carlyle has given us a biography
                    of Hoffmann, together with a translation of one of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fantasicstuckc,</hi> “Der Goldene Topf,’’ in his <hi rend="italic">German
                        Romance.</hi> (F. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
