<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0880-0863-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOILEAU-DESPREAUX, Nicolas (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    863)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883902">Crones</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918891">Expressionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n880/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOILEAU-DESPREAUX, <hi rend="smallcaps">Nicolas</hi></label>,
                    was bom at Paris on the 1st November 1636. Crone, not far from the capital, ha3
                    been frequently stated to be his birthplace, but the matter seems to be pretty
                    nearly settled by the researches of M. Labat <hi rend="italic">^Recherches
                    historiques sur V</hi><hi rend="italic">Hotel</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                    Préfecture de Police),</hi> who has discovered the very house in the Rue de
                    Jérusalem where the poet was born. He was educated at the College of Beauvais,
                    and was at first destined for the legal profession. From this, however, after a
                    short trial, he recoiled in disgust, complaining bitterly of the amount of
                    chicanery which passed under the name of law and justice. To escape such a
                    course of life he began to study for the church, and actually received a priory
                    of a small annual value, but his wishes soon turned in another direction. He
                    gave up his clerical profession, and, his father having left him a small
                    provision suffi - cient for his wants, thenceforward devoted himself to letters.
                    Such of his early poems as have been preserved hardly contain the promise of
                    what he ultimately became. The first piece in which his peculiar powers were
                    displayed was a satirical poem, <hi rend="italic">Adieus of a Poet to the City
                    of Pams,</hi> published in 1660. This was quickly followed by eight others, and
                    the number was at a later period increased to twelve. A twofold interest
                    attaches to the satires. In the first place the author skilfully parodies and
                    attacks writers who at the time were placed in the very first rank, such as
                    Chapelain, Cotin, Quinault, and Scudéri; he openly raised the standard of revolt
                    against the older poets. But in the second place he showed, both by precept and
                    practice, what were the poetical capabilities of the French language. Prose, in
                    the hands of such writers as Descartes and Pascal, had proved itself a flexible
                    and powerful instrument of expression, with a distinct mechanism and form. But
                    except with Malherbe, there had been no attempt to fashion French versification
                    according to rule or method. In Boileau for the first time appeared terseness
                    and vigour of expression, with perfect regularity of verse structure. His fame
                    was quickly established; he received a pension, and was made historiographer
                    along with his friend Racine. In 1664 he composed his prose <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dialogue des</hi><hi rend="italic">heros</hi><hi rend="italic">de roman,</hi>
                    which is a refined satire on the elaborate romances of the time. It may be said
                    to have once for all abolished them. From 1669 onwards appeared the <hi
                    rend="italic">Epistles,</hi> graver in tone than the satires, maturer in
                    thought, more exquisite and polished in style. In 1674 his two master-pieces,
                    <hi rend="italic">L'Art</hi><hi rend="italic">Poetique</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Lutrin,</hi> were published. The first, in imitation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ars Poetica</hi> of Horace, lays down the code for all future
                    French verse, and may be said to fill in French literature a parallel place to
                    that held by its prototype in Latin. On our own literature the maxims of
                    Boileau, through the translation revised by Dryden, and through the magnificent
                    imitation of them in Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Art of Criticism,</hi> have
                    exercised no slight influence. Boileau does not merely lay down rules for the
                    language of poetry, but analyses carefully the various kinds of verse
                    composition, and enunciates the principles peculiar to each. Of the four books
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Art</hi><hi rend="italic">Poetique,</hi> the first and
                    last consist of general precepts, inculcating mainly the great rule of <hi
                    rend="italic">bon sens;</hi> the second treats of the pastoral, the elegy, the
                    ode, the epigram, and satire; and the third of tragic and epic poetry. Though
                    the rules laid down are of value, their tendency is rather to hamper and render
                    too mechanical the efforts of poetry. Boileau himself, though a great critic in
                    verse, cannot be considered a great poet. The <hi rend="italic">Lutrin,</hi> a
                    mock heroic poem, of which four cantos appeared in 1674 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n881/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0881-0864"/> is by French critics considered the best of
                    Boileau’s works. It has furnished the model for the <hi rend="italic">Rape of
                    the Lock,</hi> but the English poem is superior in richness of imagination aud
                    subtilty of invention. The fifth and sixth cautos, afterwards added by Boileau,
                    rather detract from the beauty of the poem; the last canto in particular is
                    quite unworthy of his genius. In the same year which saw the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Art</hi><hi rend="italic">Poetique</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Lutrin</hi>
                    was published his translation of Longinus <hi rend="italic">On the Sublime,</hi>
                    to which were afterwards added certain critical reflections. His later
                    publications were chiefly occasional poems, in which his better powers did not
                    shine. He died 13th March 1711. Boileau was extremely delicate in youth, and his
                    constitution seems never to have been very strong. He was a man of warm aud
                    kindly feelings, honest, outspoken, and benevolent Many anecdotes are told of
                    his frankness of speech at court, and of his generous actions. He holds a
                    weU-defined place in French literature, as the first who reduced its
                    versification to rule and who taught the value of workmanship for its own sake.
                    His influence on English literature, through Pope and his contemporaries, was
                    not less strong, though less durable. Editions of Boileau's works are very
                    numerous. Perhaps the best is that published by Garnier in 1860, <hi
                    rend="italic">Oeuvres complètes,</hi> with copious notes, an essay by
                    Sainte-Beuve, and <hi rend="italic">Boloeana.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
