<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0239-0224-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BADEN, The Grand Duchy of (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    224)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n239/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BADEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">The Grand Duchy of</hi></label>,
                    is situated in the S.W. of Germany, between 47° 32' and 49° 52' N. lat., and
                    between 7° 27' and 9° 50' E. long. It is bounded on the N. by Bavaria and Hesse
                    Darmstadt; W. by Rhenish Bavaria, Alsace, and Lorraine; S. by Switzerland; and
                    E. by Wurtemberg and part of Bavaria. At the commencement of the present century
                    Baden was only a margraviate, with an area little exceeding 1300 square miles,
                    and a population of 210,000. Since then it has from time to time acquired
                    additional territory, so that its area now amounts to upwards of 5800 square
                    miles, and its population to nearly a million and a half.</p>
                <p>It consists of a considerable portion of the eastern half of the fertile valley
                    of the Rhine, and of the mountains which form its boundary. The mountainous part
                    is by far the most extensive, forming, indeed, nearly 80 per cent, of the whole
                    area. From the Lake of Constance in the south to the River Neckar is a portion
                    of the so-called Black Forest or <hi rend="italic">Schwarzwald,</hi> which is
                    divided by the valley of the Kinzig into two districts of different elevation.
                    To the south of the Kinzig the mean height is 3100 feet, and the loftiest
                    summit, the Feldberg, reaches about 4780 feet; while to the north the mean
                    height is only 2100 feet, and the Belchen, the culminating point of the whole,
                    does not exceed 4480. To the north of the Neckar is the Odenwald range, with a
                    mean of 1440 feet, and, in the Katzenbuckel, an extreme of 1980. Lying between
                    the Rhine and the Dreisam is the Kaiserstuhl, an independent volcanic group,
                    nearly 10 miles in length and 5 in breadth, the highest point of which is 1760
                    feet.</p>
                <p>The greater part of Baden belongs to the basin of the Rhine, which receives
                    upwards of twenty tributaries from the highlands of the duchy alone; a portion
                    of the territory is also watered by the Main and the Neckar. A part, however, of
                    the eastern slope of the Black Forest belongs to the basin of the Danube, which
                    there takes its rise in a number of mountain streams. Among the numerous lakes
                    which belong to the duchy are the Mummel, Wilder, Nonnenmattweiher, Titti,
                    Eichener, Schluch, &lt;fcc., but none of them are of any size. The Lake of
                    Constance, or Boden See, belongs partly to Bavaria and Switzerland.</p>
                <p>From 1819 to 1832 Baden was divided into six circles, which were reduced in the
                    latter year to the four following :—The Lake Circle or Constance, the Upper
                    Rhine or Freiburg, the Middle Rhine or Carlsruhe, and the Lower Rhine or
                    Manheim. This division, though still employed, has been legally supplanted by
                    one into the eleven circles of Constance, Villingen, Waldshut, Freiburg,
                    Lörrach, Offenburg, Baden, Carslruhe, Manheim, Heidelberg, and Mosbach. The
                    capital of the duchy is Carlsruhe, which in 1871 had a population of 36,582; the
                    other principal towns are Manheim (39,614), Freiburg (24,599), Heidelberg
                    (19,988), Pforzheim (19,801), Rastadt (11,559), Baden (10,083), Constance
                    (10,052), Bruchsal (9786), and Lahr (6710). The population is most thickly
                    clustered in the north and in the neighbourhood of the Swiss town of Basel.</p>
                <p>The mineral wealth of Baden is not very great; but the mines of Oberwert,
                    Kandern, &amp;c., produce excellent iron; there are two zinc mines and one of
                    lead; coal is worked at Diesburg, Zunsweier, Baden, &amp;c.; and silver, copper,
                    gold, cobalt, alum vitriol, and sulphur are also obtained in small quantities.
                    Gold washing, at one time extensively carried on along the Rhine, is now little
                    practised. Peat is found in abundance, as well as gypsum, china-clay, and <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n240/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0240-0225"/> potter’s earth. The duchy was formerly dependent
                    on France for its salt supply, but extensive salt works have for a number of
                    years been maintained by the Government at Dürrheim and Rappenau. In 1874 the
                    amount produced was of the value of £54,880. The mineral springs of Baden are
                    very numerous, and have acquired great celebrity,— those of Baden-Baden,
                    Badenweiler, Antogast, Griesbach, Friersbach, and Petersthal, being the most
                    frequented.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants of Baden are of various origin,—those to the N. of the Murg being
                    descended from the Alemanni, and those to the S. from the Franks, while the
                    Swabian plateau derives its name and its population from another race. This
                    distinction is still marked in the manners, the language, and the dress of the
                    different districts. The majority of the people are engaged in agricultural and
                    pastoral pursuits, for which much of the country is well adapted. In the valleys
                    the soil is particularly fertile, yielding luxuriant crops of wheat, maize,
                    barley, spelt, beans, potatoes, flax, hemp, hops, beet-root, and tobacco; and
                    even in the more mountainous parts rye, wheat, and oats are extensively
                    cultivated. There is a considerable extent of pasture land, and the rearing of
                    cattle, sheep, pigs, and goats is largely attended to. The culture of the vine
                    has recently been increasing, and the wines, which are characterised by a
                    mildness of flavour, are in good demand. The gardens and orchards supply
                    abundance of fruits, especially almonds and walnuts; and the keeping of bees is
                    common throughout the country. A greater proportion of Baden than of any other
                    of the South German states is occupied by forests. In these the predominant
                    species are the fir and pine, but many others, such as the chestnut, are well
                    represented. A third, at least, of the annual supply of timber is exported, the
                    chief consumer being Holland, though of late years Paris has derived a
                    considerable supply from this source.</p>
                <p>The manufactures of Baden were formerly very insignificant, but have greatly
                    increased since its accession to the Zollverein in 1835. They are, however,
                    chiefly confined to iron and hardware goods, and the spinning and weaving of
                    cotton. The latter industry is principally carried on at Ettlingen, Offenburg,
                    St Blaise, Zell, Schopfheim; Manheim has an extensive manufacture of mirrors,
                    and Carlsruhe of machines; while Pforzheim is famous for its production of
                    jewellery and goldsmiths’ work. Beet-root sugar is manufactured at Waghäusel
                    more largely than anywhere else in Germany. Paper, leather, and tobacco are also
                    important objects of industry. The inhabitants of the Black Forest have long
                    been celebrated for their dexterity in the manufacture of wooden ornaments and
                    toys, watches, clocks, musical boxes, organs, &amp;c. Of clocks alone about
                    600,000 are made every year.</p>
                <p>The exports of Baden, which coincide largely with the industries just mentioned,
                    are of considerable importance, but the bulk of its trade consists in the
                    transit of goods. The country is well furnished with roads and railways, the
                    greater proportion of the latter being in the hands of the state. A line runs
                    the whole length of the land, for the most part parallel with the Rhine, while
                    branches cross obliquely from east to west.</p>
                <p>The educational institutions of Baden are numerous and flourishing, and public
                    instruction is largely subsidised by the Government. There are two universities,
                    the Protestant one at Heidelberg, founded in 1386, and the Catholic one at
                    Freiburg, founded in 1457. The library at Heidelberg numbers 150,000 volumes,
                    and that at Freiburg 100,000, while there is another of almost equal size at
                    Carlsruhe. There are also lyceums at Carlsruhe, Constance, Freiburg, Heidelberg,
                    Manheim, Rastadt, and Wertheim; several gymnasiums; normal schools at Carlsruhe,
                    Ettlingen, and Meersburg, besides upwards of 2000 common schools established
                    throughout the country. There is an institution in Pforzheim for the deaf and
                    dumb, and one in Freiburg for the blind. The polytechnic school at Carlsruhe is
                    among the most efficient institutions of the kind in Germany. The preparatory
                    course extends over three years, and includes French, German, English, special
                    history, mathematics, drawing, modelling, chemistry, mineralogy and geology,
                    mechanics, &amp;c. The special courses are engineering, architecture, forestry,
                    chemistry, mechanics, commerce, and post-office service, and extend over from
                    one to four years. The ducal family of Baden belong to the Protestant section of
                    the Church, but the majority of the population are Roman Catholics. The returns
                    of the census of 1871 are as follows:—Catholics, 942,560; Protestants, 491,008;
                    other sects, 2265; and Jews, 25,703. The district where the Roman Catholic
                    preponderance was greatest was Constance, while the Protestants were slightly
                    more numerous in the district of Manheim.</p>
                <p>The government of Baden is an hereditary monarchy, with the executive power
                    vested in the grand duke, and the legislative authority in a Parliament
                    consisting of two Chambers. The upper Chamber is composed of all the princes of
                    the reigning line who are of age, the chiefs of ten noble families, the
                    possessors of hereditary landed estates worth £25,000, the Roman Catholic
                    archbishop of Freiburg, the president of the Protestant Church, a deputy from
                    each of the universities, and eight nominees of the duke. The lower Chamber
                    consists of 63 representatives, of whom 22 are elected by the burgesses of
                    certain towns, and 41 by the inhabitants of the bailiwicks. The parliamentary
                    candidate must possess tax-paying property of the value of 10,000 florins
                    (£833), or derive a salary of at least £125 from a public office. Every citizen,
                    if neither criminal nor pauper, has the right of voting, but only in the choice
                    of deputy-electors, by whom the real election of the representatives is decided.
                    The members of the lower House are elected for eight years, and meetings of
                    Parliament must take place every two years.</p>
                <p>The budgets are granted by Parliament for a term of two years. In 1875 the
                    ordinary expenses were rated at £1,572,959, and the ordinary receipts at
                    £1,557,108. The total public debt on the 1st of January 1874 was
                    £12,985,067.</p>
                <p>Since the organisation of 1864 courts are held at Constance, Freiburg, Offenburg,
                    Carlsruhe, and Manheim, the supreme court being in the city last named. Manheim
                    is also the seat of the central commission for the navigation of the Rhine.</p>
                <p>The ducal family of Baden traces its descent from the counts of Zähringen, who
                    flourished in the 11th century, and derived their title from what is now a
                    little town to the north of Freiburg. Hermann I., the second son of Count
                    Berthold I., took the title of margrave of Hochberg in Breisgau, and was
                    succeeded in 1074 by his son Hermann II., who was the first to style himself
                    margrave of Baden. On the death of the Margrave Christopher in 1527, his estates
                    were divided among his three sons, but one of them having died soon after, the
                    two survivors became the sole inheritors, and founded the two lines of
                    Baden-Baden and Baden-Durlach. The former of these, which produced one of the
                    most famous generals of the 17th century, became extinct by the death of
                    Augustus George in 1771, and its possessions were united with Baden-Durlach
                    under Charles Frederick. By the treaty of Lunéville in 1801, Baden acquired a
                    considerable addition of territory; in 1803 the margrave received the title of
                    Elector; and by the treaty of Presburg in 1805 his domains were still further
                    increased by the accession of Breisgau. On the dissolution of the empire in
                    1806, the elector <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n241/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0241-0226"/> joined tlιθ Confederation of the Rhine, and
                    received the title of Grand Duke, with 1950 square miles of additional
                    territory. Shortly after this extension and consolidation had taken place,
                    Bavaria laid claim to a portion of the duchy, but her demands were indignantly
                    rejected, and in 1818 the grand duke bestowed on the country a political
                    constitution, the fundamental principle of which was the territorial integrity
                    of Baden. In the following year this integrity was guaranteed by the Frankfort
                    Commission. The first session of the Baden parliament fell into disputes and had
                    to be dissolved; but the second, in 1820, commenced the work of reform by the
                    complete abolition of serfdom and the establishment of ministerial
                    responsibility. In 1821 the union of the two Protestant churches in Baden was
                    brought about. Other questions of importance, such as trial by jury, freedom of
                    the press, abolition of tithes, and extension of education, became subjects of
                    interest and debate; but, unfortunately, the influence of the French revolution
                    of 1830 led the democratic party to excesses, which the Government met with acts
                    of ill-advised repression. Matters were beginning to readjust themselves when
                    the revolution of 1848 again aroused the opposing forces. In 1849 the duke was
                    constrained to flee, and Brentano, the democratic leader, took possession of
                    Carlsruhe in the name of the national committee. By the 25 th of June, however,
                    the Prussian forces, after several severe engagements with the revolutionists,
                    effected the restoration of the duke, who returned to his capital on 18th
                    August; and it was not long before the country began to recover from the effects
                    of the outbreak. Not, indeed, that it became quiescent; for Baden has had its
                    full share in the political and ecclesiastical disputes that have been so rife
                    throughout Germany during recent years. The Roman Catholic clergy, with the
                    bishop of Freiburg at their head, have maintained an obstinate struggle with the
                    Liberal party, which is now predominant. The separation of church and state has
                    been established; the Jews have been admitted to full civic rights; freedom of
                    trade has been promulgated, and a number of minor reforms successfully carried
                    through. In the German war of 1866 Baden sided against Prussia; but in 1870 it
                    joined in the formation of the new German empire, and its troops are
                    incorporated in the 14th corps of the imperial army.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
