<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0876-0859-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOGRA (9th edition, volume 3, page 859)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1939163">Jute</term>
                    <term ref="fast:985280">Jutes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qr4p">Jute</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hm52s7v">Production</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n876/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOGRA</label>, correctly <hi rend="smallcaps">Baguea,</hi> a
                    district in the Râjshâhi division, within the Lieutenant-Governorship of Bengal,
                    situated between 25° 20' and 24° 20' 28" N. lat., and 88° 55' 30" and 89° 49'
                    25" E. long. It is bounded on the N. by the districts of Dinâjpur and Bangpur,
                    on the E. by the districts of Rangpur and Maimansinh, on the S. by the district
                    of Pabnâ, and on the W. by the districts of Bâjshâhi and Dinâjpur. The revenue
                    area of the district in 1870 was 2000 square miles, of which 1750 were returned
                    as under cultivation, 125 as cultivable but not actually cultivated, and 125 as
                    uncultivable waste. The census of 1872 returned the police area of the district
                    at 1500 square miles, and disclosed a population of 689,467 souls, of whom
                    556,620, or 80 per cent., were Mahometans; 130,644, or 19 per cent., Hindus; 22
                    Christians; and 2181 were classified as “others.” Density of population in the
                    census area, 59 per square mile. The district stretches out in a level plain,
                    intersected by numerous streams and dotted with patches of jungle. The Karatoyâ
                    River flows from north to south, dividing the district into two portions,
                    possessing very distinct characteristics. The eastern tract consists of rich
                    alluvial soil, well watered, and subject to fertilizing inundations, yielding
                    heavy crops of coarse rice, oilseeds, and jute. The western portion of the
                    district is high-lying and produces the finer qualities of rice. The principal
                    rivers are formed by the different channels of the Brahmaputra, which river here
                    bears the local names of the Konâi, the Dâokobâ, and the Jamunâ, the last
                    forming a portion of the eastern boundary of the district. Its bed is studded
                    with alluvial islands. The Brahmaputra and its channels, together with three
                    minor 6treams, the Bângâlï, Karatoyâ, and Alai, afford admirable facilities for
                    commerce, and render every part of the district accessible to native cargo boats
                    of large burden. The rivers swarm with fish,—the value of the fisheries being
                    estimated at .£45,000 a year. The principal products of the district are rice,
                    pease, pulses, oilseeds, jute, sugar-cane, mulberry, red pepper, and hemp for
                    smoking <hi rend="italic">(Cannabis</hi><hi rend="italic">indica).</hi> These
                    products, together with clarified butter and a little silk, form the chief
                    articles of export. The imports consist of salt, cloth, tobacco, areca-nuts,
                    copper and brass utensils, spices, iron and piece goods. The chief trading
                    markets are Bogrâ, Lakhmiganj, Buriganj, Dhupchâchiâ, &amp;c. A silk factory has
                    been established at Naodâpârâ, and is conducted with European capital, with an
                    annual outlay of about £4500. The revenue and expenditure of the district have
                    steadily increased of^ late years. In 1853 the total revenue of the district
                    amounted to £48,431, and the civil expenditure to £7282; in 1860, revenue
                    £57,744, and civil expenditure £11,013; in 1870- 71 the revenue had risen to
                    £59,979. In 1870-71 the district contained 1064 separate estates held by 2497
                    proprietors, paying a total Government land revenue of £44,347. The machinery
                    for protecting person and property consists of six magisterial and six civil
                    courts, with (1) a regular police force, numbering 54 officers and 252 men, and
                    costing Government £5975; (2), a rural constabulary or village watch, numbering
                    2552 men, and costing £6635, paid by the landholders and villagers; and (3),
                    municipal police, numbering 36 men, and costing £251. In 1871-72 there were 41
                    Government and aided schools in the district, attended by 1492 pupils, and
                    maintained at a total cost of £1398, of which £692 was contributed by the state.
                    The total number of aided and unaided schools in the district is returned in the
                    census of 1872 at 169, attended by 1685 pupils. The only town containing upwards
                    of 5000 inhabitants in the district is Bogrâ, the administrative headquarters,
                    situated on the Karatoyâ River; population in 1872, 5872; municipal income,
                    £282; expenditure, £208; rate of taxation per head, 1l⅜d. There is one other
                    municipality, Sherpur, formerly a place of importance when the East India
                    Company had silk filatures in its neighbourhood. A great part of this town is
                    now overgrown with jungle; the municipal income in 1869 was £246, the
                    expenditure £174. The climate of Bogra is mild during the winter, but sultry and
                    oppressive at other seasons. The average annual rainfall for the five years
                    ending 1869 was 82 inches, and the average annual temperature 77° Fahr.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
