<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0687-0670-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BILÄSPUR (9th edition, volume 3, page 670)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891738">Devas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800093">Agar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n687/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BILÄSPUR</label>, a district of British India, in the Central
                    Provinces, forms the northern section of the Chhattisgarh plateau, and is
                    situated between 21° 45' and 23° 10' N. lat. and 81° 30' and 83° 15' E. long. It
                    is bounded on the N. by the native states of Rewâ and Koriâ; on the E. by the
                    Udaipur tributary state of Chhotâ Nâgpur, and the district of Sambalpur; on the
                    S. by the Râipur district; and on the'W. by the hilly tracts of Mandlâ and
                    Bâlâghât. Extreme length of the district north and south, 106 miles; extreme
                    breadth from east to west, 136 miles; area, 7798 square miles. Bilâspur district
                    forms the upper half of the basin of the River Mahânadi. It is almost enclosed
                    on the north, west, and east by ranges of hills, while its southern boundary is
                    generally open and accessible, well cultivated, and closely dotted with villages
                    embedded in groups of fruit trees. The principal hüls are—(1), the Maikâl range,
                    situated in the north-western extremity of the district; (2), a chain of hills
                    forming part of the Vindhyan range, on the north; (3), the Korbâ hills, an
                    offshoot of the Vindhyas, on the eastern boundary; and (4), the Sonâkhân block
                    of hills, in the vicinity of the Mahânadi <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n688/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0688-0671"/> River. The Mahânadi is the principal river of the
                    district, and governs the whole drainage and river system of the surrounding
                    country. It takes its rise in a mountainous region which is described as the
                    wildest of all wild parts of the Central Provinces, crosses the Bilâspur
                    boundary near Seorinârâin, and after a course of 25 miles in the south-eastern
                    extremity of the district enters Sambalpur district. Within Bilâspur the river
                    is everywhere navigable for six months in the year. Minor rivers—the Sakri,
                    Hâmp, Tesuâ, Agar, Maniâri, Arpâ, Kharod, Lilâgar, Jonk, and Barer!. The most
                    important affluents of the Mahânadi are the Seonath and Hasdιi. Besides the
                    natural water supply afforded by the rivers, Bilaspur abounds in tanks,— these
                    numbering 7018, as shown in the settlement statistics. The census of 1872
                    disclosed a total population of 715,398, of whom 435,379, or 60’86 per cent.,
                    are Hindus; 7024, or *98 per cent., Mahometans; 6 Buddhists; 37 Christians; and
                    272,952, or 38 <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 15 per cent., belong to aboriginal
                    tribes, such as Gonds, Kan wars, Bhumias, Binjwars, Dhanwârs, &amp;c. Among the
                    Hindus, the Châmârs and Pankâs deserve particular notice. The former, who form
                    the shoemaker and leather-dealing caste of the Hindu community, had always been
                    held in utter contempt by the other Hindu castes. But between 1820 and 1830 a
                    religious movement, having for its object their freedom from the trammels of
                    caste, was inaugurated by a member of the caste, named Ghâsi Dâs, who preached
                    the unity of God and the equality of men. Ghâsi Dâs gave himself out as a
                    messenger of God; he prohibited the adoration of idols, and enjoined the worship
                    of the Supreme Being without any visible sign or representation. The followers
                    of the new faith call themselves <hi rend="italic">Sat</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >admis,</hi> or the worshippers of <hi rend="italic">Satndm</hi> or God. They do
                    not keep the Hindu festivals, and they defy the contempt of the Brâhmans. Ghâsi
                    Dâs, the founder of the faith, was their first high priest. He died in 1850; his
                    son succeeded him, but was assassinated (it was said by the Hindus), and the
                    grandson is the present high priest. The Châmârs in Bilâspur number 164,388, or
                    21 per cent, of the total population. The Pankâs, who form about a sixth of the
                    population, are all Kabirpanth!s, or followers of Kabir, a religious reformer of
                    the 15th century. There is no great difference between the Kabir Pankâs and the
                    Satnâmis. They both abstain from meat and liquor, marry at the age of puberty,
                    ordinarily celebrate their ceremonies through the agency of the elders of their
                    own caste, and bury their dead. The Pankas worship the Supreme Being under the
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Kabir,</hi> and the Châmârs under the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Satnam;</hi> while each community has a high priest to whom
                    reverence is paid. At present the majority of the Pankas are cultivators, though
                    formerly all were weavers. The Gonds are the most numerous among the aboriginal
                    tribes, the census of 1872 returning them at 107,359, or 15 per cent, of the
                    total district population; but so great an intermixture has taken place between
                    them and the Hindu races that they have lost their language and most of their
                    ethnical characteristics, such as the flat forehead, squat nose, prominent
                    nostril, dark skin, &amp;c., and are scarcely distinguishable from the other
                    classes of the Hindu labouring population. In addition to some of the Hindu
                    deities which they worship, the Gonds have their own gods—Bara Deva and Dùlâ
                    Deva. The Kânwârs are the next largest section of the aboriginal population, and
                    number 28,419 souls. The upper dass among them claim to be Râjputs, and are
                    divided into numerous septs. Although an aboriginal tribe, the census returns
                    them as a Hindu caste. All the northern landholders of Bilâspur belong to this
                    tribe, which consequently occupies an influential position.</p>
                <p>Rice, wheat, pulses, oil-seeds, and cotton are the chief agricultural staples.
                    The census of 1872 returns the total area of the district at 7798 square miles,
                    of which 2089 square miles are under cultivation. The following is the
                    approximate acreage under different crops :—Rice, 882,218 acres; wheat, 79,203;
                    other food grains, 225,443; oil-seeds, 56,039; sugar-cane, 6888; cotton, 72,922;
                    opium, 124; tobacco, 2317; and vegetables, 12,329; total, 1,337,483 acres, or
                    2089’81 square miles. Of the population, 438,880 live by agriculture, while
                    276,518 are non-agriculturists. The chief wealth of the district consists in its
                    agricultural produce, and it is not inaptly termed ‘ ‘ the land of plenty” by
                    the <hi rend="italic">Banjàràs</hi> or traders, who find here an inexhaustible
                    store of surplus produce for export. Scarcity of food is almost unknown. Coal
                    and iron are the minerals of the district; the former is not worked, and the
                    latter but very slightly, the annual out-turn being reported at about 15 tons
                    only. Sandstone, for building purposes, is quarried near Bilaspur and
                    Seorinârâin. The forests produce timber, edible and medicinal roots and plants,
                    lac and tasar-silk cocoons. Imports in 1867-68—sugar, £5274; metals and
                    hardware, £10,985; English piece-goods, £11,194; cattle, £9240; miscellaneous,
                    £10,531; total, £47,224. Exports—rice (as ascertained), £8659; wheat, £6803;
                    other edible grains, £150; cotton, £16,407; molasses, £297; oil-seeds, £18; lac,
                    £15,603; miscellaneous, £5609; total, £53,546. Among local industries the most
                    important is the weaving trade. It is estimated that cotton and silk cloths to
                    the value of £95,000 are every year manufactured. The traffic routes of the
                    district are five in number, the three most important of which are rugged and
                    inaccessible, unfit for wheeled carriages, admitting export or import only by
                    means of pack-bullocks during six months of the year. The other two are simply
                    tracks across the hills and through the jungle. The revenue divisions of the
                    district correspond with its physical features; the hilly area, covering about
                    5000 square miles, is almost entirely held by large landed proprietors called
                    <hi rend="italic">Zam↑nddrs,</hi> who have always occupied a somewhat
                    independent position. The open countιy, with an area of 3000 square miles, is
                    known as the <hi rend="italic">Khâlsà</hi> jurisdiction, or the tract under
                    direct revenue management through Government officers. Pendrâ, Mâtin, Uprorâ,
                    Kendâ, Lâpha, Chhûri, Korbâ, Châmpâ, Saktf, Bhâtgâon, Bilâigarh, Katangi,
                    Pandariâ, Kawardâ, and Madanpur, are the 15 <hi rend="italic">Zamindârîs</hi>
                    comprising the hilly area, of which Sakti and Kawardâ have been acknowledged as
                    feudatories. Bilâspur, Mungeli, and Seorinârâin are the three <hi rend="italic"
                    >par·</hi><hi rend="italic">ganâs</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Khdlsa</hi>
                    tract. In 1868-69, the revenues of the district were as follows :—Land-tax,
                    £27,195; excise, £892; stamps, £2234; forest, £434; assessed taxes, £1222;
                    total, £31,977. For the protection of person and property, Government maintained
                    in 1868-69 a regular police of 310 officers and men, at a total annual cost of
                    £4363, besides the village watch or rural constabulary. The executive staff of
                    the district consists of the deputy-commissioner, with two assistants and
                    several sub-collectors. Bilâspur contained, in 1868-69, 33 Government and 58
                    private schools, attended by 3076 pupils. Besides Bilâspur, to be separately
                    noticed below, there are only four towns of any importance in the district
                    :—Ratanpur, the seat of the ancient Râjâs, situated at the base of the Kendâ,
                    offshoots of the Vindhyau range, highly attractive to antiquarians and
                    archaeologists on account of its great antiquity; it is now in a dilapidated and
                    deserted state. Population, 5111. Mungeli, a rising market-town, situated on
                    th,e banks of the River Agar. Population, 3542. Kawardâ, population, 6590.
                    Seorinârâin, on the Mahanadi, a favourite residence of the Ratanpur court in
                    former days, contains a temple of the Hindu god Narayan, from which it derives
                    its name. Population about 1500. The climate of the district, though relaxing,
                    is not oppressive. Cholera occasionally breaks out in the epidemic form, being
                    generally disseminated by the Jagannâth pilgrims from Central India, whose route
                    to Orissa lies through the district. Fever and smallpox also prevail.</p>
                <p>The early history of the district is very obscure. From remote ages it was
                    governed by kings of the Haihai dynasty, known as the Chhattisgarh Râjâs, on
                    account of thirty-six forts, of which they were the lords. A genealogical list
                    of kings of this dynasty has been carefully kept up to the fifty-fifth
                    representative in the year 1740, when the country was seized without a struggle
                    by the Marhattâs of Nâgpur. From 1818 to 1830 Bilâspur came under the management
                    of the British Government) the Marhattâ chief of Nâgpur being then a minor. In
                    1854 the country finally lapsed to the British Government, the chief having died
                    without issue. During the Sepoy mutiny a hill chief of the district gave some
                    trouble, but he was speedily captured and executed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">BilAspur,</hi> the chief town of the district of the same
                    name, is situated on the south bank of the River Arpâ. It is said to have been
                    founded by a fisherwoman, named Bilâsa, three hundred years ago, and still
                    retains her name. The place, however, came to note only about one <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n689/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0689-0672"/> hundred years ago, when a Marhattâ official took
                    up his abode there, and began to build a fort which was never completed. In 1862
                    it was made the headquarters of the district, and is now a rising town. It lies
                    in 22° 2 N. lat. and 82° <hi rend="italic">5'</hi> E. long. The population was
                    estimated in 1870 at 6190, but Bilâspur is not mentioned in the census of 1872
                    as containing upwards of 5000 inhabitants.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
