<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0811-0794-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BLACK, Dr Joseph (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    794)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h70805c">Alkalies</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833576">Black</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130935">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:953778">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n811/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BLACK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr Joseph</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated chemist, was born, in 1728, at Bordeaux, where his father—a native of
                    Belfast, but of Scottish descent—was engaged in the wine trade. He was educated
                    from his twelfth to his eighteenth year at a grammar school in Belfast, whence
                    he removed, in 1746, to the university of Glasgow. There he chose medicine as
                    his profession, and devoted himself earnestly to physical science, being
                    encouraged and guided by Dr Cullen, who then lectured on chemistry in Glasgow,
                    and whose liberal and original views were in unison with Black’s own
                    aspirations. From assisting in Cullen’s chemical experiments he acquired the
                    delicate manipulative skill essential to success in original scientific
                    research.</p>
                <p>In 1751 he went to complete his medical studies at Edinburgh, and after taking
                    his medical degree there in 1754 revealed himself as a great scientific
                    discoverer. At that time the causticity of the alkalies was attributed to their
                    absorbing an imaginary fire-essence known as phlogiston, an hypothesis which
                    Black overthrew by showing that their causticity depended on their combining
                    with a ponderable gas, carbonic acid, which he named <hi rend="italic">fixed
                    air,</hi> meaning that it was found not only as a separate fluid, but as <hi
                    rend="italic">fixed</hi> in solid bodies. This discovery, made by Black in his
                    twenty-fourth year, was first sketched in a treatise, <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Acido e Cibis orto, et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >de</hi><hi rend="italic">Magnesia,</hi> and afterwards embodied in his work,
                    <hi rend="italic">Experiments on Magnesia, Quicklime, and other Alkaline
                    Substances,</hi> which Lord Brougham has declared to be “incontestibly the most
                    beautiful example of strict inductive investigation since the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Optics</hi> of Sir Isaac Newton.”</p>
                <p>These works revolutionized chemistry. Previous inves tigators imagined that
                    atmospheric air was the sole permanently aeriform element, a belief to which
                    even Hales, who had shown that solids contain elastic fluids, had adhered. But
                    when Black proved that a gas not identical with atmospheric air was found in
                    alkalies, it was made plain <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n812/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0812-0795"/> that various dissimilar gases might exist, and
                    pneumatic chemistry was founded.</p>
                <p>Although the full value of this discovery was not immediately visible, it added
                    so greatly to Black’s reputation that in 1756 he was chosen to succeed Dr Cullen
                    as lecturer on chemistry in Glasgow University. He was also appointed to the
                    chair of anatomy, but, not finding its duties congenial, exchanged it for the
                    professorship of medicine. For some time he was so assiduous in preparing his
                    lectures as to neglect fresh investigations, and even left the examination of
                    carbonic acid, or <hi rend="italic">fixed air,</hi> to be afterwards completed
                    by Cavendish. He was highly esteemed as a professor by his students and
                    colleagues, and became, through his attention and urbanity, a very popular
                    physician in Glasgow. From 1759 to 1763 he prosecuted inquiries resulting in his
                    theory of <hi rend="italic">latent heat,</hi> which may be thus summarized—A
                    solid liquefies or a fluid vaporizes through heat uniting with the solid or
                    fluid body, and a fluid solidifies or a gas liquefies through the loss of heat;
                    but in no case is this increase or diminution of heat detected by the senses or
                    the thermometer.· Black therefore named that heat <hi rend="italic">latent</hi>
                    which alters the condition, not the temperature, of a body. He likewise proved
                    that bodies of equal masses require different increments of heat to raise them
                    to the same sensible temperature—a doctrine now known as the law of <hi
                    rend="italic">specific heat.</hi></p>
                <p>His theory of latent heat he corroborated by numerous experiments, but he never
                    published a detailed account of it, in omission which enabled others to lay
                    claim to his great discovery. Thus M. Deluc, in 1788, declared himself its
                    author. In 1766 Black was elected to succeed Cullen in the chair of chemistry at
                    Edinburgh University. In this office he bestowed great care on his lectures,
                    striving to give a lucid exposition of ascertained facts rather than to effect
                    new discoveries; and such an interest did he communicate to his subject, that
                    chemistry was for a time, it is said, regarded as a fashionable accomplishment
                    in the Scottish capital.</p>
                <p>He was intimate with the great men who adorned Edinburgh society during the
                    second half of the eighteenth century, counting among his friends Watt, Hume,
                    Robertson, Hutton, Adam Smith, and, at a later period, Robison, Playfair, and
                    Dugald Stewart. His constitution had always been feeble, and he was ultimately
                    reduced to the condition of a valetudinarian, which may account for the
                    indifference he manifested during his latter years to original research. He
                    retired from his professorship in 1796, and on the 26th November 1799 passed
                    away so quietly that a cup of water, which he had held in his hand, remained
                    unspilled after he had breathed his last. At the instance of Lavoisier he had
                    been elected a member of the Paris Academy of Sciences.</p>
                <p>Black was singularly modest, gentle, and sincere; his philosophic tranquillity
                    was seldom ruffled; and his sagacious diffidence was equally conspicuous in his
                    scientific inquiries and in his social relations. He has been called the founder
                    of modern chemistry. When he began his career that branch of knowledge had only
                    recently been raised to the rank of a true science through the efforts of
                    Hermann Boerhaave, and was in many quarters even regarded with suspicion as
                    being akin to alchemy on the one hand, and to humble trades on the other. But
                    after Black’s discoveries its scope and capabilities were immensely extended,
                    and no one could then question its claim to rank with the most important
                    sciences. The only works of his which appeared in print during his lifetime were
                    <hi rend="italic">Experiments on Magnesia,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Observations on the more ready Freezing of JVater that has been boiled,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Analysis of the TVaters of some Boiling Springs in
                    Iceland.</hi></p>
                <p>His lectures on chemistry were issued after his death. <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Cf.</hi> Prof. Robison’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Black.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
