<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0602-0585-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERENGARIUS (9th edition, volume 3, page 585)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hm8r">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688k0g">Sacraments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zx91">Anger</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2s98r">Augustinians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:838229">Breading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198482">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103083">Sacraments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103074">Sacramentals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808763">Anger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829774">Bees</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n602/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BERENGARIUS</label>, a celebrated mediaeval theologian, was
                    born at Tours, 998 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> He was educated in the famous
                    school of Fulbert of Chartres, and early acquired a great reputation for
                    learning, ability, and piety. Appointed in 1031 superintendent of the cathedral
                    school of his native city, he taught with such success as to attract pupils from
                    all parts of France, and powerfully contributed to diffuse an interest in the
                    study of logic and metaphysics, and to introduce that dialectic development of
                    theology which is designated the scholastic. The earliest of his writings of
                    which we have any record is an <hi rend="italic">Exhortatory Discourse</hi> to
                    the hermits of his district, written at their own request and for their
                    spiritual edification. It shows a clear discernment of the dangers of the
                    ascetic life, and a deep insight into the significance of the Augustinian
                    doctrine of grace. About 1040 Berengar was made archdeacon of Angers. It was
                    shortly after this that rumours began to spread of his holding heretical views
                    regarding the sacrament of the supper. He had submitted the doctrine of
                    transubstantiation (already generally received both by priests and people,
                    although it had been first unequivocally taught and reduced to a regular theory
                    by Paschasius Radbert only in 831) to an independent examination, and had come
                    to the conclusion that it was contrary to reason, unwarranted by Scripture, and
                    inconsistent with the teaching of men like Ambrose, Jerome, and Augustine. He
                    did not conceal this conviction from his scholars and friends, and through them
                    the report spread widely that he denied the common doctrine respecting the
                    Eucharist. His early friend and school companion, Adelmann, archdeacon of Liège,
                    wrote to him letters of expostulation on the subject of this report in 1046 and
                    1048; and a bishop, Hugo of Langres, wrote (about 1049) a refutation of the
                    views which he had himself heard Berengar express in conversation. Berengar’s
                    belief was not shaken by their arguments and exhortations, and hearing that
                    Lanfranc, the most celebrated theologian of that age, strongly approved the
                    doctrine of Paschasius and condemned that of Ratramnus, he wrote to him a letter
                    expressing his surprise, and urging him to reconsider the question. The letter
                    arriving at Bee when Lanfranc was absent at Rome, was sent after him, but was
                    opened before it reached him, and brought under the notice of Pope Leo IX.
                    Because of it Berengar was condemned as a heretic, without being heard, by a
                    synod at Rome and another at Vercelli, both held in 1050. His enemies in France
                    cast him into prison; but the bishop of Angers and other powerful friends, of
                    whom he had a considerable number, had sufficient influence to procure his
                    release. At the Council of Tours (1054) he found a protector in the Papal
                    legate, the famous Hildebrand, who, satisfied himself with the fact that
                    Berengar did not deny the real presence of Christ in the sacramental elements,
                    succeeded in persuading the assembly to be content with a general confession
                    from him that the bread and wine, after consecration, were the body and blood of
                    the Lord, without requiring him to define how. Trusting in Hildebrand’s support,
                    and in the justice of his own cause, he presented himself at the Synod of Rome
                    in 1059, but found himself surrounded by fierce and superstitious zealots, who
                    forced him by the fear of death to signify his acceptance of the doctrine “that
                    the bread and wine, after consecration, are not merely a sacrament, but the true
                    body and the true blood of Christ, and that this body is touched and broken by
                    the hands of the priests, and ground by the teeth of the faithful, not merely in
                    a sacramental but in a real manner.” He had no sooner done so than he bitterly
                    repented his weakness; and acting, as he himself says, on the principle that “to
                    take an oath which never ought to have been taken is to estrange one’s self from
                    God, but to retract what one has wrongfully sworn to, is to return back to God,”
                    when he got safe again into France he attacked the transubstantiation theory
                    more vehemently than ever. He continued for about sixteen years to disseminate
                    his views by writing and teaching, without being directly interfered with by
                    either his civil or ecclesiastical superiors, greatly to the scandal of the
                    multitude and of the zealots, in whose eyes Berengar was “ille apostolus
                    Satanae,” and the academy of Tours the “Babylon nostri temporis.” An attempt was
                    made at the Council of Poitiers in 1075 to allay the agitation caused by the
                    controversy, but it failed, and Berengar narrowly escaped death in a tumult
                    raised by fanatics. Hildebrand, now Gregory VII., next summoned him to Rohae,
                    and, in a synod held there in 1078, tried once more to obtain a declaration of
                    his orthodoxy by means of a confession of faith drawn up in general terms; but
                    even this strong-minded and strong-willed Pontiff, although sincerely anxious to
                    befriend the persecuted theologian, and fully alive to the monstrous character
                    of the dogma of transubstantiation as propounded by Pope Nicholas II. and.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n603/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0603-0586"/>
                <p>Cardinal Humbert at the synod held in 1059, was at length forced to yield to the
                    demands of the multitude and its leaders; and in another synod at Rome (1079),
                    finding that he was only endangering his own position and reputation, he turned
                    unexpectedly upon Berengar and commanded him to confess that he had erred in not
                    teaching a change <hi rend="italic">as to substantial reality</hi> of the
                    sacramental bread and wine into the body and blood of Christ. “Then,” says
                    Berengar, “confounded by the sudden madness of the Pope, and because God in
                    punishment for my sins did not give me a steadfast heart, I threw myself on the
                    ground, and confessed with impious voice that I had erred, fearing the Pope
                    would instantly pronounce against me the sentence of condemnation, and, as a
                    necessary consequence, that the populace would hurry me to the worst of deaths.”
                    He was kindly dismissed by the Pope not long after, with a letter recommending
                    him to the protection of the bishops of Tours and Angers, and another
                    pronouncing anathema on all who should do him any injury or call him a heretic.
                    He returned home overwhelmed with shame and bowed down with sorrow for having a
                    second time been guilty of a great impiety. He immediately recalled his forced
                    confession, and besought all Christian men “to pray for him, so that his tears
                    might secure the pity of the Almighty.” He now saw, however, that the spirit of
                    the age was against him, and hopelessly given over to the belief of what he had
                    combated as a delusion. He withdrew, therefore, into solitude, and passed the
                    rest of his life in retirement and prayer on the island of St Come near Tours.
                    He died there in 1088. In Tours his memory was held in great respect, and a
                    yearly festival at his tomb long commemorated his saintly virtues.</p>
                <p>Berengar left behind him a considerable number of followers. All those who in the
                    Middle Ages denied the substantial presence of the body and blood of Christ in
                    the Eucharist were commonly designated Berengarians. These so-called
                    Berengarians differed, of course, in many respects from one another, even in
                    regard to the nature of the supper. Berengar’s own views on the subject may be
                    thus summed up :—1. That bread and wine should become flesh and blood and yet
                    not lose the properties of bread and wine was, he held, contradictory to reason,
                    and therefore irreconcilable with the truthfulness of God. A change which would
                    leave behind the properties or predicates of bread and wine, yet take away their
                    substances, the subjects of these predicates, seemed to him inherently
                    incredible. In working out the proof of this position he showed very
                    considerable dialectical skill. At the same time he employed so many arguments,
                    based on what is called nominalism, that his theory of the Eucharist has been
                    described by Μ. de Remusat as “nominalism limited to a single question.” 2. He
                    admitted a change <hi rend="italic">{conversio)</hi> of the bread and wine into
                    the body of Christ, in the sense that to those who receive them they are
                    transformed by grace into higher powers and influences—into the true, the
                    intellectual, or spiritual body of Christ—so as to sustain and impart the life
                    eternal. Christ does not descend from heaven to be portioned out by the hands of
                    priests and received into the mouths of communicants, but the hearts of true
                    believers ascend to Christ in heaven, receive into themselves his true and
                    imperishable body, and partake thereof in a spiritual manner. The unbelieving
                    receive the external sign or <hi rend="italic">sacramentum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> but the believing receive in addition, truly although invisibly, the
                    reality represented by the sign, the <hi rend="italic">res</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >sacramenti.</hi> Berengar draws his reasons for this view from Scripture. In
                    confirmation of its correctness he adduces the testimonies of the earlier church
                    teachers. 3. He rejected the notion that the sacrament of the altar was a
                    constantly renewed sacrifice, and held it to be merely a commemoration of the
                    one sacrifice of Chri3t. 4. He dwelt strongly on the importance of men looking
                    away from the externals of the sacrament to the spirit of love and piety which
                    they presuppose, and the divine power and grace, through the operation of which
                    alone they can become channels of religious life. The transubstantiation
                    doctrine seemed to him full of evil, from its tendency to lead men to overvalue
                    what was sensuous and transitory in the sacrament, and to neglect what was
                    spiritual and eternal. <hi rend="italic">5.</hi> He rejected with indignation
                    the miraculous stories told to confirm the doctrine of transubstantiation. He
                    saw in these legends unworthy inventions originated to awe and influence
                    ignorant and superstitious minds. On this account he was falsely accused of
                    denying miracles altogether. 6. Reason and Scripture seemed to him the only
                    grounds on which a true doctrine of the Lord’s supper could be rested. He had a
                    confidence in reason very rare in the 11th century, but was no rationalist. He
                    attached little importance to mere ecclesiastical tradition or authority, and
                    none to the voice of majorities, even when sanctioned by the decree of a Pope.
                    In this, as in other respects, he was a precursor of Protestantism.</p>
                <p>The opinions of Berengar are to be ascertained from the works written in
                    refutation of them by Adelmann, Lanfranc, Guilmund, &amp;c.; from the fragments
                    of the <hi rend="italic">De sacr.</hi><hi rend="italic">coena</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">adv. Lanfr. liber,</hi> edited by Stäudlin (1820-29); and from the
                    <hi rend="italic">Liber posterior,</hi> edited by A. F. and F. T. Vischer
                    (1834). See also the <hi rend="italic">Bcrcngarius Turon·</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ensis</hi> of Lessing (1770), and especially of Sudendoτf (1850); the <hi
                    rend="italic">Church Histories</hi> of Gieseler, ii. 396-411 (Eng. transi.), and
                    Neander, vi. 221-260 (Eng. transi.); PrantΓs <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                    Logik,</hi> ii. 70-75, and Hauréau’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la
                    Philosophie Scolastique,</hi> i. 225- 238. (R. F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
