<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0574-0559-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BENEFICE (9th edition, volume 3, page 559)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:864129">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1074680">Prayer</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp12">Prayer</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n574/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BENEFICE</label>, a term first applied under the Roman empire
                    to portions of land, the usufruct of which was granted by the emperors to their
                    soldiers or others for life, as a reward or <hi rend="italic">beneficium</hi>
                    for past services, and as a retainer for future services. A list of all such <hi
                    rend="italic">beneficia</hi> was recorded in the <hi rend="italic">Book of
                    Benefices (Liber</hi><hi rend="italic">Beneficiorum),</hi> which was kept by the
                    principal registrar of benefices <hi rend="italic">(Primiscrinius
                    Beneficiorum).</hi> In imitation of the practice observed under the Roman
                    empire, the term came to be applied under the feudal system to portions of land
                    granted by a lord to his vassal for the maintenance of the latter on condition
                    of his rendering military service; and such grants were originally for life
                    only, and the land reverted to the lord on the death of the vassal. In a similar
                    manner grants of land, or of the profits of land, appear to have been made by
                    the bishops to their clergy for life, on the ground of some extraordinary merit
                    on the part of the grantee. The validity of such grants was first formally
                    recognized by the Council of Orleans, 511 A.D., which forbade, however, under
                    any circumstances, the alienation from the bishoprics of any lands so granted.
                    The next following Council of Orleans, 533, broke in upon this principle, by
                    declaring that a bishop could not reclaim from his clergy any grants made to
                    them by his predecessor, excepting in cases of misconduct. This innovation on
                    the ancient practice was confirmed by the subsequent Council of Lyons, 566, and
                    from this period these grants ceased to be regarded as personal, and their
                    substance became annexed to the churches,—in other words, they were henceforth
                    enjoyed, <hi rend="italic">jure</hi><hi rend="italic">tituli,</hi> and no longer
                    <hi rend="italic">jure</hi><hi rend="italic">personali.</hi> How and when the
                    term <hi rend="italic">beneficia</hi> came to be applied to these episcopal
                    grants is uncertain, but they are designated by that term in a canon of the
                    Council of Mayence, 813.</p>
                <p>The term benefice, according to the canon law, implies always an ecclesiastical
                    office, <hi rend="italic">propter quod</hi><hi rend="italic">beneficium
                    datur,</hi> but it does not always imply a cure of souls. It has been defined to
                    be the right which a clerk has to enjoy certain ecclesiastical revenues on
                    condition of discharging certain services prescribed by the canons, or by usage,
                    or by the conditions under which his office has been founded. These services
                    might be those of a secular priest with cure of souls, or they might be those of
                    a regular priest, a member of a religious order, without cure of souls; but in
                    every case a benefice implied three things: 1. An obligation to discharge the
                    duties of an office, which is altogether spiritual; 2. The right to enjoy the
                    fruits attached to that office, which is the benefice itself; 3. The fruits
                    themselves, which are the temporalities. By keeping these distinctions in view,
                    the right of patronage in the case of secular benefices becomes intelligible,
                    being in fact the right, which was originally vested in the donor of the
                    temporalities, to present to the bishop a clerk to be admitted, if found fit by
                    the bishop, to the office to which those temporalities are annexed. Nomination
                    or presentation on the part of the patron of the benefice is thus the first
                    requisite in order that a clerk should become legally entitled to a benefice.
                    The next requisite is that he should be admitted by the bishop as a fit person
                    for the spiritual office to which the benefice is annexed, and the bishop is the
                    judge of the sufficiency of the clerk to be so admitted. By the early
                    constitutions of the Church of England a bishop was allowed a space of two
                    months to inquire and inform himself of the sufficiency of every presentee, but
                    by the ninety-fifth of the canons of 1604 that interval has been abridged to
                    twenty-eight days, within which the bishop must admit or reject the clerk. If
                    the bishop rejects the clerk within that time he is liable to a <hi
                    rend="italic">duplex querela</hi> in the ecclesiastical courts, or to a <hi
                    rend="italic">quare</hi><hi rend="italic">impedit</hi> in the common law courts,
                    and the bishop must then certify the reasons of his refusal. In cases where the
                    patron is himself a clerk in orders, and wishes to be admitted to the benefice,
                    he must proceed by way of petition, instead of by deed of presentation, reciting
                    that the benefice is in his own patronage, and petitioning the bishop to examine
                    him and admit him. Upon the bishop having satisfied himself of the sufficiency
                    of the clerk, he proceeds to institute him to the spiritual office to which the
                    benefice is annexed, but before such institution can take place, the clerk is
                    required to make a declaration of assent to the Thirty-nine Articles of Religion
                    and to the Book of Common Prayer according to a form prescribed in the Clerical
                    Subscription Act, 28 and 29 Vict. c. 122, to make a declaration against simony
                    in accordance with that Act, and to take and subscribe the oath of allegiance
                    according to the form in 31 and 32 Vict. c. 72. The bishop, by the act of
                    institution, commits to the clerk the cure of souls attached to the office to
                    which the benefice is annexed. In cases where the bishop himself is patron of
                    the benefice, no presentation or petition is required to be tendered by the
                    clerk, but the bishop having satisfied himself of the sufficiency of the clerk,
                    collates him to the benefice and office. It is not necessary that the bishop
                    himself should personally institute or collate a clerk, he may issue a fiat to
                    his vicar-general, or to a special commissary for that purpose. After the bishop
                    or his commissary has instituted the presentee, he issues a mandate under seal,
                    addressed to the archdeacon or some other neighbouring clergyman, authorizing
                    him to induct the clerk into his benefice,—in other words, to put him into legal
                    possession of the temporalities, which is done by some outward form, and for the
                    most part by delivery of the bell-rope to the clerk, who thereupon tolls the
                    bell. This form of induction is required to give the clerk a legal title to his
                    “<hi rend="italic">beneficium,</hi> although his admission to the office by
                    institution is sufficient to vacate any other benefice which he may already
                    possess.</p>
                <p>By the Lateran Council of 1215, which was received by the Church of England, no
                    clerk can hold two benefices with cure of souls, and if a beneficed clerk shall
                    take a second benefice with cure of souls, he vacates <hi rend="italic">ipso
                    facto</hi> his first benefice. Dispensations, however, could be easily obtained
                    from Rome, before the reformation of the Church of England, to enable a clerk to
                    hold several ecclesiastical dignities or benefices at the same time, and by 25
                    Henry VIII. c. 21, the power to grant such dispensations, which had been
                    exercised previously by the court of Rome, was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n575/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0575-0560"/> transferred to the archbishop of Canterbury,
                    certain ecclesiastical persons having been declared by a previous statute (21
                    Henry VIII. c. 13) to be entitled to such dispensations. The system of
                    pluralities carried with it, as a necessary consequence, systematic
                    non-residence on the part of many incumbents, and delegation of their spiritual
                    duties in respect of their cures of souls to assistant curates. The evils
                    attendant on this system were found to be so great that in 1838 an Act of
                    Parliament, 1 and 2 Vict. c. 106, was passed to abridge the holding of benefices
                    in plurality, and it was enacted that no person should hold under any
                    circumstances more than two benefices, and this privilege was made subject to
                    the restriction that his benefices were within ten statute miles of each other.
                    By a subsequent Act, 13 and 14 Vict. c. 98, the restriction has been further
                    narrowed, and no spiritual person may now hold two benefices except the churches
                    of such benefices are within three miles of each other by the nearest road, and
                    the annual value of one of such benefices does not exceed one hundred pounds. By
                    this statute the term benefice is defined to mean benefice with cure of souls
                    and no other, and therein to comprehend all parishes, perpetual curacies,
                    donatives, endowed public chapels, parochial chapelries, and chapelries or
                    districts belonging or reputed to belong, or annexed or reputed to be annexed,
                    to any church or chapel.</p>
                <p>A benefice is avoided or vacated—1, by death; 2, by resignation, if the bishop is
                    willing to accept the resignation; 3, by cession, upon the clerk being
                    instituted to another benefice or some other preferment incompatible with it; 4,
                    by deprivation and sentence of an ecclesiastical court; 5, by act of law in
                    consequence of simony; 6, by default of the clerk in neglecting to read publicly
                    in the church the Book of Common Prayer, and to declare his assent thereto
                    within two months after his induction, pursuant to 13 and 14 Car. II. c. 4, §
                    vi.</p>
                <p>The number of benefices with or without cure of souls in the Church of England,
                    before the first statute to abridge pluralities was passed in 1838 (1 and 2
                    Vict. c. 106), was about 11,000. These benefices were served by some 10,000
                    clergy, of whom rather more than 5000 were incumbents holding one or more
                    livings, and some of them altogether non-resident; the remainder were assistant
                    curates, for the most part residing in one parish and having full charge of
                    another. The effect of the Pluralities Act in the course of about 30 years has
                    been to produce a remarkable and most salutary change. It was computed in 1867
                    that the parochial benefices were 12,888 in number, and the parochial clergy
                    17,869, of whom 4931 only were assistant-curates. The patronage of 6403 of these
                    benefices was in private hands, whilst the patronage of 6485 was at the disposal
                    of the Crown, or of public bodies or public functionaries. An approximate
                    statement of the yearly value of all the benefices in England and Wales, the
                    number of which has undergone a considerable increase since 1867, was drawn up
                    in 1874 by Mr J. K. Aston for a select committee of the House of Lords on Church
                    Patronage. From this statement it appears that the yearly value of all the
                    benefices in public patronage is about £1,825,805, whilst the value of those in
                    private patronage is about £1,893,226; but in Mr Aston’s opinion these estimates
                    are below the actual value. (τ. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
