<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0482-0467-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BEAUMARCHAIS (9th edition, volume 3, page 467)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964412">Husbands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n482/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BEAUMARCHAIS</label>. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Augustin</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Caron,</hi> better known by
                    his acquired title <hi rend="smallcaps">De</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Beaumarchais,</hi> the most distinguished French comic dramatist next to
                    Molière, and aman of much importance during the pre-Revolutionary period, was
                    born at Paris in 1732. His father, who was a watchmaker, brought him up to the
                    same trade. He was an unusually precocious and lively boy, shrewd, sagacious,
                    and, like his sisters, passionately fond of music, and imbued with a strong
                    desire for rising in the world. At the age of twenty-one he invented a new
                    escapement for w atches, which was pirated by a rival maker. Young Caron at once
                    published his grievance in the newspapers, and had the matter referred to the
                    Academy of Sciences, who decided in his favour. This affair brought him into
                    notice at court; he was appointed, or at least chose to dub himself, watchmaker
                    to the king, who had called him in to examine Mme. de Pompadour’s watch. His
                    handsome figure and cool assurance soon began to make their way at court, where
                    he so earnestly desired to obtain a footing. Nor was it long before his wish was
                    accomplished. The wife of an old court official, conceiving a violent passion
                    for young Caron, persuaded her husband to make over his office to his rival, and
                    on her husband's death, a few months later, married the handsome watchmaker.
                    Caron at the same time assumed the title De Beaumarchais; and four years later,
                    by purchasing the office of secretary to the king, obtained a title of
                    nobility.</p>
                <p>While employed at court his musical talents brought him under the notice of the
                    king’s sisters, who engaged him to teach them the harp. In this way he obtained
                    access to the best society of the court, and by a fortunate accident was enabled
                    to make use of the princesses’ friendship to confer a slight favour on the great
                    banker Paris-Duverney. Duverney testified his gratitude in a most substantial
                    manner; he bestowed shares in several of his speculations upon Beaumarchais, and
                    the latter, whose business talents <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n483/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0483-0468"/> were of a high, order, soon realized a handsome
                    fortune. In 1764 he took a journey to Spain, partly with commercial objects in
                    view, but principally on account of the Clavijo affair, which was afterwards
                    made famous by the Goezman memoirs, and by Goethe’s drama. ;Four years later he
                    made his first essay on the stage with the sentimental drama <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eugenie,</hi> which was followed after an interval of two years by <hi
                    rend="italic">Les Deux Amis.</hi> Neither had more than moderate success, and it
                    was clear that, though the author might be unaware of it, his strength did not
                    lie in the grave and sentimental. Meantime the clouds of the first great storm
                    in Beaumarchais’s life were gathering round him. He was very generally disliked
                    as an upstart, and there were many ready to seize the first opportunity of
                    hurling him from the position he had attained. Duverney, his great benefactor,
                    died in 1770; but some time before his death a duplicate settlement of the
                    affairs between him and Beaumarchais had been drawn up, in which the former
                    acknowledged himself debtor to the latter for 1G,OOO francs. Duverney’s heir,
                    Count la Blache, a bitter enemy of Beaumarchais, denied the validity of this
                    document, though without directly stigmatizing it as a forgery. The matter was
                    put to trial. Beaumarchais gained his cause, but his adversary at once carried
                    the case before the parliament, and in the early part of 1773 that body was
                    preparing to give its decision on the report of one of its members, Μ. Goezman.
                    Beaumarchais was well-nigh in despair; ruin stared him in the face; he was
                    looked upon not only with dislike but with suspicion and contempt. Worst of all,
                    he was unable to obtain an interview with Goezman, in whose hands his fate
                    rested. At last, just before the day on which the report was to be given in, he
                    was informed privately that, by presenting 200 louis to Mme. Goezman and 15 to
                    her secretary, the desired interview might take place; if the result should
                    prove unfavourable the money would be refunded. The money was sent and the
                    interview obtained; but the decision was adverse, and 200 louis were returned,
                    the 15 going as business expenses to the secretary. Beaumarchais, who had
                    learned that there was no secretary save Mme. Goezman herself, insisted on
                    restitution of the 15 louis, and the lady, in her passion, denied all knowledge
                    of the affair. Her husband, who seems not to have been cognisant of the
                    transaction at first, and who, doubtless, thought the defeated litigant would be
                    easily put down, at once brought an accusation against him in parliament for an
                    attempt to corrupt a judge. The battle was fought chiefly through the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires,</hi> or reports published by the adverse parties, and in
                    it Beaumarchais’s success was most complete. All his best qualities were drawn
                    forth by the struggle; his wit, energy, and cheerfulness seemed to be doubled;
                    and for vivacity of style, fine satire, and broad humour, his famous <hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> have never been surpassed. Even Voltaire was
                    constrained to envy them. Nor was the effect of the struggle apparent only in
                    Beaumarchais himself. He was attacking the parliament through one of its
                    members, and the parliament was the universally detested body formed by the
                    chancellor Maupeou. The <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> were, therefore, hailed
                    with general delight; and the author, from being perhaps the most unpopular man
                    in France, became at once the idol of the people. The decision in the case,
                    however, so far as law went, was against him. The parliament condemned him <hi
                    rend="italic">au blâme,</hi><hi rend="italic">—i.e.,</hi> to civic degradation;
                    but he obtained restitution of his rights within two years, and finally
                    triumphed over his adversary La Blache.</p>
                <p>During the next few years his employment was of a somewhat singular nature. He
                    was engaged by the king in secret service, principally to destroy certain
                    scurrilous pamphlets concerning Mme. du Barry, the publication of which had been
                    threatened. His visits to England, on these missions, in which he w as very
                    successful, led him to take a deep interest in the impending struggle between
                    the colonies and the mother country. His sympathies were entirely with the
                    Americans; and by his unwearied exertions he succeeded in inducing the French
                    Government to give ample, though private, assistance in money and arms to the
                    insurgent colonists. He himself, partly on his oλvn account, partly as an agent,
                    carried on an enormous traffic with America. During the same period he had laid
                    the foundations of a more enduring fame by his two famous comedies, the best of
                    their class since those of Molière. The earlier, <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Barbier de Seville,</hi> after a short prohibition, was put on the
                    stage in 1775. The first representation was a complete failure. Beaumarchais had
                    overloaded the last scene with allusions to the facts of his ow n case and the w
                    hole action of the piece was laboured and heavy. But with undaunted energy he
                    set to work, cut down and remodelled the piece in time for the second
                    representation, when it achieved a complete success. The intrigues which w ere
                    necessary in order to obtain a licence for the second and more famous comedy <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Mariage</hi><hi rend="italic">de Figaro</hi> are highly
                    amusing, and throw much light on the unsettled state of public sentiment at the
                    time. The play was completed in 1781, but the opposition of Louis XVI., who saw
                    its dangerous tendencies, was not overcome till 1784. The comedy had an
                    unprecedented success. The principal character in both plays, the w orld-famous
                    <hi rend="italic">Figaro,</hi> isa completely original conception; and for
                    mingled wit, shrewdness, gaiety, and philosophic reflection, may not unjustly be
                    ranked alongside of the great Tartuffe. To English readers the Figaro plays are
                    generally known through the adaptations of them in the grand operas of Mozart
                    and Rossini; but in France they long retained popularity as acting pieces.
                    Beaumarchais’s later productions, the bombastic opera <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tarare,</hi> and the drama <hi rend="italic">The Guilty Mother,</hi> which w as
                    very popular, are hardly worthy of his genius.</p>
                <p>By his writings Beaumarchais contributed greatly, though quite unconsciously, to
                    hurry on the events that led to the Revolution. At heart he hardly seems to have
                    been a republican, and the new state of affairs did not benefit him. His
                    popularity had been somewhat lessened by the affairs Bergasse and Mirabeau, and
                    his great wealth and splendid mansion exposed him to the enmity of the envious.
                    A speculation into wdiich he entered, to supply the Convention with muskets from
                    Holland, proved a ruinous failure. He w as charged with treason to the Republic,
                    and was obliged for some time to take refuge in Holland and England. His memoirs
                    entitled, <hi rend="italic">Mes</hi><hi rend="italic">Six</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Époques,</hi> detailing his sufferings under the Republic, are not unworthy of
                    the Goezman period. His courage and happy disposition never deserted him; he <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> was gay and hopeful up to the time of his death,
                    which took place suddenly in May 1799.</p>
                <p>Lomenie, <hi rend="italic">Beaumarchais ct son Temps,</hi> 1856; Eng. trans, of
                    the same by H. S. Edwards, 4 vols., 1856. Beaumarchais’s works have been
                    published by Gudin, <hi rend="italic">7</hi> vols., 1809; and by Furne, 6 vols.,
                    1827.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
