<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0320-0305-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAMBOO (9th edition, volume 3, page 305)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zd29">Joints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rq88">Growth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c40">Shooting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:813089">Archipelagoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983905">Joints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:948571">Growth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n320/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAMBOO</label>, a genus <hi rend="italic">{Bambusa')</hi> of
                    arborescent grasses very generally distributed throughout the tropical lands of
                    the globe, but found and cultivated especially in India, China, and the East
                    Indian Archipelago. There is a large number of species enumerated; but, as is
                    the case with most plants under cultivation, much difficulty is found in
                    distinguishing species from varieties produced by artificial selection. <hi
                    rend="italic">Bambusa</hi><hi rend="italic">arundinacea</hi> is the species most
                    commonly referred to. It is a tree-like plant, rising to a height of 40, 60, or
                    even 80 feet, with a hollow stem, shining as if varnished. The stem is extremely
                    slender, not exceeding the thickness of 5 inches in some which are 50 feet high,
                    and in others reaching 15 or 18 inches in diameter. The whole is divided into
                    joints or septa called knots or internodes, the intervals between which in the
                    case of some of the larger stems is several feet. These joints or divisions are
                    formed by the crossing of the vascular bundles of fibres. They produce alternate
                    lateral buds, which form small alternate branchlets springing from the base to
                    the top, and, together with the narrow-pointed leaves issuing from them, give
                    the plant an elegant feathered appearance as it waves in the wind. The rapidity
                    of its growth is surprising. It attains its full height in a few months, and Mr
                    Fortune records the observation of a growth of from 2 to 21 feet in a single
                    day. In Malabar it is said to bear fruit when fifteen years old, and then to
                    die.</p>
                <p>The bamboo is cultivated with great care in regular plantations by the Chinese.
                    The plant is propagated by shoots or suckers deposited in pits 18 inches or 2
                    feet deep at the close of autumn or the beginning of winter. Various expedients
                    are followed to obtain good bamboos; one of the most usual being to take a
                    vigorous root and transplant <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n321/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0321-0306"/> it, leaving only four or five inches above the
                    joint next the ground. The cavity is then filled with a mixture of horselitter
                    and sulphur. According to the vigour of the root, the shoots will be more or
                    less numerous; they are destroyed at an early stage during three successive
                    years; and those springing in the fourth resemble the parent tree. The uses to
                    which all the parts and products of the bamboo are applied in Oriental countries
                    are almost endless. The soft and succulent shoots, when just beginning to
                    spring, are cut over and served up at table like asparagus. Like that vegetable,
                    also, they are earthed over to keep them longer fit for consumption; and they
                    afford a continuous supply during the whole year, though it is more abundant in
                    autumn. They are also salted and eaten with rice, prepared in the form of
                    pickles, or candied and preserved in sugar. As the plant grows older, a species
                    of fluid is secreted in the hollow joints, in which a concrete substance, highly
                    valued in the East for its medicinal qualities, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >tabaxir</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tabascheer,</hi> is gradually developed. This
                    substance, which has been found to be a purely siliceous concretion, is
                    possessed of peculiar optical properties. As a medicinal agent the bamboo is
                    almost or entirely inert, and it has never been received into the European
                    materia medica. A decoction of the leaves of the plant is, however, employed in
                    the East for pectoral affections, and the leaf-buds are said to be diuretic. The
                    grains of the bamboo are available for food, and the Chinese have a proverb that
                    it produces seed more abundantly in years when the rice crop fails, which means,
                    probably, that in times of dearth the natives look more after such a source of
                    food. The Hindus eat it mixed with honey as a delicacy, equal quantities being
                    put into a hollow joint, coated externally with clay, and thus roasted over a
                    fire. It is, however, the stem of the bamboo which is applied to the greatest
                    variety of uses. J oints of sufficient size form water buckets; smaller ones are
                    used as bottles, and among the Dyaks of Borneo they are employed as cooking
                    vessels. Bamboo is extensively used as a timber wood, and houses are frequently
                    made entirely out of the products of the plant; complete sections of the stem
                    form posts or columns; split up, it serves for floors or rafters; and,
                    interwoven in lattice-work, it is employed for the sides of rooms, admitting
                    light and air. The roof is sometimes of bamboo solely, and when split, which is
                    accomplished with the greatest ease, it can be formed into laths or planks. It
                    is employed in shipping of all kinds; some of the strongest plants are selected
                    for masts of boats of moderate size, and the masts of larger vessels are
                    sometimes formed by the union of several bamboos built up and joined
                    together.</p>
                <p>The bamboo is employed in the construction of all kinds of agricultural and
                    domestic implements, and in the materials and implements required in fishery.
                    Bows are made of it by the union of two pieces with many bands; and, the septa
                    being bored out and the lengths joined together, it is employed, as we use
                    leaden pipes, in transmitting water to reservoirs or gardens. From the light and
                    slender stalks shafts for arrows are obtained; and in the south-west of Asia
                    there is a certain species of equally slender growth, from which writing-pens or
                    reeds are made. A joint forms a holder for papers or pens, and it was in a joint
                    of bamboo that silk-worm eggs were carried from China to Constantinople during
                    the reign of Justinian. The outer cuticle of Oriental species is so hard that it
                    forms a sharp and durable cutting edge, and it is so siliceous that it can be
                    used as a whetstone. This outer cuticle, cut into thin strips, is one of the
                    most durable and beautiful materials for basket-making, and both in China and
                    Japan it is largely so employed. Strips are also woven into cages, chairs, beds,
                    and other articles of furniture, Oriental wicker-work in bamboo being unequalled
                    for beauty and neatness of workmanship. In China the interior portions of the
                    stem are beaten into a pulp, and used for the manufacture of the finer varieties
                    of paper. Bamboos are imported to a considerable extent into Europe for the use
                    of basket-makers, and for umbrella and walking-sticks. In short, the purposes to
                    which the bamboo is applicable are almost endless, and well justify the opinion
                    that “it is one of the most wonderful and most beautiful productions of the
                    tropics, and one of Nature’s most valuable gifts to uncivilized man” (A. R.
                    Wallace, <hi rend="italic">The Malay Archipelago).</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
