<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0820-0803-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BLAKE, Robert (9th edition, volume 3, page 803)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100852">Royalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n820/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BLAKE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, the famous
                    English admiral of the Commonwealth, was born at Bridgwater in Somersetshire, in
                    August 1598. His birth thus falls in the year before that of Cromwell; their
                    lives ran parallel in the service of their country; their characters present
                    many points of likeness; and they died within a few months of each other. Blake
                    was the eldest son of a well-to-do merchant, and received his early education at
                    the grammar school of Bridgwater. At the age of sixteen he was sent to Oxford,
                    entering at first St Alban’s Hall, but removing afterwards to Wadham College,
                    then recently founded by his father’s friend, Nicholas Wadham. He remained at
                    the university till 1623, and though certainly not wanting in ability or in
                    diligence, he missed, for some reason not clearly ascertained, such college
                    preferment as he naturally aimed at. From Oxford, after taking his degree of
                    M.A., he returned to his father’s house, where, through the memorable and
                    troubled years which followed, he led a quiet and retired life. His thorough
                    honesty, his public spirit and disinterestedness, his courageous utterance of
                    what he thought of the court and the church, of shipmoney and the High
                    Commission Court and the licence of the times, made him a man of mark among his
                    neighbours. And when, after eleven years of kingship without parliaments, a
                    parliament was summoned to meet in April 1640, Blake was elected by the
                    Presbyterian party to represent his native borough. This parliament, named “the
                    Short,” was dissolved in three weeks, and the career of Blake as a politician
                    was suspended. Two years later the inevitable con flict began. Blake declared
                    for the Parliament; and thinking, says Johnson, a bare declaration for right not
                    all the duty of a good man, he raised a troop of horse in his county, and
                    rendered such efficient service, that in 1643 he was entrusted with the command
                    of one of the forts of Bristol. This he stoutly held during the siege of the
                    town by Prince Rupert, and was near being hung for continuing his resistance
                    after the governor had capitulated. In the following year Colonel Blake took
                    Taunton by surprise, and notwithstanding its imperfect defences and inadequate
                    supplies, held the tewn for the Parliament against two sieges by the Royalists,
                    until July 1645, when it was relieved by Fairfax. Blake did not approve of the
                    trial and execution of Charles I.; but he adhered to the Parliamentary party
                    after the king’s death, and within a month (February 1649) was appointed, with
                    Colonels Dean and Popham, to the command of the fleet, under the title of
                    General of the Sea. In April he was sent in pursuit of Prince Rupert, who with
                    the Royalist fleet had entered the harbour of Kinsale in Ireland. There he
                    blockaded the Prince for six months; and when the latter, in want of provisions,
                    and hopeless of relief, succeeded in making his escape with the fleet and in
                    reaching the Tagus, Blake followed him thither, and again blockaded him for some
                    months. The king of Portugal refu sing permission for Blake to attack his enemy,
                    the latter made reprisals by falling on the Portuguese fleet, richly laden,
                    returning from Brazil. He captured seventeen ships and burnt three, bringing his
                    prizes home without molestation. After revictualling his fleet, he sailed again,
                    captured a French man-of-war, and then pursued Prince Rupert once more to the
                    harbour of Carthagena. The Spanish governor would not allow him to violate the
                    peace of a neutral port, and he therefore withdrew. In January 1651 he at last
                    attacked the Royalist fleet in Malaga harbour, and destroyed the whole <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n821/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0821-0804"/> with the exception of two ships. In consequence
                    of the Portuguese protest against his proceedings, a formal investigation was
                    instituted in England, which resulted in the approval of the home authorities.
                    The thanks of Parliament were voted to Blake, and he was appointed warden of the
                    Cinque Ports. He was continued in his office of admiral and general of the sea;
                    and in May following he took, in conjunction with Ayscue, the Scilly Islands.
                    For this service the thanks of Parliament were again awarded him, and he was
                    soon after made a member of the Council of State. In 1652 war broke out with the
                    Dutch, who had made great preparations for the conflict. In March the command of
                    the fleet was given to Blake for nine months; and in the middle of May the Dutch
                    fleet of forty-five ships, led by their great admiral Van Tromp, appeared in the
                    Downs. Blake, who had only twenty ships, sailed to meet them, and the battle
                    took place off Dover on May 19. The Dutch were defeated in an engagement of four
                    or five hours, lost two ships, and withdrew under cover of darkness. Attempts at
                    accommodation were made by the States, but they failed. Early in July war was
                    formally declared, and in the same month Blake captured a large part of the
                    Dutch fishery-fleet and the twelve men-of-war that formed their convoy. On
                    September 28, Blake and Penn again encountered the Dutch fleet, now commanded by
                    De Ruyter and De Witt, in the Downs, defeated it, and chased it for two days.
                    The Dutch took refuge in Goree. A third battle was fought near the end of
                    November. By this time the ships under Blake’s command had been reduced in
                    number to forty, and nearly the half of these were useless for want of seamen.
                    Van Tromp, who had been reinstated in command, appeared in the Downs, with a
                    fleet of eighty ships besides ten fire-ships. Blake, nevertheless, risked a
                    battle, but was defeated, and withdrew into the Thames. It was in his first
                    elation at this victory that Van Tromp carried the broom at his masthead in his
                    passage through the Channel, as a pledge of his determination to sweep the
                    English off the seas. His bravado was speedily avenged. The English fleet having
                    been refitted, put to sea again in February 1653; and on the 18th, Blake, at the
                    head of eighty ships, encountered Van Tromp in the Channel. The Dutch force,
                    according to Clarendon, numbered 100 ships of war, but according to the official
                    reports of the Dutch, only seventy. The battle was severe, and continued through
                    three days, the Dutch however retreating, and taking refuge in the shallow
                    waters off the French coast. In this action Blake was severely wounded. In the
                    change of Government introduced by the dismissal of the Long Parliament by
                    Cromwell (April 1653) Blake did not interfere. “It is not,” he said, “the
                    business of a seaman to mind state affairs, but to hinder foreigners from
                    fooling us.” The three English admirals put to sea again in May; and on June 3d
                    and 4th another battle was fought near the North Foreland. On the first day Dean
                    and Monk were repulsed by Van Tromp; but on the second day the scales were
                    turned by the arrival of Blake, and the Dutch retreated to the Texel. Ill health
                    now compelled Blake to retire from the service for a time, and he did not appear
                    again on the seas for about eighteen months; meanwhile he sat as a member of the
                    Little Parliament (Barebones’s). In November 1654 he was selected by Cromwell to
                    conduct a fleet to the Mediterranean to exact compensation from the Duke of
                    Tuscany, the knights of Malta, and the piratical states of North Africa, for
                    wrongs done to English merchants. This mission he executed with his accustomed
                    spirit and with complete success. Tunis alone dared to resist his demands, and
                    Tunis paid the penalty of the destruction of its two fortresses by English guns.
                    In the winter of 1655-5G, war being declared against Spain, Blake was sent to
                    cruise off Cadiz and the neighbouring coasts, to intercept the Spanish shipping.
                    One of his captains captured a part of the Plate fleet in September 1656. In
                    April 1657 Blake, then in very ill health, suffering from dropsy and scurvy, and
                    anxious to have assistance in his arduous duties, heard that the Plate fleet lay
                    at anchor in the bay of Santa Cruz, in the island of Teneriffe. The position was
                    a very strong one, defended by a castle and several forts with guns. Under the
                    shelter of these lay a fleet of sixteen ships drawn up in crescent order.
                    Captain Stayner was ordered to enter the bay and fall on the fleet. This he did.
                    Blake followed him. Broadsides were poured into the castle and the forts at the
                    same time; and soon nothing was left but ruined walls and charred fragments of
                    burnt ships. The wind was blowing hard into the bay; but suddenly, and
                    fortunately for the heroic Blake, it shifted, and carried him safely out to sea.
                    “The whole action,” says Clarendon, “was so incredible that all men who knew the
                    place wondered that any sober man, with what courage soever endowed, would ever
                    have undertaken it; and they could hardly persuade themselves to believe what
                    they had done; while the Spaniards comforted themselves with the belief that
                    they were devils and not men who had destroyed them in such a manner.” The
                    English lost one ship and 200 men killed and wounded. The thanks of Parliamant
                    were voted to officers and men; and a very costly jewel (diamond ring) was
                    presented to Blake, “as a testimony,” says Cromwell in his letter of June 10th,
                    “of our own and the Parliament’s good acceptance of your carriage in this
                    action.” “This was the last action of the brave Blake.” After again cruising for
                    a time off Cadiz, his health failing more and more, he was compelled to make
                    homewards before the summer was over. He died at sea, but within sight of
                    Plymouth, August 17, 1657. His body was brought to London and embalmed, and
                    after lying in state at Greenwich House was interred with great pomp and
                    solemnity in Westminster Abbey. In 1661 Charles II. disgraced himself by
                    ordering the exhumation of Blake’s body, with those of the mother and daughter
                    of Cromwell aud several others. They were cast out of the abbey, and were
                    reburied in the churchyard of St Margaret’s. “But that regard,” says Johnson,
                    “which was denied his body has been paid to his better remains, his name and his
                    memory. Nor has any writer dared to deny him the praise of intrepidity, honesty,
                    contempt of wealth, and love of his country.” Clarendon bears the following
                    testimony to his excellence as a commander :—“He was the first man that declined
                    the old track, and made it apparent that the science might be attained in less
                    time than was imagined. He was the first man that brought ships to contemn
                    castles on the shore, which had ever been thought very formidable, but were
                    discovered by him to make a noise only, and to fright those who could be rarely
                    hurt by them.” A life of Blake is included in the work entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Lives, English and Foreign.</hi> Dr Johnson wrote a short life of
                    him, and in 1852 appeared Mr Hepworth Dixon’s fuller narrative,, <hi
                    rend="italic">Robert Elake, Admiral and</hi><hi rend="italic">General</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">at Sea.</hi> (w. L. κ. c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
