<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0388-0373-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARERE DE VIEUZAC, Bertrand (9th edition, volume 3,
                    page 373)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1148101">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1148096">Terror</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942930">Girondists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hw9j">Girondists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zx91">Anger</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n388/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARERE DE VIEUZAC, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Bertrand</hi></label>, one of the most notorious members of the French National
                    Convention, was born at Tarbes in Gascony, September 10, 1755. He was brought up
                    to the profession of the law, and was admitted advocate to the parliament of
                    Toulouse. He wrote several trivial pieces, panegyrics of Louis XVI.,
                    Montesquieu, J. J. Rousseau, and others, which obtained prizes from provincial
                    academies, and a dissertation on a Latin inscription which procured him
                    membership of the Academy of Floral Games of Toulouse. Such was the smooth
                    beginning of a career which ultimately became unparalleled for meanness,
                    cowardice, lying, and atrocious cruelty. At the age of thirty he married. Four
                    years later, in 1789, he was elected deputy by his own province to the
                    States-general, which met in May. He had made his first visit to Paris in the
                    preceding year. His personal appearance, his manners, social qualities, and
                    liberal opinions, gave him a good standing among the multitude of provincial
                    wise-heads then thronging into Paris, eager to be the saviours of France, or at
                    least of themselves. He took his place at first with the monarchical party; and
                    his·, glib pen found occupation in the preparation of various reports, and in
                    editing a journal, the <hi rend="italic">Point du Jour,</hi> containing reports
                    of the debates of the National Assembly. For a time he formed a connection with
                    the House of Orleans, passing over soon to the republican party. Barère appears
                    to have been wholly free from the restraints of conscience or any guiding
                    principle; his conduct was regulated only by the determination to be on the side
                    of the strongest. After the close of the National Assembly he was nominated one
                    of the judges of the newly-instituted Court of Cassation. In 1792 he was elected
                    deputy to the National Convention for the department of the Hautes Pyrénées. At
                    first he took part with the Girondists; but on the trial of the king he voted,
                    with the Mountain, for the king’s death “<hi rend="italic">sans appel et sans
                    sursis.”</hi> He closed his speech with a sentence which became memorable, <hi
                    rend="italic">“L’arbre de la liberté ne saurait croître s’il n’était arrosé du
                    sang du rois.”</hi> As the Mountain became the strongest party Barère advanced
                    with it, unscrupulously carrying out its extremest projects, and playing a
                    prominent part in the Reign of Terror. The light-heartedness with which he acted
                    in these awful scenes, the fluency and flippancy of his speeches and reports,
                    procured him the title of the “Anacreon of the Guillotine.” He supported
                    Robespierre in his atrocious measure against the Girondists, crawled like a
                    slave at the feet of the “incorruptible” Maximilian till the day of his fall,
                    and then advocated his execution without a hearing. It was Barère who had
                    proposed the decree that no quarter should be given to any English or Hanoverian
                    soldier, which was unanimously adopted. This procured him admission by
                    acclamation to the Jacobin Club, from which he had been previously excluded. The
                    decree, however, remained a dead letter. A few months after the fall of the
                    Convention, proceedings were taken against Barère and his colleagues of the
                    Terror, Collot d’Herbois and Billaud-Varennes, and he was sent to the Isle of
                    Oléron. He was removed to Saintes, and thence escaped to Bordeaux, where he lay
                    in concealment for several years. In 1795 he was elected member of the Council
                    of Fire Hundred, but was not allowed to take his seat. When Napoleon Bonaparte
                    was First Consul he was anxious to employ Barère, but Barère refused the
                    overture. It was only for a while. The witling of the Terror became the hireling
                    and the spy of the new tyranny. On the fall of Napoleon, Barère played the part
                    of royalist, but on the final restoration of the Bourbons in 1815 he was
                    banished for life from France, and then withdrew into Belgium and temporary
                    oblivion. After the Revolution of July 1830 he reappeared in France, was reduced
                    by a series of lawsuits to extreme indigence, accepted a small pension assigned
                    him by Louis Philippe (on whom he had heaped <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n389/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0389-0374"/> abuse and railing), and died, the last survivor
                    of the Committee of Public Safety, January 15, lt&gt;41. Two years after his
                    death appeared <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Bertrand</hi><hi rend="italic">Barere,</hi> edited by Hippolyte Carnot and David
                    of Angers. (See Macaulay’s article in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Review,</hi> vol. lxxix., in which the character and career of Barère<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Summed up thus :—“Our opinion
                    then is this, that Barère approached nearer than any person mentioned in history
                    or fiction, whether man or devil, to the idea of consummate and universal
                    depravity. In him the qualities which are the proper objects of hatred, and the
                    qualities which are the proper objects of contempt, preserve an exquisite and
                    absolute harmony. In almost every particular sort of wickedness he has had
                    rivals. His sensuality was immoderate; but this was a failing common to him with
                    many great and amiable men. There have been many men as cowardly as he, some as
                    cruel, a few as mean, a few as impudent. There may also have been as great
                    liars, though we never met with them or read of them. But when we put every·
                    thing together, sensuality, poltroonery, baseness, effrontery, mendacity,
                    barbarity, the result is something which in a novel we should condemn as
                    caricature, and to which, we venture to say, no parallel can be found in
                    history”</p></note> are discussed with characteristic emphasis and
                    severity.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
