<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0296-0281-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BALI, or Little Java (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    281)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957121">Hinduism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968197">Imports</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s70x">Imports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26g4w">Hinduism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n296/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BALI, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Little Java</hi></label>, one
                    of the Sunda Islands, in the Eastern Seas, separated from Java by the straits of
                    the same name, which are a mile and a half wide. It is 75 miles in length; its
                    greatest breadth is 50 miles. A chain of mountains crosses the island in a
                    direction E. and W., and terminates on the E. in the volcanic peak Gunung-agung,
                    12,379 feet above the sea-level. The climate and soil are the same as in Java;
                    it has mountains of proportionate height, several lakes of great depth, and
                    streams well fitted for the purposes of irrigation. Rice is produced in great
                    quantities, and is even exported to Madura, Celebes, Timor, and Java. The other
                    productions are tobacco, maize, pulses, oil, and salt; also cotton of an
                    excellent quality. Coffee is now grown with great success; in the district of
                    Teja Kulo alone, 150,000 trees were planted in the first four months of 1873.
                    The inhabitants (estimated at about 800,000), though originally sprung from the
                    same stock as those of Java, exceed them in stature and muscular power, as well
                    as in activity and enterprising habits. “They have,” says Sir Stamford Raffles,
                    “a higher cast of spirit, independence, and manliness than belongs to any of
                    their neighbours.” They are good agriculturists and skilful artisans, especially
                    in textile fabrics and the manufacture of arms. The imports are iron and cotton
                    cloths, and opium to a great extent; in the district of Tabanan alone, forty
                    chests of this drug are annually consumed. Both imports and exports are on the
                    increase; but trade is chiefly in the hands of Europeans, Chinese, and Arabs,
                    who have their firms or agents in Batavia, Surabaya, Makassar, and Singapore.
                    The trade returns in the port of Padang Cove are estimated at £500,000 to
                    £600,000 per annum; those of Buleleng and Jembrana were about £500,000 in 1873.
                    The island is divided into the eight independent principalities of Buleleng,
                    Karang Asam, Bangli, Tabanan, Mengui, Klong-kong, Gyanyar, and Badong, each
                    under its own ruler. The deputy-commissioner of Banyuwangi in east Java is also
                    charged with the superintendence of the island of Bali in behalf of the Dutch
                    Government. Though native rule is described as very tyrannical and arbitrary,
                    especially in the principalities of Badong and Tabanan, trade and industry could
                    not flourish if insecurity of persons and property existed to any great extent.
                    The natives have also a remedy against the aggression of their rulers in their
                    own hands; it is called <hi rend="italic">Metilas,</hi> consists in a general
                    rising and renunciation of allegiance, and proves mostly successful. Justice is
                    administered from a written civil and criminal code. Slavery is abolished.
                    Hinduism, which was once the religion of Java, but has been extinct there for
                    four centuries, is still in vogue in the islands of Bali and Lombok, where the
                    cruel custom of widow burning is still practised, and the Hindu system of the
                    four castes, with a fifth or Pariah caste (called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chanddla</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">),</hi>
                    adhered to. It appears partly blended with Buddhism, partly overgrown with a
                    belief in <hi rend="italic">Kalas,</hi> or evil spirits. To appease these,
                    offerings are made to them either direct or through the mediation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Devas</hi> (domestic or agrarian deities); and if these avail not,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Menyepi,</hi> or Great Sacrifice, is resorted to. Buddhism
                    prevails only in three districts. The Mahometan religion is said to be on the
                    wane, in spite of the good influence it has exerted upon the people. Of the
                    early history of their island the Balinese knownothing. The oldest tradition
                    they possess refers to a time shortly after the overthrow of the Majapahit
                    dynasty in Java, about the middle of the I5th century; but, according tc Lassen,
                    who identifies Bali with the island visited by <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n297/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0297-0282"/> Jambulos, there must have been Indian settlers
                    there before the middle of the 1st century, by whom the present name, probably
                    cognate with the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">balin,</hi> strong, was in all
                    likelihood imposed. It was not till 1633 that the Dutch attempted to enter into
                    alliance with the native princes, and their earliest permanent settlement at
                    Port Badong only dates from 1845. Their influence was extended by the results of
                    the war which they waged with the natives about 1847-9. A geological survey of
                    the whole island is at present (1874-5) in progress under their auspices. The
                    Balinese language belongs to the same group of the Malayan class as the
                    Javanese, Sundanese, Madurese, &lt;fcc., but is as distinct from each of these
                    as French is from Italian. It is most nearly akin to the Sasak language spoken
                    in Lombok and on the east coast of Bali. The literary language has embodied many
                    of its ingredients from the Old Javanese, as spoken in Java at the time of the
                    fall of Majapahit (15th century), while the vulgar dialect has kept free from
                    such admixture. Javanese influence is also traceable in the use of three
                    varieties of speech, as in the Javanese language, according to the rank of the
                    people addressed. The alphabet is with some modifications the same as the
                    Javanese, but more complicated. The material universally used for writing on is
                    the prepared leaf of the lontar palm. The sacred literature of the Balinese is
                    written in the ancient Javanese or <hi rend="italic">Kawi</hi> language, which
                    appears to be better understood here than it is in Java. (See R. van Eck, <hi
                    rend="italic">Beknopte handleiding bij debeoefening van het Balineesche
                    taal,</hi> Utrecht, 1874.) In the years 1871 and 1872, 15,000 people died of
                    small-pox in the island; since then vaccination has been introduced by the
                    Dutch. In September 1874 several districts were fearfully ravaged by cholera; in
                    Sampidi alone out of its 3000 inhabitants 700 fell victims to the scourge; the
                    rest fled into the woods.</p>
                <p>Crawfurd’s <hi rend="italic">Descriptive Dictionary of the Indian Islands,</hi>
                    1856; P. J. Veth, <hi rend="italic">IVoordcnboek van Nedcrlandsch Indie,</hi>
                    1869; <hi rend="italic">Tijdschrift voor Nederlandsch Indie</hi> for 1874, vol.
                    ii. p. 439, <hi rend="italic">Jf.;</hi> Lassen’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Indische</hi><hi rend="italic">Alterthumskunde,</hi> iii. iv., <hi
                    rend="italic">passim;</hi> Friedrich’s “Verslag van Bali” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Trans, of Batavian Soc. of Arts and</hi><hi rend="italic">Sei.,</hi> xxiii.,
                    and a paper in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Ind. Arch.,</hi> 1849; Μ. de
                    Carnhée’s “Essai sur Bali” in <hi rend="italic">Le Moniteur</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Indes</hi><hi rend="italic">Orient.,</hi> 1846- 47; Dubois’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Vies</hi><hi rend="italic">des Gouverneurs-généraux</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> Backer’s <hi rend="italic">L’</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Archipel Indien,</hi> 1874; <hi rend="italic">Jaarboek van het Mijnwezenin N.
                    Ost.-Indie,</hi> 1874.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
