<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0440-0425-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BASTAR (9th edition, volume 3, page 425)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h12v74r">Arrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p91c">Wheat</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n440/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BASTAR</label>, a feudatory state in the Central Provinces of
                    British India, situated between 20° 10' and 17° 40' of N. lat., and 80° 30' and
                    82° 15' of E. long., bounded on the N. by the Kanker zamindâri and the Râipur
                    district; on the E. by the Bend ré Nawâgarh zamïndâri and Râipur, Jaipur state,
                    and Sabari River; on the S. by the Sironchâ district; and on the ^∖V. by the
                    Indravatf River and the Aheri zamindâri. Extreme length of the state, 170 miles;
                    extreme breadth, 120 miles; area, estimated at 13,000 square miles. Total
                    population, 78,856, consisting of— Hindus, 29,060; Musalmâns, 1704; aboriginal
                    tribes of Gond origin, 48,092. Among the latter, the Mariés are a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n441/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0441-0426"/> timid, quiet, docile race, and although addicted
                    to drinking are not quarrelsome. They inhabit the densest jungles, and are very
                    shy, avoiding contact with strangers, and flying to the hills on the least
                    alarm; but they bear a good character for honesty and truthfulness. They are
                    very scantily dressed, wear a variety of trinkets, with a knife, hatchet, spear,
                    bow and arrow, the only weapons they use. Their hair is generally shaved,
                    excepting a topknot; and tvhen not shaved it gets into a matted, tangled mass,
                    gathered into a knot behind or on the crown. The Mhris, a class of the Markts,
                    live in still denser jungles, and have little or no communication with the
                    outside world. The Mâriâs and the Jhuriâs are supposed to be a subdivision of
                    the true Gond family. All the aboriginal tribes of Bastâr worship the deities of
                    the Hindu pantheon along with their own national goddess Danteswari.</p>
                <p>The eastern part of Bastir is a flat elevated plateau, from 1600 to 2000 feet
                    above the level of the sea, the centre and north-west portions are very
                    mountainous, and the southern parts are a mixture of hill and plain. On the
                    plateau there are but few hills; the streams run slowly, and the country is a
                    mixture of plain and undulating ground covered by dense <hi rend="italic"
                    >sàl</hi> forests. Principal mountains of the district—(1), A lofty range which
                    separates it from the Sironcha district; (2), a range of equal height called the
                    Bela Dili lying in the centre of the district; (3), a range running north and
                    south near Niriyanpur; (4), Tdngri Dongri range, running east and west; (5),
                    Tulsi Dongri, bordering on the Sabari River and the Jaipur state. There is also
                    a small range running from the River Indravati to the Godavari. The Indravati,
                    the Sabari, and the Til or Tilper, are the chief rivers of the district; all of
                    them affluents of the Godavari The soil throughout the greater portion of Bastir
                    consists of light clay, with an admixture of sand, suited for raising rice and
                    wet crops. Rice, sugar, and a little wheat and gram are the agricultural
                    products of Bastir. In the jungles the Marias and Maris rear kosri <hi
                    rend="italic">(Panicum</hi><hi rend="italic">italicum)</hi> and other inferior
                    grains. The aboriginal races generally follow the migratory system of tillage,
                    clearing the jungle on selected patches, and after taking crops for two or three
                    years abandoning them for new ground. Min's do not use the plough; nor do they
                    possess buffaloes, bullocks, or cows; their only agricultural implement is a
                    long-handled iron hoe. Lac, resin, wax, galls, horns, rice, a red dye called <hi
                    rend="italic">scndrt,</hi> wild arrow-root, molasses, teakwood, and tasar-silk
                    cocoons, are the chief staples of export. 'The imports, -which considerably
                    exceed tho exports, consist of salt, piece-goods, brass utensils, cocoa-nuts,
                    pepper, spices, opium, tuπneric, cotton, wheat, &amp;c. Iron-ore is found
                    towards the eastern portion of the state, but is not much worked; gold is also
                    found in certain places. Bastir is divided into two portions—that held by the
                    Raja or chief himself, and that possessed by feudatory chiefs under him. There
                    is not a single made road within the principality. The climate of Bastar is
                    unhealthy— fever, smallpox, dysentery, diarrhoea, and rheumatism being the
                    prevailing diseases. Jagdalpur, Bijipur, Madder, and Bhupàlpatnam are the only
                    places of any note in the dependency, the first-named being the residence of the
                    Raja and the chief people of the state. The grossest ignorance and superstition
                    prevail, and the people live in constant fear of being bewitched or ruined by
                    malicious magicians. The family of the Raja of Bastar claims to be of the purest
                    Rajput blood, and traces its origin to Warangal in the Dakhin, about the
                    commencement of the 14th century. The revenue of Bastar is supposed to be £3610;
                    the tribute paid by the chief to the British Government is £305, 12s.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
