<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0627-0610-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERWICK-UPON-TWEED (9th edition, volume 3, page
                    610)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159786">Tweed</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n627/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BERWICK-UPON-TWEED</label>, a seaport town and municipal and
                    parliamentary borough, at the mouth of the Tweed, in <hi rend="italic">55°
                    46'</hi> N. lat. and l <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 59' W. long., 300 miles N.
                    by W. from London, and 47 E.S.E. from Edinburgh. Berwick proper is built chiefly
                    on the declivity and flat summit of an elevation rising abruptly from the north
                    side of the river. The liberties of the borough, commonly called “Berwick
                    Bounds,” containing an area of nearly eight square miles, extend to the N. and
                    W., and form the N.E. extremity of England. The borough also includes (since
                    1835) the townships of Tweedmouth and Spittal on the south side of the
                    river,—the latter a fishing and watering place on the coast, the former a
                    manufacturing village connected with Berwick by a bridge. The town has a
                    pleasing appearance from the neighbouring heights, especially at full tide,—sea
                    and river, ramparts, bridges and pier, buildings ancient and modern, and the
                    red-tiled roofs of the houses contributing to the view. The principal streets
                    are wide, well built, and well paved, there being a remarkable absence, in so
                    ancient a town, of narrow streets and old houses.</p>
                <p>Berwick is one of the few remaining walled towns in the United Kingdom. The
                    present ramparts were built in the reign of Elizabeth. To the north and east
                    they are formed of earth faced with stone; bastions with cavaliers are <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n628/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0628-0611"/> placed at intervals, and a ditch, now dry,
                    extends to the river. Fronting the river are four-gun and six-gun batteries
                    defending the entrance to the harbour, and a twenty-two-gun battery commanding
                    the south side. These ramparts which are perforated by five gateways, are
                    generally in good repair, but since 1822 have been destitute of guns save for
                    volunteer practice. The circuit is about 1 mile 3 furlongs; that of the older
                    walls was more than 2 miles. The ruins of the latter, built by Edward I., and
                    also surrounded by a ditch, enclose the suburbs of Castlegate, and the
                    Greens,—the fishermen’s quarter. The Bell Tower, from which alarms were given,
                    and which is least dilapidated, has been recently secured from further decay.
                    Between the extremity of these old walls and the Tweed are the remains of the
                    old castle, which was allowed to become a ruin after the union of the crowns.
                    There are no traces of the churches, monasteries, or other ancient buildings of
                    the town. The barracks, built in 1719, accommodate nearly 600 men; but they are
                    now occupied only by militia, and the governor’s house has become a private
                    dwelling.</p>
                <p>The chief public buildings are the town-hall, finished in</p>
                <p>1760, a stately building, surmounted by a spire 150 feet high, which contains a
                    peal of eight bells; the new jail, erected in 1849; the corn exchange, which is
                    the principal public hall, opened in 1858; a new infirmary; two assembly rooms;
                    Masonic and Good Templar halls. The parish church is a plain Gothic building,
                    without steeple, of the time of Cromwell. It was thoroughly and tastefully
                    renovated in 1855. The patronage belongs to the dean and chapter of Durham. A
                    week-day lectureship is in the patronage of the Mercers’ Company, London. There
                    are also in the borough, including Tweedmouth and Spittal, three other churches
                    connected with the Church of England, three with the Church of Scotland, four
                    United Presbyterian, two English Presbyterian, two Methodist, one Baptist, and
                    one Boman Catholic. The only church building worthy of notice is Wallace Green
                    United Presbyterian Church, opened in 1859. New cemeteries were opened at
                    Berwick in 1855, and at Tweedmouth in 1858. The town is well supplied with
                    educational institutions; and a local museum was established in 1867, where
                    lectures are delivered during the winter. The town and suburbs have four public
                    reading-rooms, and three newspapers are published. Two bridges connect the town
                    with the south side of the Tweed. The older, which is very substantial, was
                    finished in 1634, having taken twenty-four years in building. It has fifteen
                    arches, and is 924 feet long, but only 17 feet wide. The other, situated a
                    quarter of a mile up the river, is a magnificent railway viaduct, 126 feet high,
                    with twenty-eight arches, which extends from the railway station—a castellated
                    building on part of the site of the old castle—to a considerable distance beyond
                    the river. This bridge was opened by Queen Victoria in 1850.</p>
                <p>The Tweed is navigable as far as the old bridge, and the tide flows seven miles
                    further. The entrance to the harbour has been improved and protected by a stone
                    pier, built about sixty yeare ago, which stretches half a mile S.E. from the
                    north bank of the river’s mouth, and has at the extremity a lighthouse with two
                    fixed lights. The depth of water at the bar is 17 feet at ordinary tides, 22
                    feet at spring tides, but the channel is narrow, a large rocky portion of the
                    harbour on the north side being dry at low water. A long-felt want is now being
                    supplied by the construction of a dock, which was begun at Tweedmouth, September
                    1873. The number of vessels belonging to the port (1875) is 25 (tonnage, 1459).
                    There entered in 1873, 422 (tonnage, 35,049), and there cleared 424 (tonnage,
                    35,252). The principal exports are grain, meal, herrings, burnt ore, metal
                    castings, manures; the imports are bones and bone-ash, manure stuffs, linseed,
                    salt, timber, pig-iron. The sea-fisheries employ 230 boats in white fishing, 294
                    in herring fishing, and 52 in both. Berwick, which has long been famous for its
                    salmon fisheries, is the headquarters of the Fishing Company, which occupies
                    most of the stations on the neighbouring coast and for some miles up the river.
                    The fish are mostly sent to the London market. There is an annual fair held here
                    in the end of May, and the weekly market on Saturday. There are four banking
                    establishments; and, on the whole, the trade of the town is increasing. &gt;</p>
                <p>The ancient charter of the borough of Berwick was confirmed by various sovereigns
                    from Edward I. to James I., who added new officers and privileges, but
                    especially gifted to the burgesses all the lands within the liberties which were
                    not private property. These lands, amounting to 3077 acres, or two-thirds of the
                    whole, are partly divided into farms, partly into meadows occupied or let by the
                    resident freemen and freemen’s widows. The annual value of a meadow, seniority
                    determining the allocation, ranges at present from £11, 5s. to £2, 9s. 3d. The
                    roll of freemen contains about 1000, of whom 368 are <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n629/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0629-0612"/> resident. The total rental of the corporation’s
                    property is now about £10,800. Since the Municipal Reform Act, 1835, the borough
                    has been governed by six aidermen and eighteen councillors; and in 1842 “the
                    power of life and death” wrs removed from the Quarter Sessions to the Newcastle
                    Assizes. The custom of specially mentioning Berwick-on-Tweed after Wales, though
                    abandoned in Acts of Parliament, is still retained in certain proclamations. The
                    title of “county in itself” also helps to recall its ancient history. It is the
                    seat of a Poor Law Union, and the rateable value of the borough (1875) is
                    £53,195. Berwick has sent two members to the English parliament since the reign
                    of Mary. The registered electors number 1285, of whom 368 may vote as freemen,
                    about 200 being doubly qualified. Population in 1871, 8731, or, including the
                    conjoined townships (Tweedmouth, 2809, and Spittal, 1742), 13,282.</p>
                <p>Of the origin or early history of Berwick nothing is known. It probably sprung
                    into importance during the long struggle between the Scots and Saxons for the
                    possession of Lothian and the Merse. Egfrid, king of Northumbria, seeking to
                    extend his boundary beyond the Forth, was routed at Dunnichen, 685, and driven
                    back to the Tweed. But it was not until the battle of Carham, 1018, that the
                    latter river was finally secured as the boundary, and Berwick obtained the
                    frontier position to which it owes its fame. It seems rapidly to have grown in
                    size, wealth, and influence. Its name occurs as a royal burgh in the reign of
                    Alexander I., along with Edinburgh, Roxburgh, and Stirling, and with them, from
                    David I., it elected the tribunal which from their number was called the “Court
                    of the Four Burghs.” The castle of Berwick was one of the strongholds given up
                    to Henry II. of England to be security for the homage due by William the Lion as
                    the price of his liberty, but it was restored with the others by Richard
                    Coeur-de-Lion in 1189. At Berwick took place several of the conferences held
                    between Edward I. and the competitors for the Scottish crown, and his decision
                    in favour of Baliol was given in the castle, Nov. 1292. Four years later Edward
                    marched north to punish his rebellious vassal, and began his invasion by an
                    attack upon the town which was at once the key of the kingdom and its commercial
                    capital. The English king, familiar with the place, and infuriated by the
                    repulse of his fleet in the river, led the land attack in person. Being very
                    slightly fortified the town was speedily stormed, and no mercy was shown to the
                    inhabitants. One memorable incident is recounted. A company of trading Flemings
                    held out against the besiegers in their fortified building, the Red Hall,
                    until.it was set on fire. They were bound by their charter to defend it to the
                    last extremity against the English, and they perished in the flames. Berwick
                    never recovered commercially from the massacre and pillage of this terrible Good
                    Friday. Its efforts again to rise were hindered by the ever-renewed Border
                    warfare, and it gradually sunk to the rank of an ordinary market town.</p>
                <p>On Edward’s return from his victorious march through Scotland, he determined to
                    make the town impregnable with stone walls, but before his commands could be
                    accomplished it was recaptured by the Scots as a consequence of the English
                    defeat at Stirling Bridge. On Edward’s approach the following year, however, the
                    Scots retired, and during the remainder of his reign it continued in the hands
                    of the English. Here, in 1305, one quarter of Wallace’s body was exposed, and
                    shortly afterwards the countess of Buchan was suspended in a cage from one of
                    the castle towers, as a punishment for courageously performing the privilege of
                    her family by placing the crown on King Robert Bruce at Scone. Edward II. '»pent
                    the winter of 1310 at Berwick after an ineffectual invasion of Scotland. Here,
                    too, on June 11, 1314, the great English army assembled which was defeated a
                    fortnight later at Bannockburn. Jn 1318 the town, now well fortified, was
                    captured by Bruce, through the help of one of the garrison; a siege by Edward,
                    which followed, rendered famous by the engines employed both in the river and
                    land attacks, was not successful. It remained in the hands of the Scots till
                    1333, when it was besieged by Edward III., and the hope of relief by the
                    Scottish army being disappointed by their defeat at Halidon Hill, about 2 miles
                    from Berwick, the town and castle were immediately, according to agreement,
                    delivered up to the English king. The next 130 years saw Berwick occasionally
                    attacked by the Scots, and sometimes with success, but they held it only for
                    short periods until 1461, when Henry VI., in gratitude for refuge after the
                    battle of Towton, made it over to them. In 1482, during the disputes between
                    James III. and his nobles, it surrendered to the English army, and was never
                    retaken by the Scots. Henceforward it occupied in Scotland, in relation to
                    England, the position for long of Calais in France—an important stronghold, the
                    sole remnant of wide-spread conquest. This position explains the possession by
                    Berwick, until the union of the crowns, of a civil and military establishment
                    (with lord-chancellor, lordchamberlain, Domesday Book, governors of town and
                    castle, &amp;e.) resembling that of a small kingdom. It was that appointed by
                    Edward I. for all Scotland, and was ready to expand, as it had been compelled to
                    contract its sphere, should more territory be again acquired north of the
                    Tweed.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
