<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0629-0612-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERWICKSHIRE (9th edition, volume 3, page 612)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159786">Tweed</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n629/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BERWICKSHIRE</label>, a maritime county of Scotland, forming
                    its S.E. extremity, bounded N.E. by the German Ocean, N. by Haddington, W. by
                    Midlothian, S.W. by Roxburgh, S. by the Tweed, which separates it from
                    Northumberland, and S.E. by the liberties of the town of Berwick. Its greatest
                    length from E. to W. is 311 miles; its greatest breadth 19|; area about 464
                    square miles, or 297,161 acres. It is naturally divided into three districts,
                    <hi rend="italic">Lauderdale,</hi> or the valley of the Leader, in the W.; <hi
                    rend="italic">Laτnmermuir,</hi> the upland district occupied by the hills of
                    that name, in the N.; and the <hi rend="italic">Merse</hi> (probably a
                    corruption of “March” or borderland), the largest district, occupying the S.E.
                    of the county. The Lammermuirs are a range of round backed hills, whose average
                    height is about 1000 feet, while the highest summit, Sayrs Law, reaches 1753
                    feet. From these hills the Merse stretches to the S. and E., and is a
                    comparatively level tract of country, traversed, however, from N.W. to S.E. by
                    distinct parallel ridges. The coast line is lofty, rocky, and precipitous,
                    broken by ravines, and not accessible, except at Eyemouth harbour, for small
                    vessels, and at one or two other places for fishing-boats. St Abb’s Head, a
                    peninsular promontory with a lighthouse upon it, rises to nearly 300 feet. The
                    Eye is the only river of the county which falls into the sea. The others—the
                    Leader, the Eden, the Leet, and the Whiteadder with its tributaries, the
                    Blackadder and the Dye—all flow into the Tweed. Of these the largest and most
                    important is the Whiteadder, which has its source on the East-Lothian side of
                    the Lammermuirs, and, following a sinuous course of 35 miles, falls into the
                    Tweed within the “Bounds” of Berwick. The climate of Berwickshire is chiefly
                    influenced by its maritime position. The winter is seldom severe in the lowland
                    districts; but spring is generally a trying season on account of the east winds,
                    which often continue into summer. Drainage has remedied the former excessive
                    humidity, and the climate is now excellent, in relation both to the health of
                    the inhabitants and to the growth of vegetation.</p>
                <p>Berwickshire, geologically, consists of Silurian rocks in the hilly region,
                    Devonian or Old Red Sandstone in the southwest, and carboniferous limestone in
                    the Merse. Large masses of porphyritic and trap rock occasionally occur, of
                    which St Abb’s Head is an example. The sea-cliff to the north-west of the mouth
                    of the Eye is formed of conglomerate or pudding-stone. There is an interesting
                    and somewhat famous geological appearance at a point called Siccar, near
                    Cockburnspath, where the sea has laid open very plainly the junction of the
                    primary and secondary strata.</p>
                <p>The soils of Berwickshire are extremely various. On the same farm a great
                    diversity may be found. Along the rivers is a deep rich loam, resting on gravel
                    or clay, chiefly the former. The less valuable clay soil of the Merse has been
                    much improved by the effective system of drainage which is everywhere carried
                    out. The more sandy and gravelly soils are suitable for the turnip crops, which
                    are a marked agricultural feature of the county. To these soils the landlords
                    and tenants of Berwickshire have applied themselves with such intelligence,
                    mutual good-will, liberality, and spirit, that the county now stands in the
                    first rank in regard to agriculture. The farms are large, and are commonly held
                    by a nineteen years’lease. Nowhere is farming conducted more scientifically or
                    with better success. According to the agricultural returns for 1874, the total
                    acreage under all kinds of crops, bare fallow, and grass, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n630/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0630-0613"/> was 192,138, or more than three-fifths of the
                    entire area. Of this, 63,526 acres were under corn crops, 34,155 under green
                    crops, 56,940 under clover and grasses, and. 36,858 permanent pasture, meadow,
                    or grass not broken up in rotation (exclusive of heath or mountain land). The
                    average extent of land occupied by each occupant was 194 acres. Wheat was grown
                    on 6373 acres; barley or bere, on 21,469; oats, on 33,130; potatoes, on 2593;
                    turnips and swedes, on 30,345. Of live stock there were 5356 horses, 16,979
                    cattle, 285,578 sheep, 4527 pigs. Though about the twentieth in size of the
                    Scottish counties, Berwickshire stands fifth in the number of acres under corn
                    crops, fifth also in green crops, and ninth in the number of sheep. The
                    farm-buildings are convenient and well built. These include cottages for the
                    farm-labourers, or <hi rend="italic">hinds,</hi> and their families,—the
                    ordinary staff consisting of a steward, a shepherd, and a number of ploughmen
                    proportionate to the size of the farm. The farm-labourers, who are physically
                    well developed, are as a whole a frugal, industrious, intelligent race. They are
                    somewhat migratory in their habits, being too ready to move from place to place
                    year after year. This feature in their character, which they may have by
                    inheritance as <hi rend="italic">Borderers,</hi> has admirably fitted them for
                    colonial life, to which the lack of employment in mining or manufactures in the
                    county has largely drawn the surplus population.</p>
                <p>The minerals of Berwickshire are insignificant. Coal, copper ore, and ironstone
                    exist in such small quantities that attempts to work them have been abandoned;
                    and the limestone is at too great a distance from a coal district to warrant
                    competition with the adj oining counties. The Tweed salmon fisheries are
                    productive of an important trade, and are so subject to vicissitudes that much
                    attention has been paid to them by means of legislative enactments. The lesser
                    rivers of the Merse are held in high esteem by anglers. Besides Eyemouth there
                    are three villages—Burnmouth, Coldingham Shore, and Cove—engaged in the
                    sea-fisheries, which are of considerable and increasing value. Cod, haddock,
                    herring, ling, lobsters, and crabs are the principal produce. Berwickshire
                    cannot boast of many manufactures. Earlstoun sends out ginghams and woollen
                    cloths. At Cumledge, also, on the Whiteadder, there is a factory for heavy
                    woollen cloths; and four miles further down the river, at Chirnside Bridge, is
                    one of the largest paper mills in Scotland. The other manufactures are all
                    connected with agriculture, such as distilleries, breweries, tanneries, &amp;c.
                    The trade is also mainly agricultural. Fairs are held at Dunse, Lauder,
                    Coldstream, Greenlaw, and Oldhamstocks; but the sales of cattle and sheep are
                    now mostly accomplished at the weekly or fortnightly auction marts at Reston,
                    Dunse, and Earlstoun. The grain markets are held at Dunse and Earlstoun.
                    Berwick, from which the county derives its name, is still its chief market-town.
                    There is, however, no legal or fiscal connection between the county and the
                    borough.</p>
                <p>The early history of Berwickshire is to a great extent bound up with that of the
                    ancient frontier town; from its position it also suffered much during the Border
                    wars. The most noteworthy antiquities are Coldingham Priory in the E. and
                    Dryburgh Abbey in the S. W. They were burnt in the same year, 1545, during the
                    barbarous inroad of the English army under the earl of Hereford. About four
                    miles N. from Coldingham are the ruins of Fast Castle (“The Wolfs Crag” of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Bride of Lammermoor),</hi> situated on a peninsular cliff, 120
                    feet by 60, and 70 feet above the sea. A little further north is the Pease or
                    Peaths Bridge, built by Telford, in 1786, over the deep glen which forms the
                    celebrated pass—of old one of the strongest natural defences of Scotland. Near
                    it is Cockburnspath Tower, once a strong fortress, now in ruins. In the west of
                    Berwickshire, besides Dryburgh, there are, at Earlstoun, the remains of the
                    ancient tower “The Rhymer’s Castle,” the traditional residence of Thomas
                    Learmont, commonly called Thomas of Ercildoune or Thomas the Rhymer. About a
                    mile from Earlstoun is Cowdenknowes, on a hill above which grew the “bonnie
                    broom” of the old song. None of it now remains, it having been gradually
                    encroached upon by the plough, and the last of it killed by the severe frost of
                    1861-62. Hume Castle, the ancient seat of the Home family, also towards the
                    west, has a most commanding view, and is itself visible from nearly every part
                    of the county. Traces of Roman occupation and of ancient British settlements
                    exist in various parts of the Merse. Edin’s or Etin’s Hall, on Cockbum Law,
                    about four miles north of Dunse, still goes under the name of the Peek’s or
                    Pict’s House. There are many large mansions throughout the county, the principal
                    being Thirlestane Castle (earl of Lauderdale), Mertoun House (Lord Polwarth),
                    Mellerstain and Lennel House (earl of Haddington), Nesbit (Lord Sinclair), Dunse
                    Castle (Hay), Wedderburn and Paxton (Milne Home), Lees (Sir John Marjoribanks),
                    Ladykirk (Baroness Marjoribanks), Ayton Castle (Mitchell Innes), Hirsel (earl of
                    Home). The chief towns are Greenlaw, the county town, with a population of 823;
                    Dunse, 2618; Lauder, 1046, a royal burgh, which unites with the Haddington group
                    of burghs in returning a member to parliament; Coldstream, 1724; and Eyemouth,
                    2324, the only seaport of the county. There is one sheriff for the three border
                    counties of Berwick, Roxburgh, and Selkirk, and a sheriff-substitute holds his
                    court in Dunse. Justice of the Peace courts are held at Coldstream and at Ayton,
                    and a burgh court at Lauder. The county is divided into thirty-one parishes, and
                    it returns one member to parliament. Population of Berwickshire, 36,486—males,
                    17,414; females, 19,072.</p>
                <p>The fauna and flora of Berwickshire have been carefully described by the late Dr
                    George Johnston, and further information may be obtained regarding these from
                    the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Berwickshire Naturalists’
                    Club.</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
