<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0569-0546-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STEWART, Dugald</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 546</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n569/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STEWART, <hi rend="smallcaps">Dugald</hi></label>
                    (1753-1828), one of the most influential of the Scottish philosophers, was born
                    at Edinburgh on the 22d of November 1753. His father, Matthew Stewart (1715-85),
                    was professor of mathematics in the university of Edinburgh from 1747 till 1772,
                    and was an eminent investigator in his own department, applying the geometrical
                    methods of Simson, who had been his teacher in Glasgow. Dugald Stewart’s early
                    years were passed partly in Edinburgh and partly at Catrine in Ayrshire, where
                    his father had a small property, to which the family removed every summer on the
                    close of the academical session. Burns was an occasional visitor at Catrine,
                    which is only a few miles from Mossgiel; and the philosopher and the poet had
                    various meetings as well as some slight correspondence in later years. Dugald
                    Stewart was educated at the high school and university of his native town. At
                    school he laid the foundation of the classical knowledge and literary taste
                    which are conspicuous in his works, and which lent a charm to his prelections.
                    At the university his chief subjects were the mathematical sciences—in which he
                    attained great proficiency—and philosophy. Adam Ferguson, the historian of the
                    Roman republic, was then professor of moral philosophy in Edinburgh, and his
                    bracing ideal of ethical and political virtue commended itself highly to
                    Stewart. In 1771, having thoughts of entering the English Church, Stewart
                    proceeded to Glasgow with a view to the Snell exhibitions tenable by Glasgow
                    students at Oxford. Here he listened to the lectures of Reid, whose <hi
                    rend="italic">Inguiry,</hi> published seven years before, had laid the effective
                    foundation of what is called distinctively the Scottish philosophy. Reid became
                    Stewart’s acknowledged master and also his friend, while Stewart’s academic
                    eloquence and powers of elegant exposition gained for their common doctrines a
                    much wider acceptance than they could have secured in the clumsier and less
                    attractive presentation of Reid himself. In Glasgow Stewart boarded in the same
                    house with Archibald Alison, afterwards author of the <hi rend="italic">Essay on
                    Taste,</hi> and a close friendship sprang up between them, which remained
                    unbroken through life. After no more than a single session in Glasgow, Dugald
                    Stewart was summoned by his father, whose health was beginning to fail, to
                    conduct the mathematical classes in the university of Edinburgh. Though only
                    nineteen years of age he discharged his duties with marked ability and success;
                    and after acting three years as his father’s substitute he was elected professor
                    of mathematics in conjunction with him in 1775. Three years later Adam Ferguson
                    was appointed secretary to the commissioners sent out to the American colonies,
                    and at his urgent request<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0570-0547"/> Stewart lectured as his substitute. Thus during
                    the session 1778-79, in addition to his mathematical work, he delivered an
                    original course of lectures on morals. “To this season,” says his son, “he
                    always referred as the most laborious of his life; and such was the exhaustion
                    of the body from the intense and continued stretch of the mind that on his
                    departure for London at the close of the academical session it was necessary to
                    lift him into the carriage.” In 1783 Stewart married Helen Bannatyne, who died
                    in 1787, leaving an only son, Colonel Matthew Stewart, from whose short memoir
                    of his father the above is a quotation.</p>
                <p>In 1785, on the resignation of Ferguson, he was transferred to the chair of moral
                    philosophy, which he filled for a quarter of a century and made a notable centre
                    of intellectual and moral influence. Young men of rank and of parts were
                    attracted by his reputation from England, and even from the Continent and
                    America. A very large number of men who afterwards rose to eminence in
                    literature or in the service of the state were thus among his students. Sir
                    Walter Scott, Jeffrey, Cockburn, Francis Horner, Sydney Smith, Lord Brougham, Dr
                    Thomas Brown, James Mill, Sir James Mackintosh, and Sir Archibald Alison may be
                    mentioned among others. There is a unanimous testimony to the attractive
                    eloquence of Stewart’s lectures and the moral elevation of his teaching. “Dugald
                    Stewart,” says Lord Cockburn, “was one of the greatest of didactic orators. Had
                    he lived in ancient times, his memory would have descended to us as that of one
                    of the finest of the old eloquent sages. No intelligent pupil of his ever ceased
                    to respect philosophy, or was ever false to his principles, without feeling the
                    crime aggravated by the recollection of the morality that Stewart had taught
                    him.” Dr John Thomson, afterwards medical professor in Edinburgh, was accustomed
                    to say that the two things by which he had been most impressed in the course of
                    his life were the acting of Mrs Siddons and the oratory of Dugald Stewart. Lord
                    Cockburn, in his <hi rend="italic">Memorials,</hi> has left an interesting
                    portraiture of Stewart’s appearance and manner :—“Stewart was about the middle
                    size, weakly-limbed, and with an appearance of feebleness which gave an air of
                    delicacy to his gait and structure. His forehead was large and bald, his
                    eyebrows bushy, his eyes grey and intelligent, and capable of conveying any
                    emotion from indignation to pity, from serene sense to hearty humour, in which
                    they were powerfully aided by his lips, which, though rather large perhaps, were
                    flexible and expressive. The voice was singularly pleasing; and, as he managed
                    it, a slight burr only made its tones softer. His ear, both for music and for
                    speech, was exquisite; and he was the finest reader I have ever heard. His
                    gesture was simple and elegant, though not free from a tinge of professional
                    formality; and his whole manner was that of an academical gentleman, .... calm
                    and expository, but rising into greatness or softening into tenderness whenever
                    his subject required it.” The course on moral philosophy embraced, besides
                    ethics proper, lectures on political philosophy or the theory of government, and
                    from 1800 onwards a separate course of lectures was delivered on political
                    economy. These last were extremely important in spreading a knowledge of the
                    fundamental principles of the science at a time when they were still almost
                    unknown to the general public. Stewart’s enlightened political teaching was
                    sufficient, in the times of reaction succeeding the French Revolution, to draw
                    upon him the undeserved suspicion of disaffection to the constitution.</p>
                <p>In 1790 Stewart married a second time. Miss Cranstoun, who became his wife, was a
                    lady of birth and accomplishments, and he was in the habit of submitting to her
                    criticism whatever he wrote. A son and a daughter were the issue of this
                    marriage. The death of the former in 1809 was a severe blow to the failing
                    health of his father, and was the immediate cause of his retirement from the
                    active duties of his chair. Before that, however, Stewart had not been idle as
                    an author. In 1792 he published the first volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elements of the Philosophy of the Human Mind</hi>; the second volume appeared
                    in 1814, and the third not till 1827. In 1793 he printed a text-book, <hi
                    rend="italic">Outlines of Moral Philosophy,</hi> which went through many
                    editions; and in the same year he read before the Royal Society of Edinburgh his
                    account of the <hi rend="italic">Life and Writings of Adam Smith.</hi> Similar
                    memoirs of Robertson the historian and of Reid were afterwards read before the
                    same body and appear in his published works. In 1805 Stewart took an active part
                    in what was known as the Leslie case, that is to say, the public controversy
                    arising out of the appointment of Mr (afterwards Sir John) Leslie to the chair
                    of mathematics in the university of Edinburgh. Leslie was attacked by the
                    presbytery of Edinburgh, ostensibly on account of his views on the nature of
                    causal connexion, which were said to approximate to Hume’s. In two pamphlets
                    Stewart defended Leslie’s doctrine as philosophically tenable and theologically
                    innocuous. In 1806 he received in lieu of a pension the nominal office of the
                    writership of the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Gazette,</hi> with a salary of
                    £300. When the shock of his son’s death incapacitated him from lecturing during
                    the session of 1809-10, his place was taken, at his own request, by Dr Thomas
                    Brown, who in 1810 was appointed conjoint professor. On the death of Brown in
                    1820, Stewart, who had taken no further active part in lecturing, retired
                    altogether from the professorship, which was conferred upon John Wilson, better
                    known as “Christopher North.” From 1809 onwards Stewart lived mainly at Kinneil
                    House, Linlithgowshire, which was placed at his disposal by the duke of
                    Hamilton. From this retirement he continued to send forth a succession of works.
                    In 1810 appeared <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Essays,</hi> in 1814 the second
                    volume of the <hi rend="italic">Elements,</hi> in 1815 the first part and in
                    1821 the second part of the “Dissertation” written for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Encyclopaedia Britannica</hi> “Supplement,” entitled “A General View of the
                    Progress of Metaphysical, Ethical, and Political Philosophy since the Revival of
                    Letters.” In 1822 he was struck with paralysis, but recovered a fair degree of
                    health, sufficient to enable him to resume his studies. In 1827 he published the
                    third volume of the <hi rend="italic">Elements,</hi> and in 1828, a few weeks
                    before his death, <hi rend="italic">The Philosophy of the Active and Moral
                    Powers.</hi> He died in Edinburgh after a short illness on the 11th of June
                    1828. A monument to his memory was erected on the Calton Hill by his friends and
                    admirers.</p>
                <p>An edition of his <hi rend="italic">Collected Works,</hi> in eleven volumes
                    (1854-58), was edited by Sir William Hamilton, on whose death in 1856 it was
                    carried to completion and furnished with a memoir of Stewart by Prof. Veitch.
                    Stewart was an elegant writer rather than a profound or original thinker, and he
                    cannot be said to have added much to the philosophy of Reid (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Reid),</hi> though he contributed very largely to its
                    dissemination. His psychological observations, however, are acute and varied,
                    and his general powers of mind contributed largely to elevate the study of
                    philosophy in the United Kingdom. His reputation rests more upon the tradition
                    of his inspiring and elevating eloquence than upon any definite achievements
                    within the province of philosophy proper. (A. SE. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
