<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0847-0812-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SYNEDRIUM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 812</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1104995">Sanhedrin</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SYNEDRIUM</label> (<hi rend="italic">συvέδpιov</hi>), a Greek
                    word which means “assembly” and is especially used of judicial or representative
                    assemblies, is the name by which (or by its Hebrew transcription, םנחדין, <hi
                    rend="italic">sanhedrin, sanhedrim)</hi> that Jewish body is known which in its
                    origin was the municipal council of Jerusalem, but acquired extended functions
                    and no small authority and influence over the Jews at large (see vol. xiii. p.
                    424 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi> In the Mishnah it is called “the sanhedrin,”
                    “the great sanhedrin,” “the sanhedrin of seventy-one [members],” and “the great
                    court of justice” (<hi rend="italic">bêth dîn haggadôl).</hi> The oldest
                    testimony to the existence and constitution of the synedrium of Jerusalem is
                    probably to be found in 2 Chron, xix. 8; for the priests, Levites, and
                    hereditary heads of houses there spoken of as sitting at Jerusalem as a court of
                    appeal from the local judicatories does not correspond with anything mentioned
                    in the old history, and it is the practice of the Chronicler to refer the
                    institutions of his own time to an origin in ancient Israel. And just such an
                    aristocratic council is what seems to be meant by the gerusia or senate of
                    “elders” repeatedly mentioned in the history of the Jews, both under the Greeks
                    from the time of Antiochus the Great (Jos., <hi rend="italic">Ant.,</hi> xii. 3,
                    3) and under the Hasmonean high priests and princes. The high priest as the head
                    of the state was doubtless also the head of the senate, which, according to
                    Eastern usage, exercised both judicial and administrative or political functions
                    (comp. 1 Mac. xii. 6, xiv. 20). The exact measure of its authority must have
                    varied from time to time, at first with the measure of autonomy left to the
                    nation by its foreign lords and afterwards with the more or less autocratic
                    power claimed by the native sovereigns.</p>
                <p>As has been shown in vol. xiii. p. 424 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> the original
                    aristocratic constitution of the senate began to be modified under the later
                    Hasmoneans by the inevitable introduction of representatives of the rising party
                    of the Pharisees, and this new element gained strength under Herod the Great,
                    the bitter enemy of the priestly aristocracy.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The name <hi rend="italic">synedrium</hi>
                    first appears under Hyrcanus II. (Jos., <hi rend="italic">Ant.,</hi> xiv. 9,
                    4).</p></note> Finally under the Roman procurators the synedrium was left under
                    the presidency of the chief priest as the highest native tribunal, though
                    without the power of life and death (John xviii. 31). The aristocratic element
                    now again preponderated, as appears from Josephus and from the New Testament, in
                    which “chief priests” and “rulers” are synonymous expressions. But with these
                    there sat also “scribes” or trained legal doctors of the Pharisees and other
                    notables, who are simply called “elders” (Mark xv. 1). The Jewish tradition
                    which regards the synedrium as entirely composed of rabbins sitting under the
                    presidency and vice-presidency of a pair of chief doctors, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >nasi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ab beth din,</hi><note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The former word properly means the sovereign
                    and the latter the president of the tribunal. The false traditional application
                    is post-Mishnic.</p></note> is quite false as regards the true synedrium. It was
                    after the fall of the state that a merely rabbinical <hi rend="italic">beth
                    din</hi> sat at Jabneh and afterwards at Tiberias, and gave legal responses to
                    those who chose to admit a judicature not recognized by the civil power.
                    Gradually this illegal court usurped such authority that it even ventured to
                    pronounce capital sentences,—acting, however, with so much secrecy as to allow
                    the Roman authorities to close their eyes to its proceedings (Origen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ep. ad Afr.,</hi> § 14). That this was possible will appear less
                    surprising if we remember that in like manner the synedrium of Jerusalem was
                    able to extend an authority not sanctioned by Roman law over Jews beyond Judaea,
                    <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in Damascus (Acts ix. 2; xxii. 5).</p>
                <p>The council-chamber (<hi rend="italic">βουλή)</hi> where the synedrium usually
                    sat was between the Xystus and the temple, probably on the temple-hill, hut
                    hardly, as the Mishnah states, within the inner court. The meeting in the palace
                    of the high priest which condemned our Lord was exceptional. The proceedings
                    also on this occasion were highly irregular, if measured by the rules of
                    procedure which, according to Jewish tradition, were laid down to secure order
                    and a fair trial for the accused.</p>
                <p>Of the older literature of the subject it is enough to cite Selden, <hi
                    rend="italic">De Synedriis.</hi> The most important critical discussion is that
                    of Kuenen in the <hi rend="italic">Verslagen,</hi> &amp;c., of the Amsterdam
                    Academy, 1866, p. 131 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> A good summary is given by
                    Schürer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des jüdischen Volkes,</hi> 2d ed., § 23,
                    iii.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
