<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0391-0368-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPANGENBERG, August Gottlieb (9th edition, volume 22,
                    page 368)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x193">Moravians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026120">Moravians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204607">Suriname</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n391/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPANGENBERG, <hi rend="smallcaps">August
                        Gottlieb</hi></label> (1704-1792), Count Zinzendorf’s successor, and bishop
                    of the Moravian Brethren, was born July 14, 1704, at Klettenberg, on the south
                    of the Harz Mountains, where his father was court-preacher, and ecclesiastical
                    inspector of the grafschaft of Hohenstein. Left an orphan at the early age of
                    ten, he was sent to the excellent high school at Ilefeld, and passed thence
                    (1722), in poorest circumstances, to Jena to study law. Prof. Buddeus received
                    the poor youth into his family, and a “stipendium” was procured for him.
                    Theology rather than law was his natural destination, and it needed only the
                    impulse of the remark of Buddeus that the inevitable prospect before a true
                    theologian is ignominy and trial to convert the student of law, who was
                    profoundly exercised with religious conflicts, into a student of theology.
                    Somewhat after the manner of the Wesleys at Oxford a little later, he studied
                    the mystics, read the Bible, observed rigid devotional exercises, sought to
                    quicken his sense of sin, avoided taking the Lord’s Supper with unbelievers in
                    the Lutheran Church, and took an active part in a religious union of students
                    and in schools for poor children just outside Jena. He took his degree in 1726,
                    and began to give free lectures on theology. In 1727 he made the acquaintance of
                    the Moravian colony at Herrnhut and its head, Count Zinzendorf. A “collegium
                    pastorale practicum” for the care of the sick and poor was in consequence
                    founded by him at Jena, which the authorities at once broke up as a
                    “Zinzendorfian institution.” But Spangenberg’s relations with the Moravians were
                    confirmed by several visits to the colony, and the accident of an unfavourable
                    appeal to the lot alone prevented his appointment as chief elder of the
                    community, March 1733. Meanwhile his free lectures in Jena met with much
                    acceptance, and led to an invitation from Gotthelf Francke to the post of
                    assistant professor of theology and superintendent of the educational depart
                    ment of his orphanage at Halle. He accepted the invitation, and entered on his
                    duties in September 1732. But it soon appeared that the differences between the
                    Pietists of Halle and himself were far too serious to admit of any harmonious
                    co-operation. He found their religious life too formal, legal, external, and
                    worldly; and they could not sanction his comparative indifference to doctrinal
                    correctness and his incurable tendency to separatism in church life.
                    Spangenberg’s participation in private observances of the Lord’s Supper brought
                    matters to a crisis. His intimate connexion with Count Zinzendorf was made a
                    further charge against him. His preaching was pronounced “singular,” and an
                    “affected humility towards common people” obnoxious. He was offered by the
                    senate of the theological faculty of Halle the alternative of doing penance
                    before God, submitting to his superiors, and separating himself from Zinzendorf,
                    or leaving the matter to the decision of the king, unless he preferred to “leave
                    Halle quietly.” The case came before the king, and on April 8, 1733, Spangenberg
                    was conducted by the military outside the gates of Halle. At first he bent his
                    steps to Jena, but Zinzendorf at once sought to secure him as a fellow-labourer,
                    though, with that “jesuitry” of which Wesley subsequently complained, the count
                    wished to obtain from him a declaration which would remove from the Pietists of
                    Halle all blame with regard to the disruption. Spangenberg found amongst the
                    Moravians his life-work. He could amongst them carry out his fundamental
                    principle that the churches are but spheres in <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of
                    which Christians are to be found, and that the one church of Christ is only
                    where believers live in Christian fellowship. He joined the Moravians at a
                    moment when the stability of the society was threatened, and a wise organizer,
                    enterprising missionary, and theological teacher was imperatively required. He
                    became its theologian, its apologist, its statesman and corrector, through sixty
                    long years of incessant labour. For the first thirty years (1733-62) his work
                    was mainly devoted to the superintendence and organization of the extensive
                    missionary enterprises of the body in Germany, England, Denmark, Holland,
                    Surinam, Georgia, and elsewhere. His missionary work tended to still further
                    modify and broaden his theological opinions, unsatisfactory as the Pietists of
                    Halle had found them in 1733. It was on an island off Savannah that Spangenberg
                    startled John Wesley with his questions and profoundly influenced his entire
                    future career. One special endeavour of Spangenberg in Pennsylvania was to bring
                    over the scattered Schwenkfeldians to his faith. In 1741-42 he was in England
                    collecting for his mission and obtaining the sanction of the archbishop of
                    Canterbury. During the second half of this missionary period of his life he
                    superintended as bishop the churches of Pennsylvania, defended the Moravian
                    colonies against the Indians at the time of war between France and England,
                    became the apologist of his body against the attacks of the Lutherans and the
                    Pietists, and did much to moderate the mystical extravagances of Zinzendorf,
                    with which his simple, practical, and healthy nature was out of sympathy. The
                    second thirty years of his work (1762-92) were devoted to the consolidation of
                    the German Moravian Church. Zinzendorf’s death (1760) had left room and need for
                    his labours at home. At Herrnhut there were conflicting tendencies, doctrinal
                    and practical extravagances, and the organization of the brethren was very
                    defective. Spangenberg proved himself to be the man required. In 1777 he was
                    commissioned to draw up an <hi rend="italic">idea fidei fratrum,</hi> or
                    compendium of the Christian faith of the United Brethren, which was published
                    two years afterwards and became the accepted declaration of the Moravian belief.
                    As compared with<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n392/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0392-0369"/> Zinzendorf’s own writings, this book exhibits
                    the finer balance and greater moderation of Spangenberg’s nature, while those
                    offensive descriptions of the relation of the sinner to Christ in which the
                    Moravians at first indulged are almost absent from it. In his last years
                    Spangenberg devoted special attention to the education of the young, in which
                    the Moravians have since been so successful. He died at Berthelsdorf, September
                    18, 1792. In addition to the <hi rend="italic">Idea Fidei Fratrum,</hi>
                    Spangenberg wrote, besides other apologetic books, a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Declaration über die zeither gegen uns ausgegangenen Beschuldigungen</hi>
                    (Leipsic, 1751), an <hi rend="italic">Apologetische Schlussschrift</hi> (1752),
                        <hi rend="italic">Leben des Grafen Zinzendorf</hi> (1772-75); and his hymns
                    are well known beyond the Moravian circle.</p>
                <p>See Risler, <hi rend="italic">Leben Spangenbergs,</hi> Barby, 1794; K. F.
                    Ledderhose, <hi rend="italic">Das Leben Spangenbergs,</hi> Heidelberg, 1846;
                    Frick, <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Lebensgeschichte A. G. Spangenberg's,</hi>
                    Halle, 1884; Herzog-Plitt’s <hi rend="italic">Realencyklopädie,</hi> s.v.
                    “Spangenberg.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
