<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0198-0183-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMOLLETT, Tobias George</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 183</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155558">Travel</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355164">Travels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x51x">Atoms</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n198/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMOLLETT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Tobias George</hi></label>
                    (1721-1771), novelist, was born at Dalquburn, in the valley of Leven,
                    Dumbartonshire, in 1721. His buoyant humour and energy were the gifts of nature,
                    and early experience furnished him with abundant provocation for the harsh and
                    cynical views of human nature to be traced in his novels. At a very early age he
                    was placed in a position calculated to harden the heart of a proud and sensitive
                    child. His father, the youngest son of the laird of Bonhill, a Scottish legal
                    dignitary, married against the ambition of his family, and died young, leaving
                    three children, of whom the future novelist was the second son, entirely
                    unprovided for. The boy, being thus left dependent on the charity of relatives,
                    grudgingly and insolently bestowed, as it seemed to him, learned to look with
                    suspicion on kindly professions. He seems to have received the ordinary book
                    education of the place and period. He was sent to the neighbouring
                    grammar-school of Dumbarton—taught at the time by one of the most eminent
                    schoolmasters in Scotland—and thereafter to the university of Glasgow. He wished
                    then to enter the army, as his elder brother had done, but much against his will
                    was apprenticed to a surgeon. His<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n199/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0199-0184"/> grandfather died when he was in his eighteenth
                    year, without leaving any provision for the children of his youngest son, and in
                    his nineteenth year Smollett left Glasgow and launched himself on London in
                    quest of fortune with the tragedy of the <hi rend="italic">Regicide</hi> in his
                    pocket. He failed to get the tragedy accepted, and, reduced almost to
                    starvation, was fain to take the situation of surgeon’s mate on board a ship of
                    the line. He was present in 1741 at the siege of Cartagena. He soon quitted the
                    navy in disgust, but during his service of a few years he acquired, as Scott
                    says, “such intimate knowledge of our nautical world as enabled him to describe
                    sailors with such truth and spirit of delineation that, from that time, whoever
                    has undertaken the same task has seemed to copy more from Smollett than from
                    nature.”</p>
                <p>Returning to England in 1746, Smollett made a desperate attempt to live by his
                    pen, publishing the satires <hi rend="italic">Advice</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Reproof</hi> —satire being then in fashion—and pushing the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Regicide</hi> and other dramatic works on theatrical managers and patrons. He
                    revenged himself in his satires for the rebuffs given to his plays. Whether he
                    was ever reduced to such straits as Mr Melopoyn, whom Roderick Random met with
                    in the Fleet, is not known for certain, but it is certain that he was sharply
                    pinched; and he did not mend his circumstances by marrying a portionless lady
                    whom he had met in the West Indies. His buoyant spirit was not in the least
                    broken by adverse fortune, but it was considerably inflamed and embittered. His
                    fierce and distempered mood when he wrote <hi rend="italic">Roderick Random</hi>
                    is reflected in the characters of the novel, which are drawn with a much more
                    defiant and contemptuous hand than he used in any of his subsequent works. The
                    author was not a cold-blooded cynic, but a proud warmhearted man enraged by what
                    he considered unjust usage. He was not in a mood to dwell upon lovable traits in
                    human nature, or to find pleasure in pretty sentiments. The public, however,
                    when <hi rend="italic">Roderick Random</hi> was published —in 1748, a few months
                    before <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones—</hi> did not concern themselves with the
                    character of the author. The wealth of humorous incident, the rapidly moving
                    crowd of amusing figures, concealed all those harsher features in the picture of
                    life which quiet reflexion can now trace to the circumstances of the author,
                    smarting as he was under petty insults and real or fancied indignities. This
                    novel at once raised Smollett into reputation. It was followed after an interval
                    of three years by <hi rend="italic">Peregrine Pickle</hi> (1751), the immediate
                    popularity of which was helped by the insertion into the body of the novel of
                    two stories from real life, the memoirs of a lady of quality (Lady Vane) and the
                    memoirs of the philanthropist M'Kercher. This second masterpiece was written
                    with a much lighter heart than the first, although it must be confessed that the
                    hero is not much of an improvement on Roderick Random. Scott describes him as
                    “the savage and ferocious Pickle, who, besides his gross and base brutality
                    towards Emilia, besides his ingratitude to his uncle, and the savage propensity
                    which he shows in the pleasure he takes to torment others by practical jokes,
                    resembling those of a fiend in glee, exhibits a low and ungentlemanlike tone of
                    thinking, only one degree higher than that of Roderick Random.” There is,
                    however, this difference, that the author seems much more conscious of the bad
                    qualities of Pickle than of Random. He expends no sympathy or fine sentiment on
                    either, but Random’s defects are represented as the results of the harsh
                    treatment he had himself received, while Pickle’s appear rather as the outcome
                    of a naturally harsh and insolent character. Both are far from being model
                    gentlemen, but Pickle is several degrees lower rather than one degree higher
                    than Random. In the second novel there is a still richer crowd of characters,
                    quaint, amusing, disgusting, and contemptible; but there is more of a tendency
                    to secure variety by extravagant caricature. For some of the indecencies in the
                    first edition Smollett apologized, and withdrew them in a second edition, but he
                    still left enough to satisfy the greediest taste in that particular. He also
                    withdrew a very offensive allusion to Fielding, and in his next novel, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Adventures of Ferdinand, Count Fathom,</hi> paid that great
                    rival the compliment of imitation. Though Smollett was far from being a servile
                    imitator, there can be no doubt that he profited greatly by Fielding’s example
                    in all the higher essentials of his craft. This, his third effort, although it
                    has not the same exuberant humour and fresh variety of character, is vastly
                    better in point of constructive skill and sustained power of description. It
                    looks as if he had deliberately set himself to show that he too as well as the
                    author of <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones</hi> could make a plot. The vileness of
                    Fathom’s character is so repulsive that the novel is much less often read than
                    others of Smollett’s; but it is his greatest feat of invention, being not a mere
                    string of lively adventures, but a connected series in the progressive movement
                    of the villain’s career. It contains some of Smollett’s most cynical comments on
                    human motives, as well as passages that illustrate strikingly his real goodness
                    of heart. He was not at home, however, in the direct expression of tender
                    sentiment; when any of his persons gush, they do so with such wordiness and
                    extravagance as to give them an air of insincerity.</p>
                <p>With the composition of <hi rend="italic">Count Fathom</hi> in 1753 Smollett’s
                    invention seemed to be exhausted for the time.' For the next ten years he
                    occupied himself with miscellaneous literary work, translating <hi rend="italic"
                    >Don Quixote</hi> (published 1755), compiling a <hi rend="italic">Compendium of
                    Voyages and Travels</hi> (1757), and producing a <hi rend="italic">History of
                    England from the Landing of Caesar to the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle</hi> (1757),
                    followed by a continuation down to the date of publication (1761-65). Smollett,
                    in short, from the time of his first success made his living as a professional
                    man of letters. He obtained a medical degree from a German university about
                    1752, and set up as a physician, but seems never to have acquired much practice.
                    He turned this experience to account, however, by caricaturing in <hi
                    rend="italic">Count Fathom</hi> the arts of rising in the profession. He had
                    very little more success in his attempts to write for the stage. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Regicide</hi> was never acted, and, when it was published in 1749
                    to expose the folly of managers in not accepting it, the verdict of the public
                    was rather with the managers than with the author. Smollett’s single success on
                    the stage was a farce with a political object, <hi rend="italic">The Reprisals,
                    or the Tars of Old England,</hi> produced in 1757 to excite feeling against the
                    French. As a journalist also Smollett was not particularly successful, partly
                    perhaps because he attached himself to the losing side,—the Tory and High Church
                    party. He edited their organ <hi rend="italic">The Critical Review</hi> for some
                    years, and in 1759 suffered imprisonment for an attack on Admiral Knowles. At
                    the beginning of the reign of George III. he supported Lord Bute’s ministry in
                    <hi rend="italic">The Briton,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">The Briton</hi> was
                    driven out of the field by Wilkes’s <hi rend="italic">North Briton.</hi>
                    Altogether Smollett’s revenue from play-writing and journalism seems to have
                    been small, unless his party services were requited independently of the sale of
                    his papers. But his name stood high with booksellers. He introduces himself in
                    <hi rend="italic">Humphrey Clinker</hi> as a dispenser of literary patronage,
                    surrounded by a number of humble dependants. These were probably the hacks to
                    whom he gave employment in his journals and in such booksellers’ jobs as his
                    translation of Voltaire and the compilation entitled <hi rend="italic">The
                    Present State of all Nations, containing a Geographical, Natural, Commercial,
                    and Political History of all the Countries of the Known World</hi> (1763).<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n200/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0200-0185"/> In the course of this hard miscellaneous
                    task-work, under which Smollett’s health gave way completely, he wrote by
                    instalments for the <hi rend="italic">British Magazine</hi> (in 1760 and 1761)
                    the curious satirical romance of <hi rend="italic">Sir Lancelot Greaves.</hi> It
                    is only in externals that this work bears any resemblance to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Don Quixote.</hi> The author seems to have hesitated between making Sir
                    Lancelot a mere madman and making him a pattern of perfectly sane generosity.
                    The fun and the seriousness do not harmonize. The young knight’s craze for
                    riding about the country to redress wrongs armed <hi rend="italic"
                    >cap-a-pie</hi> is too harshly out of tune with the rightness of his sympathies
                    and the grave character of the real abuses against which his indignation is
                    directed. In execution the work is very unequal and irregular, but the opening
                    chapters are very powerful, and have been imitated by hundreds of novelists
                    since Smollett’s time.</p>
                <p>Upon the failure of his health in 1763 Smollett went abroad and lived in France
                    and Italy for three years. He published two volumes of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Travels</hi> soon after his return in 1766. Three years more he spent in
                    England, trying in vain to get some consular post abroad, where the climate
                    might suit his shattered constitution. His extremely clever and extremely coarse
                    political satire, <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of an Atom,</hi> published in
                    1769, was probably inspired partly by resentment at the neglect of his own
                    claims by successive ministries. He left England soon after its publication, and
                    spent the last two years of his life in a house at Monte Novo in the
                    neighbourhood of Leghorn. Here, labouring under a painful and wasting disease,
                    he composed his last work, <hi rend="italic">The Expedition of Humphrey
                    Clinker,</hi> published in 1771. This is generally regarded as his best novel.
                    It certainly is the most pleasant reading, much softer and more humane in tone,
                    while equally alive with vivid sketches and studies of character and a
                    never-failing supply of ludicrous adventures. The loose and easy plan does not
                    require for its execution the sustained power shown in <hi rend="italic">Count
                    Fathom·,</hi> but, on the other hand, it leaves the novelist free to introduce
                    greater variety of character and incident. None of his novels gives a better
                    impression of Smollett’s versatility than <hi rend="italic">Humphrey
                    Clinker,</hi> and there is none of them to which his successors have been more
                    indebted. But whoever would understand how much the English novel owes to
                    Smollett must read all his five fictions and not merely the most celebrated
                    three. His influence upon novel-writing was wider even than Fielding’s. He died
                    at Monte Novo on 21st October 1771. (<hi rend="smallcaps">w.m.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
