<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0142-0127-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SKYE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 127</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1138503">Summer</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:936952">Gabbro</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n142/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SKYE</label>, the largest island of the Inner Hebrides,
                    Scotland, is situated between the mainland of Inverness-shire, within which
                    county it is included, and the group of the Outer Hebrides. It lies between 57°
                    1' 12" and 57° 42' 30" N. lat. and 5° 38' 50" and 6° 47' 8" W. long. It is
                    separated from the mainland at its eastern corner by Loch Alsh and Kyle Rhea,
                    the channel at the narrowest point having a breadth of only about 3 furlongs.
                    Southwards Kyle Rhea widens out into the Sound of Sleat, and to the west of Loch
                    Alsh there is a sudden widening of the gap to the extent of about 9 miles. Along
                    the eastern shore are the islands of Pabba, Scalpa, Raasay, Fladda, and Rona.
                    The Minch separating Lewis and the mainland bounds Skye on the north, and the
                    Little Minch to the northwest separates it from North Uist and Harris. The total
                    area is 411,703 acres or 643 square miles. The coastline is extremely irregular,
                    abounding in inlets of a great variety of form and size, and in the north and
                    west it is wildly precipitous. The island is naturally divided into three parts,
                    each marked off by its distinctive geology and scenery. By much the largest
                    division lies to the north of a line drawn from Loch Brittle to the head of Loch
                    Sligachan. In this area the rocks are almost wholly varieties of basalt,
                    disposed in nearly horizontal sheets, which give a singular tabular shape to the
                    hills and terraced forms to the slopes. To the east of Loch Snizort are the
                    basaltic groups which include the Storr Rock (2360 feet), with its curious
                    columns, and the Quiraing (1774 feet), with its verdant platform in the centre
                    of a range of rugged cliffs. In the north-west are Macleod’s Tables (1601 feet)
                    and some smaller summits. The central division may be defined along its southern
                    border by a line drawn from Loch Slapin to Broadford. Its rocks are almost
                    wholly of volcanic origin, and belong mainly to two groups, each characterized
                    by its peculiar mountain outlines. The dark gabbros and dolerites form the
                    jagged ridges of the Cuillins, and reach in Scuir-na-Gillean a height of 3167
                    feet, and in Blaaven 3042 feet. To the north-east of the Cuillins tower in
                    striking contrast the pyramidal Red Mountains, consisting of granite, syenite,
                    quartz-porphyry, and various allied rocks, and reaching in Glamaig a height of
                    2670 feet. The third division includes all the rest of the island, and consists
                    of two tolerably distinct tracts. The more northerly of these lies along the
                    base of the Red Hills, and forms the narrow part of Skye between Strathaird and
                    Broadford Bay. It is composed mainly of Secondary rocks (Lias and Oolite),
                    through which the eruptive masses of the Red Hills have been thrust. The more
                    southerly part comprises the district of Sleat, and consists of red sandstone
                    (Torridon sandstone or Cambrian), rising in Scuir-na-Coinnich to 2401 feet, and
                    of various crystalline schists and quartzites which stretch from Loch Alsh along
                    the Sound of Sleat to the southern point of the island. A considerable tract of
                    limestone lies in the centre of Strath Parish, some of which has been altered by
                    the eruptive rocks into a pure white marble. There are several inland lochs of
                    considerable size, the largest being Loch Coruisk, remarkable for the gloomy
                    grandeur of its situation in the heart of the Cuillins.</p>
                <p>On account of the damp climate the land is better adapted for rearing sheep and
                    cattle than for tillage. A large number of cattle of the West Highland breed are
                    grazed on the moors. The sheep are principally blackfaced, but some Cheviots are
                    also kept. The greater portion of the inhabitants are crofters, who inhabit
                    chiefly miserable huts with a fireplace in the middle of the floor, the smoke
                    escaping by a hole in the roof. The number of crofts in Skye, according to the
                    report of the Crofters Commission 1884, was 2051. The number of families ejected
                    by decrees from their holdings between 1840 and 1860 was 5012, representing a
                    population of 25,060, and between 1860 and 1883 1948, representing a population
                    of 9740. Many of the crofters support themselves partly by fishing. In the Loch
                    Carron and Skye district the number of boats in 1884 was 950, employing 2904 men
                    and boys. From 20,627 in 1821 the population of Skye had increased to 23,082 in
                    1841, but by 1871 it had decreased to 17,330 and in 1881 to 16,889, of whom
                    16,099 were Gaelic-speaking. The number of females was 8903 and of males 7986.
                    Portree, the principal town, has a population of 893.</p>
                <p>See, besides the works referred to under <hi rend="smallcaps">Hebrides,</hi>
                    Alexander Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Summer in Skye,</hi> 1865; Robert Buchanan's
                    <hi rend="italic">The Hebrid, Isles,</hi> 1883; and <hi rend="italic">Report of
                    the Crofters Commission, 1884.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
