<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0104-0089-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SINCLAIR, Sir John, Bart</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 89</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1065224">Planning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n104/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SINCLAIR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John, Bart</hi></label>.
                    (1754-1835), a voluminous Scottish author, was descended from the Sinclairs of
                    Ulbster, a branch of the noble house of Caithness. He was the eldest son of
                    George Sinclair and Janet, daughter of William, Lord Strathnaver, and was born
                    at Thurso Castle, 10th May 1754. For a short time he had Logan the poet as a
                    private tutor, and, after studying Greek and Latin at the high school of
                    Edinburgh, entered the university in his thirteenth year. He was admitted a
                    member of the faculty of advocates in 1775, and was subsequently called to the
                    English bar (Lincoln’s Inn), but, prefering politics to law, was in 1780 elected
                    member of parliament for his native county. As Caithness was then only
                    alternately represented with Bute, he was in 1784 chosen for Lostwithiel,
                    Cornwall, and in 1796 for Petersfield, Hampshire, his parliamentary career
                    extending almost uninterruptedly over thirty years till July 1811. In 1782 he
                    began the issue of those pamphlets on various subjects connected with the
                    welfare of the nation which made him perhaps the most voluminous author of his
                    time, his separate publications, as given in his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi>
                    amounting in all to three hundred and sixty-seven. His reputation as a financier
                    and political economist was firmly established by his publication in 1784 of the
                    <hi rend="italic">History of the Public Revenue of the British Empire,</hi> to
                    subsequent editions of which was added a <hi rend="italic">Review of the
                    Financial Administration of the Right Hon. William Pitt.</hi> The adoption of
                    his plan for the issue of exchequer bills during the great commercial stagnation
                    of 1793 prevented the ruin of a large number of merchants and manufacturers; and
                    in 1797 Pitt consulted him when the treasury threatened to become exhausted,
                    with the result that the scheme known as the “loyalty loan” was established. On
                    4th February 1786 Sinclair was created a baronet of Great Britain. After
                    succeeding his father in 1770 he had set himself to improve the family estates,
                    thus changing in a great degree the aspect of Caithness and affording employment
                    to a largely increased number of the population. In 1791 he established at
                    Edinburgh a society<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n105/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0105-0090"/> for the improvement of breeds of sheep; and in
                    1793 he circulated a plan for a board of agriculture and internal improvement.
                    When the board was shortly afterwards established by a charter from the orown he
                    was nominated its first president. From the agricultural reports published by
                    this society he compiled his <hi rend="italic">Code of Agriculture,</hi>
                    published in 1819. About 1790 he conceived a plan for a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Statistical Account of Scotland,</hi> and the work was published in twenty-one
                    volumes, 1791-1799.</p>
                <p>Sir John Sinclair was also the author of a number of tracts on naval and military
                    subjects; and in 1794 he raised for the defence of the kingdom a regiment of a
                    thousand men, at first called the “Caithness Fencibles,” afterwards the
                    “Rothesay and Caithness Fencibles”; a second battalion of a thousand men was
                    raised by him in 1795, which took part in suppressing the rebellion in Ireland
                    in 1798. Though originally a supporter in parliament of the war policy of Pitt,
                    he afterwards joined the “armed neutrality” party, which advocated retrenchment
                    and reform. In 1805 he was appointed by Pitt a commissioner for superintending'
                    the construction of roads and bridges in the north of Scotland. He was a member
                    of most of the agricultural societies of the Continent, and held as many as
                    twenty-five foreign diplomas. He was a fellow of the Royal Societies of London
                    and Edinburgh, a fellow of the Antiquarian Society of London, and president of
                    the Highland Society of London. No man of his time took a more comprehensive and
                    enlightened interest in the general welfare of the country or conferred on it
                    more substantial benefits. He enjoyed the esteem and intimate friendship of many
                    eminent contemporaries both at home and abroad, with several of whom he kept up
                    an extensive correspondence. He died 21st December 1835.</p>
                <p>By his first wife, a daughter of Alexander Maitland of Stoke Newington near
                    London, he had two daughters, of whom the elder, Hannah, was the authoress of a
                    work on the <hi rend="italic">Principles of the Christian Faith.</hi> By his
                    second wife, the Hon. Diana Macdonald, only daughter of Alexander, first Lord
                    Macdonald, he had thirteen children, of whom the eldest son, George (1790-1860),
                    who succeeded to the baronetcy, was a schoolfellow of Byron and Peel at Harrow,
                    and is styled by Byron the “prodigy of our school days”; the third son, John
                    (1797-1875), became archdeacon of Middlesex, and, besides the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoirs</hi> of his father, wrote several theological works; and the fourth
                    daughter, Catherine (1800-1864), who for many years acted as his secretary,
                    after his death achieved some distinction as an authoress, her principal works
                    being <hi rend="italic">Modern Accomplishments,</hi> 1836; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Scotland and the Scotch,</hi> 1840; <hi rend="italic">Modern Flirtation,</hi>
                    1841; and <hi rend="italic">Popular Legends and Bible Truths,</hi> 1852.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Correspondence of the Right Hon. Sir John Sinclair, Βart.,
                    with Reminiscences of Distinguished Characters,</hi> 2 vols., London, 1831; and
                    <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life and Works of the Right Hon. Sir John
                    Sinclair,</hi> 2 vols., Edinburgh, 1837.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
