<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0176-0161-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SLOTH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 161</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mp4vr0s">Edentata</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40863522">Americana</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wn8t">Mammals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm4366w">Vertebrae</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv1s">Ribs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1006948">Mammals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1165531">Vertebrae</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:863820">Claws</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1095872">Rest</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807467">Americana</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:946934">Gray</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205585">Panama</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205578">Ecuador</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1228307">Nicaragua</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n176/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SLOTH</label>. The general characters by which the family <hi
                    rend="italic">Bradypodidae</hi> are distinguished from the rest of the order <hi
                    rend="italic">Edentata</hi> have been given in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mammalia</hi> (vol. XV. p. 384). The sloths, as the animals of this family are
                    called on account of the habitual sluggishness of their movements, are the most
                    strictly arboreal of all mammals, living entirely among the branches of trees,
                    usually hanging under them, with their backs downwards, and clinging to them
                    with the simple hook-like organs to which the terminations of all their limbs
                    are reduced. When they are obliged from any cause to descend to the ground,
                    which they rarely, if ever, do voluntarily, their limbs, owing to their unequal
                    length and the peculiar conformation of the feet—which allows the animals to
                    rest only on the outer edge—are most inefficient for terrestrial progression,
                    and the sloths crawl along a level surface with considerable difficulty. Though
                    generally slow and inactive, even when in their natural haunts, they can on
                    occasions travel with considerable rapidity along the branches, and, as they do
                    not leap, like most other arboreal creatures, they avail themselves of the
                    swaying of the boughs by the wind to pass from tree to tree. They feed entirely
                    on leaves and young shoots and fruits, which they gather in their mouth, the
                    fore-limbs aiding in dragging boughs within reach, but not being used as hands,
                    as they are by monkeys, squirrels, &amp;c. When sleeping they roll themselves up
                    in a ball, and, owing to the dry shaggy character of their hair, are very
                    inconspicuous among the mosses and lichens with which the trees of their native
                    forests abound; and the concealment thus afforded is heightened in some species
                    by the peculiar greenish tint of the outer covering,—very uncommon in mammals.
                    This is not due to the colour of the hair itself, but to the presence upon its
                    surface of an alga, the lodgement of which is facilitated by the fluted or rough
                    surface of the exterior of the hair, and the growth of which is promoted by the
                    dampness of the atmosphere in the gloomy tropical forests, as it soon disappears
                    from the hair of animals kept in captivity in England. Sloths are nocturnal,
                    silent, inoffensive, and solitary animals, and produce usually but one young at
                    birth. They appear to show an almost reptilian tenacity of life, surviving the
                    most severe injuries and large doses of poisons, and exhibiting longer
                    persistence of irritability of muscular tissue after death than other
                    mammals.</p>
                <p>The sloths were all included in the Linnean genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bradypus,</hi> but Illiger very properly separated the species with but two
                    claws on the fore-feet, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Choloepus,</hi>
                    leaving <hi rend="italic">Bradypus</hi> for those with three.</p>
                <p>Genus <hi rend="italic">Bradypus.—</hi> Three-toed sloths. Teeth usually <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> on each side; no tooth
                    projecting greatly beyond the others; the first in the upper jaw much smaller
                    than any of the others; the first in the lower jaw broad and compressed; the
                    grinding surfaces of all much cupped. Vertebrae: C 9, D and L 20 (of which 15 to
                    17 bear ribs), S 6, C 11. All the known species present the remarkable
                    peculiarity of possessing nine cervical vertebrae, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>
                    nine vertebrae in front of the one which bears the first thoracic rib (or first
                    rib connected with the sternum, and corresponding in its general relations with
                    the first rib of other mammals); but the ninth, and sometimes the eighth, bears
                    a pair of short movable ribs. The arms or fore-limbs are considerably longer
                    than the hind legs. The bones of the fore-arm are complete, free, and capable of
                    pronation and supination. The hand is long, very narrow, habitually curved, and
                    terminates in three pointed curved claws, in close apposition with each other;
                    they are, in fact, incapable of being divaricated, so that the hand is reduced
                    to the condition of a triple hook, fit only for the function of suspension from
                    the boughs of trees. The foot closely resembles the hand in its general
                    structure and mode of use. The sole is habitually turned inwards and cannot be
                    applied to the ground in walking. The tongue is short and soft, and the stomach
                    large and complex, bearing some resemblance to that of the ruminating animals.
                    The windpipe or trachea has the remarkable peculiarity among mammals—not
                    unfrequent among birds and reptiles—of being folded on itself before it reaches
                    the lungs. The mammae are two and pectoral in position.</p>
                <p>“Ai” is the common name given in books to the three-toed sloths. They were all
                    comprised by Linnaeus under the species <hi rend="italic">Bradypus
                    tridactylus.</hi> More recently Dr Gray has described as many as eleven, ranged
                    in two genera, <hi rend="italic">Bradypus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Arctopithecus;</hi> but the distinctions which he assigns both to species and
                    to genera do not bear close examination. Some are covered uniformly with a grey
                    or greyish brown coat; others have a dark collar of elongated hairs around the
                    shoulders (<hi rend="italic">B</hi>. <hi rend="italic">torquatus)</hi>; some
                    have the hair of the face very much shorter than that of the rest of the head
                    and neck; and others have a remarkable-looking patch of soft short hair on the
                    back between the shoulders, consisting when best marked of a median stripe of
                    glossy black, bordered on each side by bright<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n177/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0177-0162"/> orange, yellow, or white. There are also
                    structural differences in the skulls, as in the amount of inflation of the
                    pterygoid bones, which indicate real differences of species; but the materials
                    in our museums are not yet sufficient to correlate these with external
                    characters and geographical distribution. The habits of all are apparently
                    alike. They are natives of Guiana, Brazil, and Peru, and one if not two species
                    <hi rend="italic">(B. infuscatus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B.
                    castaneiceps)</hi> extend north of the Isthmus of Panama as far as Nicaragua. Of
                    the former of these Dr Seeman says that, though generally silent, a specimen in
                    captivity uttered a shrill sound like a monkey when forcibly pulled away from
                    the tree to which it was holding.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Godman and Salvin’s <hi rend="italic">Biologia
                    Centrali-Americana,</hi> p. 184.</p></note></p>
                <p>Genus <hi rend="italic">Choloepus.—</hi> Teeth <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> /
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>; the most anterior in both jaws separated by an
                    interval from the others, very large, caniniform, wearing to a sharp, bevelled
                    edge against the opposing tooth, the upper shutting in front of the lower when
                    the mouth is closed, unlike the true canines of heterodont mammals. Vertebrae: C
                    6 or 7, D 23-24, L 3, S 7-8, C 4-6. One species (<hi rend="italic">C</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">didactylus)</hi> has the ordinary number of vertebrae in the neck;
                    but an otherwise closely allied form (<hi rend="italic">C</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">hoffmanni)</hi> has but six. The tail is very rudimentary. The
                    hand generally resembles that of <hi rend="italic">Bradypus</hi>; but there are
                    only two functional digits, with claws,—those answering to the second and third
                    of the typical pentadactyle manus. The structure of the hind limb generally
                    resembles that of <hi rend="italic">Bradypus,</hi> the appellation “two-toed”
                    referring only to the anterior limb, for in the foot the three middle toes are
                    functionally developed and of nearly equal size. <hi rend="italic">C.
                    didactylus,</hi> which has been longest known, is commonly called by the native
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Unau.</hi> It inhabits the forests of Brazil. <hi
                    rend="italic">C. hoffmanni</hi> has a more northern geographical range,
                    extending from Ecuador through Panama to Costa Rica. Its voice, which is seldom
                    heard, is like the bleat of a sheep, and if the animal is seized it snorts
                    violently. Both species are very variable in external coloration. (W. H. F.
                    )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
