<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0202-0187-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SNAIL (9th edition, volume 22, page 187)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42f7jv62">Pulmonata</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4p01z">Spires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xg7p">Gills</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1083853">Pulmonata</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814446">Arion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130034">Spires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942722">Gills</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n202/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SNAIL</label>. In England the word “snail” in popular
                    language is associated with Gasteropods which inhabit land or fresh water and
                    which possess large conspicuous spiral shells; terrestrial Gasteropods in which
                    the shell is rudimentary and concealed are distinguished as “slugs.” In Scotland
                    the word “slug” is absent from the vernacular vocabulary, both shell-bearing and
                    shell-less inland molluscs being known as snails. Marine Gasteropods are
                    occasionally termed “sea-snails,” and the compounds “pond-snails,”
                    “river-snails,” “water-snails” are in common use. The commonest land-snails are
                    those species which constitute the family <hi rend="italic">Helicidae,</hi>
                    order <hi rend="italic">Pulmonata,</hi> sub-order <hi rend="italic"
                        >Stylommatophora.</hi> The other two families of the same sub-order, <hi
                        rend="italic">Limacidae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Onchidiidae,</hi> include
                    all the slugs. In the first of these are comprised all the slugs known in Great
                    Britain, and indeed in Europe. The <hi rend="italic">Onchidiidae</hi> are
                    entitled to the name “sea-slugs,” as they are shell-less Pulmonates living on
                    the seashore, though not actually in the sea. The term “water-snails” includes
                    the whole of the remaining sub-order of the <hi rend="italic">Pulmonata,</hi>
                    namely, the <hi rend="italic">Basommatophora,</hi> in which the eyes are
                    sessile. This division comprises two families, <hi rend="italic">Limnaeidae</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Auriculidae·,</hi> some of the members of the first are
                    amphibious, some entirely aquatic; the snails of the second family are found
                    near but not in the water. Thus the whole of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pulmonata</hi> which breathe air, are destitute of gill-plumes and
                    operculum, and have a complicated hermaphrodite reproductive system are either
                    snails or slugs. But there are a considerable number of snails, both terrestrial
                    and aquatic, which are not Pulmonates. The land-snails which have no gill-plume
                    in the mantle-chamber and breathe air, but have the sexes separated, and possess
                    an operculum belong to the order <hi rend="italic">Azygobranchia,</hi> of which
                    they form a distinct sub-order, the <hi rend="italic">Pneumonochlamyda,</hi>
                    containing three families, <hi rend="italic">Cyclostomidae, Helicinidae,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Aciculidae.</hi> The fresh-water snails which are not
                    Pulmonates are the <hi rend="italic">Paludinidae, Valvatidae,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Ampullaridae,</hi> together with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Neritina,</hi> a genus of the <hi rend="italic">Neritidae.</hi> These all
                    possess a fully developed gill-plume and are typical Azygobranchiates of the
                    sub-order <hi rend="italic">Holochlamyda,</hi> most of the members of which are
                    marine.</p>
                <p>The family <hi rend="italic">Helicidae</hi> has a world-wide distribution. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Helix</hi> the spire forms a more or less obtuse-angled cone;
                    there are above 1200 species, of which 24 are British. <hi rend="italic">Helix
                        nemoralis,</hi> L., of which <hi rend="italic">H. hortensis</hi> is a
                    variety, is one of the commonest forms. <hi rend="italic">Helix pomatia,</hi>
                    L., is the largest species, and is known as the “edible snail”; it is commonly
                    eaten in France and Italy, together with other species. It was formerly believed
                    to have been introduced into Britain by the Romans, but there is no doubt that
                    it is a native. In <hi rend="italic">Succinea</hi> the cone of the spire is
                    acute-angled; three species are British. In <hi rend="italic">Vitrina</hi> the
                    spire is very flat and the surface glassy. In <hi rend="italic">Bulimus</hi> the
                    spire is elongated with a pointed apex. <hi rend="italic">Pupa</hi> is named
                    from its resemblance to a chrysalis, the apex being rounded. The shell of <hi
                        rend="italic">Clausilia</hi> is sinistral and its aperture is provided with
                    a hinged plate. The commoner European slugs of small size all belong to the
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Limax,</hi> in which the opening of the mantle-chamber
                    is posterior. <hi rend="italic">L. flavus</hi> is the cellar slug. <hi
                        rend="italic">L. agrestis, L. arborum, L. maximus,</hi> occur in gardens and
                    fields. The larger black slugs are species of <hi rend="italic">Arion, of</hi>
                    which two are British, <hi rend="italic">A. ater</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A.
                        hortensis. Testacella haliotidea</hi> is common in Great Britain and
                    throughout Europe.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Limnaeidae</hi> occur in all parts of the world. <hi
                        rend="italic">Limnaeus</hi> contains the largest species. <hi rend="italic"
                        >L. pereger,</hi> Miiller, is ubiquitous in Great Britain and common all
                    over Europe. All the species are usually infested with C <hi rend="italic"
                        >ercariae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rediae,</hi> the larval forms of
                    Trematode parasites of vertebrates. <hi rend="italic">L. truncatulus</hi>
                    harbours the <hi rend="italic">Cercaria</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Fasciola
                        hepatica,</hi> the liver-fluke, which causes rot in sheep. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ancylus,</hi> which occurs in rivers, has a minute limpet-like shell. <hi
                        rend="italic">Planorbis</hi> has the spire of the shell in one plane. <hi
                        rend="italic">Physa</hi> is smaller than <hi rend="italic">Limnaeus</hi> and
                    has the upper part of the spire much shorter. In the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Auriculidae</hi> the aperture is denticulated. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Auricilla</hi> is confined to the East Indies and Peru. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Carychium minimum</hi> is British.</p>
                <p>Of the Cy <hi rend="italic">clostomidae</hi> only one species, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cyclostoma elegans,</hi> Miiller, is British; it hides under stones and
                    roots. The <hi rend="italic">Helicinidae</hi> are exotic, ranging from the West
                    Indies to the Philippines. Of the <hi rend="italic">Aciculidae,</hi> which are
                    all minute, <hi rend="italic">Acicula lineata</hi> is British.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ampullaridae</hi> are confined to the tropics. <hi
                        rend="italic">Ampullaria</hi> has very long tentacles and a long siphon
                    formed by the mantle.<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n203/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0203-0188"/><hi rend="italic">Valvata</hi> is common in
                    fresh waters throughout Britain; the gill when the animal is expanded is
                    protruded beyond the mantlechamber. The <hi rend="italic">Paludinidae</hi> are
                    common in the northern hemisphere. <hi rend="italic">Paludina</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Bithynia</hi> are both British genera. In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Paludina</hi> the whorls of the spiral are very prominent; the genus is
                    viviparous. <hi rend="italic">Bithynia</hi> is smaller and the shell
                    smoother.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Neritina</hi> has a very small spire, the terminal portion of
                    the shell containing nearly the whole animal.</p>
                <p>For the morphology and classification of snails, see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Mollusca,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 648 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> A history of the
                    British forms is given in Gwyn Jeffreys’s <hi rend="italic">British
                        Conchology,</hi> 1862, and by Forbes and Hanley in <hi rend="italic">British
                        Mollusca.</hi> For specie-graphical details, see Woodward’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Manual of the Mollusca,</hi> 1875, and Bronn’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Thierreich</hi> (Weichthiere). For <hi rend="italic">Fasciola
                        hepatica,</hi> see Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Quart. Journ. Mie. Sci.,</hi>
                    1882.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
