<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0466-0443-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STAFFORD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 443</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dq72">Salt</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26q56k">Deeds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1104337">Salts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208478">Chad</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n466/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STAFFORD</label>, a parliamentary and municipal borough of
                    England, and the county town of Staffordshire, is situated on the left bank of
                    the river Sow, almost in the heart of England. It is 123 miles from London and
                    29 ¼ from Birmingham, and is in the southern division of the hundred of
                    Pirehill. The principal trades of the town are tanning and the manufacture of
                    boots and shoes, more especially for ladies. The oldest church is that of St
                    Chad, said to be originally of Saxon origin. It was formerly a large and
                    beautiful church, with chancel, nave, aisles, transepts, and a central tower,
                    but has suffered severely from time, neglect, and rough treatment. Restoration
                    was begun in 1855, and the operations led to the discovery of some fine
                    interlacing Norman arches and a beautiful Norman archway with some rich
                    sculptured work between the nave and tower. These were restored in 1856 and a
                    new roof was put on the chancel in memory of Izaak Walton. In 1874, the nave,
                    arcades, and open-timbered roof were restored in memory of Mr Thomas Salt; in
                    1874-75 the south aisle was rebuilt, and in 1884-85 the tower. The finest of the
                    churches in Stafford is undoubtedly St Mary’s, which was admirably restored in
                    1844-45 by Sir Gilbert Scott, at a cost of £30,000. It contains some good
                    monuments, and several very fine memorial windows of stained glass. Other
                    churches worthy of mention are Christ Church, St Paul’s, and St Thomas’s. The
                    grammar school is a very old foundation, enlarged by Edward VI.; the present
                    building was erected in 1862. The free library was opened in 1882, and is now
                    fairly well supplied with books. The William Salt library contains a unique
                    collection of books, deeds, autographs, engravings, and drawings relating to the
                    county, collected by Mr Salt and presented by his widow. It contains some 7000
                    volumes, between 2000 and 3000 deeds, and more than 9000 drawings, autographs,
                    and valuable MSS., mostly relating to the history, topography, Ac., of the
                    county. The town also possesses a good museum, collected principally by Mr
                    Clement L. Wragge, and called by his name; specially interesting is its almost
                    perfect collection of fossils. Stafford also contains a good school of art and a
                    mechanics’ institute. Other prominent buildings are the shire hall, in which the
                    assizes and quarter sessions are held, and the borough hall; the latter contains
                    the municipal offices, and also has a large hall for public meetings. Stafford
                    is well supplied with charitable institutions, among which may be mentioned the
                    general infirmary, built in 1766; the county lunatic asylum in 1818; and the
                    Coton Hill institution for the insane in 1854, beautifully situated on rising
                    ground, which commands extensive views of some of the loveliest country in the
                    county, while its own grounds are tastefully laid out. The householders of
                    Stafford formerly possessed the right of using some very extensive common land
                    situated north of the town; in 1880, however, all that remained (134 acres) was
                    enclosed, and is now held for the people by a committee of householders elected
                    annually. A part of this land, called Stone Flat, is preserved as a public
                    recreation ground. Of another common named Coton Field, consisting of about 180
                    acres, 70 acres were in 1884 transferred absolutely to the freemen, and have
                    been divided into 401 garden allotments, which are let at a small rental to
                    resident freemen or their widows. The parliamentary borough (area 774 acres,
                    with population of 18,904 in 1881) was extended in 1885, and is now identical
                    with the municipal borough. The area of this is 1012 acres, and the population,
                    14,437 in 1871, was in 1881 19,977. The Act of 1885 reduced the parliamentary
                    representation from two members to one.</p>
                <p>Stafford was of considerable importance before the Conquest. The site was at
                    first known as Berteliney or Betheney, from the island on which the earliest
                    houses were built. As the town grew its name was changed into that of Stafford
                    or Stadford. In 913 Ethelfleda, sister of Edward the Elder, erected a
                    fortification here, generally called a castle, but doubtless one of those
                    defensive mounds which from their admirable positions were afterwards selected
                    by the Normans as the sites of their castles and strongholds. About a year and a
                    half afterwards Edward the Elder built a tower, with walls and a fosse round it.
                    Pennant says this was on the mount called Castle Hill by Speed. Stafford is
                    mentioned in Domesday as a city paying £9 in customs. 1 here were 18 royal
                    burgesses, and the earls of Mercia possessed twenty mansions. The number of
                    houses entered is 178. William built a castle on the old site, of which he
                    appointed Robert de lorn<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n467/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0467-0444"/> governor, who took the name De Stafford from that
                    of the town, aud was the originator of the great family of the Staffords. At
                    this time it contained a royal mint; some of the coins are still extant, hearing
                    on the obverse the head and name of the king, and on the reverse “Godwinne on
                    Staef.” Godwinne was the "king’s moneyer.” The castle of Robert de Torri was
                    rebuilt by Ralph de Stafford in the reign of Edward III.; during the Civil War
                    it was held for the Royalists by the earl of Northampton, but was taken for the
                    Parliament by Sir William Brereton in May 1643. The castle was soon afterwards
                    demolished by order of the Parliament. When fortified, Stafford had four gates.
                    That on the south, near the river bridge, called the Green-gate, was taken down
                    in 1780. The arch of the East-gate was standing a few years ago. The Gaol-gate
                    was in ruins in 1680. The site of the fourth gate is unknown. King John
                    confirmed and enlarged the privileges granted by the old charter. This was again
                    confirmed by Edward VI., and on August 6, 1575, Elizabeth visited the town.
                    Stafford adopted the Local Government Act, 1858, on April 23, 1872; and in 1876
                    an Act was obtained for extending the borough boundaries. The corporation now
                    consists of a mayor, eight aldermen, and twenty-four councillors.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
