<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0846-0811-06" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SYNAGOGUE (9th edition, volume 22, page 811)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:984280">Judaism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079211">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698j66">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61d88">Judaism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n846/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SYNAGOGUE</label> (<hi rend="italic">συvαγωγή</hi>),
                    literally “assemblage,” is the term employed to denote either a congregation of
                    Jews, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> a local circle accustomed to meet together
                    for worship and religious instruction, or the building in which the congregation
                    met. In the first sense the word is a translation of כנםת, <hi rend="italic"
                        >keneseth,</hi> in the second of כית הכנםח, <hi rend="italic">bêth
                        hakheneseth.</hi> The germ of the synagogue, that is, of religious
                    assemblages dissociated from the ancient ritual of the altar, may be found in
                    the circle of the prophets and their disciples (see especially Isa. viii. 16 <hi
                        rend="italic">sqj)</hi>; but the synagogue as an institution characteristic
                    of Judaism arose after the work of Ezra, and is closely connected with the
                    development of that legal Judaism to which his reformation gave definite shape.
                    From the time of Ezra downwards it was the business of every Jew to know the
                    law; the school <hi rend="italic">(beth ham-midrāsh)</hi> trained scholars, but
                    the synagogue, where the law was read every Sabbath (Acts xv. 21), was the means
                    of popular instruction. Such synagogues existed in all parts of Judaea in the
                    time of Psalm lxxiv. 8 (probably a psalm of the Persian period); in Acts xv. 21
                    it appears that they had existed for many generations “in every city.” This held
                    good not only for Palestine but for the Dispersion; in post-Talmudic times the
                    rule was that a synagogue must be built wherever there were ten Jews. And,
                    though the name “synagogue” varies with <hi rend="italic">προσευχή</hi> (“place
                    of prayer ”), it appears that everywhere the assemblage was primarily one for
                    instruction in the law: the synagogue, as Philo puts it, was a <hi rend="italic"
                        >διδασκαλειov</hi>. A formed institution<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0847-0812"/> of this sort required some organization: the
                    general order of the service was directed by one or more “rulers of the
                    synagogue” (<hi rend="italic">ἀρχισυνάγωγοι</hi>, Luke xiii. 14; Acts xiii. 15),
                    who called on fit persons to read, pray, and preach; alms were collected by two
                    or more “collectors” (<hi rend="italic">gabbâe sedākā}·,</hi> and a “minister”
                        (<hi rend="italic">hazzān, ὑπηρέτης,</hi> Luke iv. 20) had charge of the
                    sacred books (preserved in an “ark”) and of other ministerial functions,
                    including the teaching of children to read. The discipline of the congregation
                    was enforced by excommunication (<hi rend="italic">hērem)</hi> or temporary
                    exclusion (<hi rend="italic">niddûy),</hi> and also by the minor punishment of
                    scourging (Matt. x. 17), inflicted by the <hi rend="italic">hazzân.</hi> The
                    disciplinary power was in the hands of a senate of elders (<hi rend="italic"
                        >πpεσβύτεpoι, γερουσία),</hi> the chief members of which were <hi
                        rend="italic">ἄρχοντες.</hi> The principal service of the synagogue was held
                    on Sabbath morning, and included, according to the Mishnah, the recitation of
                    the <hi rend="italic">shema</hi> (Deut. vi. 4-9, xi. 13-21; Numb. xv. 37-41),
                    prayer, lessons from the law and prophets with Aramaic translation, a sermon
                        (<hi rend="italic">derashah)</hi> based on the lesson (Acts xiii. 15), and
                    finally a blessing pronounced by the priest or invoked by a layman. On Sabbath
                    afternoon and on Monday and Thursday there was a service without a lesson from
                    the prophets; there were also services for all feast-days. Synagogues were built
                    by preference beside water for the convenience of the ceremonial ablutions
                    (comp. Acts xvi. 13); and remains of very ancient buildings of this class exist
                    in several parts of Galilee; they generally lie north and south, and seem to
                    have had three doors to the south, and sometimes to have been divided by columns
                    into a nave and two aisles.</p>
                <p>Jewish tradition has a great deal to say about a body called “the great
                    synagogue,” which is supposed to have been the supreme religious authority from
                    the cessation of prophecy to the time of the high priest Simeon the Just, and is
                    even said (by modern writers since Elias Levita) to have fixed the Old Testament
                    canon (cp. vol. V. p. 3 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi> But Kuenen in his essay
                    “Over de Mannen der Groote Synagoge” (<hi rend="italic">Verslagen</hi> of the
                    Amsterdam Academy, 1876) has shown that these traditions are fiction, and that
                    the name <hi rend="italic">keneseth haggadôla</hi> originally denoted, not a
                    standing authority, but the great convocation of Neh. viii.-x.</p>
                <p>Compare in general Schürer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des jüdischen
                        Volkes,</hi> §27, where the older literature is catalogued. For the usages
                    of the synagogue in more recent times, see Buxtorf, <hi rend="italic">Synagoge
                        Judaica,</hi> Basel, 1641.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
