<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0597-0574-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STOMACH, Diseases of the</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 574</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="26" ref="fasttopic:1133761">Stomach</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1050382">Pain</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1140998">Symptoms</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:930458">Food</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="26" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s18">Stomach</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz9r">Pain</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v30g">Symptoms</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n597/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STOMACH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Diseases of the</hi></label>.
                    Only the more common and serious varieties of gastric disease can be here
                    referred to. The majority of them exhibit, as their most marked and sometimes
                    their only feature, the symptoms of <hi rend="smallcaps">Dyspepsia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(q.v)</hi> Hence the diagnosis of the forms of stomach disease is
                    frequently a matter of much difficulty. Nevertheless a careful consideration of
                    the history and the manifested phenomena of a given case may often lead to a
                    correct identification of its nature. The present notice refers in general terms
                    to the most prominent symptoms which usually characterize the chief gastric
                    disorders.</p>
                <p>The stomach is liable to inflammatory affections, of which the condition of
                    catarrh, or irritation of its mucous membrane, is the most frequent and most
                    readily recognized. This may exist in an acute or a chronic form, and depends
                    upon some condition, either local or general, which produces a congested state
                    of the circulation in the walls of the stomach.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Acute Gastric Catarrh</hi> may arise from various causes, of
                    which the most important are—(1) constitutional conditions, such as the gouty or
                    rheumatic, or an inherited tendency to irritability of the digestive organs; (2)
                    errors in diet, particularly excessive quantity, indigestible quality, imperfect
                    mastication, extremes of temperature of the food, toxic agents, especially
                    alcohol, in excess, or food in a state of decomposition; (3) atmospheric
                    influences, as appears evident from its tendency to occur in very warm or very
                    cold weather or in the case of sudden temperature alternations.</p>
                <p>The chief change the stomach undergoes affects its mucous membrane, which is in a
                    state of congestion, either throughout or in parts. It is more than probable
                    that this condition produces an alteration in the secreting function of the
                    organ, and that its peptic juices become less potent, the effect of which will
                    be to retard the process of digestion and favour the occurrence of decomposition
                    and fermentation in its contents, thus aggravating the original evil. The
                    symptoms are those well known as characterizing an acute “bilious attack,”
                    consisting in loss of appetite, sickness or nausea, and headache, frontal or
                    occipital, often accompanied with giddiness. The tongue is furred, the breath
                    foetid, and there is pain or discomfort in the region of the stomach, with sour
                    eructations, and frequently vomiting, first of food and then of bilious matter.
                    An attack of this kind tends to subside in a few days, especially if the
                    exciting cause be removed. Sometimes, however, the symptoms recur with such
                    frequency as to lead to the more serious chronic form of the disease.</p>
                <p>The treatment bears reference, in the first place, to any known source of
                    irritation, which, if it exist, may be expelled by an emetic or purgative. This,
                    however, is seldom necessary, since vomiting is usually present. For the relief
                    of sickness and pain the sucking<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0598-0575"/> of ice and counter-irritation over the region of
                    the stomach are of service. Further, remedies which exercise a soothing effect
                    upon an irritable mucous membrane, such as bismuth or weak alkaline fluids, and
                    along with these the use of a light milk diet, are usually sufficient to remove
                    the symptoms.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Chronic Gastric Catarrh</hi> may result from the acute or may
                    arise independently. It is not unfrequently connected with antecedent disease in
                    other organs, such as the lungs, heart, liver, or kidneys, and it is specially
                    common in persons addicted to alcoholic excess. In this form the texture of the
                    stomach is more seriously affected than in the acute. It is permanently in a
                    state of congestion, and its mucous membrane and muscular coat undergo
                    thickening and other changes, which, besides markedly affecting the function of
                    digestion, may lead to stricture of the pyloric orifice of the stomach and its
                    results, to be subsequently referred to. The symptoms are those of dyspepsia in
                    an aggravated form (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Dyspepsia),</hi> of which
                    discomfort and pain after food, with distension and frequently vomiting, are the
                    chief; and the treatment must be conducted in reference to the causes giving
                    rise to it. The careful regulation of the diet (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Dietetics),</hi> both as to the amount, the quality, and the intervals between
                    meals, demands special attention. Of medicinal agents, bismuth, arsenic, nux
                    vomica, and the mineral acids are all of acknowledged efficacy, as are also
                    preparations of pepsin.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ulcer of the Stomach</hi> (gastric ulcer, perforating ulcer) is
                    of not unfrequent occurrence, and is a disease of much gravity. Its causes are
                    probably not fully understood, yet the following points may be regarded as
                    generally admitted :—(1) that the disease is twice as common in females as in
                    males, and that it is found to affect domestic servants more frequently than any
                    other class; (2) that it occurs for the most part in early life, the period from
                    twenty to thirty including the great majority of the cases; (3) that it appears
                    to be connected in many instances with, impairment of the circulation in the
                    stomach and the formation of a clot in a small blood-vessel (thrombosis); (4)
                    that such an occurrence may arise in connexion with an impoverished state of the
                    blood (anaemia), which is actually the condition present in many of the cases,
                    but that it may also arise from diseased blood-vessels, the result of
                    long-continued catarrh, or from the irritation and debilitating effects of hot
                    or cold substances.</p>
                <p>It is held that when any such obstruction takes place in a bloodvessel the
                    nutrition of a limited area of the stomach is cut off, and the part is apt to
                    undergo disintegration all the more readily from the unresisted action of the
                    gastric juices upon it. Hence an ulcer is formed. This ulcer is usually of small
                    size (¼ to 1 inch in diameter), of round or oval form, and tends to advance, not
                    superficially, but to penetrate through the coats of the stomach. Its most usual
                    site is upon the posterior wall of the upper or lesser curvature of the stomach
                    and near to the pyloric orifice. It may undergo a healing process at any stage,
                    in which case it may leave but little trace of its existence; while, on the
                    other hand, it may in the course of cicatrizing produce such an amount of
                    contraction as to lead to stricture of the pylorus. But, again, perforation may
                    take place, which in most cases is quickly fatal, unless previously the stomach
                    has become, as it may, adherent to another organ, by which the dangerous effects
                    of this occurrence may be averted. Usually there is but one ulcer, but sometimes
                    there are more.</p>
                <p>The symptoms to which this disease gives rise are often exceedingly indefinite
                    and obscure, and in some cases the diagnosis has been first made out by the
                    sudden occurrence of a fatal perforation. Generally, however, there are certain
                    evidences more or less distinct which tend to indicate the probable presence of
                    a gastric ulcer. First among these is <hi rend="italic">pain,</hi> which is in
                    some measure present at all times, but is markedly increased after food. This
                    pain is situated either in front, at the lower end of the sternum, or fully more
                    commonly behind, about the middle of the back. Sometimes it is felt at one or
                    both sides. It is often extremely severe, and is usually accompanied with much
                    tenderness to touch, and also with a sense of oppression and inability to wear
                    tight clothing. The pain is probably largely due to the active movements of the
                    stomach set up by the presence of the food. Accompanying the pain there is
                    frequently <hi rend="italic">vomiting,</hi> either very soon after the food is
                    swallowed or at a later period. This tends in some measure to relieve the pain
                    and discomfort, and in many instances the patient rather encourages this act.
                    Vomiting of blood (haematemesis) is a frequent symptom, and is most important
                    diagnostically. It may show itself either to a slight extent, and in the form of
                    a brown or coffee-like mixture, or as an enormous discharge of pure blood of
                    dark colour and containing clots. The source of the blood is some vessel or
                    vessels which the ulcerative process has ruptured. Blood is also found mixed
                    with the discharges from the bowels, rendering them dark and tarry looking. The
                    general condition of a patient with gastric ulcer is as a rule that of
                    ill-health, showing pallor, more or less emaciation, and debility. The tongue
                    presents a red irritable appearance, and there is usually constipation of the
                    bowels.</p>
                <p>The course of a case of gastric ulcer is very variable. In some instances it
                    would appear to be acute, making rapid progress to a favourable or unfavourable
                    termination. In most, however, the disease is chronic, lasting for months or
                    years; and in those cases where the ulcers are multiple or of extensive size
                    incomplete healing may take place and relapses of the symptoms occur from time
                    to time. Ulcers are sometimes present and give rise to no marked symptoms; and
                    it has occurred to the writer to see more than one instance of this kind where
                    fatal perforation suddenly took place, and where <hi rend="italic"
                    >post-mortem</hi> examination revealed the existence of longstanding ulcers
                    which could not possibly have been made out by any evidences furnished during
                    life. While gastric ulcer is always to be regarded as a dangerous disease, its
                    termination, in the great majority of cases, is in recovery. It frequently,
                    however, leaves the stomach in a delicate condition, necessitating the utmost
                    care as regards diet. Occasionally, though rarely, the disease proves fatal by
                    sudden haemorrhage but a fatal result is more frequently due to perforation and
                    the extrusion of the contents of the stomach into the peritoneal cavity, in
                    which case death usually occurs in from twelve to forty-eight hours, either from
                    shock or from peritonitis. Should the stomach become adherent to another organ,
                    and fatal perforation be thus prevented, there may remain as the result of this
                    a permanent condition of dyspepsia, owing to interference with the natural
                    movements of the stomach during digestion; while again stricture of the pylorus
                    and consequent dilatation of the stomach is an occasional result of the
                    cicatrization of an ulcer in its neighbourhood.</p>
                <p>Of prime importance in the treatment of this disease is the careful adjustment of
                    the diet, the conditions existing in the stomach obviously requiring that the
                    food administered should be of as bland and soft a character as possible. Of all
                    substances milk forms the most suitable aliment, and, while there may be
                    instances in which it fails to agree, even when mixed with lime water or
                    previously boiled, these are comparatively few. The peptonized foods originally
                    suggested by Sir Wm. Roberts of Manchester are frequently found of much service
                    in this disease. Light soups as well as milk may sometimes be administered in
                    this way with benefit. The quantity, the intervals between the times of
                    administration, and the temperature, as well as the quantity, of the food demand
                    careful attention. In severe cases, where the presence of food in the stomach
                    gives rise to much suffering, nourishment by the bowel may be given for a time
                    with great advantage. Of medicinal remedies the most serviceable are large doses
                    of bismuth, with which it may be necessary to conjoin small doses of opium or of
                    hydrocyanic acid for the relief of pain. The careful administration of nitrate
                    of silver has been recommended as a means of promoting the healing of the
                    ulcers, but this end is probably more readily accomplished by the remedies and
                    especially by the method of diet already referred to, combined with rest. When
                    haemorrhage occurs it is relieved by ice and by such styptics as gallic acid,
                    ergot of rye, lead, alum, &amp;c., while in the dread event of perforation the
                    only means of affording relief is opium.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cancer of the Stomach</hi> is one of the most common forms of
                    internal cancerous disease. It occurs for the most part in persons at or after
                    middle life, and in both sexes equally. Hereditary tendency may not unfrequently
                    be traced.</p>
                <p>The most common varieties of cancer affecting the stomach are scirrhus,
                    medullary, and colloid, and the parts affected are usually the inlet or outlet
                    orifices; but the morbid process may spread widely in the stomach wall. When in
                    the neighbourhood of the pylorus a stricture is frequently produced as the
                    disease advances. The cancerous growth usually commences in the submucous
                    tissue, but as it progresses it tends to ulcerate through the mucous membrane,
                    and in this process haemorrhage and haematemesis may occur. Tho symptoms of this
                    disease are in many instances so indefinite as to render the diagnosis for a
                    long time conjectural. They are mostly those of dyspepsia, with more or less
                    pain, discomfort, and vomiting, particularly after meals. The vomited matters
                    are often of coffee-ground appearance, due to admixture with blood, but copious
                    haematemesis is less frequent than in cases of gastric ulcer. The patient loses
                    flesh and strength and soon comes to acquire the cachectic aspect commonly
                    associated with cancer. The diagnosis is rendered all the more certain when, as
                    is frequently the case, a tumour can be detected on examination over the region
                    of the stomach, but there are many instances where no such evidence is obtained
                    and where the nature of the disease is left to be made out by the age of the
                    patient and by the intractable and progressive character of the symptoms. Cases
                    of cancer of the stomach advance with more or less rapidity to a fatal
                    termination, which is usually quickest in tho medullary form. In most instances
                    death takes place in from six to twelve months. The treatment can only be
                    palliative, but much relief may often be afforded by a careful attention to
                    diet, by the treatment applicable to dilatation of the stomach, and by the use
                    of opium.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stricture of the Pylorus</hi> may, as has been already
                    indicated, result from the various morbid conditions affecting the stomach to
                    which reference has been made, namely, catarrh, ulcer, and cancer. By whatever
                    means produced, the effect is an obstruction to the transmission through the
                    pyloric orifice into the intestines of the contents of the stomach, the
                    occurrence of dilatation of the organ, with<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0599-0576"/> weakening of its walls, and the consequent
                    accumulation aud fermentation of partially digested food. This condition gives
                    rise to much discomfort, heartburn, and pain, and to the occurrence every few
                    days of a copious vomiting of fermenting material, in which may be found on
                    microscopic examination the fungoid growths of <hi rend="italic">Sarcina</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Torulae.</hi> With the continuance of the disease the
                    symptoms tend to increase and to wear out the patient’s strength, since little
                    or no assimilation is possible, and death sooner or later takes place from
                    inanition. For a long time this condition was regarded as incurable in every
                    case, till the method of treatment, originally suggested by Kussmaul, of washing
                    out the stomach daily or less frequently was found to yield remarkably
                    beneficial results in almost all cases, and, in many instances of non-cancerous
                    disease, to accomplish an actual cure. This plan of treatment is now largely
                    resorted to, and it has proved to be a valuable addition to the therapeutics of
                    gastric diseases. (J. O. A. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
