<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0184-0169-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMITH, Adam</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 169</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1112660">Sentimentalism</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1172973">Wealth</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198483">Brown</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n184/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMITH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Adam</hi></label> (1723-1790),
                    the greatest of political economists, was the only child of Adam Smith,
                    comptroller of the customs at Kirkcaldy in Fifeshire, Scotland, and of Margaret
                    Douglas, daughter of Mr Douglas of Strathendry, near Leslie. He was born at
                    Kirkcaldy on 5th June 1723, some months after the death of his father. Of a weak
                    constitution, he required and received during his early years the most tender
                    care of an affectionate mother, which he repaid in after life by every attention
                    which filial gratitude could dictate. When he was three years old he was taken
                    on a visit to his uncle at Strathendry, and when playing alone at the door of
                    the house was carried off by a party of “tinkers.” Fortunately he was at once
                    missed, and the vagrants pursued and overtaken in Leslie wood. He received his
                    early education in the school of Kirkcaldy under David Miller, amongst whose
                    pupils were many who were afterwards distinguished men. Smith showed as a boy
                    great fondness for books and remarkable powers of memory; and his friendly and
                    generous disposition made him popular amongst his schoolfellows. He was sent in
                    1737 to the university of Glasgow, where he attended the lectures of Dr
                    Hutcheson; and in 1740 he went to Baliol College, Oxford, as exhibitioner on
                    Snell’s foundation, with a view to his taking orders in the English Church. He
                    remained at that university for seven years. At Glasgow his favourite studies
                    had been mathematics and natural philosophy; but at Oxford he appears to have
                    devoted himself almost entirely to moral and political science and to the
                    cultivation of the ancient and modern languages. He also laboured to improve his
                    English style by the practice of translation, particularly from the French. He
                    was not impressed with a favourable opinion of the system of education then
                    pursued at Oxford. After his return to Kirkcaldy he resided there two years with
                    his mother, continuing his studies; he had relinquished the idea of entering the
                    ecclesiastical profession, but had not yet adopted any other plan for his future
                    life. In 1748 he removed to Edinburgh, and there, under the patronage of Lord
                    Karnes, gave lectures on rhetoric and belles-lettres. About this time commenced
                    his acquaintance with David Hume, which afterwards ripened into an intimate
                    friendship, founded on mutual esteem; his relations with that great thinker must
                    have powerfully influenced the formation of his opinions. In 1751 he was elected
                    professor of logic at Glasgow, and in the following year was transferred to the
                    chair of moral philosophy in the same university, which had become vacant by the
                    death of Thomas Craigie, the successor of Hutcheson. This position he occupied
                    for nearly twelve years, which he long afterwards declared to have been “by far
                    the most useful, and therefore by far the happiest and most honourable period of
                    his life.” He was highly esteemed by his colleagues, of whom, on his side, he
                    speaks as “very excellent men.” His course of lectures, as Professor Millar
                    informs us, was divided into four parts—(1) natural theology; (2) ethics; (3) a
                    treatment of that branch of morality which relates to justice, a subject which
                    he handled historically after the manner of Montesquieu, “endeavouring to trace
                    the gradual progress of jurisprudence, both public and private, from the rudest
                    to the most refined ages, and to point out the effects of those arts which
                    contribute to subsistence and to the accumulation of property in producing
                    corresponding improvements or alterations in law and government”; (4) a study of
                    those political regulations which are founded, not upon the principle of
                    justice, but that of expediency, and which are calculated to increase the
                    riches, the power, and the prosperity of a state. Under this view he considered
                    the political institutions relating to commerce, to finances, to ecclesiastical
                    and military establishments. He first appeared as an author by contributing two
                    articles to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> (an earlier journal than
                    the present, which was commenced in 1755, but of which only two numbers<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>These two numbers were
                    reprinted in 1818. Smith’s letter to the editors is specially interesting for
                    its account of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie</hi> and its criticism of
                    Rousseau’s pictures of savage life.</p></note> were published),—one on Johnson’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> and the other a letter to the editors on the
                    state of literature in the different countries of Europe. In 1759 appeared his
                    <hi rend="italic">Theory of Moral Sentiments,</hi> embodying the second portion
                    of his university course, to which was added in the 2d edition an appendix with
                    the title, “Considerations concerning the first Formation of Languages.” After
                    the publication of this work his ethical doctrines occupied less space in his
                    lectures, and a larger development was given to the subjects of jurisprudence
                    and political economy. Stewart gives us to understand that he had already, as
                    early as 1752, adopted the liberal views of commercial policy which he
                    afterwards preached with so much effect; and this we should have been inclined
                    to believe independently from the fact that such views were propounded in that
                    year in the <hi rend="italic">Political Discourses</hi> of his friend Hume. His
                    residence at Glasgow brought him into personal relations with many intelligent
                    men from whose practical experience he could derive information on mercantile
                    questions; and, on the other hand, we are told, his reasonings convinced several
                    eminent merchants of that city of the soundness of the principles of free trade,
                    which were at variance with their previous opinions.</p>
                <p>In 1762 the senatus academicus of Glasgow conferred on him the honorary degree of
                    doctor of laws. In 1763 he was invited to take charge of the young duke of
                    Buccleuch on his travels. He accepted the proposal, and resigned his
                    professorship. He went abroad with his pupil in March 1764; they remained only a
                    few days at Paris and then settled at Toulouse, then the seat of a parliament,
                    where they spent eighteen months in the best society of the place, afterwards
                    making a tour in the south of France and passing two months at Geneva. Returning
                    to Paris about Christmas of 1765, they remained there till the October of the
                    following year. The period was one of intellectual and social ferment, and Smith
                    was brought into relation with the most eminent persons of the time. He lived in
                    the society of Quesnay, Turgot, D’Alembert, Morellet, Helvétius, Marmontel, and
                    the duke de la Rochefoucault. It was the regard he entertained for the young
                    nobleman<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The duke
                    undertook a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Theory of Moral
                    Sentiments,</hi> but the Abbé Blavet’s version appeared (1774) before his was
                    completed and he then relinquished the design. An earlier French translation had
                    been published (1764) under the title <hi rend="italic">Métaphysique de
                    l'Âme</hi>; and there is a later one—the best—by the marquis de Condorcet (1798,
                    2d ed. 1830).</p></note> last named that dictated the omission in the later
                    editions of his <hi rend="italic">Moral Sentiments</hi> of the name of the
                    celebrated ancestor of the duke, whom he had associated with Mandeville as
                    author of one of the “licentious sys-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n185/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0185-0170"/> terns” reviewed in the seventh part of that work.
                    Smith was without doubt much influenced by his contact with the members of the
                    physiocratic school, especially with its chief, though Dupont de Nemours
                    probably goes too far in speaking of Smith and himself as having been
                    “condisciples chez M. Quesnay.” Smith afterwards described Quesnay as a man “of
                    the greatest modesty and simplicity,” and declared his system of political
                    economy to be, “with all its imperfections, the nearest approximation to truth
                    that had yet been published on the principles of that science.” In October 1766
                    tutor and pupil returned home, and they ever afterwards retained strong feelings
                    of mutual esteem. For the next ten years Smith lived with his mother at
                    Kirkcaldy, only paying occasional visits to Edinburgh and London; he was engaged
                    in close study during most of this time, but unbent his mind in familiar
                    intercourse with a few friends. He describes himself to Hume during this period
                    as being extremely happy, comfortable, and contented. He was now occupied on his
                    <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of
                    Nations,</hi> which there is some reason for believing he had begun at Toulouse.
                    That great work appeared in 1776.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Mr J. E. T. Rogers published in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Academy,</hi> 28th February 1885, a letter of Smith to William Pulteney,
                    written in 1772, from which he thinks it probable that the work lay "unrevised
                    and unaltered” in the author’s desk for four years. A similar conclusion seems
                    to follow from a letter of Hume in Burton’s <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> ii. p.
                    461.</p></note> After its publication, and only a few months before his own
                    death, Hume wrote to congratulate his friend— <hi rend="italic">“Euge!
                    belle!</hi> dear Mr Smith, I am much pleased with your performance, and the
                    perusal of it has taken me from a state of great anxiety. It was a work of so
                    much expectation by yourself, by your friends, and by the public, that I
                    trembled for its appearance; but am now much relieved. Not but that the reading
                    of it requires so much attention, and the public is disposed to give so little,
                    that I shall still doubt for some time of its being at first very popular. But
                    it has depth, and solidity, and acuteness, and is so much illustrated by curious
                    facts that it must at last take the public attention.” Smith attended Hume
                    affectionately during a part of his last illness, and soon after the death of
                    the philosopher there was published, along with his autobiography, a letter from
                    Smith to Strahan, in which he gave an account of the closing scenes of his
                    friend’s life and expressed warm admiration for his character. This letter
                    excited some rancour among the theologians, and Dr George Horne, afterwards
                    bishop of Norwich, published in 1777, by way of comment on it, <hi rend="italic"
                    >A Letter to Adam Smith on the Life, Death, and Philosophy of his Friend David
                    Hume, by one of the people called Christians.</hi> But Smith took no notice of
                    this effusion.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A story
                    was told by Sir Walter Scott, and is also related in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Edinburgh Review,</hi> of an “unfortunate rencontre,” arising out of the
                    publication of the same letter, between Smith and Dr Johnson, during the visit
                    of the latter to Glasgow. The same story is given in a note in Wilberforce’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Correspondence,</hi> the scene being somewhat vaguely laid in
                    “Scotland.” But it is impossible that it should be true; for Johnson made his
                    tour in 1773, whilst Hume’s death did not take place till 1776. Smith seems not
                    to have met Johnson in Scotland at all. It appears, however, from Boswell’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Life,</hi> under date of 29th April 1778, that Johnson had on one
                    occasion quarrelled with Smith and treated him rudely at Strahan’s house,
                    apparently in London; but, as Robertson met Johnson “for the first time”
                    immediately after that incident, and as we know that Robertson met him in
                    Scotland, it follows that the “unlucky altercation” at Strahan’s must have
                    occurred before the Scotch tour, and could have had nothing to do with the
                    letter on Hume’s death.</p></note> He was also attacked by Archbishop Magee for
                    the omission in subsequent editions of a passage of the <hi rend="italic">Floral
                    Sentiments</hi> which that prelate had cited with high commendation as among the
                    ablest illustrations of the doctrine of the atonement. Smith had omitted the
                    paragraph in question on the ground that it was unnecessary and mis placed; but
                    Magee suspected him of having been influenced by deeper reasons.</p>
                <p>The greater part of the two years which followed the publication of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Wealth of Nations</hi> Smith spent in London, enjoying the society
                    of the most eminent persons of the day, amongst whom were Gibbon, Burke,
                    Reynolds, and Beauclerk. In 1778 he was appointed, through the influence of the
                    duke of Buccleuch, one of the commissioners of customs in Scotland, and in
                    consequence of this fixed his residence at Edinburgh. His mother, now in extreme
                    old age, lived with him, as did also his cousin, Miss Jane Douglas, who assisted
                    him in the care of his aged parent, and superintended his household. Much of his
                    now ample income is believed to have been spent in secret charities, and he kept
                    a simple, though hospitable, table, at which, “without the formality of an
                    invitation, he was always happy to receive his friends.” “His Sunday suppers,”
                    says M‘Culloch, “were long celebrated at Edinburgh.” One of his favourite places
                    of resort in these years was a club of which Dr Hutton, Dr Black, Dr Adam
                    Ferguson, John Clerk the naval tactician, Robert Adam the architect, as well as
                    Smith himself, were original members, and to which Dugald Stewart, Professor
                    Playfair, and other eminent men were afterwards admitted. Another source of
                    enjoyment was the small but excellent library he possessed; it is still
                    preserved in his family; Professor Nicholson has had access to it, and was
                    struck by the varied nature of the collection, and especially by the large
                    number of books of travel and poetry which it contained. In 1787 he was elected
                    lord rector of the university of Glasgow, an honour which he received with
                    “heartfelt joy.” If we can believe a note in Wilberforce’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Correspondence,</hi> he visited London in the spring of the same year, and was
                    introduced by Dundas<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>An
                    interesting letter of Smith to Dundas (1st November 1779) on free trade for
                    Ireland is printed in the <hi rend="italic">Eng. Hist. Review,</hi> No.
                    2.</p></note> to Pitt, Wilberforce, and others. From the death of his mother in
                    1784, and that of Miss Douglas in 1788, his health and strength gradually
                    declined, and after a tedious and painful illness he died on 17th July 1790.</p>
                <p>Before his decease Smith directed that all his manuscripts except a few selected
                    essays should be destroyed, and they were accordingly committed to the flames.
                    Of the pieces preserved by his desire the most valuable is his tract on the
                    history of astronomy, which he himself described as a “fragment of a great
                    work”; it was doubtless a portion of the “connected history of the liberal
                    sciences and elegant arts” which, we are told, he had projected in early life.
                    Among the papers destroyed were probably, as Stewart suggests, the lectures on
                    natural religion and jurisprudence which formed part of his course at Glasgow,
                    and also the lectures on rhetoric which he delivered at Edinburgh in 1748. To
                    the latter Blair seems to refer when, in his work on <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric
                    and Belles-Lettres</hi> (1783), he acknowledges his obligations to a manuscript
                    treatise on rhetoric by Smith, part of which its author had shown to him many
                    years before, and which he hoped Smith would give to the public. It was probably
                    the lectures on jurisprudence which Smith had in view when, some time before his
                    death expressing regret that he “had done so little,” he added, “I meant to have
                    done more, and there are materials in my papers of which I could have made a
                    great deal.” He had promised at the end of his <hi rend="italic">Theory of Moral
                    Sentiments</hi> a treatise on the general principles of jurisprudence from the
                    historical point of view, which would doubtless have been a development of his
                    university lectures on that subject.</p>
                <p>In person Smith was of about the middle size, well made and stout, though not
                    corpulent. His features are said to be well represented in the medallion by
                    Tassie engraved in M‘Culloch’s edition of the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of
                    Nations.</hi> His discourses as professor were almost entirely extemporary, and,
                    as he was always interested in his subject, he never failed to interest his
                    hearers. He was sometimes, Millar tells us, embarrassed and spoke with
                    hesitation at the outset; but “as he advanced the matter seemed to crowd upon
                    him, his manner became warm and animated, and his expression easy and fluent.”
                    In society, except amongst intimate friends, he spoke but seldom, and was rather
                    disposed to enjoy in silence the gaiety of those around him. He often seemed
                    altogether occupied with his own thoughts, or might even have been supposed,
                    from his looks and gestures, to be “in the fervour of composition.” “He was the
                    most absent man in company,” says Alexander Carlyle, “that I<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n186/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0186-0171"/> ever saw, moving his lips and talking to himself
                    and smiling in the midst of large companies.” When called on to give his opinion
                    of the matter under discussion he was apt to do so too much in the manner of a
                    lecture. Easy and flowing as is the style of his books, yet to the end he wrote
                    slowly and with difficulty; he did not usually himself take pen in hand, but
                    dictated to an amanuensis, whilst he walked up and down his apartment. In
                    character he was sincere and earnest, in manner apparently cold, but capable of
                    strong feelings, whether of personal affection or of moral indignation. His
                    frequent acts of beneficence were marked by delicacy no less than by liberality.
                    He was a model of filial love and duty, and took to the last the warmest
                    interest in all that concerned the welfare of his friends.</p>
                <p>As a moral philosopher Smith cannot be said to have won much acceptance for his
                    fundamental doctrine. This doctrine is that all our moral sentiments arise from
                    sympathy, that is, from the principle of our nature “which leads us to enter
                    into the situations of other men and to partake with them in the passions which
                    those situations have a tendency to excite.” Our direct sympathy with the agent
                    in the circumstances in which he is placed gives rise, according to this view,
                    to our notion of the propriety of his action, whilst our indirect sympathy with
                    those whom his actions have benefited or injured gives rise to our notions of
                    merit and demerit in the agent himself. It seems justly alleged against this
                    system by Dr Thomas Brown that “the moral sentiments, the origin of which it
                    ascribes to our secondary feelings of mere sympathy, are assumed as previously
                    existing in the original emotions with which the secondary feelings are said to
                    be in unison.” A second objection urged, perhaps with less justice, against the
                    theory is that it fails to account for the authoritative character which is felt
                    to be inherent in our sense of right and wrong—for what Butler calls the
                    “supremacy of conscience.” But those who most strongly dissent from Smith’s
                    general doctrine are warm in their admiration of the eloquence of his
                    style—sometimes, however, faulty on the side of redundancy— and the felicity of
                    his illustrations. In all its minor details, says Brown, “the work may be
                    considered as presenting a model of philosophic beauty,” and it is universally
                    admitted that the author has thrown much light on many delicate and subtle
                    phenomena of our moral nature. The minute observation and the rare ingenuity
                    which he shows in dealing with the finer traits of character and the less
                    obvious indications of feeling remind us of the similar qualities exhibited in a
                    different field in the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of Nations.</hi></p>
                <p>It is on the latter work that Smith’s fame mainly rests. Under <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Political Economy</hi> (vol. xix. pp. 365-370) will be found a
                    detailed analysis of the economic scheme contained in it, and an examination of
                    its spirit and tendency as a contribution to the philosophy of society. We have
                    there sufficiently exposed the exaggeration which represents Smith as the
                    creator of political economy. But the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of Nations</hi>
                    is, without doubt, the greatest existing book on that department of knowledge,
                    the only attempt to replace and so antiquate it—that of John Stuart Mill—having,
                    notwithstanding its partial usefulness, on the whole decidedly failed. Buckle,
                    however, goes too far when he pronounces it “the most important book ever
                    written,” just as he similarly exceeds due measure when he makes its author
                    superior as a philosopher to Hume. Mackintosh more justly said of it that it
                    stands on a level with the treatise <hi rend="italic">De Jure Belli et
                    Pacis,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Human Understanding,</hi> and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Spirit of Laws,</hi> in the respect that these four works are
                    severally the most conspicuous landmarks in the progress of the sciences with
                    which they deal. And, when he added that the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of
                    Nations</hi> was “perhaps the only book which produced an immediate, general,
                    and irrevocable change in some of the most important parts of the legislation of
                    all civilized states,” he scarcely spoke too strongly if we understand him as
                    referring to its influence as an agent of demolition. It certainly operated
                    powerfully through the harmony of its critical side with the tendencies of the
                    half-century which followed its publication to the assertion of personal freedom
                    and “natural rights.” It discredited the economic policy of the past, and
                    promoted the overthrow of institutions which had come down from earlier times,
                    but were unsuited to modern society. As a theoretic treatment of social economy,
                    and therefore as a guide to social reconstruction and practice in the future, it
                    is provisional, not definitive. But here too it has rendered eminent service: it
                    has established many truths and dissipated many obstinate prejudices; it has
                    raised the views of all thinking men on national wealth to a higher level; and,
                    when the study of its subject comes to be systematized on the basis of a general
                    social philosophy more complete and durable than Smith’s, no contributions to
                    that final construction will be found so valuable as his.</p>
                <p>Buckle has the idea that the two principal works of Smith, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theory of Moral Sentiments</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of
                    Nations,</hi> are mutually complementary parts of one great scheme, in which
                    human nature is intended to be dealt with as a whole,—the former exhibiting the
                    operation of the benevolent feelings, the latter of what, by a singular
                    nomenclature, inadmissible since Butler wrote, he calls “the passion of
                    selfishness.” In each division the motor contemplated is regarded as acting
                    singly, without any interference of the opposite principle.</p>
                <p>This appears to be an artificial and misleading notion. Neither in the plan of
                    Smith’s university course nor in the well-known passage at the end of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Moral Sentiments</hi> is there any indication of his having
                    conceived such a bipartite scheme. The object of the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of
                    Nations</hi> is surely in no sense psychological, as is that of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Moral Sentiments.</hi> The purpose of the work is to exhibit
                    social phenomena, not to demonstrate their source in the mental constitution of
                    the individual. And Buckle seems to have fallen into the error of confounding
                    “sympathy” with benevolence, or at least of regarding their spheres as
                    coextensive. It is only in his ethical treatise that Smith carries back the
                    pursuit of wealth to its ultimate motive; and, when he does so, instead of
                    tracing it to a selfish principle, which is to be placed in contrast with
                    sympathy, he expressly declares it to have its origin in “a regard to the
                    sentiments of mankind”; in other words, he makes it a consequence of the desire
                    of sympathy.</p>
                <p>In relation to Smith’s personality, which is at present our principal object, it
                    may be observed that his moral features are exhibited in an interesting way in
                    his great work. The most marked characteristics thus reflected are his strong
                    sympathy with the working classes, his contempt for vulgar politics, and his
                    hatred of the spirit of monopoly,—the last manifesting itself especially in his
                    suspicion of the public conduct of merchants and manufacturers. The first of
                    these sentiments breaks out in several places, as in the discussion of the laws
                    of settlement and in the remarks on combinations, and notably in the
                    often-quoted passage where he says: “It is but equity that those who feed,
                    clothe, and lodge the whole body of the people should have such a share of the
                    produce of their own labour as to be themselves tolerably well fed, clothed, and
                    lodged.” He has no respect for that “insidious and crafty animal, vulgarly
                    called a statesman or politician,” and complains that the “sneaking arts of
                    underling tradesmen” are erected into political maxims for the conduct of a
                    great empire. “All for ourselves and nothing for other people seems in every age
                    of the world to have been the vile maxim of the masters of mankind.” The project
                    of shutting out every other nation from a share in the benefits of our colonial
                    trade he brands as an “invidious and malignant” one. He never tires of
                    condemning the “mean rapacity,” the “monopolizing spirit,” the “impertinent
                    jealousy,” the “interested sophistry” of the capitalist class. “Our merchants
                    and manufacturers,” he says—and the remark is not yet out of date—“complain much
                    of the effect of high wages in raising the price, and thereby lessening the
                    sale, of their goods both at home and abroad; they say nothing concerning the
                    bad effects of high profits; they are silent with respect to the pernicious
                    effects of their own gains; they complain only of those of other people.” “Their
                    interest is never exactly the same with that of the public; they have generally
                    an interest to deceive and even to oppress the public; and they accordingly have
                    upon many occasions both deceived and oppressed it.” This class he regarded, in
                    fact, as corrupting by its selfishness the policy of the European nations and in
                    particular of England, and as constituting the strength of the opposition, which
                    he feared would be insuperable, to a system of commercial freedom. The general
                    impression of its author which the book leaves behind it is that of a large,
                    healthy, and generous nature, earnest in insisting on fair play for all and
                    prompt to denounce with contemptuous vehemence anything which wore the
                    appearance of injustice.</p>
                <p>Our principal authority for the biography of Smith is Dugald Stewart’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Account of his Life and Writings,</hi> originally read (1793)
                    before the Royal Society of Edinburgh, and afterwards prefixed to Smith’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Essays on Philosophical Subjects,</hi> as edited by Black and
                    Hutton. Additional particulars are given in Brougham’s <hi rend="italic">Men of
                    Letters and Science,</hi> Burton’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Hume,</hi> and
                    Alexander Carlyle’s <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi>; and some
                    characteristic anecdotes of him will be found in <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of
                    the Life and Works of Sir John Sinclair</hi> (1837). For comments on his <hi
                    rend="italic">Theory of Moral Sentiments,</hi> see, besides Stewart, as cited
                    above, Dr T. Brown’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of the Human Mind,</hi> lects.
                    80 and 81; Sir J. Mackintosh’s <hi rend="italic">Dissertation on the Progress of
                    Ethical Philosophy;</hi> J. A. Farrer’s <hi rend="italic">Adam Smith</hi>
                    (1881), in the series entitled <hi rend="italic">English Philosophers</hi>; and
                    the art. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ethics</hi> in the present work. On the <hi
                    rend="italic">Wealth of Nations,</hi> the student may consult the prefaces to
                    M‘Culloch's, Rogers’s, and Nicholson’s editions of that work; Rogers’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Historical Gleanings</hi> (1869); the art. “Smith” in Coquelin and
                    Guillaumin’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de l'Economie Politique·,</hi>
                    Bagehot’s <hi rend="italic">Economic Studies</hi> (1880); and Cossa’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Guide to the Study of Political Economy</hi> (Eng. trans., 1880),
                    chap. v., where the author has enumerated the most important memoirs by foreign
                    writers on Smith as an economist. (J. K. I.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
