<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0046-0031-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SICYON (9th edition, volume 22, page 31)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180699">Workshops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896967">Dorians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978609">Ionians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m29x">Dorians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03xx31">Shields</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n46/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SICYON</label> was a city in the east of Achaia, Greece,
                    about 2 miles inland from the Corinthian Gulf, situated on and below a hill in
                    the angle formed by the confluence<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n47/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0047-0032"/> of the rivers Asopus and Helisson; the site
                    is now occupied by the village of Vasilika. It possessed a harbour on the coast
                    round which was a well-fortified town, which was almost a suburb of the main
                    city (<hi rend="italic">∑ικυωvίωv λιµήv</hi>). The ancient and native form of
                    the name was <hi rend="italic">∑ϵκυὠv</hi>. The earliest inhabitants were
                    Ionians; but it was conquered by the Dorian invaders of Argolis, who extended
                    their dominion over Corinth, Sicyon, and the whole valley of the Asopus.
                    Phalces, son of the first Dorian king of Argos, Temenus, was said to have been
                    the conqueror of Sicyon and founder (<hi rend="italic">oἰκιστής</hi>) of the
                    Dorian city, which, like Corinth, probably continued for a long time subject to
                    the powerful kings of Argos. The population of the Dorian Sicyon was divided
                    into four tribes; the Dorian conquerors constituted three—viz., the usual Dorian
                    tribes Hylleis, Dymanes, and Pamphyli—and a part of the pre-Dorian population
                    constituted the fourth tribe, which was called Aegialeis. (Previous to the
                    Dorian conquest the city bore, according to Strabo, the name Aegiali, or
                    according to Pausanias Aegialeia.) The rest of the ancient population were
                    reduced to the state of serfs, called <hi rend="italic">κaτωva-κοϕόροι</hi> or
                        <hi rend="italic">κορυνηϕόροι,</hi> whose position was similar to that of
                    the Helots in Sparta. As in most of the cities of Greece, the conflict between
                    the aristocracy and the commons, who were superior in number but inferior in
                    organization, in education, and in power, resulted in the rise of a dynasty of
                    tyrants, the Orthagoridae, who destroyed the rule of the Dorian oligarchy and
                    reigned in Sicyon for a century, from about 665 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    Under the strong hand of these dynasts Sicyon attained great wealth. Lying near
                    the great commercial centre Corinth, and possessing a harbour, it shared in the
                    immense development of trade with the Italian peninsula which took place in the
                    8th and 7th centuries. Its marine was considerable, though apparently never of
                    the first rank; at a later time it sent fifteen triremes to fight against the
                    Persians at Salamis. The bronze work of Sicyon was renowned, as Strabo mentions;
                    and we may gain some conception of its style from some of the bronzes found at
                    Olympia, which have probably been fabricated either at Sicyon or in the closely
                    connected workshops of Argos. The Daedalid sculptors Dipoenus and Scyllis from
                    Crete settled in Sicyon about the beginning of the 6th century, and gave the
                    first impulse to a school of art, working mainly in bronze or in wood covered
                    with bronze, which lasted for some generations at Sicyon, Corinth, and Argos,
                    and played a very prominent part in the development of Greek art. The early
                    bronze work of the Sicyo-Argive workshops in all probability formed the model
                    after which the Hesiodic description of the Shield of Hercules was composed by a
                    poet of the 7th century. The fame of Sicyonian bronze work gave rise to the
                    epithet <hi rend="italic">Tϵλχιvία</hi>, which was sometimes applied to the
                    city. Terra-cotta vases which have been fabricated at Sicyon are found in
                    Etruria, whither they were exported in the Italian trade. They closely resemble
                    in style the vases of Corinth, from which they are distinguished by the peculiar
                    form of the letter <hi rend="italic">epsilon</hi> in the inscriptions painted on
                    them, and they usually belong to the 6th century. The market-gardens of the
                    fertile Asopus valley supplied the populous Corinth with fruit and vegetables.
                    At least in later times the fine shoes made in Sicyon were widely used in
                    Greece. In the 4th century Sicyon continued to be one of the foremost states in
                    an artistic point of view. The Sicyonian school of painting was founded by
                    Eupompus, and some of the greatest foreign artists, such as Pamphilus and
                    Apelles, studied in it. Lysippus also, who gave a new impulse and tone to Greek
                    sculpture, was a native of Sicyon.</p>
                <p>In the dynasty of the Orthagoridae Andreas began to reign about 665, his son
                    Myron before 648; of Aristonymus, son of Myron, nothing is known; Myron II., son
                    of Aristonymus, reigned seven years; Isodamus, brother and murderer of Myron
                    II., reigned a short time, and about 596 was replaced by his younger brother
                    Clisthenes, who ruled till about 565. The dynasty ended with Clisthenes, who had
                    no son; but his institutions continued in force for sixty years longer, until
                    Sicyon came under the influence of the Peloponnesian confederacy, in which the
                    Dorian Sparta was the chief power. The policy of the Orthagoridae had always
                    been strongly anti-Dorian, and under the Dorian reaction the most unfavourable
                    colour was given to their actions; hence grew the extremely unpleasant picture
                    of them in the pages of Herodotus, who gives the current Peloponnesian accounts
                    of the 5th century. These accounts are contradicted by the long rule of the
                    dynasty and the permanence of their policy after their extinction. Myron I. won
                    a chariot-race at Olympia in 648, and dedicated a bronze <hi rend="italic"
                        >ϴάλαμos</hi> (probably a large chest or <hi rend="italic">ναΐσκος</hi>
                    covered with bronze), with an inscription, which Pausanias saw in the Olympian
                    treasury of the Sicyonians. The building of this treasury is ascribed to him by
                    Pausanias, but excavation has shown that the building is not earlier than 500;
                    it consists of a simple cella with a pronaos <hi rend="italic">in antis,</hi>
                    and is built of Sicyonian stones, cut and numbered at Sicyon, and thence
                    transported by water to Olympia. Clisthenes was the most powerful and famous of
                    the Sicyonian despots, and he continued the anti-Dorian policy of his
                    predecessors; but, as we have seen, it is impossible to trust the details of his
                    action as given by Herodotus (v. 67). He is said to have forbidden the
                    rhapsodists to recite the epics in which the fame of Dorian heroes was sung, and
                    to have encouraged the worship of Dionysus, a non-Dorian deity. Another object
                    of his policy was to secure the favour of the Delphian oracle, and he used all
                    his power in the Sacred War on the side of Delphi against Crissa (590 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> He won a victory in the chariot-race at Delphi
                    in 582. Clisthenes had no son, and he desired to obtain the noblest of the
                    Greeks as a husband for his daughter Agariste. The story of the wooing of
                    Agariste as it was current in Athens, probably in poetic form, has been
                    preserved by Herodotus. Clisthenes, when declared victor at the Olympian games
                    (572 or 568), invited the best of the Greeks to Sicyon. Twelve representatives
                    from all parts of Greece (whose names are chosen by the poet with little regard
                    to chronological possibility) assembled there and spent a year as guests of
                    Clisthenes. First among them all were two Athenians, one of whom, Megacles the
                    Alcmaeonid, was at last preferred to his rival Hippoclides; and the careless
                    remark of the latter, “Hippoclides cares not,” became proverbial. Megacles and
                    Agariste were parents of Clisthenes, who became famous after 510 as the second
                    founder of the Athenian democracy, and their grand-daughter Agariste was mother
                    of the still more famous Pericles. When Sicyon again came under the Dorian
                    influence shortly before 500, the oligarchical form of government was
                    reintroduced and lasted till about 369, when the democracy was again
                    established; but its form was used by Euphron to exercise his own power, and
                    after him a series of tyrants ruled the city, till in 251 Aratus reintroduced
                    the democratic government and Sicyon joined the Achaean league. Under the Roman
                    rule Sicyon profited by the destruction of Corinth in 146 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.c.</hi>; it received part of the Corinthian territory together with the
                    presidency of the Isthmian games. But it sank into decay as Corinth revived, and
                    was almost depopulated when Pausanias visited it in the 2d century after Christ.
                    Among the bishoprics of the Byzantine time New Sicyon occurs regularly; it is
                    probable that this was a town on a new site near the old city. (W. M. RA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
