<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0616-0593-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STRAW MANUFACTURES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 593</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205585">Panama</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1134466">Straw</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1064480">Pipe</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1064723">Piping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm20">Pipe</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr59">Braiding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n616/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STRAW MANUFACTURES</label>. Straw forms the raw material of
                    some not unimportant industries. It serves for the thatching of roofs, for a
                    paper-making material, for ornamenting small surfaces as a “straw mosaic,” for
                    plaiting into door and table mats, mattresses, Ac., and for weaving and plaiting
                    into light baskets, artificial flowers, Ac. These applications, however, are
                    insignificant in comparison with the place occupied by straw as a raw material
                    for the straw bonnets and hats worn by both sexes. Of the various materials
                    which go to the fabrication of plaited head-gear the most important is wheaten
                    straw. It is only in certain areas that straw suitable for making plaits is
                    produced. The straw must have a certain length of “pipe” between the knots, must
                    possess a clear delicate golden colour, and must not be brittle. The most
                    valuable straw for plaits is grown in Tuscany, and from it the well-known Tuscan
                    plaits and Leghorn hats are made. The straw of Tuscany, specially grown for
                    plaiting, is distinguished into three qualities,— <hi rend="italic">Pontederas
                    Semone</hi> being the finest, <hi rend="italic">Mazzuolο</hi> the second
                    quality, from which the bulk of the plaits are made, while from the third
                    quality, <hi rend="italic">Santa Fioro,</hi> only “Tuscan pedals” and braids are
                    plaited. The wheat-seed for these straws is sown very thickly on comparatively
                    elevated and arid land, and it sends up long attenuated stalks. When the grain
                    in the ear is about half developed the straw is pulled up by the roots, dried in
                    the sun, and subsequently spread out for several successive days to be bleached
                    under the influence of alternate sunlight and night-dews. The pipe of the upper
                    joint alone is selected for plaiting, the remainder of the straw being used for
                    other purposes. These pipes are made up in small bundles, bleached in sulphur
                    fumes in a closed chest, assorted into sizes, and so prepared for the plaiters.
                    Straw plaiting is a domestic industry among the women and young children of
                    Tuscany and some parts of Emilia. Tuscan plaits and hats vary enormously in
                    quality and value; the plait of a hat of good quality may represent the work of
                    four or five days, while hats of the highest quality may each occupy six to nine
                    months in making. The finest work is excessively trying to the eyes of the
                    plaiters, who can at most give to it two or three hours’ labour daily. The
                    exports of plaits and manufactured hats from Leghorn average in value £480,000
                    annually, about one half of the goods going to America.</p>
                <p>The districts around Luton in Bedfordshire and the neighbouring counties have,
                    since the beginning of the 17th century, been the British home of the
                    straw-plait industry. The straw of certain varieties of wheat cultivated in that
                    region is, in favourable seasons, possessed of a fine bright colour and due
                    tenacity and strength. The straw is cut as in ordinary harvesting, but is
                    allowed to dry in the sun before binding. Subsequently straws are selected from
                    the sheaves, and of these the pipes of the two upper joints are taken for
                    plaiting. The pipes are assorted into sizes by passing them through graduated
                    openings in a grilled wire frame, and those of good colour are bleached by the
                    fumes of sulphur. Spotted and discoloured straws are dyed either in pipe or in
                    plait. The plaiters work up the material in a damp state, either into whole
                    straw or split straw plaits. Split straws are prepared with the aid of a small
                    instrument having a projecting point which enters the straw pipe, and from which
                    radiate the number of knife-edged cutters into which the straw is to be split.
                    The plaiting of straw in the Luton district formerly gave employment to many
                    thousands of women and young children; but now vast quantities of plaits are
                    imported at a very cheap rate from Canton in China. The result is that, while
                    the Luton trade is extending, the number of persons it there gives occupation is
                    greatly diminished. In 1871 about 50,000 persons<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n617/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0617-0594"/> were employed in the straw industry, and in 1881
                    the number was only about 31,000. The plaits are sewed partly by hand and in a
                    special sewing-machine, and the hats or bonnets are finished by stiffening with
                    gelatin size, and blocking into shape with the aid of heat and powerful
                    pressure, according to the dictates of fashion. The annual output of the
                    straw-plait industry in England is estimated to amount in value to about
                    £4,000,000.</p>
                <p>In the United States straw-plait work is principally centred in the State of
                    Massachusetts.</p>
                <p>Many substances besides straw are worked into plaits and braids for bonnets.
                    Among these may be noticed thin strips of willow and cane, and the fronds of
                    numerous palms. “Brazilian” hats made from the fronds of the palmetto palms, <hi
                    rend="italic">Sabal Palmetto</hi> and S. <hi rend="italic">mexicana,</hi> are
                    now largely made at St Albans. The famous Panama hats, fine qualities of which
                    at one time were worth £20 to £30 each, are made from the leaves of the screw
                    pine, <hi rend="italic">Carludovica palmata.</hi> They are now manufactured at
                    Dresden, Strasburg, and Nancy, and can be purchased at 30s. or £2.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
