<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0180-0165-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMELL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 165</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mp4vr0s">Edentata</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tm5k">Valentines</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p24h">Papuans</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d52v">Bones</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4fx73z68">Bone</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727k92">Nose</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n17f">Skull</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1163796">Valentines</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1939238">Negroes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:805532">Allene</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1052751">Papuans</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:835916">Bone</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:835991">Bones</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1039494">Nose</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1047771">Organisms</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n180/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMELL</label> is a sensation excited by the contact with the
                    olfactory region of certain substances, usually in a gaseous condition and
                    necessarily in a state of fine subdivision. The sense is widely distributed
                    throughout the animal kingdom. The lower animals, especially those breathing in
                    water, become cognizant of the presence of odoriferous matter near them without
                    touch, vision, or hearing, and we suppose that they do so by some sense of taste
                    or smell, or a combination of both. In such cases smell has been appropriately
                    termed “taste at a distance,” by which is meant that particles of matter may be
                    diffused through the water so as to come into contact with the terminal organ
                    and give rise to a sensation such as would have been excited had the matter from
                    which the particles emanated come directly into contact with the nerve-endings.
                    It is therefore of no great importance whether such sensations in humble aquatic
                    organisms are termed taste or smell. In the higher air-breathing animals,
                    however, the senses are differentiated: that of taste is found at the entrance
                    of the alimentary canal, whilst that of smell guards the opening of the
                    respiratory tract. This view assists in the interpretation of various structures
                    met with in the lower forms which have been fairly regarded by naturalists as
                    olfactory organs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Comparative View of Olfactory Organs.—</hi> In various <hi
                    rend="italic">Medusae</hi> pit-like depressions, lined with ciliated epithelium,
                    on the dorsal side of the excavation in which the “marginal” bodies are found,
                    have been called olfactory regions. In many <hi rend="italic">Arthropoda</hi>
                    the sense of smell is located in delicate tubular structures, or conical
                    projections, found on the antennae and connected with nerves. Similar organs are
                    met with in <hi rend="italic">Crustacea.</hi> In <hi rend="italic">Cyclops
                    (Copepοda), Isopoda,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Thoracostraca</hi> olfactory
                    hairs are present as delicate appendages of the anterior antennae, chiefly in
                    the male sex. In <hi rend="italic">Schizopoda</hi> the anterior antennae have a
                    comb-like prominence bearing a great number of olfactory hairs. <hi
                    rend="italic">Insecta</hi> have olfactory organs largely developed, usually in
                    the form of hairs, cones, or knobs on the antennae, and connected with
                    gangliated nerve-endings. Olfactory organs are also met with in <hi
                    rend="italic">Mollusca</hi>: in <hi rend="italic">Larmellibranchiata</hi> they
                    appeal· as hairs on the margin of the mantle; in aquatic <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gasteropoda</hi> as tufts of hairs scattered over the surface of the body and
                    specially aggregated in those parts where<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n181/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0181-0166"/> tactile sensibility is highly developed; in
                    terrestrial <hi rend="italic">Gasteropoda</hi> the antennae have on their end
                    plates a number of club-shaped cells with rods, which are held to be olfactory,
                    and recently in the same class Sprengel has shown that an organ “which was
                    supposed to be a rudimentary gill, and is innervated from the supra-intestinal
                    ganglion,” has an olfactory function. In <hi rend="italic">Ascidians</hi> the
                    olfactory region is believed to be a depression on the wall of the pharynx,
                    situated in front of the ganglion, and lined with ciliated epithelium.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Fishes</hi> the olfactory organs consist of a membrane (the
                    pituitary membrane) lining one or two pits, to which the olfactory or first pair
                    of cranial nerves are distributed. This highly vascular membrane is usually
                    thrown into numerous folds, so as to admit of an extensive surface being packed
                    into small space, and it is covered by ciliated epithelium. In the lowest
                    vertebrate, <hi rend="italic">Amphioxus,</hi> the olfactory organ is a simple
                    unsymmetrical pit at the anterior end of the nervous system. In the hag fishes
                    (<hi rend="italic">Myxinidse)</hi> the olfactory pit has a posterior opening
                    which pierces the palate and can be closed by a valvular apparatus. In the
                    lampreys (<hi rend="italic">Petromyzon)</hi> the flask-shaped nasal sac opens on
                    the top of the head, and from this a tube descends which expands into a blind
                    sac towards the base of the skull. In all other fishes the olfactory organs are
                    double and have no communication with the mouth. In osseous fishes the olfactory
                    capsules or sacs are covered with skin which is usually pierced by two openings
                    for each sac. Some, such as the wrasses, have a single nasal opening; and where
                    there are two the anterior can be closed by a valve. The olfactory region may be
                    extensive owing to the pituitary membrane being thrown into plaits or folds, and
                    it may be divided into two portions, one quite smooth and the other plicated.
                    The smooth portion, probably acting as a reservoir, may be large, extending down
                    to the palate, as in the mackerel, or to the back part of the palate, as in the
                    wolf-fish (Owen). The nasal cavities exist below the snout in sharks, near the
                    angles of the mouth in the rays, and beneath the fore part of the head, behind
                    the base of the rostrum, in the sawfish. In such fishes the olfactory organ is
                    guarded by valves, containing cartilaginous plates moved by muscles, and we may
                    therefore conclude with Owen “that these fishes scent as well as smell, <hi
                    rend="italic">i. e.,</hi> actively search for odoriferous impressions by rapidly
                    changing the current of water through the olfactory sac.”</p>
                <p>The olfactory organs of <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi> are always paired
                    cavities, opening internally either anteriorly within the lips or further back,
                    as in the batrachians and salamandrines. In the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Perennibranchiates</hi> (Siren, Proteus, Axolotl) there are no outward signs of
                    olfactory organs, and the thick upper lip must be raised to bring the plicated
                    sac with its two remote orifices into view (Owen). In the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tritonidae</hi> (newts) and <hi rend="italic">Salamandrinae</hi> (salamanders)
                    the olfactory membrane is smooth and lines an oval bag having an external
                    nostril, guarded by a valvular fold of skin, and a palatal opening. Frogs and
                    toads (<hi rend="italic">Batrachia)</hi> have also an external nostril with a
                    flap of skin, and the palatal opening is wide and near the fore part of the
                    mouth. The skulls of extinct saurians of marine habits (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Ichthyosaumιs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Plesiosaurus)</hi> show that the
                    external nostrils opened near the orbits at a distance from the muzzle. In
                    snakes (<hi rend="italic">Ophidia)</hi> the external nostrils are double, and
                    the internal nostril is single and in the median line. In water snakes the
                    external orifices can be closed by valves.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Chelonia</hi> (turtles, tortoises) and in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Crocodilia</hi> the external nasal opening is single and near the end of the
                    snout; but in <hi rend="italic">Chelonia</hi> the nostrils are really distinct,
                    although their external apertures coincide. In the turtle the nasal cavity is
                    large and contains a twisted shell-like cartilage, so as to give extent of
                    surface to the darkly pigmented and highly vascular pituitary membrane. In the
                    crocodiles and alligators the nostrils can be closed by a valvular lobe, and in
                    the gavials (<hi rend="italic">Rhamphostoma gangeticum</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Rhynchosuchus schlegelii)</hi> the integument can be raised round
                    the nostril in the form of a tube so as to bring the orifice to the surface of
                    the water without exposing the other parts of the head (Owen). In all <hi
                    rend="italic">Crocodilia</hi> the nasal cavity is of great length, commencing at
                    the fore part of the muzzle and ending beneath the occiput by a single aperture,
                    and the surface of this long olfactory meatus is increased by the meatus
                    communicating with large cells or sinuses. In snakes and lizards a second
                    olfactory organ is found embedded between the turbinals and the vomer and is
                    known as “Jacobson’s organ.” It has the form of a cup or depression round a
                    cartilaginous papilla and is supplied by a nerve which arises from the end of
                    the olfactory lobe.</p>
                <p>The olfactory organs of <hi rend="italic">Birds</hi> are somewhat similar to
                    those of the cold-blooded reptiles and amphibians in that “the external nostrils
                    are simple perforations, having no movable cartilages or muscles provided for
                    dilating or contracting their apertures, as in mammalia” (Owen). The extent of
                    the olfactory surface is increased by projections and folds of turbinated bones
                    and not by large accessory cavities. With the exception of the apteryx and
                    dinornis, the olfactory nerve passes out of the skull by a single foramen. The
                    external nostrils are in the majority of birds placed at the sides of the upper
                    mandible; but in some cases, as in the toucans, they are found at the base of
                    the bill, and in the apteryx they open at the extremity of the long upper
                    mandible. In herons the apertures are so small as scarcely to admit the point of
                    a pin; and in the pelicans they are wanting, and odours get access to the
                    olfactory organ from the palate. The <hi rend="italic">Rasores</hi> (scratching
                    birds) have the nostrils defended by a scale, and the crows (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Corvidae)</hi> have a bunch of stiff feathers for the same purpose. The septum
                    or partition between the nostrils is usually complete and is formed of bone and
                    cartilage. The outer wall of each nasal passage is furnished with three turbinal
                    or twisted shell-like bones, of which the middle is the largest, thus affording
                    a considerable extent of olfactory surface. In most birds there are two
                    posterior nasal apertures communicating with the palate; but in some, as in the
                    cormorant and gannet, the passages unite and there is only one opening. In birds
                    the upper part of the nasal passage is more especially devoted to the sense of
                    smell, whilst the lower part may be regarded as the beginning of the respiratory
                    tract. This is indicated by the arrangement of the nerves, the olfactory nerve
                    being distributed to the membrane covering the septum and the superior and
                    middle turbinated bones, whilst the lower portion and lower turbinals are
                    supplied by the fifth nerve,—a nerve of general sensibility. The upper turbinals
                    reach their greatest development in the apteryx, where they are attached,
                    according to Owen, to the whole outer part of the prefrontals. This bird has
                    amongst birds the largest olfactory nerves in proportion to its size, and it
                    would appear to be guided by the sense of smell to the worms that form its food.
                    A contrast as regards the anatomical arrangements for the olfactory sense is
                    well seen on comparing the turkey with the vulture. In the turkey the olfactory
                    nerve is small, about one-fifth the size of that in the vulture, and is
                    distributed over a small middle turbinal, there being no extension over a
                    superior turbinal. The vulture, on the other hand, has a large nerve and the
                    olfactory region is extensive, owing to the largely developed superior turbinal
                    bone. There can be no doubt that the carrion - eating vulture is guided from
                    great distances to its food by the sense of smell, although it will be assisted
                    by its powerful sense of vision.</p>
                <p>The sense of smell reaches its highest development in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mammalia.</hi> The anatomical surface is enormously extended in many cases, not
                    only by the complication of the ethmoidal labyrinth, but also by the nasal
                    passages communicating with spaces in the neighbouring cranial and facial bones.
                    The olfactory nerves also are very numerous and arise from a special encephalic
                    centre. They pass out of the skull by numerous holes in the cribriform or
                    sieve-like plate of the prefrontal bone, which, on account of this peculiarity,
                    is called the ethmoid bone. These nerves ramify on the olfactory membrane,
                    covering the upper or ethmo-turbinal bones. The cavity containing the organ of
                    smell is bounded by the prefrontal, vomerine, nasal, sphenoid, pterygoid,
                    palatine, maxillary, and premaxillary bones, and it is usually in connexion with
                    air-cavities or sinuses in many or all of the bones of the skull. The median
                    partition by which the two nostrils are formed consists of bone and cartilage
                    and is built up by processes of the prefrontals, the vomer, and by the ridges of
                    the nasals, palatines, maxillaries, and premaxillaries with which the vomer
                    articulates. Each passage thus formed is the beginning of the respiratory tract,
                    and is continued forwards into a more or less mobile part called a nose, snout,
                    or proboscis, whilst posteriorly it communicates with the upper part of the
                    pharynx, into which opens the windpipe. On the outer wall there are three
                    turbinal bones—superior, middle, and inferior—dividing partially the nasal
                    cavity into three meatuses or passages. The superior meatus is between the
                    superior and middle turbinated bones, the middle meatus between the middle and
                    inferior turbinated bones, and the inferior meatus between the inferior
                    turbinated bones and the floor of the nose (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Anatomy,</hi> vol. i. p. 823, fig. 7; also vol. i. pl. XIX. fig. 2). Many of
                    the lower mammals have in addition a process from the frontal and nasal bones,
                    sometimes called the superior spongy bone, which is not the same as the superior
                    turbinated, as described in the anatomy of the human being. The extent of
                    olfactory surface is enormously increased by numerous plicae or processes of
                    bone which to a great extent mask the comparatively simple arrangement above
                    described. In <hi rend="italic">Ornithorhynchus</hi> there is a single olfactory
                    nerve escaping through an aperture in the prefrontal bone; in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Echidna,</hi> the other member of the <hi rend="italic">Monotremata,</hi> there
                    are numerous olfactory nerves and a large development of ethmo-turbinals. In
                    many <hi rend="italic">Marsupials</hi> the sense of smell is largely developed,
                    and in some (<hi rend="italic">Osphranter)</hi> the turbinated bones are so
                    large as to cause a lateral bulging of the nasal cavity, forming a marked
                    feature of the skull. In <hi rend="italic">Rodents</hi> the ethmo-turbinals may
                    be subdivided into lamellae so as to increase the olfactory surface; such is the
                    case in the common hare. In the porcupine the sinuses developed from the
                    olfactory cavity are of large size, forming a spongy mass surrounding the cavity
                    of the skull in which the anterior portion of the brain lies. In <hi
                    rend="italic">Insectivora</hi> the olfactory surface is very large. Thus in the
                    mole the ethmo-turbinal has not fewer than eight lamellae or plates and the
                    external nose is developed into a snout capable of considerable movement. Such a
                    snout is very large and mobile in the elephant shrews. Armadillos and ant-eaters
                    (<hi rend="italic">Edentata)</hi> have a strong sense of smell. Thus in <hi
                    rend="italic">Dasypus</hi> the nasal portion of the skull is about equal in<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n182/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0182-0167"/> volume to all the rest, and in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chlamydophorus</hi> (dwarf armadillo) the frontals are raised “into a pair of
                    domes” by sinuses in them communicating with the large olfactory cavity. In most
                    armadillos the external nose is strengthened by small bones. The air sinuses in
                    the sloth extend upwards into the frontals and downwards into the sphenoid bone.
                    No <hi rend="italic">Cetaceans</hi> have olfactory organs, except the baleen or
                    whalebone whales, and thus are devoid of the sense of smell. In the manatee (<hi
                    rend="italic">Sirenia)</hi> the nasal openings are placed far forwards and have
                    movable cartilages, and the bony walls of the nasal passages are not extensive
                    in proportion to the size of the rest of the skull. The elephants (<hi
                    rend="italic">Proboscidea)</hi> have the part of the nasal cavity concerned in
                    smell contracted and narrow, but the cavity is prolonged into the trunk, at the
                    end of which are the nostrils; the nasal cavity communicates with sinuses
                    permeating every bone of the cranium. The tapirs have a shorter but very mobile
                    proboscis, and the development of the nasal passages is extensive. The horse has
                    the power of dilating and contracting each nostril, and the cribriform plates
                    transmit very numerous olfactory nerves from the olfactory bulbs, which are
                    large in proportion to the size of the rest of the brain. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Suidae</hi> (swine) have a large and complex olfactory region; the accessory
                    sinuses or spaces attain a great development; the nose is prolonged and
                    truncate, the cartilages forming a complete tube, which is a continuation of the
                    bony nostrils, and these tubes open on a naked disk. In the ox and sheep the
                    olfactory region is large, but not so large as in the horse. The external,
                    glandular, and moist part of the nose is a linear tract running from the
                    mid-furrow of the upper lip to the oblique nostril in the sheep, and this
                    portion passes through many gradations in size, as seen in the roebuck,
                    fallow-deer, red-deer, and the ox. The <hi rend="italic">Carnivora</hi> have the
                    ethmo-turbinal and maxillo-turbinal regions even more largely developed than in
                    <hi rend="italic">Herbivora,</hi> and the latter portion reaches its maximum in
                    the seals, where “these turbinals seem to block up the entry of the nasal
                    respiratory passages, and must warm the air in arctic latitudes as well as
                    arrest every indication from the effluvia of alimentary substances or prey”
                    (Owen). In <hi rend="italic">Quadrumana</hi> the nasal chamber becomes shorter
                    and gains in depth, but not proportionally. In the platyrhine monkeys the
                    cartilage forming the septum becomes flattened anteriorly, pushing the nostrils
                    outwards. In the catarrhines this flattening is much less, so that the nostrils
                    are approximated. In both groups the nostrils are not terminal. In <hi
                    rend="italic">Man</hi> the chief characteristic is the prominence of the fore
                    part of the chambers, with the nostrils on the lower surface, and the nose is
                    supported by eleven pieces of cartilage, of which one is medial, the others
                    lateral, in five pairs. The size and form of the septal or medial cartilage
                    mainly determine the shape and prominence of the nose. It is least developed but
                    thickest in the Negro and Papuan races. (For a description of the muscles of the
                    nose in man, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> vol. i. p. 837.)</p>
                <p>The interior of the nose is divided physiologically into two portions,—(1) the
                    upper <hi rend="italic">(regio olfactoria),</hi> which embraces the upper part
                    of the septum, the upper turbinated bone, and a portion of the middle turbinated
                    bone; and (2) the lower portion of the cavity <hi rend="italic">(regio
                    respiratoria).</hi> The olfactory region proper has a thicker mucous membrane
                    than the respiratory; it is covered by a single layer of epithelial cells, often
                    branched at their lower ends and containing a yellow or brownish red pigment;
                    and it contains peculiar tubular glands named “Bowman’s glands.”</p>
                <p>The respiratory portion contains ordinary serous glands. In the olfactory region
                    also are the terminal organs of smell. These are long narrow cells passing to
                    the surface between the columnar epithelium covering the surface. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> vol. i. p. 885, fig. 76.) The body of the cell is
                    spindle-shaped and it sends up to the surface a delicate rod-like filament,
                    whilst the deeper part is continuous with varicose nerve-filaments, the ends of
                    the olfactory nerve. In the frog the free end terminates in fine hairs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Physical Causes of Smell.—</hi> Electrical or thermal stimuli
                    do not usually give rise to olfactory sensations. Althaus states that electrical
                    stimulation caused a sensation of the smell of phosphorus. To excite smell it is
                    usually supposed that substances must be present in the atmosphere in a state of
                    fine subdivision, or existing as vapours or gases. The fineness of the particles
                    is remarkable, because if the air conveying an odour be filtered through a tube
                    packed with cotton wool and inserted into the nose a smell is still discernible.
                    This proceeding completely removes from the air organisms less than the <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100000</hi> th of an inch in
                    diameter which are the causes of putrefaction and fermentation. A grain or two
                    of musk will scent an apartment for years and at the end of the time no
                    appreciable loss of weight can be detected. Substances exciting smell are no
                    doubt usually gases or vapours. Only a few tentative efforts have been made to
                    connect the sense with the chemical constitution of the substance. One of the
                    most important of these is in an <hi rend="italic">Essay on Smell,</hi> by Dr.
                    William Ramsay of University College, Bristol. The following gases have no smell
                    :—hydrogen, oxygen, nitrogen, water gas, marsh gas, olefiant gas, carbon
                    monoxide, hydrochloric acid, formic acid vapour, nitrous oxide, and ammonia. (It
                    is necessary, of course, to distinguish between the sensation of smell and the
                    irritant action of such a gas as ammonia.) The gases exciting smell are
                    chlorine, bromine, iodine, the compounds of the first two with oxygen and water,
                    nitric peroxide, vapours of phosphorus and sulphur, arsenic, antimony,
                    sulphurous acid, carbonic acid, almost all the volatile compounds of carbon
                    except those already mentioned, some compounds of selenium and tellurium, the
                    compounds of chlorine, bromine, and iodine with the above-named elements, and
                    some metals. Chlorine, bromine, iodine, sulphur, selenium, and tellurium, which
                    are volatile and give off vapour at ordinary temperatures, have each a
                    characteristic smell. Ramsay points out that as a general rule substances having
                    a low molecular weight have either no smell or simply cause irritation of the
                    nostrils. He also shows that in the carbon compounds increase of specific
                    gravity as a gas is associated to a certain point with a sensation of smell.
                    Take the marsh gas or methane series commonly called the paraffins. The first
                    two have no smell; ethane (fifteen times as heavy as hydrogen) has a faint
                    smell; and it is not till butane (thirty times heavier than hydrogen) that a
                    distinct sensation of smell is noticed. Again, a similar relation exists among
                    the alcohols. Methyl alcohol has no smell. Ethyl, or ordinary alcohol free from
                    ethers and water, has a faint smell; “and the odour rapidly becomes more marked
                    as we rise in the series, till the limit of volatility is reached, and we arrive
                    at solids with such a low vapour tension that they give off no appreciable
                    amount of vapour at the ordinary temperature.” Acids gain in odour with increase
                    in density in the form of gas. Thus formic acid is devoid of smell; acetic acid
                    has a characteristic smell; and the higher acids of the series—propionic,
                    butyric, valerianic—increase in odour. It would appear also that “the character
                    of a smell is a property of the element or group which enters into the body
                    producing the smell, and tends to make it generic.” Many compounds of chlorine,
                    hydrogen, compounds of sulphur, selenium, and tellurium, the paraffins, the
                    alcohols, the acids, the nitrites<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n183/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0183-0168"/> the amines, the pyridine series, the benzene
                    group, have each a characteristic odour. Ramsay has advanced the theory that the
                    sense of smell “is excited by vibrations of a lower period than those which give
                    rise to the sense of light or heat,” and he points out a series of important
                    facts in support of this view. He states that to produce the sensation of smell
                    a substance must have a molecular weight at least fifteen times that of
                    hydrogen. For instance, the specific gravity of marsh gas is eight (no smell),
                    of ethane fifteen (faint smell), of propane twenty-two (distinct smell). Again,
                    prussic acid has a specific gravity of fifteen, and many persons fail to detect
                    its odour. Further, Ramsay supposes that smell may be excited by vibrations, and
                    suggests that the period of vibration of the lighter molecules is too rapid to
                    affect the sense; at last a number of vibrations is reached capable of exciting
                    the sense organ; and beyond an upper limit the sense is again lost. Graham
                    pointed out that odorous substances are in general readily oxidized.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Bain, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Senses and Intellect,</hi> 3d ed., p. 152.</p></note> Tyndall showed that many
                    odorous vapours have a considerable power of absorbing heat. Taking the
                    absorptive capacity of the air as unity, the following absorptions were observed
                    in the respective cases :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Name of Perfume.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Absorption per 100.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Name of Perfume.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Absorption per 100.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Patchouli</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">30</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Lavender</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">60</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Sandal-wood</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">32</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Lemon</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Geranium</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">33</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Portugal</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">67</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Oil of cloves</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">33∙5</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Thyme</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Otto of roses</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">36∙5</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Rosemary</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">74</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Bergamot</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">44</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Oil of laurel</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Neroli</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">47</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Cassia</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">109</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In comparison with the air introduced in the experiments the weight of the odours
                    must be almost infinitely small. “Still we find that the least energetic in the
                    list produces thirty times the effect of the air, whilst the most energetic
                    produces 109 times the same effect.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Tyndall, <hi rend="italic">Contributions to Molecular
                    Physics in Domain of Radiant Heat,</hi> p. 99.</p></note></p>
                <p>Venturi, B. Prévost, and Liégeois have studied the well-known movements of
                    odoriferous particles, such as camphor, succinic acid, &amp;c., when placed on
                    the surface of water, and they have suggested that all odoriferous substances in
                    a state of fine subdivision may move in a similar way on the moist surface of
                    the olfactory membrane, and thus mechanically irritate the nerve-endings. This
                    explanation is too coarse; but it is well known that the odours of flowers are
                    most distinctly perceived in the morning, or after a shower, when the atmosphere
                    contains a considerable amount of aqueous vapour. It would appear also that the
                    odours of animal effluvia are of a higher specific gravity than the air, and do
                    not readily diffuse,—a fact which may account for the pointer and bloodhound
                    keeping their noses to the ground. Such smells are very persistent and are
                    apparently difficult to remove from any surface to which they have become
                    attached. The smell of a corpse may haunt a living person for days,
                    notwithstanding copious ablutions and change of clothes.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Liégeois, <hi rend="italic">Archiv de
                    Physiol.,</hi> 1868.</p></note><hi rend="italic">Special Physiology of
                    Smell.—</hi> It is necessary that the air containing the odour be driven
                    forcibly against the membrane. Thus the nostrils may be filled with eau de
                    Cologne, or with air impregnated with sulphuretted hydrogen, and still no odour
                    is experienced if the person does not breathe. When a sniff is made the air
                    within the nasal passages is rarefied, and, as the air rushes in to equilibrate
                    the pressure, it is forcibly propelled against the olfactory surface. The
                    olfactory surface must be moist; if it is dry, or is covered with too thick a
                    layer of mucus (as in catarrh), the sense is much weakened or lost.</p>
                <p>The first moment of contact is the most acute and the sense quickly becomes
                    blunted. The first scent of a flower is the strongest and sweetest; and after a
                    few minutes' exposure the intensity of even a foetid odour may not be perceived.
                    This fact may be accounted for on the supposition that the olfactory membrane
                    becomes quickly coated with a thin layer of matter, and that the most intense
                    effect is produced when the odoriferous substances are applied to a clean
                    surface. The intensity of smell depends on (1) the area of olfactory surface
                    affected, and (2) the degree of concentration of the odoriferous matter. It is
                    said that musk to the amount of the two-millionth of a milligramme, and one part
                    of sulphuretted hydrogen in 1,000,000 parts of air, may be perceived. If the two
                    nostrils are filled with different odorous substances, there is no mixture of
                    the odours, but we smell sometimes the one and sometimes the other (Valentin).
                    Morphia, mixed with sugar and taken as snuff, paralyses the olfactory apparatus,
                    while strychnine makes it more sensitive (Lichtenfels and Fröhlich).</p>
                <p>The delicacy of the sense is much greater in many of the lower animals than in
                    man, and it is highly probable that the dog or cat obtain information by means
                    of this sense which a human being cannot get. Odours may excite in the minds of
                    many animals vivid impressions, and they have probably a memory of smells which
                    the human being does not possess. Even in man the sense may be greatly improved
                    by exercising it. A boy, James Mitchell, was born blind, deaf, and dumb, and
                    chiefly depended on smell for keeping up a connexion with the outer world. He
                    readily observed the presence of a stranger in the room and he formed his
                    opinions of persons apparently from their characteristic smells. In some rare
                    cases, the sense of smell is congenitally absent in human beings, and it may be
                    much injured by the practice of snuffing or by diseases of the nose affecting
                    the olfactory membrane. Subjective impressions of smells, like spectral
                    illusions or sounds in the ears, are occasionally, but rarely observed in the
                    insane. Finally, it may be observed that the sense of odour gives information as
                    to the characters of food and drink and as to the purity of the air. In the
                    lower animals, also, the sense is associated with the sexual functions.</p>
                <p>See art. “Olfaction” by François Franck, in <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire
                    Encyclopédique des Sciences Médicales,</hi> 2d series, where a full historical
                    bibliography is given; Hermann’s <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der Physiologie: d.
                    Sinnesorgane: Zweiter Theil, Geruchsinne,</hi> by Prof. V. Vintschgau, p. 226;
                    Owen’s <hi rend="italic">Comp. Anatomy and Physiol. of Vertebrates</hi>; Bain,
                    <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 147; Grant Allen’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Physiological Aesthetics,</hi> p. 77; Ramsay, <hi rend="italic">Nature,</hi>
                    vol. xxvi. p. 187; and for James Mitchell’s case, see Dugald Stewart’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Works,</hi> vol. iv. p. 300. (J. G. M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
