<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0069-0054-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SILIUS ITALICUS (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    54)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dj16">Stoics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084105">Punica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133750">Stoics</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n69/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SILIUS ITALICUS</label>, a Latin epic poet, was born in 25
                    and died in 101 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> His birthplace is unknown. From
                    his cognomen Italicus the conclusion has been drawn that he came from the town
                    of Italica in Spain; but Latin usage would in that case have demanded the form
                        <hi rend="italic">Italicensis,</hi> and it is highly improbable that Martial
                    would have failed to name him among the literary celebrities of Spain in the
                    latter half of the 1st century. The conjecture that Silius was from Italica, the
                    capital of the Italian confederation during the Social War, is open to still
                    stronger objection. Most likely some ancestor of the poet acquired the title
                    “Italicus” from having been a member of one of the corporations of “Italici” who
                    are often mentioned in inscriptions from Sicily and elsewhere. In early life
                    Silius was a renowned forensic orator, later a safe and cautious politician,
                    without ability or ambition enough to be legitimately obnoxious to the cruel
                    rulers under whom he lived. But mediocrity was hardly an efficient protection
                    against the murderous whims of Nero, and Silius was generally believed to have
                    secured at once his own safety and his promotion to the consulship by putting
                    his oratorical powers to discreditable use in the judicial farces which often
                    ushered in the doom of the emperor’s victims. He was consul in the year of
                    Nero’s death (69), and is mentioned by Tacitus as having been one of two
                    witnesses who were present at the conferences between Vitellius and Flavius
                    Sabinus, the elder brother of Vespasian, when the legions from the East were
                    marching rapidly on the capital. The life of Silius after his consulship is well
                    depicted by the younger Pliny:—“He conducted himself wisely and courteously as
                    the friend of the luxurious and cruel Vitellius; he won repute by his
                    proconsulship of Asia, and obliterated by the praiseworthy use he made of his
                    leisure the stain he had incurred through his active exertions in former days.
                    In dignity and contentment, avoiding power and therefore hostility, he outlived
                    the Flavian dynasty, keeping to a private station after his governorship of
                    Asia.” His poem contains only two passages relating to the Flavians; in both
                    Domitian is eulogized as a warrior; in one he figures as a singer whose lyre is
                    sweeter than that of Orpheus himelf. Silius had evidently little taste for
                    bowing down in the house of Rimmon, and refrained from using the many
                    opportunities which his epic afforded for humouring the vanity of the imperial
                    house. He was a great student and patron of literature and art, and a passionate
                    collector. Two great Romans of the past, Cicero and Virgil, were by him
                    idealized and veritably worshipped; and he was the happy possessor of their
                    estates at Tusculum and Naples. The later life of Silius was passed on the
                    Campanian shore, hard by the tomb of Virgil, at which he offered the homage of a
                    devotee. He closely emulated the lives of his two great heroes: the one he
                    followed in composing epic verse, the other in debating philosophic questions
                    with his friends of like tastes. Among these was Epictetus, who judged him to be
                    the most philosophic spirit among the Romans of his time, and Cornutus, the
                    Stoic, rhetorician, and grammarian, who appropriately dedicated to Silius a
                    commentary upon Virgil. Though the verse of Silius is not wrapped in Stoic gloom
                    like that of Lucan, yet Stoicism lends in many places a not ungraceful gravity
                    to his poem. Silius was one of the numerous Romans of the early empire who had
                    the courage of their opinions, and carried into perfect practice the theory of
                    suicide adopted by their school. Stricken by an incurable disease, he starved
                    himself to death, keeping a cheerful countenance to the end.</p>
                <p>Whether Silius committed to writing his philosophic dialogues or not, we cannot
                    say. Chance has preserved to us his epic poem entitled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Punica,</hi> in seventeen books, and comprising some fourteen thousand
                    lines. The epics of Silius, Lucan, Statius, and Valerius Flaccus are but a few
                    waifs carried down to us by the wandering stream of time from the vast mass of
                    post-Virgilian epics. Long before Silius bethought himself of his epic all
                    possible historical and mythological themes had been worn to tatters by these
                    poets. In choosing the Second Punic War for his subject, Silius had, we know,
                    many predecessors, as he doubtless had many followers. From the time of Naevius
                    onwards every great military struggle in which the Romans had been engaged had
                    found its poet over and over again. In justice to Silius and Lucan, it should be
                    observed that the mythologic poet had a far easier task than the historic. In a
                    well-known passage Petronius pointedly describes the difficulties of the
                    historic theme. A poet, he said, who should take upon him the vast subject of
                    the civil wars would break down beneath the burden unless he were “full of
                    learning,” since he would have not merely to record facts, which the historians
                    did much better, but must possess an unshackled<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n70/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0070-0055"/> genius, to which full course must be given by
                    the use of digressions, by bringing divine beings on to the stage, and by giving
                    generally a mythologic tinge to the subject. The Latin laws of the historic epic
                    were fixed by Ennius, and were still binding when Claudian wrote. They were
                    never seriously infringed, except by Lucan, who substituted for the <hi
                        rend="italic">dei ex machina</hi> of his predecessors the vast, dim, and
                    imposing Stoic conception of destiny. By protracted application, and being (to
                    use the significant phrase of Petronius) “full of learning,” Silius had acquired
                    excellent recipes for every ingredient that went to the making of the
                    conventional historic epic. Though he is not named by Quintilian, he is probably
                    hinted at in the mention of a class of poets who, as the writer says, “write to
                    show their learning.” To seize the moments in the history, however unimportant,
                    which were capable of picturesque treatment; to pass over all events, however
                    important, which could not readily be rendered into heroics; to stuff out the
                    somewhat modern heroes to something like Homeric proportions; to subject all
                    their movements to the passions and caprices of the Olympians; to ransack the
                    poetry of the past for incidents and similes on which a slightly new face might
                    be put; to foist in by well-worn artifices episodes, however strange to the
                    subject, taken from the mythologic or historic glories of Rome and Greece,—all
                    this Silius knew how to do, as he knew his own fingers and nails. He did it all
                    with the languid grace of the inveterate connoisseur, and with a simplicity
                    foreign to his time, which sprang in part from cultivated taste and horror of
                    the venturesome word, and in part from the subdued tone of a life which had come
                    unscathed through the reigns of Caligula, Nero, and Domitian. The more
                    threadbare the theme, and the more worn the machinery, the greater the need of
                    genius. Two of the most rigid requirements of the ancient epic were abundant
                    similes and abundant single combats. But all the obvious resemblances between
                    the actions of heroic man and external nature had long been worked out, while
                    for the renovation of the single combat little could be done till the hero of
                    the Homeric type was replaced by the mediaeval knight. Silius, however, had
                    perfect poetic appreciation, with scarce a trace of poetic creativeness. No
                    writer has ever been more correctly and more uniformly judged by contemporaries
                    and by posterity alike. Only the shameless flatterer, Martial, ventured to call
                    his friend a poet as great as Virgil. But the younger Pliny gently says that he
                    wrote poems with greater diligence than talent, and that, when, according to the
                    fashion of the time, he recited them to his friends, “he sometimes found out
                    what men really thought of them.” It is indeed strange that the poem lived on.
                    Silius is never mentioned by ancient writers after Pliny except Sidonius, who,
                    under different conditions and at a much lower level, was such another as he.
                    Since the discovery of Silius by Poggio, no modern enthusiast has arisen to sing
                    his praises, and in the last sixty years he has found no editor, even for his
                    text. Eighteenth-century editors, at a time when modern Silii were numerous in
                    the field of literature and more fashionable than they have been since, found in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Punica</hi> passages not unworthy of comparison with the
                        <hi rend="italic">Hcnriade,</hi> and thought that Silius did not disgrace
                    Virgil; but even such gentle commendation is not likely to be repeated again.
                    Vet, by the purity of his taste and his Latin in an age when taste was fast
                    becoming vicious and Latin corrupt, by his presentation to us of a type of a
                    thousand vanished Latin epics, and by the historic aspects of his subject,
                    Silius merits better treatment from scholars than he has received. The general
                    reader he can hardly interest again. He is indeed of imitation all compact, and
                    usually dilutes what he borrows; he may add a new beauty, but new strength he
                    never gives. Hardly a dozen lines anywhere are without an echo of Virgil, and
                    there are frequent admixtures of Lucretius, Horace, Ovid, Lucan, Homer, Hesiod,
                    and many other poets still extant. If we could reconstitute the library of
                    Silius we should probably find that scarcely an idea or a phrase in his entire
                    work was wholly his own.</p>
                <p>The raw material of the <hi rend="italic">Punica</hi> was supplied in the main by
                    the third decade of Livy, though Silius may have consulted other historians of
                    the Hannibalic war. Such facts as are used are generally presented with their
                    actual circumstances unchanged, and in their historic sequence. The spirit of
                    the Punic times is but rarely misconceived,—as when to secret voting is
                    attributed the election of men like Flaminius and Varro, and distinguished
                    Romans are depicted as contending in a gladiatorial exhibition. Silius clearly
                    intended the poem to consist of twenty-four books, like the Iliad and the
                    Odyssey, but after the twelfth he hurries in visible weariness to the end and
                    concludes with seventeen. The general plan of the epic follows that of the Iliad
                    and the Aeneid. Its theme is conceived as a duel between two mighty nations,
                    with parallel dissensions among the gods. Scipio and Hannibal are the two great
                    heroes who take the place of Achilles and Hector on the one hand and of Aeneas
                    and Turnus on the other, while the minor figures are all painted with Virgilian
                    or Homeric pigments. In the delineation of character our poet is neither very
                    powerful nor very consistent. His imagination was too weak to realize the actors
                    with distinctness and individuality. His</p>
                <p>Hannibal is evidently at the outset meant for an incarnation of cruelty and
                    treachery, the embodiment of all that the vulgar Roman attached to the name
                    “Punic.” But in the course of the poem the greatness of Hannibal is borne in
                    upon the poet, and his feeling of it betrays itself in many touches. Thus he
                    names Scipio “the great Hannibal of Ausonia”; he makes Juno assure the
                    Carthaginian leader that if fortune had only permitted him to be born a Roman he
                    would have been admitted to a place among the gods; and, when the ungenerous
                    monster of the first book accords in the fifteenth a splendid burial to
                    Marcellus, the poet cries, “You would fancy it was a Sidonian chief who had
                    fallen.” Silius deserves little pity for the failure of his attempt to make
                    Scipio an equipoise to Hannibal and the counterpart in personal prowess and
                    prestige of Achilles. He becomes in the process almost as mythical a figure as
                    the mediaeval Alexander. The best drawn of the minor characters are Fabius
                    Cunctator, an evident copy of Lucan’s Cato, and Paullus, the consul killed at
                    Cannae, who fights, hates, and dies like a genuine man.</p>
                <p>Clearly it was a matter of religion with Silius to repeat and adapt all the
                    striking episodes of Homer and Virgil. Hannibal must have a shield of marvellous
                    workmanship like Achilles and Aeneas; because Aeneas descended into Hades and
                    had a vision of the future history of Rome, so must Scipio have his revelation
                    from heaven; Trebia, choked with bodies, must rise in ire like Xanthus, and be
                    put to flight by Vulcan; for Virgil’s Camilla there must be an Asbyte, heroine
                    of Saguntum; the beautiful speech of Euryalus when Nisus seeks to leave him is
                    too good to be thrown away,—furbished up a little, it will serve as a parting
                    address from Imilce to her husband Hannibal. The descriptions of the numerous
                    battles are made up in the main, according to epic rule, of single
                    combats—wearisome sometimes in Homer, wearisome offener in Virgil, painfully
                    wearisome in Silius. The different component parts of the poem are on the whole
                    fairly well knit together, and the transitions are not often needlessly abrupt;
                    yet occasionally incidents and episodes are introduced with all the irrelevancy
                    of the modern novel. A son of Regulus escapes from Thrasymene to a hut, merely
                    to find there an old servant of his father, and to afford him the opportunity of
                    telling over again the tale of the first war against the Carthaginians. To give
                    scope for a eulogy of Cicero, an ancestor of his fights at Cannae, and strong
                    devices sometimes usher in such stories as the judgment of Paris and the choice
                    of Hercules. The interposition of the gods is, however, usually managed with
                    dignity and appropriateness.</p>
                <p>As to diction and detail, we miss, in general, power rather than taste. The metre
                    runs on with correct smooth monotony, with something always of the Virgilian
                    sweetness, though attenuated, but nothing of the Virgilian variety and strength.
                    The dead level of literary execution is seldom broken by a rise into the region
                    of genuine pathos and beauty, or by a descent into the ludicrous or the
                    repellent. There are few absurdities, but the restraining force is trained
                    perception and not a native sense of humour, which, ever present in Homer, not
                    entirely absent in Virgil, and sometimes finding grim expression in Lucan, fails
                    Silius entirely. The address of Anna, Dido’s sister, to Juno compels a smile.
                    Though deified on her sister’s death, and for a good many centuries already an
                    inhabitant of heaven, Anna meets Juno for the first time on the outbreak of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Second</hi> Punic War, and deprecates the anger of the
                    queen of heaven for having deserted the Carthaginians and attached herself to
                    the Roman cause. Hannibal’s parting address to his child is also comical: he
                    recognizes in the “heavy wailing” of the year-old babe “the seeds of rages like
                    his own.” But Silius might have been forgiven for a thousand more weaknesses
                    than he has if in but a few things he had shown strength. The grandest scenes in
                    the history before him fail to lift him up; his treatment, for example, of
                    Hannibal’s Alpine passage falls immensely below Lucan’s vigorous delineation of
                    Cato’s far less stirring march across the African deserts.</p>
                <p>But in the very weaknesses of Silius we may discern merit. He at least does not
                    try to conceal defects of substance by contorted rhetorical conceits and feebly
                    forcible exaggerations. In his ideal of what Latin expression should be he comes
                    near to his contemporary Quintilian, and resolutely holds aloof from the tenor
                    of his age. Perhaps his want of success with the men of his time was not wholly
                    due to his faults. His self-control rarely fails him; it stands the test of the
                    horrors of war, and of Venus working her will on Hannibal at Capua. The reader
                    of Statius and even Propertius will be thankful for the rarity of recondite
                    epithets, such as “Rhoetean destiny,” “Garamantian standards,” “Lagean river,”
                    “Smyrnaean strings.” Only a few passages here and there betray the true silver
                    Latin extravagance, as when Hannibal is compared for speed to a tigress reft of
                    her cubs, which darts forth <hi rend="italic">and in a few hours</hi> traverses
                    the Caucasus, and with a “winged” leap flies across <hi rend="italic">the
                        Ganges</hi>; or when the Carthaginians after Capua launch their spears but
                    are too enervated to <hi rend="italic">make them whiz</hi>; or when the
                    plague-stricken and famine-<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n71/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0071-0056"/> wasted men of Syracuse hide their diminished
                    faces far within their helmets, and carefully shade their pallor lest hope
                    should arise for the enemy. In the avoidance of rhetorical artifice and
                    epigrammatic antithesis Silius stands in marked contrast to Lucan. Yet he can be
                    pointed; so of Fabius, “laudum cladumque quieta Mente capax”; and of Scaevola,
                    “Aspera semper amans et par cuicumque periclo”; and of Africa, “Altrix bellorum
                    bellatorumque virorum Tellus, nec fidens nudo sine fraudibus ensi.” Looking at
                    Silius merely as a poet he may not deserve high praise; but, as he is a unique
                    specimen and probably the best of a once numerous class, the preservation of his
                    poem among the remains of Latin literature is a fortunate accident.</p>
                <p>The poet’s full name, Ti. Catius Silius Italicus, is preserved in an inscription
                        (<hi rend="italic">C. I. L.,</hi> vi. 1984). The poem was discovered in a
                    MS., possibly at Constance, by Poggio, in 1416 or 1417; from this now lost MS.
                    all existing MSS., which belong entirely to the 15th century, are derived. A
                    valuable MS. of the 8th or 9th century, found at Cologne by L. Carrion in the
                    latter part of the 16th century, disappeared soon after its discovery. Two <hi
                        rend="italic">editiones principes</hi> appeared at Rome in 1471; the
                    principal editions since have been those of Heinsius (1600), Drakenborch (1717),
                    and Ernesti (Leipsic, 1791). A useful <hi rend="italic">variorum</hi> edition is
                    that of Lemaire (Paris, 1823). The recent <hi rend="italic">lucubrationes</hi>
                    on Silius are mostly small pamphlets, enumerated by Engelmann <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Bibl. Script. Class.,</hi> 1878). (J. S. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
