<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0388-0365-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPALATIN, George</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 365</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xd69">Canonization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:893284">Diet</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n388/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPALATIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>
                    (1484-1545). George Burkhardt, a subordinate figure of some interest in the
                    history of the Reformation in Germany, was born on January 17, 1484, at Spalt
                    (whence he assumed the name Spalatinus), about 25 miles from Nuremberg, where
                    his father was an artisan.</p>
                <p>He went to Nuremberg for education when he was thirteen years of age, and two
                    years afterwards to the university of Erfurt, where he took his bachelor’s
                    degree within a year, in 1499. There he attracted the notice of Marschalk, the
                    most influential professor, who made Spalatin his amanu-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n389/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0389-0366"/> ensis and took him to Wittenberg. In 1505
                    Spalatin went to Erfurt to study jurisprudence, was recommended to Mutianus, and
                    was welcomed by the little band of German humanists of whom Mutianus was chief.
                    His friend got him the post of teacher of young monks in a convent in the
                    Georgenthal and pastor in the high church there. In 1508 he was ordained priest
                    by Bishop John von Laasphe, who had ordained Luther. He had no great love for
                    convent or pastoral work, and in 1509 Mutianus recommended him to Frederick the
                    Wise, the elector of Saxony, who employed him to act as tutor to his son, the
                    future elector, John Frederick. This appointment really determined Spalatin’s
                    life and work. He speedily gained the confidence of the famous elector, who
                    employed him in many affairs. He sent him to Wittenberg in 1511 to act as tutor
                    to his nephews, and procured for him a canon’s stall in Altenberg. In 1512 the
                    elector made him his librarian. This brought him into correspondence with a
                    large number of literary men, and he began to collect all kinds of literary and
                    especially of historical information, of which he made extensive use later in
                    his chronicles. He was promoted to be court chaplain and confidential secretary
                    to the elector, and took charge of all his private and public correspondence. He
                    thus became one of the most important men at the electoral court, which then was
                    the centre of German life.</p>
                <p>Spalatin had never cared for theology, and, although a priest and a preacher, had
                    been a mere humanist. It was to Luther that he owed his awakening to the reality
                    of a spiritual life. How he first became acquainted with the reformer it is
                    impossible to say—probably at Wittenberg; but Luther from the first exercised a
                    great power over him, and became his chief counsellor in all moral and religious
                    matters. His letters to Luther have been lost, but Luther’s answers remain, and
                    are extremely interesting. Spalatin was Luther’s devoted friend during the
                    stormiest days of the Reformation, and was the means of bringing the great
                    elector to take the side of the outspoken professor in his university of
                    Wittenberg. He read Luther’s writings to the elector, and translated for his
                    benefit those in Latin into German. He accompanied Frederick to the diet of
                    Augsburg, and shared in the negotiations with the papal legates, Cajetan and
                    Miltitz. He was with the elector when Charles was chosen emperor and when he was
                    crowned. He was with his master at the diet of Worms. In short, he stood beside
                    Frederick as his confidential adviser in all the troubled diplomacy of the
                    earlier years of the Reformation. Singularly cautious, perhaps timid, before the
                    crisis came and while it could be averted, Spalatin found courage when the
                    crisis had come. He would have dissuaded Luther again and again from publishing
                    books or engaging in overt acts against the papacy, but, when the thing was
                    done, none was so ready to translate the book, or to justify the act.</p>
                <p>On the death of Frederick the Wise, Spalatin was as much engaged in diplomatic
                    service as before, but he no longer lived at court. He went into residence as
                    canon at Altenberg, and incited the chapter to institute reforms somewhat
                    unsuccessfully. He married in the same year. During the later portion of his
                    life, from 1526 onwards, he was chiefly engaged in the visitation of churches
                    and schools in electoral Saxony, reporting on the confiscation and application
                    of ecclesiastical revenues. His practical experience in German affairs made him
                    very successful in his delicate task, and he was asked to undertake the same
                    work for Albertine Saxony. He was also permanent visitor of Wittenberg
                    university, and made an annual report of its condition to the elector. Shortly
                    before his death he fell into a state of profound melancholy, and died January
                    16, 1545, at Altenberg.</p>
                <p>Spalatin left behind him a large number of literary remains, both published and
                    unpublished. His original writings are almost all historical. A list of them may
                    be found in Seelheim’s <hi rend="italic">George Spalatin als sächs.
                    Historiograph,</hi> 1878. There is no good life of Spalatin, nor can there be
                    until his letters have been collected and edited, a work still to be done.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
