<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0471-0448-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STAMPS (9th edition, volume 22, page 448)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w950q6z">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx74153">Documents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xq0p">Dependencies</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896108">Documentation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:890814">Dependency</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n471/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STAMPS</label>. The stamp duty is a tax imposed upon a great
                    variety of legal and other documents, and forms a branch of the national
                    revenue. The stamp is a cheap and convenient mode of certifying that the revenue
                    regulations have been complied with. Stamp duties appear to have been invented
                    by the Dutch in 1624. They were first imposed in England in 1694 by 5 and 6
                    Will. and Mary, c. 21, as a temporary means of raising funds for carrying on the
                    war with France. They now depend upon a very large number of statutes, the
                    principal one being the Stamp Act, 1870, 33 and 34 Vict. c. 97 (which extends to
                    the United Kingdom). The amount of stamp duty varies from one halfpenny
                    (postage) to thousands of pounds (probate or succession). It appears scarcely
                    necessary in this place to set out at length the various stamp duties payable in
                    the United Kingdom, inasmuch as those of the most usual occurrence will readily
                    be found in ordinary books of reference.</p>
                <p>Stamp duties are either fixed, such as the duty of one penny on every cheque
                    irrespective of its amount, or <hi rend="italic">αd valorem,</hi> as the duty on
                    a conveyance, which varies according to the amount of the purchase money. The
                    duty is denoted generally by an impressed, less frequently by an adhesive,
                    stamp, sometimes by either at the option of the person stamping. Thus an inland
                    bill of exchange (unless payable on demand) must have an impressed stamp, a
                    foreign bill of exchange an adhesive stamp, while an agreement or receipt stamp
                    may be of either kind. It should be noticed that certain documents falling
                    within a class which as a rule is subject to stamp duty are for reasons of
                    public policy or encouragement of trade exempted from the duty by special
                    legislation. Examples of such documents are Bank of England notes, agreements
                    within § 17 (but not those within § 4) of the Statute of Frauds (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Fraud),</hi> agreements between a master of a ship and his
                    crew, transfers of ships or shares in ships, indentures of apprenticeship for
                    the sea service, petitions forwarded by post to the crown or a House of
                    Parliament, and most instruments relating to the business of building and
                    friendly societies.</p>
                <p>As a general rule a document must be stamped at the time of execution, or a
                    penalty (remissible by the commissioners of inland revenue) is incurred. The
                    penalty is in most cases £10, sometimes much more; in the case of policies of
                    marine insurance it is £100. Some instruments cannot be stamped at all after
                    execution, even with payment of the penalty. Such are bills of exchange and
                    promissory notes (where an impressed stamp is necessary), bills of lading,
                    proxies for voting at meetings of proprietors of joint-stock companies, and
                    receipts after a month from date. An unstamped instrument cannot be pleaded or
                    given in evidence except in criminal proceedings or for a collateral purpose. If
                    an instrument chargeable with duty be produced as evidence in a court, the
                    officer whose duty it is to read the instrument is to call the attention of the
                    judge to any omission or insufficiency of the stamp, and if the instrument is
                    one which may legally be stamped after execution, it may, on payment of the
                    amount of the unpaid duty and the penalty payable by law, and a further sum of
                    £1, be received in evidence, saving all just exceptions on other grounds. The
                    rules of the Supreme Court, 1883 (Ord. xxxix. r. 8, re-enacting a provision of
                    the Common Law Procedure Act), provide that a new trial is not to be granted by
                    reason of the ruling of a judge that the stamp upon any document is sufficient
                    or that the document does not require a stamp. The stamp upon a document subject
                    to the stamp laws of a foreign state is usually admissible in evidence in a
                    court of the United Kingdom if it conform in other respects to the rules
                    governing the admissibility of such documents, even though it be improperly
                    stamped according to the law of the foreign country. The admissibility of
                    documents belongs to the <hi rend="italic">ordinatοria litis</hi> rather than
                    the <hi rend="italic">decisoria litis,</hi> and is governed by the <hi
                        rend="italic">lex fori</hi> rather than the <hi rend="italic">lex loci
                        contractus,</hi> unless indeed that law makes a stamp necessary to the
                    validity of the instrument. As to bills of exchange, the Bills of Exchange Act,
                    1882, 45 and 46 Vict. c. 61, § 72, provides that where a bill is issued out of
                    the United Kingdom it is not invalid by reason only that it is not stamped in
                    accordance with the law of the place of issue, and that where a bill issued out
                    of the United Kingdom conforms as regards requisites in form to the law of the
                    United Kingdom it may for the purpose of enforcing payment thereof be treated as
                    valid as between all persons who negotiate, hold, or become parties to it in the
                    United Kingdom.</p>
                <p>By the Stamp Duties Management Act, 1870, 33 and 34 Vict, c. 98, the stamp duties
                    are put under the management of the commissioners of inland revenue, who are
                    empowered to grant licences to deal in stamps, and to make allowance for spoiled
                    or misused stamps. Certain offences, such as forging a die or stamp, selling or
                    using a forged stamp, &amp;c,, are made felonies punishable with penal servitude
                    for life as a maximum.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States.—</hi> The subject of stamp duties is of unusual
                    historical interest, as the passing of Grenville’s Stamp Act of 1765 (5 Geo.
                    III. c. 12) directly led to the American revolution. The Act was, indeed,
                    repealed the next year as a matter of expediency by 6 Geo. III. c. 11, but 6
                    Geo. III. c. 12 declared the right of the British legislature to bind the
                    colonies by its Acts. The actual yield of the stamp duties under the Act of 1765
                    was, owing to the opposition in the American colonies, only £4000—less than the
                    expenses of putting the Act into force. The stamp duties of the United States
                    are now under the superintendence of the commissioner of internal revenue. These
                    duties, which depend upon a great body of statutory law, will be found in the
                    Revised Statutes, tit. xxxv.</p>
                <p>The principal authorities on the subject of this article are Tilsley, <hi
                        rend="italic">Stamp Laws,</hi> and Dowell, <hi rend="italic">Stamp
                        Duties.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
