<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0427-0404-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPIRITUALISM (9th edition, volume 22, page 404)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w950q6z">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015465">Mediums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130184">Spiritualists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n427/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPIRITUALISM</label>. The term “spiritualism” is used by
                    philosophical writers to denote the opposite of materialism. It is also used in
                    a narrower sense to describe the belief that the spiritual world manifests
                    itself by producing in the physical world effects inexplicable by the known
                    laws, of nature. The belief in such occasional manifestations has probably
                    existed as long as the belief in the existence of spirits apart from human
                    bodies, and a complete examination into it would involve a discussion of the
                    religions of all ages and nations. In 1848, however, a peculiar form of it,
                    believed to be based on abundant experimental evidence, arose in America and
                    spread there with great rapidity and thence over the civilized world. To this
                    movement, which has been called “modern spiritualism,” the discussion in the
                    present article is confined. The movement began in a single family. In 1848 a Mr
                        and<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n428/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0428-0405"/> Mrs Fox and their two daughters, living at
                    Hydeville (Wayne), New York, were much disturbed by unexplained knockings. At
                    length Kate Fox discovered that the cause of the sounds was intelligent and
                    would make raps as requested, and, communication being established, the rapper
                    professed to be the spirit of a murdered pedlar. An investigation into the
                    matter seemed to show that none of the Fox family were concerned in producing
                    the rappings; but the evidence that they were not concerned is insufficient,
                    although similar noises had been noticed occasionally in the house before they
                    lived there. It was, however, at Rochester, where the two Fox girls soon
                    afterwards went to live with a married sister (Mrs Fish) that modern
                    spiritualism assumed its present form, and that communication was, as it was
                    believed, established with lost relatives and deceased eminent men. The presence
                    of certain “mediums” was required to form the link between the worlds of the
                    living and of the dead, and Kate Fox and her sister were the first mediums.
                    Spiritualists do not as yet claim to know what special qualities in mediums
                    enable spirits thus to make use of them. The earliest communications were
                    carried on by means of “raps,” or, as Mr Crookes calls them, “percussive
                    sounds.” It was agreed that one rap should mean “no” and three “yes,” while more
                    complicated messages were—and are—obtained in other ways, such as calling over
                    or pointing to letters of the alphabet, when raps occur at the required
                    letters.</p>
                <p>The idea of communicating with the departed was naturally attractive even to the
                    merely curious, still more to those who were mourning for lost friends, and most
                    of all to those who believed that this was the commencement of a new revelation.
                    The first two causes have attracted many inquirers; but it is the last that
                    chiefly gives to modern spiritualism its religious aspect. Many came to witness
                    the new wonder, and the excitement and interest spread rapidly. “Spirit-circles”
                    were formed in several families, and other mediums discovered, exhibiting
                    phenomena of various kinds (see below). The interest in mesmerism and the
                    phenomena of hypnotic trance, which was widely diffused at this time both in
                    America and Europe (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Magnetism, Animal,</hi> vol. xv. p.
                    277 <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> was favourable to the new idea. Information
                    about other worlds and from higher intelligences was thought to be obtained from
                    persons who could be put into the sleep-waking state, of whom Andrew Jackson
                    Davis was in America the most prominent example. His work, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nature's Divine Revelations</hi> (New York, 1847), was alleged to have been
                    dictated in “clairvoyant” trance. Many reputed “clairvoyants” developed into
                    mediums. The movement spread like an epidemic. There is very little evidence to
                    show that it arose anywhere spontaneously<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">It is possible that the family of Dr
                                Phelps were unaware of the “Rochester knockings” when the
                                disturbances began in his house at Stratford, Connecticut, in 1850
                                (see Capron’s</hi> Modern Spiritualism, its Facts, <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c.); but these disturbances, as recorded, have a closer
                                resemblance to the ordinary occurrences at a spiritualistic seance
                                than those which took place at Tedworth in 1661 (see Glanvill's</hi>
                            Sadducismus Triumphatus) <hi rend="italic">and at Slawensik in 1806 (see
                                Kerner’s</hi> Seherin von Prevorst), <hi rend="italic">aud others
                                too numerous to mention.</hi></p></note>; but those who sat with the
                    Foxes were often found to become mediums themselves and then in their turn
                    developed mediumship in others. The mere reading of accounts of seances seemed
                    to develop the peculiar susceptibility in some persons, while others, who became
                    mediums ultimately, did so only after prolonged and patient waiting.</p>
                <p>There seems to have been little practical interest in spiritualism in Europe till
                    Mrs Hayden, a professional medium from Boston, came over in 1852. It spread like
                    wildfire within a few months of her arrival,—its first development being in the
                    form of a mania for table-turning, which seems to have prevailed all over Europe
                    in 1853.</p>
                <p>Daniel Dunglas Home, the next medium of importance who appeared in London, came
                    over from America in 1855. But it was at Keighley in Yorkshire that spiritualism
                    as a religious movement first made any mark in England, and it was there that
                    the first English spiritualistic periodical, the <hi rend="italic">Yorkshire
                        Spiritual Telegraph,</hi> was started in 1855. The extent to which the
                    movement has spread and the present number of spiritualists are very difficult
                    to estimate. Vague calculations have from time to time been attempted: in 1867
                    one spiritualist estimated the number in America at 11,000,000 or two-fifths of
                    the population, and another has held 3,000,000 to be an extreme estimate (see
                        <hi rend="italic">Spiritual Magazine</hi> for 1867). The periodicals devoted
                    to spiritualism may perhaps be taken to indicate the present state of the
                    movement. There are in England two weekly newspapers, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Light</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Medium and Daybreak</hi>; one of these
                    has advertisements of Sunday meetings in sixty different towns and in eighty
                    different rooms. The spiritualistic journals outside Great Britain number about
                    100, though probably only about a quarter of these are of any importance. Of
                    these 30 are in English (26 published in America and 4 in the Australian
                    colonies), 15 to 20 in French, and 6 in German. But nearly 40 are published in
                    Spanish in Spain and South America. Private circles which meet regularly are
                    believed to be numerous in England; and there are numerous public and
                    semi-public trance-speaking and clairvoyant mediums, especially among the miners
                    in the north.</p>
                <p>In the present article it is impossible to give an exhaustive catalogue of the
                    phenomena and modes of communication of modern spiritualism. Many have not now
                    appeared for the first time in history, though it is difficult to suppose any
                    historical connexion between the new developments and the old. Perhaps the most
                    striking parallelism is that between the proceedings at modern seances and those
                    connected with the later Greek oracles.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">See</hi> Essays Classical, <hi
                                rend="italic">by F. W. H. Myers, 1883.</hi></p></note> The greater
                    part of the phenomena may be divided into two classes. To the first and earliest
                    developed class belong what may be called the physical phenomena of
                    spiritualism,—those, namely, which, if correctly observed and due neither to
                    conscious or unconscious trickery nor to hallucination on the part of the
                    observers, exhibit a force hitherto unknown to science, acting in the physical
                    world otherwise than through the brain or muscles of the medium. The earliest of
                    these phenomena were the raps already spoken of and other sounds occurring
                    without apparent physical cause, and the similarly mysterious movements of
                    furniture and other objects; and these were shortly followed by the ringing of
                    bells and playing of musical instruments. Later followed the appearance of
                    lights; quasi-human voices; musical sounds, produced, it is supposed, without
                    instruments; the “materialization” or presence in material form of what seem to
                    be human hands and faces, and ultimately of complete figures, alleged to be not
                    those of any person present, and sometimes claimed by witnesses as deceased
                    relatives; “psychography,” or “direct writing and drawing,” asserted to be done
                    without human intervention; “spirit-photography,” or photographing of human and
                    other forms invisible to all but specially endowed seers; unfastening of cords
                    and bonds; elongation of the medium’s body; handling of red-hot coals; and the
                    apparent passage of solids through solids without disintegration. The phenomena
                    observed at Tedworth belong to this class. Somewhat similar was the Cock Lane
                    ghost in 1762.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">See</hi> Gentleman's Magazine, <hi rend="italic"
                                >1762.</hi></p></note> A practice of causing heavily loaded tables
                    to rise by “magic” seems to have existed among the German Jews in the 17th
                        century.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Von Harless,</hi> Aegyptische Mysterien, <hi
                                rend="italic">1856, pp. 130-132.</hi></p></note> Kerner records
                        movements<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n429/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0429-0406"/> of objects in connexion with Madame Hauffe in
                        1825-28,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Seherin von Prevorst.</hi></p></note> and such
                    movements also occurred in presence of the so-called electric girl in 1846.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tanchou, <hi
                                rend="italic">Enquête sur l'authenticité des phénomènes électriques
                                d'Angélique Cottin,</hi> Paris, 1846.</p></note> The second class of
                    phenomena, which we may call the automatic, consists in table-tilting and
                    turning with contact; writing, drawing, &amp;c., through the medium’s hand;
                    convulsive movements and involuntary dancing; entrancement, trance-speaking, and
                    personation by the medium of deceased persons, attributed to temporary
                    “possession ”; seeing spirits and visions and hearing phantom voices. This class
                    bears affinity to some of the phenomena of hypnotism and of certain nervous
                    complaints, to certain epidemics of the Middle Ages,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Hecker, <hi rend="italic">Epidemies
                                of the Middle Ages,</hi> 1859.</p></note> and to phenomena that have
                    occurred at some religious revivals. According to quotations given by
                        Chevreul,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">De la baguette divinatoire,</hi> &amp;c.,
                        1854.</p></note> the divining-rod was used at the end of the 17th century
                    for obtaining answers to questions, as table-tilting now is. In a third class
                    must be placed the cure of disease by healing mediums. This cannot well be
                    treated apart from mesmeric healing and “faith cures” and “mind cures,” and
                    belongs to medical psychology.</p>
                <p>The class of automatic phenomena are much the commonest. The investigations of
                    Carpenter on unconscious cerebration and of Faraday on unconscious muscular
                        action<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> 2d July 1853; see also on this subject
                            C'hevreul, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi></p></note> have shown that it
                    is not necessary to look outside the medium’s own brain and organism for the
                    explanation of such things as automatic writing and table turning. It is about
                    the matter communicated by these means that the controversy now turns.
                    Spiritualists maintain that true information is thus given, provably unknown to
                    the medium or other persons present, or at least expressed in a way obviously
                    beyond their powers to originate. Another view, which is now gaining ground, is
                    that the information in some exceptional cases does not come from the mind of
                    the medium, but is due to the influence wrought on his mind by that of other
                    persons, and more than this is not proved.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>See Ch. Richet, “La Suggestion Mentale,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Revue Philosophique,</hi> December 1884, and <hi
                                rend="italic">Proc. Soc. for Psychical Research,</hi> vols. ii. and
                            iii.</p></note></p>
                <p>At no period of the spiritualistic movement has the class of physical phenomena
                    been accepted altogether without criticism. Most spiritualists know that much
                    fraud in connexion with them has been discovered—frequently by spiritualists
                    themselves—and that the conditions favourable to obtaining them are often such
                    as favour fraud. It is with a full knowledge of these difficulties in the way of
                    investigation that they maintain that unmistakably genuine phenomena are of
                    constant occurrence. Many volumes containing accounts of such phenomena have
                    been printed, and appeal is often made to the mass of evidence so accumulated.
                    “No physical science can array a tithe of the mass of evidence by which
                    psychism” <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> what is usually called spiritualism) “is
                    supported,” says Serjeant Cox.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Mechanism of Man: What am I?</hi> vol.
                            ii. p. 313, 1879.</p></note> But the majority of these accounts have
                    scarcely any scientific value. Spiritualists have, as a rule, sought to convince
                    not by testimony but by ocular demonstration. Yet, if there is not a mass of
                    scientific evidence, there are a number of witnesses—among them distinguished
                    men of science and others of undoubted intelligence—who have convinced
                    themselves by observation of the genuineness of the phenomena,—a fact of
                    undeniable importance, even without careful records, when the witnesses are
                    otherwise known to be competent and trustworthy observers. Mr Maskelyne has
                        affirmed<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi
                                rend="italic">Pall Mall Gazette,</hi> 18th, 20th, and 23d April
                            1885.&gt;</p></note> that he has witnessed tableturning where he was
                    satisfied that there was neither trickery nor unconscious muscular action.
                    Moreover, if the phenomena are not genuine, we have to assume a large amount of
                    apparently aimless fraud.</p>
                <p>Amongst the proposed explanations of these phenomena that of hallucination need
                    not detain us long. Sensory hallucination of several persons together who are
                    not in a hypnotic state is a rare phenomenon, and therefore not a probable
                    explanation. Moreover, it cannot be regarded as being generally applicable,
                    partly because material traces of what occurs often remain, and partly because
                    of the general agreement not only of all the witnesses but of all the senses as
                    to what is perceived, as distinguished from what is inferred. Nevertheless
                    something of the kind may occasionally have happened, especially at some of the
                    seances of Home.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See,
                            e.g., <hi rend="italic">Report on Spriritualism of the Committee of the
                                London,</hi> Dialectical Society, 1871, pp. 367-369, 207. See also
                            Guldenstubbe, <hi rend="italic">De la réalité des esprits,</hi> 1857, p.
                            66.</p></note> If collective hallucination really occurs at seances, it
                    is a very interesting fact, and deserves to be carefully studied.</p>
                <p>What may broadly be called conjuring is, however, a much more probable
                    explanation of most of the recorded phenomena; and in the vast majority of cases
                    the witnesses do not seem to have duly appreciated the possibilities of
                    conjuring, nor to have taken sufficient precautions to exclude it. Besides, not
                    even a conjuror knows all the possibilities of his art and can describe in
                    detail all the accidental circumstances which may on any particular occasion
                    favour deception, and perhaps never exactly recur. We require, therefore, to
                    know not only that the witness is careful and accurate but that he has allowed a
                    sufficiently wide margin for the possibilities of conjuring; and some leading
                    spiritualists do not allow this. It is often urged that mediums are not
                    conjurors because they frequently fail, whereas “imposture can be reproduced at
                    will,” and because they can produce the phenomena in private rooms, and under
                    conditions which exclude the possibility of conjuring. But the phenomena
                    produced by mediums in private rooms would generally be uninteresting and
                    unsuited to public performance, so that it would not pay a professional conjuror
                    to practise them. Amateur conjurors might do something in this way, and the
                    present writer has seen one imitate successfully some of the phenomena of
                    professional mediums for “direct writing”; but to compete with mediums on really
                    equal terms the conjuror must have the same conditions throughout, and this is
                    difficult to arrange, since it involves securing witnesses who are doubtful as
                    to whether what they see is conjuring or not. Still more important to the
                    conjuror is that very privilege of failing whenever he pleases, so largely used
                    by mediums, that he may avail himself of accidental opportunities for trickery,
                    which would be interfered with by a settled programme. The extent to which the
                    absence of programme obtains at seances appears from the following statement by
                    a leading spiritualist who writes under the <hi rend="italic">nom de plume</hi>
                    of “M.A. (Oxon.)”: “In 99 out of every 100 cases people do <hi rend="italic"
                        >not</hi> get what they want or expect. Test after test, cunningly devised,
                    on which the investigator has set his mind, is put aside, and another
                        substituted.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Human Nature,</hi> 1876, p. 267.</p></note> In other
                    words, the evidence is rarely strictly experimental, and this not only gives
                    facilities for fraud but makes it necessary to allow a much larger margin for
                    accidents, mistakes, and mal-observation. It must be borne in mind that the most
                    excellent moral character in the medium is no guarantee against trickery, unless
                    it can be proved that he was in no abnormal mental condition when the phenomena
                    occurred; for extraordinary deceptions have been carried on by hysterical
                    patients and others with no apparent motive but a desire to secure
                    attention.</p>
                <p>One of the possibilities to be allowed for is that of un-<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n430/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0430-0407"/> usual muscular endowment in the medium. For
                    instance, in 1851, the remarkable loud double raps occurring in the presence of
                    the Fox girls, which in 1849 had puzzled several investigating committees at
                    Rochester, were explained by Professors Flint, Lee, and Coventry of Buffalo as
                    produced by rapidly partially dislocating and restoring the knee and other
                    joints. They stated that they had experimented with another lady who could do
                    the same; and, challenged by Mrs. Fish, they tried some experiments with her and
                    Margaretta Fox which strongly supported their view.</p>
                <p>Besides the general arguments for supposing that the physical phenomena of
                    spiritualism may be due to conjuring, there are two special reasons which gain
                    in force as time goes on. (1) Almost every medium who has been prominently
                    before the public has at some time or other been detected in fraud, or what
                    cannot be distinguished from fraud except on some violently improbable
                    hypothesis; and (2), although it is easy to devise experiments of various kinds
                    which would place certain phenomena above the suspicion of conjuring, by
                    eliminating the necessity for continuous observation on the part of the
                    investigators, there is no good evidence that such experiments have ever
                    succeeded. Nevertheless there does exist evidence for the genuineness of the
                    physical phenomena which deserves consideration. Count Agénor de Gasparin, in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Tables Tournantes</hi> (Paris, 1854), gives an account of
                    what seem to have been careful experiments with his own family and friends,
                    which convinced him that by some unknown force tables could be got to move
                    without contact. He did not believe that spirits had anything to do with it. His
                    experiments were conducted in broad daylight and with sceptical witnesses (whose
                    testimony, however, he does not give) looking on outside the circle. The minutes
                    of the sub-committee No. 1 of the committee of the Dialectical Society <hi
                        rend="italic">(op. cit.,</hi> pp. 373-391) report that tables moved without
                    contact, whilst all the persons present knelt on chairs (the backs of which were
                    turned to the table), with their hands on the backs. The report, however, would
                    be of greater value if the names of the medium and of the working members of the
                    committee were given —we only know that of Sergeant Cox—and if they had written
                    independent accounts of what they witnessed. The conditions of some of Mr
                    Crookes’s experiments with D. D. Home on alterations in the weight of a
                    partially suspended board<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                ><p><hi rend="italic">Quart. Journ, of Science,</hi> July and
                            October 1871; republished, with other papers by Mr Crookes, under the
                            title of <hi rend="italic">Researches on the Phenomena of
                                Spiritualism,</hi> 1874-76.</p></note> appear to have been so simple
                    that it is difficult to imagine how the witnesses can have been deceived. Some
                    very remarkable evidence is contained in “Researches in Spiritualism during the
                    Year 1872-3,” by “M.A. (Oxon.),” published in a spiritualistic periodical called
                        <hi rend="italic">Human Nature,</hi> March and August 1874. The papers give
                    accounts of phenomena obtained through the writer’s own mediumship, generally in
                    the presence of one or two friends, and extending over almost the whole range of
                    spiritualistic manifestations.</p>
                <p>But what chiefly interests spiritualists is the assurance of life and progress
                    after death, and the moral and religious teaching, which they obtain through
                    automatic writing and trance-speaking. It was discovered very early in the
                    movement that the accuracy of these communications could not always be relied
                    on; but it is maintained by spiritualists that by the exercise of the reason and
                    judgment, by prolonged acquaintance with particular communicating intelligences,
                    and by proofs of identity with persons known to have been trustworthy on earth,
                    it is possible to obtain valuable information from beings not infallible, but
                    with the knowledge of spirit life superadded to their earthly experience. Still
                    the agreement between communications so received has not been sufficiently great
                    for anything like a universal spiritualistic creed to have been arrived at. In
                    France the doctrine of successive reincarnations with intervals of spirit life
                    promulgated by Allan Kardec (Léon Hippolyte Denisart Rivail) forms a prominent
                    element of spiritualistic belief. This view has, however, made but little way in
                    England and America, where the opinions of the great majority of spiritualists
                    vary from orthodox Christianity to Unitarianism of an extreme kind. Probably it
                    would be impossible to unite spiritualists in any creed, which, besides the
                    generally accepted belief in God and immortality, should postulate more than the
                    progress of the spirit after death, and the power of some of the dead to
                    communicate with the living by means of mediums.</p>
                <p>Spiritualism has been accused of a strong tendency to produce insanity; the
                    charge, however, seems to be in the main a mistaken inference from the fact that
                    the delusions of the insane not unfrequently take the form of supposed converse
                    with invisible beings. It is, however, probable that the spiritualistic theories
                    of possession and obsession sometimes injure persons with incipient insane
                    impulses, by weakening their sense of responsibility for these and their efforts
                    to control them. Spiritualism has also been accused of fostering free love and
                    other doctrines subversive of society. But this charge too has been made without
                    adequate grounds; for, though certain spiritualistic bodies have at times taught
                    such doctrines, they have always been repudiated by the mass of spiritualists.
                    The great scandal of spiritualism is undoubtedly the encouragement it gives to
                    the immoral trade of fraudulent mediumship.</p>
                <p>In addition to the works already mentioned, the student, for a general idea of
                    the whole subject, should consult the following :— E. W. Capron, <hi
                        rend="italic">Modern Spiritualism, its Facts,</hi> &amp;c., Boston, 1855,
                    for the early history of the movement in America; Edmonds and Dexter, <hi
                        rend="italic">Spiritualism,</hi> New York, 1854-55; R. Hare, <hi
                        rend="italic">Experimental Investigations of the Spirit Manifestations,</hi>
                    New York, 1856; Allan Kardec, <hi rend="italic">Livre des Esprits,</hi> 1st ed.
                    1853; Mrs De Morgan, <hi rend="italic">From Matter to Spirit,</hi> London, 1863,
                    with preface by Professor De Morgan; Alfred Russel Wallace, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Miracles and Modern Spiritualism,</hi> 1876; M.A. (Oxon.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Spirit Identity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Spirit
                        Teaching·,</hi> Zöllner, <hi rend="italic">Wissenschaftliche
                        Abhandlungen</hi> (the part relating to spiritualism has been translated
                    into English under the title <hi rend="italic">Transcendental Physics</hi> by C.
                    C. Massey). A succinct account of typical frauds of spiritualism is contained in
                    D. D. Home’s <hi rend="italic">Lights and Shadows of Spiritualism,</hi> 2d ed.,
                    1877-78. (E. M. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
