<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0553-0530-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STEIN, Heinrich Friedrich Karl, Baron vom und
                    zum</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 530</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wk9g">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="25" ref="fasttopic:1132936">Steins</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092555">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092647">Reformers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n553/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STEIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Heinrich Friedrich Karl, Baron
                    vom und zum</hi></label> (1757-1831), one of the greatest of German statesmen,
                    and perhaps the most influential forerunner of Bismarck in the creation of
                    German unity, was born at Nassau on October 26, 1757. He was a member of the
                    independent noblesse or knighthood of the German empire (Reichsritter-schaft),
                    and his ancient family seat, Burg Stein, lies on a hill rising above the Lahn
                    opposite Nassau. In his autobiography he speaks of his parents as “pious and
                    genuinely German,” and ascribes to their teaching his own religious and
                    patriotic feelings, his sense of the dignity of his family and order, and his
                    conviction of the duty of devoting his life to the public weal. Though the
                    youngest but one of ten children, Stein was selected by his parents as the
                    “Stammhalter,” or representative and maintainer of the family name and dignity,
                    and his elder brothers acquiesced in this arrangement.</p>
                <p>From 1773 to 1777 Stein studied political economy, jurisprudence, and history at
                    the university of Göttingen, where he made his first acquaintance with English
                    institutions, his knowledge and appreciation of which are often manifest in his
                    later career. His original intention was to qualify for an appointment in the
                    imperial courts, but this sphere of work was little to his taste, and in 1780 he
                    took the step, somewhat unusual for an imperial knight, of entering the service
                    of Prussia. He became an official in the mining department, and by 1784 had
                    risen to be head of the administration of mines and manufactures for Westphalia.
                    In 1796 he was made supreme president of the provincial chambers of Westphalia,
                    an appointment which gave him opportunity to evince his great administrative
                    talents. In 1785 his administrative career was interrupted for a short time by a
                    diplomatic mission to the elector of Mainz, and in 1786-87 he made a long
                    professional tour in England, chiefly in the mining districts.</p>
                <p>In 1804 Stein was created a minister of state, with the portfolio of excise,
                    customs, manufactures, and trade. In this capacity he abolished the internal
                    customs duties throughout Prussia, and effected several other needed reforms;
                    but he was unable to modify the general disastrous tenour of the Prussian
                    policy, which was now ripening for the catastrophe of Jena. Stein’s
                    remonstrances with the king and his strictures upon the course of the
                    administration were couched in the most open and unsparing language, and they
                    were specially directed against the system of government through privy cabinet
                    counsellors, who had practically come to supplant the ministers without
                    possessing either an official knowledge of affairs or a ministerial
                    responsibility. He refused to join in the reconstituted ministry after Jena
                    unless this abuse were done away with, and Frederick William III., already
                    wounded by the frankness of Stein’s criticism, sent him his dismissal in a most
                    ungracious form (January 3, 1807). When the king, however, found himself left in
                    the lurch by his ally Russia, at the peace of Tilsit (July 9, 1807), he turned
                    in despair to the strong and candid counsellor he had dismissed half a year
                    before, and invited Stein to re-enter his service, practically on his own terms.
                    Curiously enough Stein’s appointment as minister president was encouraged by
                    Napoleon, who seems to have seen in him merely the clever organizer and
                    financier, who would most easily put Prussia in a position to pay the enormous
                    war indemnity levied on it. Stein took office on October 4, 1807, and at once
                    began that weighty series of organic reforms with which his name is most
                    indissolubly connected. The emancipation edict appeared on October 9, 1807, a
                    few days after the formal receipt of his powers, and the municipal ordinance was
                    published on November 19, 1808. In the interim he co-operated zealously with
                    Scharnhorst in the reconstitution of the army, carried out a number of important
                    financial and administrative reforms, and prepared the way for a thorough<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n554/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0554-0531"/> reconstruction of the whole framework of
                    government, which, however, he himself was not to have an opportunity to
                    effect.</p>
                <p>Stein’s momentous ministry did not last much more than a year. Napoleon soon
                    awoke to the eminently patriotic and energetic character of the man he had
                    incautiously recommended, and an intercepted letter gave him the opportunity to
                    demand Stein’s dismissal. Frederick William had no option but to comply, as he
                    shrank from the only possible alternative of an open breach with the French
                    emperor. Stein was proscribed by Napoleon, his property in Westphalia was
                    confiscated, and he himself had to take refuge in Austria from the French
                    troops.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The belief that
                    Stein occupied himself during his retirement in propagating his opinions through
                    the “Tugendbund” seems from recent investigations to be erroneous. He had no
                    sympathy with secret societies, and all indications go to show that he rather
                    disapproved of the league than otherwise.</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1812 the czar Alexander invited Stein to St Petersburg, where he filled the
                    post of unofficial adviser to his imperial majesty on German or rather on
                    anti-Napoleonic affairs; and it would perhaps be difficult to overestimate the
                    influence of the proximity of such a man in keeping Alexander’s courage screwed
                    to the sticking-point. When the scene of the campaign of 1812 was transferred to
                    Germany, Stein was entrusted with the administration of the Prussian districts
                    occupied by the Russian troops, and he shares with Yorck the merit of arousing
                    East Prussia to take arms against the French, and so of calling the “Landwehr”
                    into existence for the first time. To Stein also mainly belongs the credit of
                    effecting that union of Russia and Prussia (treaty of Kalisch, February 27,
                    1813) which was perhaps the main factor in the overthrow of Napoleon. After the
                    battle of Leipsic Stein became supreme president of a central commission
                    appointed to administer the lands occupied by the allied armies, in which post
                    he was indefatigable in providing the men and material necessary for a
                    successful prosecution of the war. When the military struggle was over Stein’s
                    work was practically done. The two tendencies of absolutism on the one hand and
                    particularism on the other which determined the tone of the Vienna congress were
                    equally repugnant to him, and he took little part in its deliberations. He also
                    refused the invitations of Austria and Prussia to represent them at the
                    Frankfort diet, a makeshift in which he had no confidence or hope. The rest of
                    his life he spent in retirement, sharing his time between Frankfort and his
                    property in Westphalia, and the only office he ever again filled was that of
                    marshal of the provincial estates. In 1819 he founded the society for the
                    publication of the <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Germanise Historica,</hi> which
                    has since done such admirable work. He died on June 29, 1831, in his
                    seventy-fourth year, on his estate of Cappenberg in Westphalia, leaving a family
                    of three daughters. His wife was Countess von Walmoden-Gim-born of Hanover, a
                    granddaughter of George II.</p>
                <p>Stein’s distinguishing merit as a statesman is that he was practically the first
                    to see the urgent necessity of German unity, to contemplate its realization as
                    possible, and to inaugurate a policy likely to bring it about. That which, now
                    that it has been accomplished by Stein’s great successor, seems to us almost a
                    matter of course, was a mere chimera to most of our forefathers, and it required
                    the faculty of a political seer to attain Stein’s clear views of future
                    possibilities. Stein saw, too, that the only hope of salvation lay in the people
                    as such,—that he must enlist the sympathies of the nation and raise its moral
                    tone. To this end a series of great and just reforms was necessary. If a deep
                    national sentiment was to be evoked, the people must be freed from feudal
                    burdens; if they were to carry on an effective struggle for independence, they
                    must first acquire personal liberty. His emancipation edict, therefore, which
                    has been called the habeas corpus act of Prussia, abolished serfdom, did away
                    with the distinctions of caste, and abrogated the feudal restrictions upon the
                    free disposition of person and property (compare <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Prussia,</hi> vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xx.</hi> pp. 11, 12). This reform,
                    however, Stein found, in a sense, ready to his hand; it was demanded by the
                    spirit of the times, and can hardly be looked on as a purely individual
                    achievement. His most distinctive work was a great scheme of political reform,
                    in which he contemplated the conversion of the absolute monarchy of Prussia into
                    a free representative state. He wisely began the process by introducing the
                    principle of free local government in his Stadte-Ordnung, or municipal
                    ordinance. The people had to be roused to take an interest in governing
                    themselves, and it was easier to expand this interest from the local to the
                    national than to work down from the national to the local. Stein did not see
                    much more than this beginning of his plans, but the famous “Political Testament”
                    he drew up on leaving office show's how wide-sweeping were the reforms he
                    contemplated. The right of self-government was to be extended to the rural
                    communes, and a thorough reform of every branch of the administration was to be
                    effected, while the coping-stone of the new edifice was to take the form of a
                    free representative parliament. Time, however, has been on his side, and it is
                    not too much to say with Prof. Von Treitschke that every advance Germany has
                    since made in political life has brought it nearer the ideals of Stein.</p>
                <p>The standard work on Stein is the biography by G. H. Pertz, G vols., 1849-55, but
                    few English readers will feel the need of going beyond Prof. Seeley’s admirable
                    <hi rend="italic">Life and Times of Stein,</hi> London, 1879, which also
                    contains a full bibliography. (J. F. M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
