<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0215-0200-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SNIPE (9th edition, volume 22, page 200)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rb9k">Snipes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40v89n0g">Goat</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1121883">Snipes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151360">Tinkers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006685">Males</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n215/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SNIPE</label> (Anglo-Saxon <hi rend="italic">Snite,</hi>
                    Icelandic <hi rend="italic">Snipa,</hi> Dutch <hi rend="italic">Snip</hi>,
                    German <hi rend="italic">Schnepfe),</hi> one of the commonest Limicoline birds,
                    in high repute no less for the table than for the exciting sport it affords. It
                    is the <hi rend="italic">Scοlοpax gallinago</hi> of Linnaeus, but by many later
                    writers separated from that genus, the type of which is the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Woodcock</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> and hence has been variously
                    named <hi rend="italic">Gallinago caelestis, G. media,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >G. scolopacina.</hi> Though considerable numbers are still bred in the
                    British Islands, notwithstanding the diminished area suitable for them, most of
                    those that fall to the gun are undoubtedly of foreign origin, arriving from
                    Scandinavia towards the close of summer or later, and many will outstay the
                    winter if the weather be not too severe, while the home-bred birds emigrate in
                    autumn to return the following spring. Of late years British markets have been
                    chiefly supplied from abroad, mostly from Holland.</p>
                <p>The Snipe is fortunately too well known to need description, for a description of
                    its variegated plumage, if attempted, would be long. It may be noticed, however,
                    as subject to no inconsiderable variation, especially in the extent of dark
                    markings on the belly, flanks, and axillaries, while examples are occasionally
                    seen in which no trace of white, and hardly any of buff or grey, is visible,—the
                    place of these tints being taken by several shades of chocolatebrown. Such
                    examples were long considered to form a distinct species, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >S. sabinii,</hi> but its invalidity is now generally admitted. Other
                    examples in which buff or rust-colour predominates have also been deemed
                    distinct, and to these has been applied the epithet <hi rend="italic"
                        >russata.</hi> Again, a slight deviation from the ordinary formation of the
                    tail, whose rectrices normally number 14, and present a rounded termination, has
                    led to the belief in a species, <hi rend="italic">S. brehmi,</hi> now wholly
                    discredited. But, setting aside two European species, to be presently noticed
                    more particularly, there are at least a score, more or less nearly allied,
                    belonging to various parts of the world, for no considerable territory is
                    without its representative. Thus North America produces <hi rend="italic">G.
                        wilsoni,</hi> so like the English Snipe as not to be easily distinguished
                    except by the possession of 16 rectrices, and Australia has <hi rend="italic">G.
                        australis,</hi> a larger and somewhat differently coloured bird with 18
                    rectrices. India, while affording a winter resort to multitudes of the common
                    species, which besides Europe extends its breeding range over the whole of
                    northern Asia, has the so-called Pin-tailed Snipe, <hi rend="italic">G.
                        stenura,</hi> in which the number of rectrices is still greater, varying
                    from 20 to 28, it is said, though 22 seems to be the usual number. This curious
                    variability, deserving more attention than it has yet received, only occurs in
                    the outer feathers of the series, which are narrow in form and extremely stiff,
                    there being always 10 in the middle of ordinary breadth.</p>
                <p>Those who only know the Snipe as it shows itself in the shooting-season, when
                    without warning it rises from the boggy ground uttering a sharp note that sounds
                    like <hi rend="italic">scape, scape,</hi> and, after a few rapid twists, darts
                    away, if it be not brought down by the gun, to disappear in the distance after a
                    desultory flight, have no conception of the bird’s behaviour at breeding-time.
                    Then, though flushed quite as suddenly, it will fly round the intruder, at times
                    almost hovering over his head. But, if he have patience, he will see it mount
                    aloft and there execute a series of aerial evolutions of an astounding kind.
                    After wildly circling about, and reaching a height at which it appears a mere
                    speck, where it winnows a random zigzag course, it abruptly shoots downwards and
                    aslant, and then as abruptly stops to regain its former elevation, and this
                    process it repeats many times. A few seconds, more or less according to
                    distance, after each of these headlong descents a mysterious sound strikes his
                    ear—compared by some to drumming and by others to the bleating of a sheep or
                        goat,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hence in many
                            languages the Snipe is known by names signifying ‘Flying Goat,”
                            “Heaven’s Ram,” as in Scotland by “Heather-bleater.”</p></note> which
                    sound evidently comes from the bird as it shoots downwards, and then only; but
                    how the sound is made is a question on which many persons are still undecided.
                    There are those who maintain that it proceeds from the throat, while some
                    declare it is produced by the wings, which sharp-sighted observers say they can
                    see in tremulous motion.</p>
                <p>Others, again, assert that it is caused by the vibration of the webs of the outer
                    rectrices, and these last have in support of their opinion the fact that a
                    similar sound may be made by affixing those feathers to the end of a rod and
                    drawing them rapidly downwards in the same position as they occupy in the bird’s
                    tail while it is performing the feat.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Cf. Meves, <hi rend="italic">(Efvers. K. Vet.-Akad.
                                Forh.,</hi> 1856, pp. 275-277 (transl. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Naumannia,</hi> 1858, pp. 116, 117), and <hi rend="italic">Proc.
                                Zool. Society,</hi> 1858, p. 202, with Wolley’s remarks thereon, <hi
                                rend="italic">Zool. Garten,</hi> 1876, pp. 204-208.</p></note> But,
                    however it be produced, the air will also ring with loud notes that have been
                    syllabled <hi rend="italic">tinker, tinker, tinker,</hi> while other notes in a
                    different key, something like <hi rend="italic">djepp, djepp, djepp</hi> rapidly
                    uttered, may be heard as if in response. The nest is always on the ground and is
                    a rather deep hollow wrought in a tuft of herbage, and lined with dry
                    grass-leaves. The eggs are four in number, of a dark olive colour, blotched and
                    spotted with rich brown. The young when freshly hatched are beautifully clothed
                    in down of a dark maroon, variegated with black, white, and buff.</p>
                <p>The Double or Solitary Snipe of English sportsmen, <hi rend="italic">S.
                        major,</hi> a larger species, also inhabits northern Europe and may be
                    readily recognized by the white bars in its wings and by its 16 or occasionally
                    18 rectrices. It has also a very different behaviour. When flushed it rises
                    without alarm-cry, and flies heavily. In the breeding season mud of its
                    love-performance is exhibited on the ground, and the sounds to which it gives
                    rise are of another character; but the exact way in which its “drumming” is
                    effected has not been ascertained. Its gesticulations at this time have been
                    well described by Prof. Collett in a communication to Mr Dresser’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Birds of Europe</hi> (vol. vii. pp. 635-637). It visits Great
                    Britain every year at the close of summer, but in very small numbers, and is
                    almost always seen singly—not uncommonly in places where no one could expect to
                    find a Snipe.</p>
                <p>The third species of which any details can here be given is the Jack-<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Though this word is
                            clearly not intended as a nickname, such as is the prefix which custom
                            has applied to the Daw, Pie, Redbreast, Titmouse, or Wren, one can only
                            guess at its origin or meaning. It may be, as in Jackass, an indication
                            of sex, for it is a popular belief that the Jack-Snipe is the male of
                            the common species; or, again, it may refer to the comparatively small
                            size of the bird, as the “jack” in the game of bowls is the smallest of
                            the balls used, and as fishermen call the smaller Pikes
                        Jacks.</p></note> or Half-Snipe, <hi rend="italic">S. gallinula,</hi> the
                    smallest and most beautifully coloured of the group. Without being as numerous
                    as the common or full Snipe, it is of frequent occurrence in Great Britain from
                    September to April (and occasionally both earlier and later); but it breeds
                    only, so far as is known, in northern Scandinavia and Russia; and the first
                    trustworthy information on that subject was obtained by Wolley in June 1853,
                    when he found several of its nests near Muonioniska in Lapland.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>His account was published
                            by Hewitson in May 1855 <hi rend="italic">{Eggs Br. Birds,</hi> 3d ed.,
                            ii. pp. 356-358).</p></note> Instead of rising wildly as do most of its
                    allies, it generally lies so close as to let itself be almost trodden upon, and
                    then takes wing silently, to alight at a short distance (if it escape the gun),
                    and to return to the same place on the morrow. In the breeding-season, however,
                    it is as noisy and conspicuous as its larger brethren while executing its aerial
                    evolutions.</p>
                <p>As a group the Snipes are in several respects highly specialized, but here there
                    is only space to mention the sensitiveness of the bill, which, though to some
                    extent noticeable in many Sandpipers (see vol. xxi. p. 260), is in Snipes
                    carried to an extreme by a number of filaments, belonging to the fifth pair of
                    nerves, which run almost to the tip, and open immediately under the soft cuticle
                    in a series of cells that give this portion of the surface of the
                    premaxillaries, when exposed, a honeycomb-like appearance. Thus the bill becomes
                    a most delicate organ of sensation, and by its means the bird, while probing for
                    food, is at once able to distinguish the nature of the objects it encounters,
                    though these are wholly out of sight. So far as is known, the sternum of all the
                    Snipes, except the Jack-Snipe, departs from the normal Limicoline formation, a
                    fact which tends to justify the removal of that species to a separate genus, <hi
                        rend="italic">Limnocryptes.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>The so-called Painted Snipes, forming the genus <hi
                                rend="italic">Rhynchaea,</hi> demand a few words. Four species have
                            been described, natives respectively of South America, Africa, India
                            with China, and Australia. In all of these it appears that the female is
                            larger and more brilliantly coloured than the male, and in the
                            Australian species she is further distinguished by what in most birds is
                            emphatically a masculine property, though its use is here
                            unknown,—namely, a complex trachea, while the male has that organ
                            simple. He is also believed to undertake the duty of
                        incubation.</p></note><hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n216/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0216-0201"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
