<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0467-0444-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STAIR, James Dalrymple, First Viscount</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 444</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07378">Covenanters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46m3337r">Civilization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="39" ref="fasttopic:1131380">Stairs</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n467/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STAIR, <hi rend="smallcaps">James Dalrymple, First
                    Viscount</hi></label> (1619— 1695), was born in May 1619 at Drummurchie in
                    Ayrshire. He was descended from a family for several generations inclined to the
                    principles of the Reformation, and had ancestors both on the father’s and the
                    mother’s side amongst the Lollards of Kyle. His father James Dalrymple, laird of
                    the small estate of Stair in Kyle, died when he was an infant; his mother, Janet
                    Kennedy of Knockdaw, is described as “a woman of excellent spirit,” who took
                    care to have him well educated. From the grammar school at Mauchline he went in
                    1633 to the university of Glasgow, where he graduated in arts on July 26, 1637.
                    Next year he went to Edinburgh, probably with the intention of studying law, but
                    the troubles of the times then approaching a crisis led him to change his
                    course, and we next find him serving in the earl of Glencairn’s regiment in the
                    war of the Covenant. What part he took in it is not certainly known, but he was
                    in command of a troop when recalled in 1641 to compete for a regency (as a
                    tutorship or professorship was then called) in the university of Glasgow. He was
                    elected in March. Mathematics, logic, ethics, and politics were the chief
                    subjects of his lectures, and a notebook on logic by one of his students has
                    been preserved. His activity and skill in matters of college business were
                    praised by his colleagues, who numbered amongst them some of the leading
                    Covenanting divines, and his zeal in teaching was gratefully acknowledged by his
                    students. After nearly seven years’ service he resigned his regency, and removed
                    to Edinburgh, where he was admitted to the bar on February 17, 1648. This step
                    had probably been rendered easier by his marriage four years before to Margaret
                    Ross, co-heiress of Balneil in Wigtown. Stair’s practice at the bar does not
                    appear to have been large; his talents lay rather in the direction of learning
                    and business than of oratory or advocacy. His reputation and the confidence
                    reposed in him were shown by his appointment in 1649 as secretary to the
                    commission sent to The Hague to treat with Charles II. by the parliament of
                    Scotland. The negotiation having been broken off through the unwillingness of
                    the young king to accept the terms of the Covenanters, Stair was again sent in
                    the following year to Breda, where the failure of Montrose’s expedition forced
                    Charles to change his attitude, and to return to</p>
                <p>Scotland as the covenanted king. Stair had preceded him, and met him on his
                    landing in Aberdeenshire, probably carrying with him the news of the execution
                    of Montrose, which he had witnessed.</p>
                <p>During the Commonwealth Stair continued to practise at the bar; but like most of
                    his brethren he refused in 1654 to take the oath of allegiance to the
                    Commonwealth and abjuration of royalty. Three years later, on the death of Lord
                    Balcomie, Stair was appointed one of the commissioners for the administration of
                    justice in Scotland on the recommendation of Monk. His appointment to the bench
                    on 1st July 1657 by Monk was confirmed by Cromwell on the 26th. Stair’s
                    association with the English judges at this time must have enlarged his
                    acquaintance with English law, as his travels had extended his knowledge of the
                    civil law and the modern European systems which followed it. He thus acquired a
                    singular advantage when he came to write on law, regarding it from a
                    cosmopolitan or international rather than a merely local or national point of
                    view. His actual discharge of judicial duty at this time was short, for after
                    the death of Cromwell the courts in Scotland were shut,—a new commission issued
                    in 1660 not having taken effect, it being uncertain in whose name the commission
                    ought to run. It was during this period that Stair became intimate with Monk,
                    who is said to have been advised by him when he left Scotland to call a full and
                    free parliament. Soon after the Restoration Stair went to London, where he was
                    received with favour by Charles, knighted, and included in the new nomination of
                    judges in the Court of Session on 13th February 1661. He was also put on various
                    important commissions, busied himself with local and agricultural affairs, and,
                    like most of the Scottish judges of this and the following century, acted with
                    zest and credit the part of a good country gentleman.</p>
                <p>In 1662 he was one of the judges who refused to take the declaration that the
                    National Covenant and the Solemn League and Covenant were unlawful oaths, and,
                    forestalling the deposition which had been threatened as the penalty of
                    continued non-compliance, he placed his resignation in the king’s hands. The
                    king, however, summoned him to London, and allowed him to take the declaration
                    under an implied reservation. The next five years of Stair’s life were
                    comparatively uneventful, but in 1669 a family calamity, the exact facts of
                    which will probably never be ascertained, overtook him. His daughter Janet, who
                    had been betrothed to Lord Rutherfurd, was married to Dunbar of Baldoon, and
                    some tragic incident occurred on the wedding night, from the effects of which
                    she never recovered. As the traditions vary on the central fact, whether it was
                    the bride who stabbed her husband, or the husband who stabbed the bride, no
                    credence can be given to the mass of superstitions and spiteful slander which
                    surrounded it, principally levelled at Lady Stair. In 1670 Stair served as one
                    of the Scottish commissioners who went to London to treat of the Union; but the
                    project, not seriously pressed by Charles and his ministers, broke down through
                    a claim on the part of the Scots to what was deemed an excessive representation
                    in the British parliament. In January 1671 Stair was appointed president of the
                    Court of Session. In the following year, and again in 1673, he was returned to
                    parliament for Wigtownshire, and took part in the important legislation of those
                    years in the department of private law. During the bad time of Lauderdale’s
                    government Stair used his influence in the privy council and with Lauderdale to
                    mitigate the severity of the orders passed against ecclesiastical offenders, but
                    for the most part he abstained from attending a board whose policy he could not
                    approve. In 1679 he went to London to defend the court against charges of
                    partiality and injustice which had been made against it, and was<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n468/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0468-0445"/> thanked by his brethren for his success. When in
                    the following year the duke of York came to Scotland, Stair distinguished
                    himself by a bold speech, in which he congratulated the duke on his coming
                    amongst a nation which was entirely Protestant. This speech can have been little
                    relished, and the duke was henceforth his implacable enemy. His influence
                    prevented Stair from being made chancellor in 1681, on the death of the duke of
                    Rothes.</p>
                <p>The parliament of this year, in which Stair again sat, was memorable for two
                    statutes, one in private and the other in public law. The former, relating to
                    the testing of deeds, was drawn by Stair, and is sometimes called by his name.
                    Although it is susceptible of some improvement, the two centuries during which
                    it has regulated this important branch of practical conveyancing is a testimony
                    to the skill of the draftsman. The other was the infamous Test Act, probably the
                    worst of the many measures devised at this period with the object of fettering
                    the conscience by oaths. Stair also had a minor share in the form which this law
                    finally took, but it was confined to the insertion of a definition of “the
                    Protestant religion”; by this he hoped to make the test harmless, but his
                    expectation was disappointed, and the form in which it emerged from parliament
                    was such that no honest man could take it. Yet, self-contradictory and absurd as
                    it was, the Test Act was at once rigidly enforced. Argyll, who declared he took
                    it only in so far as it was consistent with itself and the Protestant religion,
                    was tried and condemned for treason, and narrowly saved his life by escaping
                    from Edinburgh Castle the day before that fixed for his execution. Stair,
                    dreading a ’similar fate, went to London to seek a personal interview with the
                    king, who had more than once befriended him, perhaps remembering his services in
                    Holland; but the duke of York intercepted his access to the royal ear, and when
                    he returned to Scotland he found a new commission of judges issued, from which
                    his name was omitted. He retired to his wife’s estate in Galloway, and occupied
                    himself with preparing for the press his great work, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Institutions of the Law of Scotland,</hi> which he published in the autumn of
                    1681, with a dedication to the king.</p>
                <p>He was not, however, allowed to pursue his legal studies in peaceful retirement.
                    His wife was charged with attending conventicles, his factor and tenants
                    severely fined, and he was himself not safe from prosecution at any moment. A
                    fierce dispute arose between Claverhouse and his son, the master of Stair,
                    relative to the regality of Glenluce; and, both having appealed to the privy
                    council, Claverhouse, as might have been expected, was absolved from all the
                    charges brought against him, and the master was deprived of the regality. Stair
                    had still powerful friends, but his opponents were more powerful, and he
                    received advice to quit the country. He repaired to Holland in October 1684,
                    took up his residence, along with his wife, some of his younger children, and
                    his grandchild, afterwards the field-marshal Stair, at Leyden. While there he
                    published the <hi rend="italic">Decisions of the Court of Session between 166G
                    and 1671,</hi> of which he had kept a daily record, and a small treatise on
                    natural philosophy, entitled <hi rend="italic">Physiologia Nova
                    Experimentalis.</hi></p>
                <p>In his absence a prosecution for treason was raised against him and others of the
                    exiles by Sir G. Mackenzie, the lord advocate. He was charged with accession to
                    the rebellion of 1679, the Ryehouse plot, and the expedition of Argyll. With the
                    first two he had no connexion; with Argyll’s unfortunate attempt he had no doubt
                    sympathized, but the only proof of his complicity was slight, and was obtained
                    by torture. The proceedings against him were never brought to an issue, having
                    been continued by successive adjournments until 1687, when they were dropped.
                    The cause of their abandonment was the appointment of his son, the master of
                    Stair, who had made his peace with James II., as lord advocate in room of
                    Mackenzie, who was dismissed from office for refusing to relax the penal laws
                    against the Catholics. The master only held office as lord advocate for a year,
                    when he was “degraded to be justice clerk”—the king and his advisers finding him
                    not a fit tool for their purpose. Stair remained in Holland till the following
                    year, when he returned under happier auspices in the suite of William of Orange.
                    William, who had made his acquaintance through the pensionary Fagel, was ever
                    afterwards the firm friend of Stair and his family. The master was made lord
                    advocate; and, on the murder of President Lockhart in the following year, Stair
                    was again placed at the head of the Court of Session. An unscrupulous
                    opposition, headed by Montgomery of Skelmorlie, who coveted the office of
                    secretary for Scotland, and Lord Ross, who aimed at the presidency of the court,
                    sprang up in the Scottish parliament; and an anonymous pamphleteer, perhaps
                    Montgomery himself or Ferguson the Plotter, attacked Stair in a pamphlet
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">The Late Proceedings of the Parliament of Scotland
                    Stated and Vindicated.</hi> He defended himself by publishing an <hi
                    rend="italic">Apology,</hi> which, in the opinion of impartial judges, was a
                    complete vindication. Shortly after its issue he was created Viscount Stair. He
                    had now reached the summit of his prosperity, and the few years which remained
                    of his old age were saddened by private aud public cares. In 1692 he lost his
                    wife, the faithful partner of his good and evil fortune for nearly fifty years.
                    The massacre of Glencoe, which has marked the master of Stair with a stain which
                    his great services to the state cannot efface,—for he was undoubtedly the
                    principal adviser of William in that treacherous and cruel deed,—was used as an
                    opportunity by his adversaries of renewing their attack on the old president.
                    His own share in the crime was remote; it was alleged that he had as a privy
                    councillor declined to receive Glencoe’s oath of allegiance, though tendered, on
                    the technical ground that it was emitted after the day fixed, but even this was
                    not clearly proved. But some share of the odium which attached to his son was
                    naturally reflected on him. Other grounds of complaint were not difficult to
                    make up, which found willing supporters in the opposition members of parliament.
                    A disappointed suitor brought in a bill in 1693 complaining of his partiality.
                    He was also accused of domineering over the other judges and of favouring the
                    clients of his sons. Two bills were introduced without naming him but really
                    aimed at him,—one to disqualify peers from being judges and the other to confer
                    on the crown a power to appoint temporary presidents of the court. The complaint
                    against him was remitted to a committee, which after full inquiry completely
                    exculpated him; and the two bills, whose incompetency he demonstrated in an able
                    paper addressed to the commission and parliament, were allowed to drop. He was
                    also one of a parliamentary commission which prepared a report on the regulation
                    of the judicatures, afterwards made the basis of a statute in 1695 supplementary
                    to that of 1672, and forming the foundation of the judicial procedure in the
                    Scottish courts down to the present century. On November 29, 1695, Stair, who
                    had been for some time in failing health, died in Edinburgh, and was buried in
                    the church of St Giles.</p>
                <p>In the same year there was published in London a small volume with the title <hi
                    rend="italic">A Vindication of the Divine Perfections, Illustrating the Glory of
                    God in them by Reason and Revelation, methodically digested,—By a Person of
                    Honour.</hi> It was edited by the two Nonconformist divines, William Bates and
                    John Howe, who had been in exile in Holland along with Stair, and is undoubtedly
                    his work. Perhaps it had been a sketch of the “Inquiry Concerning Natural
                    Theology” which he had contemplated writing in 1681.<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n469/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0469-0446"/> It is of no value as a theological work, for
                    Stair was no more a theologian than ho was a man of science, but it is of
                    interest as showing the serious bent of his thoughts and the genuine piety of
                    his character.</p>
                <p>It is as a legal writer and a judge that he holds a pre-eminent place amongst
                    many distinguished countrymen belonging to his profession. The full title of his
                    great work, which runs as follows— <hi rend="italic">The Institutions of the Law
                    of Scotland, deduced from its Originals, and collated with the Civil, Canon, and
                    Feudal Laws and with the Customs of Neighbouring Nations—</hi> is fully borne
                    out by the contents, and affords evidence of the advantage Stair had enjoyed
                    from his philosophical training, his foreign travels, and his intercourse with
                    Continental jurists as well as English lawyers. It is no narrow technical
                    treatise, but a comprehensive view of jurisprudence as based on philosophical
                    principles and derived from a Divine Author. But neither does it lose itself in
                    generalities; for it is the work of a lawyer and judge intimately acquainted
                    with every detail in the practical application of law in his native country.
                    Unfortunately for its permanent fame and use, much of the law elucidated in it
                    has now become antiquated through the decay of the feudal part of Scottish law
                    and the large introduction of English law, especially in the departments of
                    commercial law and equity. But its spirit still animates Scottish law and
                    educates Scottish lawyers, and it may be hoped will continue to do so, saving
                    them from being the slaves of precedent or the victims of the utilitarian
                    philosophy which regards all positive law as conventional and destitute of
                    necessary principles derived from the nature of the world and man.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Physiologia</hi> was favourably noticed by Boyle, and is
                    interesting as showing the activity of mind of the exiled judge, who returned to
                    the studies of his youth with fresh zest when physical science was approaching
                    its new birth. But he was not able to emancipate himself from formulae which had
                    cramped the education of his generation, and had not caught the light which
                    Newton spread at this very time by the communication of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Principia</hi> to the Royal Society of London.</p>
                <p>Stair was fortunate in his descendants. “The family of Dalrymple,” observes Sir
                    Walter Scott, “produced within two centuries as many men of talent, civil and
                    military, of literary, political, and professional eminence, as any house in
                    Scotland.” His five sons were all remarkable in their professions. The master of
                    Stair, who became the first earl, was an able lawyer, but still abler
                    politician. Sir James Dalrymple of Borthwick, one of the principal clerks of
                    session, was a very thorough and accurate historical antiquary. Sir Hew
                    Dalrymple of North Berwick succeeded his father as president, and was reckoned
                    one of the best lawyers and speakers of his time. Thomas Dalrymple became
                    physician to Queen Anne. Sir David Dalrymple of Hailes was lord advocate under
                    Anne and George I. Stair’s grandson the fieldmarshal and second earl gained
                    equal credit in war and diplomacy. His great-grandson Sir David Dalrymple, Lord
                    Hailes, also rose to the bench, where he had an honourable character for
                    learning as a civil and humanity as a criminal judge. But his literary exceeded
                    his legal fame. As an honest and impartial historian he laid the foundations of
                    the true narrative of Scottish history, from which all his successors have
                    largely borrowed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">For a fuller account of the life of Stair, see</hi> Annals of
                    the Viscount and First and Second Earls of Stair, <hi rend="italic">by J. Murray
                    Graham, and</hi> Memoir of Sir James Dalrymple, First Viscount Stair, <hi
                    rend="italic">1875, by Ae. J. G. Mackay. (Ae. M.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
