<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0194-0179-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMOKE ABATEMENT (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    179)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1121689">Smoking</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1121641">Smoke</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935806">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:846775">Carbon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885665">Cutlers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr9h">Smoking</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mm2f">Smoke</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm44">Cutlers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j53c">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hm52s7v">Production</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n194/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMOKE ABATEMENT</label>. The nuisance created by coal smoke
                    seems to have been recognized in London as early as the reign of Queen
                    Elizabeth; but it is only in more modern times that the question has come to be
                    regarded as one of real practical importance, and even yet it is far from
                    receiving that general attention which it demands.<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n195/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0195-0180"/> In 1785 the first smoke-abating invention was
                    patented by James Watt, who, as the inventor of the steam-engine, is responsible
                    for so many boiler fires and so much consumption of coal. In 1815 Cutler
                    patented the first would-be smokeless grate for domestic purposes; and his
                    principle of feeding underneath was afterwards adopted by Dr Neil Arnott in a
                    grate which has now been in use in one form or another for more than half a
                    century. There is now a vast number of such inventions, good and bad. In 1819
                    the attention of parliament was directed to the question, and a select committee
                    was appointed “to inquire how far persons using steam-engines and furnaces could
                    erect them in a manner less prejudicial to public health and comfort.” This
                    committee gave an encouraging report. In 1843 another select committee
                    recommended the introduction of a bill prohibiting the production of smoke from
                    furnaces and steam-engines. In 1845 yet another select committee reported that
                    such an Act could not in the existing state of affairs be made to apply to
                    dwelling-houses. The Acts of 1845 and 1847 followed as the results of these
                    inquiries; and since then there has been much legislation brought to bear on
                    factories and railways. The results have been most beneficial; but very much
                    still remains to be done. One is apt to think that, because steam-engines and
                    factories consume individually much more coal than dwellinghouses, they alone
                    are responsible for the smoke nuisance, forgetting how greatly the
                    dwelling-houses outnumber the factories. In reality there is little doubt that
                    domestic fires are mainly responsible for the smoky condition of the atmosphere
                    of our towns; and they for the most part continue to evolve smoke undeterred by
                    legislation or scientific invention. In 1881, however, a movement was commenced
                    by the National Health Society and the Kyrle Society, which resulted in a great
                    smoke-abatement exhibition being held at South Kensington. At the close of the
                    exhibition a national smoke-abatement institution, with offices in London, was
                    incorporated by authority of the Board of Trade.</p>
                <p>A knowledge of the nature of coal and of the chemical changes that it undergoes
                    when burnt is essential for an understanding of the smoke problem. More detailed
                    information on these points is given under <hi rend="smallcaps">Coal,</hi> where
                    the several varieties are described. For the purposes of this article coals may
                    be classified as smoke-producing and smokeless, the former including all those
                    varieties most commonly used as fuel. The elementary constituents of such coals
                    are carbon (generally about 80 per cent. of the whole), hydrogen, nitrogen,
                    oxygen, and sulphur; and they also contain a varying quantity of earthy impurity
                    or ash. The process which occurs in a coal fire consists of two distinct
                    operations. The first, which requires a comparatively low temperature and is
                    independent of the presence of air, is one of destructive distillation, and is
                    similar to that which occurs in the retorts of gasworks. It results in the
                    decomposition of the coal, and in the rearrangement of its constituent elements
                    and the formation of the following substances :—(1) hydrogen, marsh gas,
                    carbonic oxide, olefiant gas, benzine, other hydrocarbons of the type of marsh
                    gas or of benzine, water,—all of which are either gaseous at the temperature at
                    which they are formed or capable of being converted into gas at somewhat higher
                    temperatures, and all of which are combustible except the water; (2) ammonia and
                    other compounds of nitrogen, and certain compounds of sulphur, which are also
                    volatile and combustible; (3) coke, which consists of carbon (and ash) and is
                    nonvolatile but combustible. It is these products of distillation, not the coal
                    itself, that burn, in the strict sense of the word; and this second process
                    requires the presence of air and also a much higher temperature than the first.
                    If the combustion is perfect, the only products are (1)</p>
                <p>water-vapour, (2) carbonic acid, (3) nitrogen, and (4) sulphurous acid, the first
                    of which contains all the hydrogen originally present in the coal, the second
                    all the carbon, the fourth all the sulphur, while the nitrogen is liberated as
                    such together with the very much larger volumes of nitrogen derived from the air
                    which has supplied the necessary oxygen. All these products of combustion are
                    discharged through the chimney.</p>
                <p>Two things are necessary for the ensuring of such complete combustion, viz., an
                    adequate, but not too large, supply of air, properly administered, and the
                    maintenance of the requisite temperature. In practice, however, these conditions
                    are never perfectly fulfilled, and consequently the combustion of coal is always
                    more or less imperfect and gives rise to a complex mixture of vapours. This
                    mixture contains not only the combustion products already mentioned but also the
                    following unburnt or partly burnt distillation products :—(5) hydrogen, (6)
                    hydrocarbons, (7) carbonic oxide, which contains a lower proportion of oxygen
                    than carbonic acid, (8) unburnt carbon in a very finely divided state,—and also
                    considerable volumes of unused air.</p>
                <p>Usually the name “smoke” is applied to this vaporous mixture discharged from a
                    chimney only when it contains a sufficient amount of finely divided carbon to
                    render it dark-coloured and distinctly visible. The quantity, however, of this
                    particular ingredient is apt to be overrated. It always bears an extremely small
                    proportion to the vast volumes of water-vapour, carbonic acid, and nitrogen with
                    which it is mixed; it probably never amounts, even in the worst cases, to 3 per
                    cent. of the weight of the coal from which it is formed; and its importance,
                    reckoned in terms of so much fuel wasted, is certainly not greater than that of
                    the unburnt hydrogen and hydrocarbons. It is perhaps best to use the name
                    “smoke” for all the products of imperfect combustion (5 to 8) which are
                    avoidable, as contrasted with the necessary and unavoidable ingredients (1 to 4)
                    of the mixture. The problem of smoke abatement is thus seen to resolve itself
                    into the problem of the production of perfect combustion.</p>
                <p>The first advantage to be gained by the solution of this problem is an important
                    saving in fuel. It has been calculated that at least twice as much coal is used
                    in boiler fires and six times as much in domestic fires as is theoretically
                    required for the production of the effects obtained. A considerable portion of
                    this loss is due to causes other than those that can be treated of here, and
                    some is certainly unavoidable; but there is no doubt that much of this enormous
                    waste could be prevented by improved methods of combustion, such as would solve
                    the smoke problem. The second advantage to be looked for is a great gain in
                    cleanliness and public convenience. Not only would there be an end to sooty
                    chimneys but the atmosphere of towns would no longer be polluted as it is now by
                    the discharge of unburnt carbon, whose total quantity is enormous, though the
                    amount contained in any given puff of smoke is very small. The “London fog”
                    would be a thing of the past,—not because fogs would become any less frequent
                    than now in London and other large cities, but because they would lose their
                    distinctive character of grimy opacity. It is often stated that these fogs are
                        <hi rend="italic">caused</hi> by the smoke that blackens them; but this is
                    an error. The combustion of coal is certainly responsible for their existence,
                    but it is the sulphur of the coal (oxidized ultimately to sulphuric acid), and
                    not the carbon, that is the active agent. And so long as coal is burnt at all
                    this manufacture of sulphuric acid and of fogs must continue; it is not to be
                    got rid of by improved methods of combustion, though the character of the fogs
                    may be materially altered for the better. The evil effects of town<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n196/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0196-0181"/> air on plant life and human lungs, also often
                    attributed to preventible smoke, are in like manner due to this non-preventible
                    sulphuric acid. The great gain in cleanliness, however, that would follow the
                    abolition of smoke cannot be overrated.</p>
                <p>The methods that have been suggested for the abolition of smoke may be divided
                    into two great classes, viz., those that seek to attain this end by improving
                    the appliances for the burning of bituminous coal, and those that propose to
                    abolish its use and substitute for it some other kind of fuel. The proposals of
                    the first class may be divided into those applicable to domestic purposes and
                    those applicable to boiler fires and other large-scale operations. Those of the
                    second class may be divided according to the nature of the fuel which they
                    suggest. The innumerable inventions of the first class depend for their success
                    (so far as they are successful) on the attention bestowed on the scientific
                    requisites for complete combustion, viz., a sufficient but not too great supply
                    of air, the thorough admixture of this air with the products of the destructive
                    distillation of the coal, and the maintenance of a high temperature within the
                    fire. In our old and crude methods the facts which most militate against the
                    attainment of these desiderata are—(l)that large masses of fresh fuel are
                    continually being thrown on at the top, which cool down the fire just at that
                    point where highest temperature is required; (2) that the products of the
                    distillation of this fresh fuel, heated from below, do not get properly mixed
                    with air till they have been drawn up the chimney; (3) that unduly large volumes
                    of cold air are continually being sucked up through the fire, cooling it and
                    carrying its heat away from where it is wanted, and yet without remedying the
                    second evil. In the improved methods regularity of supply of both fuel and air
                    is sought so as to maintain a steady evolution of distillation products, a
                    steady temperature, and a steady and complete combustion. In many cases it is
                    sought to warm fresh air before it enters the room by a regenerative system, the
                    heat being taken from the escaping gases which would otherwise carry it up the
                    chimney; and in some cases the air which feeds the fire is heated in the same
                    way.</p>
                <p>We cannot here discuss the merits of individual inventions; but we may summarize
                    the chief results of the tests applied at the South Kensington Exhibition. These
                    tests, for domestic grates and stoves, included a chemical examination of the
                    chimney gases, observations of the “smoke-shade” as indicating the proportion of
                    unburnt carbon, and a record of the amount of coal burnt, of the rise of
                    temperature produced, of the radiation, and of the amount of heat lost by being
                    carried away through the chimney. Domestic grates and stoves were divided into
                    six classes as follows :—(1) open grates having ordinary bottom grids and upward
                    draught; (2) open grates having solid floors (adapted for “slow combustion ”)
                    and upward draught; (3) open grates fed from below,—supplied with fresh fuel
                    beneath the incandescent fuel; (4) open grates fed from the back or from the
                    sides or from hoppers; (5) open grates having downward or backward or lateral
                    draught; (6) close stoves. Each of these classes was subdivided according as the
                    apparatus was “air-heating” or “non-air-heating,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>
                    according as an attempt was or was not made to save heat on the regenerative
                    principle. This attempt does not appear to have been distinctly successful in
                    any class except the fifth; indeed the evidence of the tests as a whole is
                    rather against the air-heating principle. The following table gives the average
                    results of tests for each class and sub-class as regards general rise of
                    temperature and radiation per pound of coal and smoke-shade. The figures under
                    the last head refer to a standard of shades ranging from 0 (smoke imperceptible)
                    to 10 (black and dense). It was found in practice that the results of this
                    smoke-shade test were in general accord with those of the chemical examination
                    of the chimney gases. The letters “a” and “n” in the first column signify
                    air-heating and non-air-heating respectively, the average results for the whole
                    class being given before those for each sub-class. All the experiments were made
                    with Wallsend coal, a fair representative of the bituminous coals.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Class.</cell>
                        <cell>No, of appliances tested.</cell>
                        <cell>Average rise of temp. per lb of coal per hour, in degrees Fahr.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Average radiation per lb of coal per hour, in degrees
                            Fahr.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Average smoke-shade.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>2∙88</cell>
                        <cell>3∙58</cell>
                        <cell>3∙01</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, a</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>3∙37</cell>
                        <cell>2∙88</cell>
                        <cell>3∙22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, n</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>2∙45</cell>
                        <cell>4∙21</cell>
                        <cell>2∙78</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>2∙99</cell>
                        <cell>4∙07</cell>
                        <cell>3∙23</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, a</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>2∙81</cell>
                        <cell>3∙93</cell>
                        <cell>4∙11</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, n</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>3∙02</cell>
                        <cell>4∙09</cell>
                        <cell>3∙09</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3 n</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>3∙81</cell>
                        <cell>3∙61</cell>
                        <cell>2∙82</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, a</cell>
                        <cell>none</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>3∙05</cell>
                        <cell>3∙14</cell>
                        <cell>2∙66</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, a</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>2∙41</cell>
                        <cell>2∙42</cell>
                        <cell>2∙23</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, n</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>3∙37</cell>
                        <cell>3∙50</cell>
                        <cell>2∙88</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>3∙38</cell>
                        <cell>3∙70</cell>
                        <cell>2∙73</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, a</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>3∙45</cell>
                        <cell>4∙00</cell>
                        <cell>2∙29</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, n</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>3∙28</cell>
                        <cell>3∙22</cell>
                        <cell>3∙21</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>4∙14</cell>
                        <cell>1∙66</cell>
                        <cell>2∙11</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, a</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3∙79</cell>
                        <cell>1∙78</cell>
                        <cell>1∙58</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, n</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>4∙23</cell>
                        <cell>1∙64</cell>
                        <cell>2∙25</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1-5 (total average).</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>3∙22</cell>
                        <cell>3∙62</cell>
                        <cell>2∙89</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>From this table the following facts, among others, may be deduced :—(<hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>) the air-heating principle has not been applied with
                    success except in class 5; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) close stoves (class 6) are
                    superior to open grates (total average of classes 1-5) in respect of freedom
                    from smoke and of general heating effect, but they are greatly inferior in
                    radiating power,—a deficiency which partly explains their unpopularity in the
                    United Kingdom; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the “slow-combustion” principle gives
                    a high radiation factor, but is otherwise not successful; (<hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi>) the class of air-heating grates with downward, backward, or lateral
                    draughts is, on the whole, most efficient.</p>
                <p>Much attention has been devoted for many years to the question of how to work
                    boiler fires, both for locomotives and for fixed appliances, with the least
                    possible production of smoke and the greatest possible evaporative power. Here
                    the desiderata are essentially the same as in the case of domestic fires, viz.,
                    adequate admixture of the combustible vapours given off by the coal with the
                    necessary air and the maintenance of a high temperature; and the principles
                    involved are consequently also the same, though the appliances are necessarily
                    different. These improvements may be all classed under one or other of two
                    heads, according as the mode of supplying the fuel or the mode of supplying the
                    air is the subject of the improvement. These two kinds of improvement may of
                    course be combined. The article <hi rend="smallcaps">Furnace</hi> may be
                    consulted; see also <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam-Engine,</hi> sect. “Boilers.”</p>
                <p>In the old forms of furnace fresh fuel, as it is wanted, is supplied by hand
                    labour, the furnace doors being opened and large quantities of coal thrown in.
                    One result of this is the inrush of great volumes of cold air, which, aided by
                    the equally cold fuel, lowers the general temperature of the furnace. Mechanical
                    stokers meet this difficulty by supplying the coal regularly in small quantities
                    at a time. They may be divided into those which deliver the coal at the front
                    and gradually push it backward, those which scatter it generally over the
                    surface of the grate, and those which raise it from below so that the products
                    of its distillation pass through the already incandescent fuel. The mechanism by
                    which these results are attained is often of a complex nature.</p>
                <p>It is generally recognized that air cannot be efficiently<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n197/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0197-0182"/> supplied to the furnace if admitted only in
                    front, and accordingly there have been many plans devised for supplying it also
                    at the back. In some cases currents of air are induced by steam-jets; but this
                    plan has not proved very successful. The best inventions are on the regenerative
                    principle. In them the air, before entering the furnace, is made to circulate
                    through chambers heated externally by the products of combustion, and, having
                    thus acquired a high temperature and absorbed heat that would otherwise have
                    been lost, is admitted through openings at the bridge. Many of these appliances
                    are almost absolutely smokeless, and they are much in use.</p>
                <p>The advocates of the total or partial disuse of smoke-producing coals are
                    variously in favour of the following substitutes—anthracite, coke, liquid fuel,
                    and gas.</p>
                <p>For some purposes anthracite and other coals containing a high percentage of
                    carbon may be, and have long been, advantageously used as fuel. They yield a
                    much smaller percentage of distillation products than ordinary coals, and
                    produce no smoke, or almost none. But they are difficult to ignite, and in small
                    fires difficult to keep burning; they give very little flame, and are
                    comparatively expensive, so that they are under considerable disadvantage as
                    compared with the usual kinds of coal. Many of the grates and stoves exhibited
                    at South Kensington were specially devised for burning anthracite, and some of
                    them are decidedly successful; but it is not likely that anthracite will ever
                    take the place of bituminous coal to any great extent in the British Isles.
                    There the great coal-fields undoubtedly are the natural sources of fuel, and no
                    proposal involving a complete neglect of this fact can ever be successfully
                    carried out.</p>
                <p>This remark, however, does not apply to the use of coke and of gas, which are
                    themselves made from coal. Coke is produced in large quantities both for its own
                    sake and as a bye-product in the manufacture of gas for lighting purposes, and
                    is largely used in various kinds of furnace. It gives no smoke; but it resembles
                    anthracite also in being but ill adapted to use in open grates on account of the
                    difficulty of ignition and the absence of flame (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Fuel).</hi></p>
                <p>In America, where natural petroleum is obtained in such enormous quantities, the
                    experiment has been made of using it as the source of heat for boilers. A jet of
                    superheated steam (at about 600° Fahr.) is blown into the hot combustion chamber
                    and the oil and air enter mixed with it. The results are said to be
                    excellent,—the fire smokeless and the efficiency high. The residue from
                    coal-tar, after the naphtha and light oils have been recovered from it, can also
                    be advantageously used in this way. The chief disadvantage attending the use of
                    liquid fuels such as petroleum seems to lie in the fact that they are somewhat
                    dangerous, fatal accidents having occurred in America; and the range of their
                    application is necessarily limited. To use them for the heating of houses is of
                    course quite out of the question.</p>
                <p>Of all the schemes and inventions for the abatement of smoke that one which
                    proposes to distil coal in one operation, and to burn the products of the
                    distillation in another and quite separate operation, is without doubt the most
                    thoroughly scientific; and to it, rather than to patent grates and furnaces, we
                    must look for the ultimate solution of the question. Many arguments may be
                    adduced in favour of gas-heating as opposed to coal-heating, the most important
                    of which are here briefly given. (1) Coal gives, on distillation, not only gas
                    and coke, which are both good heating agents, but intermediate products, many of
                    which are of commercial value; these include ammonia, benzine, carbolic acid,
                    anthracine, &amp;c. As science advances the value of coal-tar will probably be
                    enhanced by further discoveries; already it gives the raw material for the
                    preparation of numberless beautiful dyes, of antiseptics, and of some drugs, and
                    quite lately a substance described as an admirable substitute for sugar has been
                    prepared from it. All these intermediate products are now, according to our
                    barbarous methods of burning coal, used simply as fuel. (2) Gas can be laid on
                    in pipes to any spot, can be lit or turned out at any moment, and can be so
                    managed that less heat is frittered away and more applied to the specific object
                    than in the case of coal-burning. (3) It produces no smoke and leaves no ash or
                    cinder, so that cleanliness is attained and much labour and expense are saved.
                    (4) The coke produced during the preparation of the gas has uses of its own as
                    solid fuel and for other purposes. (5) As has been already said, sulphur is an
                    ingredient of all coals, and sulphuric acid is one of the necessary results of
                    burning them, not to be got rid of by “smoke abatement.” Coal gas, however, can
                    to a great extent be freed from sulphur compounds, and it is possible that the
                    purification methods in vogue may hereafter be improved, so that we have here a
                    means, if any exist, of curing the chief evils of our present system,—injury to
                    our respiratory organs, production of fogs, and destruction of vegetation in
                    towns. The principal disadvantage of the proposal is to be found in the high
                    cost of coal gas, which now varies generally from 3s. to 4s. per 1000 cubic
                    feet, whereas it has been calculated that it would have to cost not more than
                    1s. or at most 1s. 6d. to compete successfully with coal. There is no doubt,
                    however, that the cost might, and it probably will, be brought down to this, as
                    the high rate is due to causes not inherent in the nature of things. Sir William
                    Siemens proposed that two sets of mains should be laid in English towns, one for
                    heating and one for lighting gas, and showed that the first and last portions of
                    every preparation of gas are possessed of very low illuminating power, but if
                    collected apart would do excellently for heating purposes, while the rest would
                    be improved for lighting. It is probable, however, that electricity will
                    ultimately drive gas out of the field as an illuminating agent and that it will
                    then be relegated to its true place as a heating agent. When that is done coal
                    will no longer be burnt as a whole, but only those of its products (gas and
                    coke) which are good for heating and for nothing else.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, ordinary coal gas has already, expensive as it now is, been largely
                    applied to certain purposes, notably to cooking stoves and other domestic
                    requirements, to gas-engines (in which the generation of steam is unnecessary),
                    and to bakers’ ovens; and these inventions are calculated materially to diminish
                    the smoke nuisance. In order to obtain an economical gas capable of being
                    generated on the spot and used for operations on a large scale, Sir W. Siemens
                    devised a gas-producer in which coal is partially burnt in a limited atmosphere
                    and is wholly converted into gaseous products (chiefly carbonic oxide), only the
                    ash being left. This “producer-gas” is a weak fuel, being largely diluted with
                    atmospheric nitrogen, and is therefore inapplicable to domestic purposes; but
                    for many others it suits admirably, one of the best examples of its application
                    being Siemens’s own regenerative gas furnace for melting steel (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Siemens).</hi> Other gas-producers have been patented, and
                    the cost of the gas so made is as low as 4d. per 1000 cubic feet, or even less.
                    It is probably, however, but a temporary substitute for true coal gas. In the
                    use of this latter we shall, without doubt, find the true scientific solution of
                    the smoke-abatement problem. As an example of what gaseous fuel can do, it may
                    be mentioned that in Pittsburgh in Pennsylvania the furnaces are now being fed
                    by natural oil gas and that that city, once one of the dirtiest of manufacturing
                    towns, is becoming one of the cleanest.<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n198/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0198-0183"/><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> The
                    specifications of patents may be consulted. See also C. W. Williams, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Combustion of Coal and the Prevention of Smoke</hi>
                    (London, 1858); W. W. Barr, <hi rend="italic">Practical Treatise on the
                        Combustion of Coal</hi> (Indianapolis, 1879); <hi rend="italic">Official
                        Report of the Smoke-Abatement Committee</hi> (London, 1882); <hi
                        rend="italic">Smoke-Abatement Exhibition Review</hi> (London, 1882); and
                    papers and discussions in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society of
                        Chemical Industry,</hi> 1881 and following years. (<hi rend="smallcaps">o.
                        m.</hi>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
