<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0071-0056-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SILK (9th edition, volume 22, page 56)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39453">Silk</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1919447">Pasteurization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1118724">Silk</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866185">Cocoons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903849">Eggs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n71/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SILK</label> is a fibrous substance produced by many insects,
                    principally in the form of a cocoon or covering within which the creatures are
                    enclosed and protected daring the period of their principal transformations. The
                    webs and nests, &amp;c., formed by spiders are also of silk. But the fibres used
                    for manufacturing purposes are exclusively produced by the mulberry silk-moth of
                    China, <hi rend="italic">Bombyx mori,</hi> and a few other moths closely allied
                    to that insect (see vol. iv. p. 596). Among the Chinese the name of the silkworm
                    is “si,” Corean “soi”; to the ancient Greeks it became known as <hi
                        rend="italic">σήρ,</hi> the nation whence it came was to them <hi
                        rend="italic">Σηρϵς,</hi> and the fibre itself <hi rend="italic"
                        >σηρικόν,</hi> whence the Latin <hi rend="italic">sericum,</hi> the French
                        <hi rend="italic">soie,</hi> the German <hi rend="italic">Seide,</hi> and
                    the English <hi rend="italic">silk.</hi></p>
                <p>The silk industry originated in China; and according to native records it has
                    existed there from a very remote period. The empress Se-ling-she, wife of a
                    famous emperor, Hwang-te (2640 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>), encouraged the
                    cultivation of the mulberry tree, the rearing of the worms, and the reeling of
                    silk. This empress is said to have devoted herself personally to the care of
                    silkworms, and she is by the Chinese credited with the invention of the loom. A
                    voluminous ancient literature testifies not only to the antiquity but also to
                    the importance of Chinese sericulture, and to the care and attention bestowed on
                    it by royal and noble families. The Chinese guarded the secrets of their
                    valuable art with vigilant jealousy; and there is no doubt that many centuries
                    passed before the culture spread beyond the country of its origin. Through Corea
                    a knowledge of the silkworm and its produce reached Japan, but not before the
                    early part of the 3d century. One of the most ancient books of Japanese history,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Nihongi,</hi> states that towards 300 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.</hi> some Coreans were sent from Japan to China to engage competent
                    people to teach the arts of weaving and preparing silk goods. They brought with
                    them four Chinese girls, who instructed the court and the people in the art of
                    plain and figured weaving; and to the honour of these pioneer silk weavers a
                    temple was erected in the province of Setsu. Great efforts were made to
                    encourage the industry, which from that period grew into one of national
                    importance. At a period probably little later a knowledge of the working of silk
                    travelled westward, and the cultivation of the silkworm was established in
                    India. According to a tradition the eggs of the insect and the seed of the
                    mulberry tree were carried to India by a Chinese princess concealed in the
                    lining of her headdress. The fact that sericulture was in India first
                    established in the valley of the Brahmaputra and in the tract lying between that
                    river and the Ganges renders it probable that it was introduced overland from
                    the Chinese empire. From the Ganges valley the silkworm was slowly carried
                    westward and spread in Khotan, Persia, and the states of Central Asia.</p>
                <p>Most critics recognize in the obscure word <hi rend="italic">dmeshek,</hi> Amos
                    iii. 12, a name of silk corresponding to the Arabic <hi rend="italic"
                        >dimaks,</hi> late Greek <hi rend="italic">µέταξα</hi> English <hi
                        rend="italic">damask,</hi> and also follow the ancients in understanding <hi
                        rend="italic">meshi,</hi> Ezek. xvi. 10, 13, of “silken gauze.” But the
                    first notice of the silkworm in</p>
                <p>Western literature occurs in Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Anim.,</hi> v. 19
                    (17), 11 (6), where he speaks of “a great worm which has horns and so differs
                    from others. At its first metamorphosis it produces a caterpillar, then a
                    bombylius, and lastly a chrysalis,—all these changes taking place within six
                    months. From this animal women separate and reel off the cocoons and afterwards
                    spin them. It is said that this was first spun in the island of Cos by Pamphile,
                    daughter of Plates.” Aristotle’s vague knowledge of the worm may have been
                    derived from information acquired by the Greeks with Alexander the Great; but
                    long before this time raw silk must have begun to be imported at Cos, where it
                    was woven into a gauzy tissue, the famous <hi rend="italic">Coa vestis,</hi>
                    which revealed rather than clothed the form.</p>
                <p>Towards the beginning of the Christian era raw silk began to form an important
                    and costly item among the prized products of the East which came to Rome.
                    Allusions to silk and its source became common in classical literature; but,
                    although these references show familiarity with the material, they are
                    singularly vague and inaccurate as to its source; even Pliny knew nothing more
                    about the silkworm than could be learned from Aristotle’s description. The
                    silken textures which at first found their way to Rome were necessarily of
                    enormous cost, and their use by men was deemed a piece of effeminate luxury.
                    From an anecdote of Aurelian, who neither used silk himself nor would allow his
                    wife to possess a single silken garment, we learn that silk was worth its weight
                    in gold.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding its price and the restraints otherwise put on the use of silk the
                    trade grew. Under Justinian a monopoly of the trade and manufacture was reserved
                    to the emperor, and looms, worked by women, were set up within the imperial
                    palace at Constantinople. Justinian also endeavoured, through the Christian
                    prince of Abyssinia, to divert the trade from the Persian route along which silk
                    was then brought into the east of Europe. In this he failed, but two Persian
                    monks who had long resided in China, and there learned the whole art and mystery
                    of silkworm rearing, arrived at Constantinople and imparted their knowledge to
                    the emperor. By him they were induced to return to China and attempt to bring to
                    Europe the material necessary for the cultivation of silk, which they effected
                    by concealing the eggs of the silkworm in a hollow cane. From the precious
                    contents of that bamboo tube, brought to Constantinople about the year 550, were
                    produced all the races and varieties of silkworm which stocked the Western
                    world, and which gave trade, prosperity, and untold wealth to great communities
                    for more than twelve hundred years. The necessity for again going to the East
                    for a supply of silkworm eggs has only arisen in our own day.</p>
                <p>Under the care of the Greeks the silkworm took kindly to its Western home and
                    flourished, and the silken textures of Byzantium became famous. At a later
                    period the conquering Saracens obtained a mastery over the trade, and by them it
                    was spread both east and west,— the textures becoming meantime impressed with
                        the<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n72/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0072-0057"/> patterns and colours peculiar to that people.
                    They established the trade in the thriving towns of Asia Minor, and they planted
                    it as far west as Sicily, as Sicilian silks of the 12th century with Saracenic
                    patterns still testify. Ordericus Vitalis, who died in the first half of the
                    12th century, mentions that the bishop of St Evroul, in Normandy, brought with
                    him from Apulia in southern Italy several large pieces of silk, out of the
                    finest of which four copes were made for his cathedral chanters. The cultivation
                    and manufacture spread northwards to Florence, Milan, Genoa, and Venice—all
                    towns which became famous for silken textures in mediaeval times. In 1480 silk
                    weaving was begun under Louis XI. at Tours, and in 1520 Francis I. brought from
                    Milan silkworm eggs, which were reared in the Rhone valley. About the beginning
                    of the 17th century Olivier de Serres and Laffémas, somewhat against the will of
                    Sully, obtained royal edicts favouring the growth of mulberry plantations and
                    the cultivation of silk; but it cannot be said that these industries were firmly
                    established till Colbert encouraged the planting of the mulberry by premiums,
                    and otherwise stimulated local efforts.</p>
                <p>Into England silk manufacture was introduced during the reign of Henry VI.; but
                    the first serious impulse to manufactures of that class was due to the
                    immigration in 1585 of a large body of skilled Flemish weavers who fled from the
                    Low Countries in consequence of the struggle with Spain then devastating their
                    land. Precisely one hundred years later religious troubles again gave the second
                    and most effective impetus to the silk-trade of England, when the revocation of
                    the edict of Nantes sent simultaneously to Switzerland, Germany, and England a
                    vast body of the most skilled artisans of France, who planted in these countries
                    silk-weaving colonies which are to this day the principal rivals of the French
                    manufacturers. The bulk of the French Protestant weavers settled at
                    Spitalfields, London,—an incorporation of silk throwsters having been there
                    formed in 1629. James I. used many efforts to encourage the planting of the
                    mulberry and the rearing of silkworms both at home and in the colonies. In 1825
                    a public company was formed and incorporated under the name of the British,
                    Irish, and Colonial Silk Company, with a capital of £1,000,000, principally with
                    the view of introducing sericulture into Ireland, but it was a complete failure,
                    and the rearing of the silkworm cannot be said ever to have become a branch of
                    British industry.</p>
                <p>In 1522 Cortes appointed officials to introduce sericulture into New Spain
                    (Mexico), and mulberry trees were then planted and eggs were brought from Spain.
                    The Mexican adventure is mentioned by Acosta, but all trace of the culture had
                    died out before the end of the century. In 1609 James I. attempted to reinstate
                    the silkworm on the American continent, but his first effort failed through
                    shipwreck. An effort made in 1619 obtained greater success, and, the materials
                    being present, the Virginian settlers were strongly urged to devote attention to
                    the profitable industry of silk cultivation. Sericulture was enjoined under
                    penalties by statute; it was encouraged by bounties and rewards; and its
                    prosecution was stimulated by learned essays and rhapsodical rhymes, of which
                    this is a sample:—</p>
                <p>Where Wormes and Food doe naturally abound A gallant Silken Trade must there be
                    found.</p>
                <p>Virginia excels the World in both—</p>
                <p>Envie nor malice can gaine say this troth!</p>
                <p>In the prospectus of Law’s great <hi rend="italic">Compagnie des Indes
                        Occidentales</hi> the cultivation of silk occupies a place among the glowing
                    attractions which allured so many to disaster. Onward till the period of the War
                    of Independence bounties and other rewards for the rearing of worms and silk
                    filature continued to be offered; and just when the war broke out Benjamin
                    Franklin and others were engaged in nursing a filature into healthy life at
                    Philadelphia. With the resumption of peaceful enterprise, the stimulus of
                    bounties was again applied—first by Connecticut in 1783; and such efforts have
                    been continued sporadically down almost to the present day. Bounties were last
                    offered by the State of California in 1865-66, but the State law was soon
                    repealed, and an attempt to obtain State encouragement again in 1872 was
                    defeated. About 1838 a speculative mania for the cultivation of silk developed
                    itself with remarkable severity in the United States. It was caused principally
                    through the representations of Samuel Whitmarsh as to the capabilities of the
                    South Sea Islands mulberry (<hi rend="italic">Morus multicaulis</hi>) for
                    feeding silkworms; and so intense was the excitement that plants and crops of
                    all kinds were displaced to make room for plantations of <hi rend="italic"
                        >multicaulis.</hi> In Pennsylvania as much as $300,000 changed hands for
                    plants in one week, and frequently the young trees were sold two and three times
                    over within a few days at ever-advancing prices. Plants of a single year’s
                    growth reached the ridiculous price of $1 each at the height of the fever,
                    which, however, did not last long, for in 1839 the speculation collapsed; the
                    famous <hi rend="italic">Morus multicaulis</hi> was found to be no golden tree,
                    and the costly plantations were uprooted.</p>
                <p>The most singular feature in connexion with the history of silk is the persistent
                    efforts which have been made by monarchs and other potentates to stimulate
                    sericulture within their dominions, efforts which continue to this day in
                    British colonies, India, and America. These endeavours to stimulate by
                    artificial means have in scarcely any instance resulted in permanent success. In
                    truth raw silk can only be profitably brought to the market where there is
                    abundant and very cheap labour,—the fact that China, Japan, Bengal, Piedmont,
                    and the Levant are the principal producing localities making that plain.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Silkworm.</hi></p>
                <p>The mulberry-feeding moth, <hi rend="italic">Bombyx mori,</hi> which is the
                    principal source of silk, belongs to the <hi rend="italic">Bombycidae,</hi> a
                    family of <hi rend="italic">Lepidoptera</hi> in which are embraced some of the
                    largest and most hand some moths (see vol. iv.</p>
                <p>p 596). <hi rend="italic">B. mori</hi> is itself an inconspicuous moth</p>
                <p>(figs. 1 and 2) of an ashy white colour, with a body in the case of the male not
                    half an inch in length, the female being a little longer and stouter. Its wings
                    are short and weak; the fore pair are falcate, and the hind pair do not reach to
                    the end of the body. The larva (fig. 3) is hair less, of an ashy grey or cream
                    colour, attains to a length of from 3</p>
                <p>to 3 ½ inches, and is slender in comparison with many of its allies.</p>
                <p>The second thoracic ring is humped, and there is a spine-like horn or
                    protuberance at the tail. The common silkworm produces as a rule only one
                    generation during the year; but there are races in cultivation which<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n73/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0073-0058"/> are bivoltine, or two-generationed, and some
                    are multi-voltine. Its natural food is the leaves of mulberry trees. The silk
                    glands or vessels consist of two long thick-walled sacs running along the sides
                    of the body, which open by a common orifice—the spinneret or seripositor—on the
                    under lip of the larva. Fig. 4 represents the head (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                    and feet (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of the common
                    silkworm, while <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is a dia grammatic view of the silk
                    glands.</p>
                <p>As the larva ap proaches maturity these vessels be come gorged with a clear
                    viscous fluid, which, upon being exposed to the air immediately hardens to a
                    solid mass. Advantage is taken of this peculiarity to prepare from
                    fully-developed larvae silkworm gut used for casting lines in rod-fishing, and
                    for numerous other purposes where lightness, tenacity, flexibility, and strength
                    are essential. The larvae are killed and hardened by steeping some hours in
                    strong acetic acid; the silk glands are then separated from the bodies, and the
                    viscous fluid drawn out to the condition of a fine uniform line, which is
                    stretched between pins at the extremity of a board. The board is then exposed to
                    the sunlight till the lines dry and harden into the condition of gut. The
                    preparation of gut is, however, merely an unimportant collateral manufacture.
                    When the larva is fully mature, and ready to change into the pupa condition, it
                    proceeds to spin its cocoon, in which operation it ejects from both glands
                    simultaneously a line or thread about 4000 yards in length, moving its head
                    round in regular order continuously for three days or thereby. The thread so
                    ejected forms the silk of com merce, which as wound in the cocoon consists of
                    two filaments—one from each gland—laid side by side and agglutinated into one
                    fibre (Fr. <hi rend="italic">bave)</hi> by their own adhesive constituents.
                    Under the microscope, therefore, cocoon silk presents the appearance (fig. 5) of
                    a somewhat flattened com bination of two filaments placed side by side, being on
                    an average from ∙033 to ∙036 mm. broad by ∙020 to ∙025 mm. in thickness. The
                    cocoons are white or yellow in colour, oviform in shape, with often a
                    constriction in the middle (fig. 6). According to race, &amp;c., they vary con
                    siderably in size and weight, but on an average they measure from an inch to an
                    inch and a half in length, and from half an inch to an inch in diameter. They
                    form hard, firm, and compact shells with some straggling flossy filaments on the
                    exterior, and the interior layers are so closely and densely agglutinated as to
                    constitute a parchment-like mass which resists all attempts at unwinding. The
                    whole cocoon with its enclosed pupa weighs from 15</p>
                <p>grains for the smaller races to about 50</p>
                <p>grains for the breeds which spin large cocoons. From two to three weeks after the
                    completion of the cocoon the enclosed insect is ready to escape; it moistens one
                    end of its self-made prison, thereby enabling itself to push aside the fibres
                    and make an opening by which the perfect moth comes forth. The sexes almost
                    immediately couple; the female in from four to six days lays her eggs, numbering
                    500 and upwards; and, with that the life cycle of the moth being complete, both
                    sexes soon die. <hi rend="italic">Sericulture.</hi></p>
                <p>The art of sericulture concerns itself with the rearing of silkworms under
                    artificial or domesticated conditions, their feeding, the formation of cocoons,
                    the securing of these before they are injured and pierced by the moths, and the
                    maturing of a sufficient number of moths to supply eggs for the cultivation of
                    the following year. The first essential is a stock of mulberry trees adequate to
                    feed the worms in their larval stage. The leaves preferred in Europe are those
                    of the white-fruited mulberry, <hi rend="italic">Morus alba</hi>, but there are
                    numerous other species which appear to be equally suitable. The soil in which
                    the mulberry grows, and the age and condition of the trees, are important
                    factors in the success of silkworm cultivation; and it has been too often proved
                    that the mulberry will grow in situations where, from the nature of the leaf the
                    trees put forth and from other circumstances, silkworms cannot be profitably
                    reared. An elevated position with dry friable well-drained soil produces the
                    best quality of leaves. Throughout the East the species of mulberry cultivated
                    are numerous, but, as these trees have been grown for special purposes at least
                    for three thousand years, they show the complex variations peculiar to most
                    cultivated plants.</p>
                <p>The eggs of the silkworm, called <hi rend="italic">graine,</hi> are hatched out
                    by artificial heat at the period when the mulberry leaves are ready for the
                    feeding of the larvae. These eggs are very minute—about one hundred weighing a
                    grain; and a vast number of hatched worms may at first be kept in a small space;
                    but the rapid growth and voracious appetite of the caterpillars demand quickly
                    increasing and ample space. Pieces of paper punctured with small holes are
                    placed over the trays in which the hatching goes on; and the worms, immediately
                    they burst their shell, creep through these openings to the light, and thereby
                    scrape off any fragments of shell which, adhering to their skin, would kill them
                    by constriction. The rearing-house in which the worms are fed (Fr. <hi
                        rend="italic">magnanerie)</hi> must be a spacious, well-lighted, and
                    well-ventilated apartment, in which scrupulous cleanliness and sweetness of air
                    are essential, and in which the temperature may to a certain extent be under
                    control. The worms are more hardy than is commonly supposed, and endure
                    variations of temperature from 62° to 78° F. without any injury; but higher
                    temperature is very detrimental. The lower the temperature at which the worms
                    are maintained the slower is their growth and development; but their health and
                    vigour are increased, and the cocoon they spin is proportionately bigger. The<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n74/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0074-0059"/> worms increase in size with astonishing
                    rapidity, and no less remarkable is their growing voracity. Certain races moult
                    or cast their skin three times during their larval existence, but for the most
                    part the silkworm moults four times—about the sixth, tenth, fifteenth, and
                    twenty-third days after hatching. As these moulting periods approach, the worms
                    lose their appetite and cease eating, and at each period of change they are left
                    undisturbed and free from noise. The worms from 1 oz. of graine—numbering, say,
                    40,000—consume in their first stage about 6 lb of picked leaf, in the second 18
                    lb, in the third 60 lb, fourth 180 lb, and in their final stage 1098 lb,— in all
                    1362 lb of mulberry leaf; but from that is to be deducted about 590 lb of
                    unconsumed fragments removed in the litter, giving of leaf really consumed 772
                    lb. An ounce of graine so treated may yield from 80 to 120 lb of cocoons, 85 per
                    cent. of which consists of the weight of chrysalides and 15 per cent. of pure
                    cocoon. The growth of the worms during their larval stage is thus stated by
                    Count Dandolo:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Weight per 100.</cell>
                        <cell>Size in Lines.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Worms newly hatched</cell>
                        <cell>1 gr.</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>After 1st moult</cell>
                        <cell>15 ,,</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, 2d ,,</cell>
                        <cell>94 ,,</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, 3d ,,</cell>
                        <cell>400 ,,</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>,, 4th ,,</cell>
                        <cell>1628 ,,</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Greatest weight and size</cell>
                        <cell>9500 ,,</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>When the caterpillars are mature and ready to undergo their transformation into
                    the pupa condition, they cease eating for some time and then begin to ascend the
                    brushwood branches or echelletes provided for them, in which they set about the
                    spinning of their cocoons. Crowding of positions must now be guarded against, to
                    prevent the spinning of double cocoons <hi rend="italic">(doubions)</hi> by two
                    worms spinning together and so interlacing their threads that they cannot be
                    reeled. The insects complete their cocoons in from three to four days, and in
                    two or three days thereafter the cocoons are collected, and the pupa killed to
                    prevent its further progress and the bursting of the shell by the fully
                    developed moth. Such cocoons as are selected for the production of graine, on
                    the other hand, are collected, freed from the external floss, and preserved at a
                    temperature of from 66° to 72° Fahr., and after a lapse of from eleven to
                    fifteen days the moths begin to make their appearance. The coupling which
                    immediately takes place demands careful attention; the males are afterwards
                    thrown away, and the impregnated females placed in a darkened apartment till
                    they deposit their eggs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Biseases.—</hi> That the silkworm is subject to many and
                    serious diseases is only to be expected of a creature which for upwards of 4000
                    years has been propagated under purely artificial conditions, and these most
                    frequently of a very insanitary nature, and where, not the healthy life of the
                    insect, but the amount of silk it could be made to yield was the object of the
                    cultivator. Among the most fatal and disastrous of these diseases with which the
                    cultivator had long to grapple was “muscardine,” a malady due to the development
                    of a fungus, <hi rend="italic">Botrytis bassiana,</hi> in the body of the
                    caterpillar. The disease is peculiarly contagious and infectious, owing to the
                    development of the fungus through the skin, whence spores are freed, which,
                    coming in contact with healthy caterpillars, fasten on them and germinate
                    inwards, giving off corpuscles within the body of the insect. Muscardine,
                    however, has not been epidemic for many years. But about the year 1853 anxious
                    attention began to be given in France to the ravages of a disease among
                    silkworms, which from its alarming progress threatened to issue in national
                    disaster. This disease, which at a later period became known as “pebrine,” —a
                    name given to it by M. de Quatrefages, one of its many investigators, —had first
                    been noticed in France at Cavaillon in the valley of the Durance near Avignon.
                    Pebrine manifests itself by dark spots in the skin of the larvae; the eggs do
                    not hatch out, or hatch imperfectly; the worms are weak, stunted, and unequal in
                    growth, languid in movement, fastidious in feeding; many perish before coming to
                    maturity; if they spin a cocoon it is soft and loose, and moths when developed
                    are feeble and inactive. When sufficient vitality remains to produce a second
                    generation it shows in increased intensity the feebleness of the preceding. The
                    disease is thus hereditary, but in addition it is virulently infectious and
                    contagious. From 1850 onwards French cultivators were compelled, in order to
                    keep up their silk supply, to import graine from uninfected districts. The area
                    of infection increased rapidly, and with that the demand for healthy graine
                    correspondingly expanded, while the supply had to be drawn from increasingly
                    remote and contracted regions. Partly supported by imported eggs, the production
                    of silk in France was maintained, and in 1853 reached its maximum of 26,000,000
                    kilos of cocoons, valued at 117,000,000 francs. From that period,
                    notwithstanding the importation at great cost of foreign graine, reaching in
                    some years to 60,000 kilos, the production of silk fell off with startling
                    rapidity: in 1856 it was not more than 7,500,000 kilos of cocoons; in 1861 and
                    1862 it fell as low as 5,800,000 kilos; and in 1865 it touched its lowest weight
                    of about 4,000,000 kilos. In 1867 De Quatrefages estimated the loss suffered by
                    France in the 13 years following 1853, from decreased production of silk and
                    price paid to foreign cultivators for graine, to be not less than one milliard
                    of francs. In the case of Italy, where the disease showed itself later but even
                    more disastrously, affecting a much more extended industry, the loss in 10 years
                    De Quatrefages stated at two milliards. A loss of £120,000,000 sterling within
                    13 years, falling on a limited area, and on one class within these two
                    countries, constituted indeed a calamity on a national scale, calling for
                    national effort to contend with its devastating action. The malady, moreover,
                    spread eastward with alarming rapidity, and, although it was found to be less
                    disastrous and fatal in Oriental countries than in Europe, the sources of
                    healthy graine became fewer and fewer, till only Japan was left as an uninfected
                    source of European graine supply.</p>
                <p>A scourge which so seriously menaced the very existence of the silkworm in the
                    world necessarily attracted a great amount of attention. The disease was studied
                    by the most eminent men of science; reports and suggestions innumerable were
                    made, and a whole pharmacopoeia of remedies proposed. So early as 1849 M. Guérin
                    Méneville observed in the blood of diseased silkworms certain vibratory
                    corpuscles, but neither did he nor the Italian Signor Filippi, who studied them
                    later, connect them distinctly with the disease. The corpuscles were first
                    accurately described by Signor Cornalia, whence they are spoken of as the
                    corpuscles of Cornalia. The French Academy charged MM. de Quatrefages, Decaisne,
                    and Peligot with the study of the disease, and these learned men issued two
                    elaborate reports— <hi rend="italic">Études sur les Maladies Actuelles des Vers
                        à Soie,</hi> 1859, and <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles Recherches sur les
                        Maladies Actuelles des Vers à Soie,</hi> 1860; but the suggestions they were
                    able to offer had not the effect of stopping the march of the disease. In 1865
                    M. Pasteur undertook a Government commission for the investigation of the
                    malady. Attention had been previously directed to the corpuscles of Cornalia,
                    and it had been found, not only that they occurred in the blood, but that they
                    gorged the whole tissues of the insect, and their presence in the eggs
                    themselves could be microscopically demonstrated. Pasteur set himself to
                    elucidate the life-history of these corpuscles, and he soon established (1) that
                    the corpuscles are the special characteristic of the disease, and that these
                    invariably manifest themselves, if not in earlier stages, then in the mature
                    moths; (2) that the corpuscles are parasites, and not only the sign but the
                    cause of the disease; and (3) that the disease manifests itself by heredity, by
                    contagion with diseased worms, and by the eating of leaves on which corpuscles
                    are spread. In this connexion he established the very important practical
                    conclusion that worms which contract the disease during their own life-cycle
                    retain sufficient vitality to feed, develop, and spin their cocoon, although the
                    next generation is invariably infected and shows the disease in its most
                    virulent and fatal form. But this fact enabled the cultivator to know with
                    assurance whether the worms on which he bestowed his labour would yield him a
                    harvest of silk. He had only to examine the bodies of the moths yielding his
                    graine: if they were free from disease then a crop was sure; if they were
                    infected the education would assuredly fail. Pasteur brought out the fact that
                    the malady had existed from remote periods and in many unsuspected localities.
                    He found corpuscles in Japanese cocoons and in many specimens which had been
                    preserved for lengthened periods in public collections. Thus he came to the
                    conclusion that the malady had been inherent in many successive generations of
                    the silkworm, and that the epidemic condition was only an exaggeration of a
                    normal state brought about by the method of cultivation and production of graine
                    pursued. The cure proposed by Pasteur was simply to take care that the stock
                    whence graine was obtained should be healthy, and the offspring would then be
                    healthy also. Small educations reared apart from the ordinary magnanerie, for
                    the production of graine alone were recommended. At intervals of five days after
                    spinning their cocoons specimens were to be opened and the chrysalides examined
                    microscopically for corpuscles. Should none have appeared till towards the
                    period of transformation and escape of the moths, the eggs subsequently hatched
                    out might be depended on to yield a fair crop of silk; should the moths prove
                    perfectly free from corpuscles<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n75/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0075-0060"/> after depositing their eggs the next
                    generation would certainly live well through the larval stage. For special
                    treatment towards the regeneration of an infected race, the most robust worms
                    were to be selected, and the moths issuing from the cocoons were to be coupled
                    in numbered cells, where the female was to be confined till she deposited her
                    eggs. The bodies of both male and female were to be examined for corpuscles, and
                    the eggs of those found absolutely free from taint were preserved for similar
                    “cellular” treatment in the following year. By this laborious and painstaking
                    method it has been found possible to re-establish a healthy stock of valuable
                    races from previously highly-infected breeds. The rearing of worms in small
                    educations under special supervision has been found to be a most effective means
                    of combating pebrine. In the same way the rearing of worms for graine in the
                    open air, and under as far as possible natural conditions, has proved equally
                    valuable towards the development of a hardy, vigorous, and untainted stock. The
                    open-air education was originally proposed by Dr Chavannes of Lausanne, and
                    largely carried out in the canton of Vaud by M. Roland, who reared his worms on
                    mulberry trees enclosed within “manchons” or cages of wire gauze and canvas. The
                    insects appeared quickly to revert to natural conditions; the moths brought out
                    in open air were strongly marked, lively, and active, and eggs left on the trees
                    stood the severity of the winter well, and hatched out successfully in the
                    following season. M. Roland’s experience demonstrated that not cold but heat is
                    the agent which saps the constitution of the silkworm and makes it a ready prey
                    to disease.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wild Silks.—</hi> The ravages of pebrine and other diseases had
                    the effect of attracting prominent attention to the numerous other insects,
                    allies of the mulberry silkworm, which spin serviceable cocoons. It had been
                    previously pointed out by Captain Hutton, who devoted great attention to the
                    silk question as it affects the East Indies, that at least six species of <hi
                        rend="italic">Bombyx,</hi> differing from <hi rend="italic">B. mori,</hi>
                    but also mulberry-feeding, are more or less domesticated in India. These include
                        <hi rend="italic">B. tex</hi><hi rend="italic">tor,</hi> the boro-</p>
                <p>pooloo of Ben gal, a large species having one generation yearly and pro ducing a
                    soft flossy cocoon; the Chinese monthly worm, <hi rend="italic">B.
                        sinensis,</hi> having several generations, and making a small cocoon; and
                    the Madrasi worm of Bengal (<hi rend="italic">B croesi)</hi>, the</p>
                <p>Dassee or Desi worm of Bengal (<hi rend="italic">B</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">fortunatus),</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B. arracanensis,</hi>
                    the Burmese worm,—all of which yield several generations in the year and form
                    reelable cocoons.</p>
                <p>Besides these there are many other mulberry-feeding <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bombycidae</hi> in the East, principally belonging to the genera <hi
                        rend="italic">Theophila</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ocinara,</hi> the cocoons
                    of which have not attracted cultivators. The moths yielding wild silks which
                    have obtained most attention belong to the extensive and handsome family <hi
                        rend="italic">Saturnidae.</hi> The most important of the species at the
                    present time is the Chinese tussur or tasar worm, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Antheraea</hi><hi rend="italic">pernyi</hi> (figs. 7, 8), an oak-feeding
                    species, native of</p>
                <p>Mongolia, from which is derived the greater part of the so-called tussur silk now
                    imported into</p>
                <p>Europe. Closely allied to this is the Indian tussur moth (fig. 9) <hi
                        rend="italic">An</hi><hi rend="italic">theraea mylitta,</hi> found
                    throughout the whole of India feeding on the bher tree, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Zizyphus jujuba,</hi> and on many other plants. It yields a large compact
                    cocoon (fig. 10) of a silvery grey colour, which Mr Thomas Wardle of Leek, who
                    has devoted a great amount of attention to the wild-silk question, has succeeded
                    in reeling. Next in promising qualities is the muga or moonga worm of Assam, <hi
                        rend="italic">Antheraea assama,</hi> a species to some extent domesticated
                    in its native country. The yama-mai worm of Japan, <hi rend="italic">Antheraea
                        (Samia) yama-mai,</hi> an oak-feeder, is a race of considerable importance
                    in Japan, where it was said to be jealously guarded against foreigners. Its eggs
                    were first sent to Europe by M. Duchêne du Bellecourt, French consul-general in
                    Japan in 1861; but early in March following they hatched out, when no leaves on
                    which the larvae would feed were to be found. In April a single worm got
                    oak-buds, on which it throve, and ulti mately spun a cocoon whence a female moth
                    issued, from which M. Guérin Méneville named and described the species. A
                    further supply of eggs was secretly obtained by a Dutch physician M. Pompe van
                    Meedervoort in 1863, and, as it was now known that the worm was an oak-feeder,
                    and would thrive on the leaves of European oaks, great results were anticipated
                    from the cultivation of the yama-mai. These ex pectations, however, for various
                    reasons, have been disappointed. The moths hatch out at a period when oak leaves
                    are not ready for their feeding, and the silk is by no means of a quality to
                    compare with that of the common mulberry worm. The mezan-koorie moth of the
                    Assamese, <hi rend="italic">Antheraea mezankooria,</hi> yields a valuable
                    cocoon, as does also the Atlas moth, <hi rend="italic">Attacus atlas,</hi> which
                    has an omnivorous larva found throughout India, Ceylon, Burmah, China, and Java.
                    The Cynthia moth, <hi rend="italic">Attacus cynthia,</hi> is domesticated as a
                    source of silk in certain provinces of China, where it feeds on the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ailanthus glandulosa.</hi> The eria or arrindi moth of Bengal
                    and Assam, <hi rend="italic">At</hi><hi rend="italic">tacus ricini,</hi> which
                    feeds on the castor-oil plant, yields seven generations yearly, forming loose
                    flossy orange-red and sometimes white cocoons.</p>
                <p>The ailanthus silkworm of Europe is a hybrid between <hi rend="italic">A.
                        cynthia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A. ricini,</hi> first obtained by Guérin
                    Méneville, and now spread through many silk-growing regions. These are only a
                    few of the moths from which silks of various useful ness can be produced; but
                    none of these presents qualities, saving perhaps cheapness alone, which can put
                    them in competition with common silk.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Physical and Chemical Relations of Silk.</hi></p>
                <p>Common cocoons enclosing chrysalides weigh each from 16 to 50 grains, or say from
                    300 to 600 of small breeds and from 270 to 300 of large breeds to the lb.
                    One-seventh of this weight is pure cocoon, and of that not more than one-half is
                    obtainable as reeled silk, the remainder consisting of surface floss and of hard
                    gummy husk or "knub." The total length of double thread or “bave’’ which the
                    silk-worm winds into its cocoon may amount to 4000 yards; the quantity reelable
                    therefrom rarely exceeds 900 yards, and may range from 330 to 650 yards. It is
                    found that the reelable fibre is as a rule thickest and strongest at the middle
                    portion, tapering down very notably towards each extremity. In 1885 Mr T. Wardle
                    of Leek showed by an elaborate series of measurements that the transverse
                    section of common silk double thread or bave measures on the average <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 900</hi> to <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 1000</hi> in. at the
                    thinnest and from <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                        700</hi> to <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 800</hi>
                    in. at the thickest part, and in some instances the middle was one-third
                    thicker, stronger, and more elastic than the ends. As a great deal of silk
                    remains on the husk after reeling, it is obvious that the thread last emitted by
                    the silkworms on the inner wall of the cocoons must be of extreme tenuity. The
                    silk of the various species of <hi rend="italic">Antheraea</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Attacus</hi> is also thicker and stronger at the centre of the
                    reeled portion than towards its extremities; but the diameter is much greater<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n76/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0076-0061"/> than that of common silk, and the filaments
                    under the microscope (fig. 11) present the appearance of flat bands, the
                    exudation from the two spinnerets being joined at their flat edges.</p>
                <p>On this account the fibres of tussur silk tend to split up into fine fibrillae
                    under the various preparatory processes in manufactur ing, and its riband struc
                    ture is the cause of the glassy lustre peculiar to the woven and finished
                    fibres.</p>
                <p>Silk fibre consists essentially of a centre or core of fibroin, with a covering
                    of sericin or silk albumen, and a little waxy and colouring matter. Fibroin,
                    which is analogous to horn, hair, and like dermal products, constitutes about 66
                    per cent. of the entire mass, and has a composition represented by the formula C
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 15</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 23</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 5</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>. It has the
                    characteristic appearance of pure silk,—a brilliant soft white body with a
                    pearly lustre,—insoluble in water, alcohol, and ether, but it dissolves freely
                    in concentrated alkaline solutions, mineral acids, strong acetic acid, and in
                    ammoniacal solution of oxide of copper. Sericin, which constitutes the gummy
                    covering (Fr. <hi rend="italic">gres)</hi> of the fibre, is a gelatinous body
                    which dissolves readily in warm soapy solutions, and in hot water, in which on
                    cooling it forms a jelly with even as little as 1 per cent. of the substance. It
                    is precipitated from hot solutions by alcohol, falling as a white powder. Its
                    formula is C <hi rend="subscript"> l8</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 25</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 5</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>. According to the
                    researches of P. Bolley, the glands of the silkworm contain semiliquid fibroin
                    alone, and it is on exposure to the air that the surface is acted on by oxygen,
                    transforming the external pellicle into the more soluble form of sericin. Silk
                    is highly hygroscopic, taking up as much as 30 per cent. of water without
                    feeling perceptibly damp. It is a most perfect non-conductor of electricity, and
                    in its dry state the fibres frequently get so electrically excited as to
                    seriously interfere with their working, so that it becomes necessary to moisten
                    them with glycerin or soapy solutions. Silk is readily distinguished from wool
                    and other animal fibres by the action of an alkaline solution of oxide of lead,
                    which darkens wool, &amp;c., owing to the sulphur they contain, but does not
                    affect silk, which is free from that body. Again, silk dissolves freely in
                    common nitric acid, which is not the case with wool. From vegetable fibres silk
                    is readily distinguished by the bright yellow colour it takes from a solution of
                    picric acid, which does not adhere to vegetable substances. The rod-like
                    appearance of silk and its absence of markings under the microscope are also
                    easily recognizable features of the fibre.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Silk Manufacture.</hi></p>
                <p>Here we must distinguish between the reeled silk and the spun or waste silk
                    manufactures. The former embraces a range of operations peculiar to silk,
                    dealing as they do with continuous fibres of great length, whereas in the spun
                    silk industry the raw materials are treated by methods analogous to those
                    followed in the treatment of other fibres. It is only floss, injured and
                    unreelable cocoons, the husks of reeled cocoons, and other waste from reeling,
                    with certain wild silks, which are treated by the spun silk process, and the
                    silk thereby produced loses much of the beauty, strength, and brilliance which
                    are characteristic of the manufactures from reeled silk.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Filature or Reeling.—</hi> When the cocoons have been gathered
                    the chrysalides they contain are killed either· by dry heat or by exposure to
                    steam. All cocoons stained by the premature death of the chrysalides <hi
                        rend="italic">(chiques),</hi> pierced cocoons, double cocoons, and any from
                    other causes rendered unreelable, are put aside for the spun-silk manufacture.
                    Then the uninjured cocoons are by themselves sorted into classes having similar
                    shades of colour, size, and quality of fibre. This assortment is of great
                    consequence for the success of the reeling operations, as uniformity of quality
                    and evenness and regularity of fibre are the most valuable features in raw silk.
                    The object of reeling is to bring together the filaments <hi rend="italic"
                        >(bave)</hi> from two or more (generally four or five, but sometimes up to
                    twenty) cocoons, and to form them into one continuous, uniform, and regular
                    strand, which constitutes the "raw silk” of commerce. To do this, the natural
                    gum of the cocoons which holds the filaments together must be softened, the ends
                    of the filaments of the required number of cocoons must be caught, and means
                    must be taken to unwind and lay these filaments together, so as to form a single
                    uniform rounded strand of raw silk. As the reeling proceeds the reeler has to
                    give the most careful attention to the thickness of the strand being produced,
                    and to introduce new cocoons in place of any from which the reelable silk has
                    become exhausted. In this way a continuous uniform fibre or strand of raw silk
                    of indefinite length is produced. The apparatus used for these purposes in some
                    localities is of a very primitive kind, and the reeling being uneven and lumpy
                    the silk is of inferior quality and low value. With comparatively simple
                    appliances, on the other hand, a skilled reeler, with trained eye and delicate
                    touch, can produce raw silk of remarkably smooth and even quality. According to
                    the method commonly adopted in North Italy and France the cocoons are for a few
                    minutes immersed in water a little under the boiling point, to which a small
                    quantity of alkali has been added. A girl with a small hand brush of twigs keeps
                    stirring them in the water till the silk softens, and the outer loose fibres
                    (floss) get entangled with the twigs and come off till the end of the main
                    filament <hi rend="italic">(maître brin)</hi> is found. These ends being
                    secured, the cocoons are transferred to a basin or tray containing water heated
                    to from 75° to 85° Fahr., in which they float while the silk is being reeled
                    off. If the water is too cold the gum does not soften enough and the cocoons
                    rise out of the basin in reeling; if it is too hot the cocoons collapse and fall
                    to the bottom. The ends of the requisite number of filaments being brought
                    together, they are passed through an eyelet or guide, and similarly another
                    equal set are passed through a corresponding guide. The two sets of filaments
                    are then crossed or twisted around each other several turns as if to make one
                    thread, after which they are separated and passed through separate guides to the
                    reel round which they are separately wound. When a large number of cocoons are
                    to be combined into one strand they may be reeled from the tray in four sets,
                    which are first crossed in pairs, then combined into two, and those two then
                    crossed and afterwards combined into a single strand. The object of crossing <hi
                        rend="italic">(croissage)</hi> is to round, smooth, and condense the
                    separate filaments of each set into one strand, and as the surface of the
                    filaments are gummy and adhesive it is found on drying that they have
                    agglutinated into a compact single fibre of raw silk. In the most approved
                    modern filatures there is a separate cocoon boiler <hi rend="italic"
                        >(cuiseuse),</hi> an oblong tank containing water boiled by steam heat. In
                    these the cocoons are immersed in rectangular perforated boxes for about three
                    minutes, when they are transferred to the beating machine <hi rend="italic"
                        >(batteuse),</hi> an earthenware trough having a perforated false bottom
                    through which steam keeps the water at a temperature of from 140° to 160°. In
                    this water the cocoons are kept stirring by small brushes rotated by mechanical
                    means, and as the silk softens the brushes gradually rise out of the water,
                    bringing entangled with them the loose floss, and thereby revealing the main
                    filament of each cocoon. The cocoons are next, in sufficient number, transferred
                    to the reeler’s tray <hi rend="italic">(bacinella),</hi> where the water is
                    heated to about 120°. From the tray the filaments are carried through a series
                    of porcelain and glass eyelets, so arranged that the strand returns on itself,
                    two portions of the same strand being crossed or intertwisted for rounding and
                    consolidation, instead of the croissage of two separate strands as in the old
                    method. The reel to which the raw silk is led consists of a light six-armed
                    frame, enclosed within a wooden casing having a glass frame in front, the
                    enclosure being heated with steam-pipes. To keep the strands from directly
                    overlaying each other and so adhering, the last guide through which the silk
                    passes has a reciprocating motion whereby the fibre is distributed within
                    certain limits over the reel. A sectional view of the reeling apparatus and
                    arrangements—now in common use in Italy—is shown in fig. 12.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Throwing.—</hi> Raw silk, being still too fine and delicate for
                    ordinary use, next undergoes a series of operations called throwing, the object
                    of which is to twist and double it into more substantial yarn. The first
                    operation of the silk throwster is winding. He receives the raw silk in hanks as
                    it is taken from the reel of the filature, and putting it on a light reel of a
                    similar construction,<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n77/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0077-0062"/> called the swifts, he winds it on bobbins
                    with a rapid reciprocating motion, so as to lay the fibre in diagonal lines.
                    These bobbins are then in general taken to the first spinning frame, and there
                    the single strands receive their first twist, which rounds them, and prevents
                    the compound fibre from splitting up and separating when, by the subsequent
                    scouring operations, the gum is removed which presently binds them into one.
                    Next follows the operation of cleaning, in which the silk is simply reeled from
                    one bobbin to another, but on its way it passes through a slit which is
                    sufficiently wide to pass the filament but stops the motion when a thick lump or
                    nib is presented. In the doubling, which is the next process, two or more
                    filaments are wound together side by side on the same reel, preparatory to their
                    being twisted or thrown into one yarn. Bobbins to the number of strands which
                    are to be twisted into one are mounted in a creel on the doubling frame, and the
                    strands are passed over smooth rods of glass or metal through a reciprocating
                    guide to the bobbin on which they are wound. Each separate strand passes through
                    the eye of a faller, which, should the fibre break, falls down and instantly
                    stops the machine, thus effectually calling attention to the fact that a thread
                    has failed. The spinning or throwing which follows is done on a frame with
                    upright spindles and flyers, the yarn as it is twisted being drawn forward
                    through guides and wound on revolving bobbins with a reciprocating motion. From
                    these bobbins the silk is reeled into hanks of definite length for the market.
                    Numerous attempts have been made to simplify the silk-throwing by combining two
                    or more operations on one machine, but not as yet with much success.</p>
                <p>According to the qualities of raw silk used and the throwing operations undergone
                    the principal classes of thrown silk are—(1) “singles,” which consist of a
                    single strand of twisted raw silk made up of the filaments of eight to ten
                    cocoons; (2) tram or weft thread, consisting of two or three strands of raw silk
                    not twisted before doubling and only lightly spun (this is soft, flossy, and
                    comparatively weak); (3) organzine, the thread used for warps, made from two and
                    rarely three twisted strands spun in the direction contrary to that in which
                    they are separately twisted. Silks for sewing and embroidery belong to a
                    different class from those intended for weaving, and thread-makers throw their
                    raw silks in a manner peculiar to themselves.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Numbering of Silk.—</hi> The numbering (<hi rend="italic"
                        >titrage)</hi> of raw and thrown silks, by which the size or fineness of the
                    yarn is stated, is determined by constant length with variable weight, whereas
                    other yarns are indicated by constant weight with variable length. The original
                    standard length was 9600 Paris ells = 11,400 metres, the number being the weight
                    in deniers of 24 grains = 1∙275 grammes. This still remains the most common
                    standard, and in practice the number is ascertained by the weight in grains, <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 24</hi> of a denier of a
                    hank containing 476 metres (properly 475 j metres = 400 Paris ells). According
                    to this standard a single cocoon filament weighs 2 to 3∙5 deniers, a 3 to 4
                    cocoon strand ranges from 7 to 10 deniers, and a 16 or 17 cocoon strand is
                    numbered from 48 to 52. Spun silk is numbered on a different principle. In the
                    United Kingdom it is determined by the cotton standard, the number of skeins of
                    840 yards per lb. In Continental manufacturing centres generally the standard is
                    the number of écheveaux of 500 metres contained in a half kilogramme, or, more
                    simply, the number of kilometres per kilogramme. According to the resolution of
                    the international congress for promoting uniformity in the numbering of yarns,
                    held at Vienna in 1873 and at Brussels in 1874, the grade of silk ought now to
                    be expressed by ten times the number of grammes given by a hank of 1000
                    metres.</p>
                <p>These methods of indicating grades of silk give, however, only the most imperfect
                    idea as to the quality of the thread; and specially they convey no information
                    as to uniformity of diameter and strength. To test the raw material in respect
                    of uniformity a most ingenious American invention, the serigraph, has been
                    introduced, and is now largely used. The serigraph has two reels mounted on one
                    spindle, or at least so arranged that they make precisely the same number of
                    revolutions. The reels are covered with india-rubber, and No. 2 is 3 per cent.
                    greater in circumference than No. 1. The silk to be tested is placed on No. 1
                    reel and from that wound on No. 2, which, being of greater diameter, puts a
                    certain amount of strain on the elastic fibre. In passing from the one reel to
                    the other the silk is carried over an agate hook attached to the bob of a
                    pendulum, so that the strain on the yarn is communicated to the pendulum. The
                    strain caused by the 3 per cent. tension of course varies with the strength of
                    the yarn to which it is applied, being greater with increased strength and
                    thickness, and falling away just as the strength of the yarn decreases. Thus the
                    yarn in passing over the agate hook keeps by its tension the pendulum at one
                    particular position while it is uniform, but when it increases in strength it
                    raises the pendulum higher, and when it becomes weaker the pendulum falls. To
                    the extremity of the pendulum is attached a pencil or marker, which traces on a
                    web of paper, travelling at a rate in fixed proportion to the winding, the
                    changes in the pendulum, and thus is obtained a graphic record in a most
                    distinct manner of every variation in the strength of the silk. The precise spot
                    where any imperfection occurs is shown on the tracing, which thus not only
                    absolutely certifies the quality of the yarn, but also automatically measures
                    the quantity reeled.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Conditioning.—</hi> Silk in the raw and thrown state, as has
                    already been pointed out, absorbs a large amount of moisture, and may contain
                    from 20 to 30 per cent. of water without being manifestly damp. As it is largely
                    sold by weight it becomes necessary to ascertain its condition in respect of
                    absorbed water, and for that purpose official conditioning houses are
                    established in all the considerable centres of silk trade. In these the silk is
                    tested or conditioned, and a certificate of weight issued in accordance with the
                    results. The silk is for four hours exposed to a dry heat of 230° Fahr., and
                    immediately thereafter weighed. To the weight 11 per cent. is added as the
                    normal proportion of water held by the fibre.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scouring.—</hi> Up to this point the silk fibre continues to be
                    comparatively lustreless, stiff, and harsh, from the coating of albuminous
                    matter (gum or <hi rend="italic">gres)</hi> on its surface. As a preliminary to
                    most subsequent processes the removal of the whole or some portion of this gum
                    is necessary by boiling-off, scouring, or <hi rend="italic">decreusage.</hi> To
                    boil off say 300 lb of thrown silk, about 60 lb of fine white soap is shred, and
                    dissolved in about 200 gallons of pure water. This solution is maintained at a
                    heat of 195°, and in it the hanks of raw silk are immersed, hung on a wooden
                    rod, the hanks being continually turned round so as to expose all portions
                    equally to the solvent influence of the hot solution. After being dried, the
                    hanks are packed in linen bags and boiled for three hours in a weaker soapy
                    solution, then washed out in pure warm water and dried in a centrifugal
                    hydro-extractor. According to the amount of gum to be boiled off the soap
                    solutions are made strong or weak; but care has to be exercised not to overdo
                    the scouring, whereby loss of strength, substance, and lustre would result. For
                    some purposes—making of gauzes, crapes, flour-bolting cloth, and for what is
                    termed “souples”—the silk is not scoured, and for silks to be dyed certain dark
                    colours half-scouring is practised. The perfect scouring of French silks removes
                    from 25 to 27 per cent. of their weight, and Chinese silks lose from 30 to 31
                    per cent. Scouring renders all common silks, whether white or yellow in the raw,
                    a brilliant pearly white, with a delicate soft flossy texture, from the fact
                    that the fibres which were agglutinated in reeling, being now degummed, are
                    separated from each other and show their individual tenuity in the yarn. Silks
                    to be finished white are at this point bleached by exposure in a closed chamber
                    to the fumes of sulphurous acid, and at the close of the process the hanks are
                    washed in pure cold water to remove all traces of the acid.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Spun Silk Manufacture.—</hi> The materials of the spun silk
                    trade are—(1) the floss or loose outer fibres which surround ordinary cocoons;
                    (2) the remains of cocoons after the reelable silk has been removed; (3) waste
                    from throwing processes and from all the stages through which reeled silk passes
                    in manufacturing; (4) unreelable cocoons, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> those
                    which are pierced, torn, or cut, stained by dead chrysalides, &amp;c., and
                    double cocoons; (5) cocoons of various wild silks, which are either unreelable
                    or most profitably worked by carding. The waste spinners’ first duty is to bring
                    these diverse materials into uniform fibrous condition for spinning. In dealing
                    with cocoons and cocoon husks, the fibres, which are gummed together into a
                    dense compact mass, must be so washed, softened, and freed from each other that
                    they can be readily teased and torn into a tow-like mass. For this purpose they
                    are washed with a strong hot soap solution in a revolving washing machine, in
                    which they are continuously subjected for three or four hours to<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n78/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0078-0063"/> the action of falling stampers. From this
                    treatment they are taken to the cold-water washing machine, where they are
                    treated with a continuous spray of pure water whilst revolving in the tub under
                    the action of falling stampers, as in the hot-water machine. Next the cocoons
                    are rinsed in a spray of pure water, then the moisture is expelled in a
                    hydro-extractor, and so, thoroughly degummed and softened, they are allowed to
                    dry. For further treatment they are damped with a sprinkling of weak solution of
                    Marseilles soap, then beaten either with the hand or by means of a machine. This
                    machine has a series of leather straps attached to an endless band, which by its
                    rapid revolution causes the straps to hit with a quick whipping stroke against
                    the surface of a revolving tray on which are placed the washed cocoons. The
                    beating serves to free the fibres fully from each other, and expels in the form
                    of a fine dust the remains of chrysalides from the interior of the cocoons. It
                    now remains only by the operation of the cocoon opener to tease out and separate
                    the fibres into a kind of lap. The cocoon-opener is a modified carding machine,
                    the drum or cylinder of which is covered with strong card teeth. On this drum
                    the fibres collect as they are opened and teased out, and when the teeth are
                    full the lap so formed is stripped off by the attendant. The silken fibres are
                    now ready for the operations preparatory to spinning.</p>
                <p>To bring raw waste other than cocoons to this point a different series of
                    operations are necessary. The removal of the gum is first usually effected by a
                    process of fermentation or maceration instead of washing with soap, whereby a
                    great saving of soap is secured. Into a large tank a quantity of waste is
                    packed, and soaked with a weak soapy solution which is maintained by steam at
                    about 170°. The tank is closed over, and in the course of a few days
                    fermentation begins, and according to circumstances is allowed to go on from two
                    to three weeks. From time to time proof samples are withdrawn to observe the
                    progress of the rotting, as over-fermentation would result in the same injury
                    which arises from over-scouring, —weakness of fibre, loss of lustre, and waste
                    of substance. By maceration the silk loses from 20 to 30 per cent. of its
                    weight. From the maceration vat the silk is conveyed to the hot-water washing
                    machine, where with a weak soapy solution it is washed under the influence of
                    stampers for about five minutes. Great care is necessary to prevent the silk
                    from cooling before this washing, as thereby the macerated slime would form an
                    almost insoluble deposit on the silk fibre. From the hot soap solution the silk
                    is taken to the cold-water machine, where, with the aid of stampers, it
                    undergoes a thorough and prolonged washing. After being hung over hurdles to dry
                    it is sprinkled with a weak solution of Marseilles soap, and then dried by means
                    of the hydro-extractor and subsequent exposure in a heated well-ventilated
                    chamber. At this point both cocoon waste, as already described, and floss waste
                    are in the same condition.</p>
                <p>The spinner has now to deal with a mass of entangled fibres of all lengths, which
                    he must render even, parallel, and comparatively uniform in length before it can
                    be spun. The fibres are slightly damped with a weak soapy solution and taken to
                    a filling drum, which consists of a large cylinder having set into it, parallel
                    with its axis, from twelve to twenty rows of strong steel spikes. A feeding
                    apron of cloth covered with card-teeth is provided to the machine, and, as the
                    fibre is carried forward towards the drum, a similar card-teeth-covered band
                    travels close over the surface of the apron, so that the fibre is presented to
                    the drum from between two sets of card-teeth. The rows of spikes catch the fibre
                    as presented to them, draw it through the card-teeth, and carrying it with them
                    lap it around the drum in regular combed-out order. When the spikes are
                    sufficiently filled, the lap is cut at each set of spikes, and so stripped from
                    the drum it forms a definite number of “stricks,” of the breadth of the drum
                    itself and the length of the space between the sets of spikes. These stricks are
                    caught in wooden clamps or “books,” which are fastened in the bed of the flat
                    dressing frame. Over them an endless band travels, having on it at short
                    intervals belts of heckle-teeth, called combs, which comb out doubled and short
                    fibres, and, acting first on one end of the strick and next on the other, leave
                    the silk in the condition of beautifully parallel and comparatively uniform
                    flakes. The product of the first combing, called the first draft, is the longest
                    and purest fibre. The material combed out as it fills the comb teeth is caught
                    in books, and when itself combed out forms second drafts, shorter and less
                    valuable than the first; and again the combings of second drafts, when combed,
                    form third drafts still shorter. In this way five or six separate drafts or
                    combings from the original lap are obtained, all increasingly short and impure.
                    The final combed waste is treated by a different process for making noil or
                    bourette yarn.</p>
                <p>A new form of dressing-frame is now coming into favour, in which the stricks of
                    silk have their ends rolled round wooden rods, and so secured between wooden
                    clamps on the surface of a huge cylinder which revolves so slowly that the
                    attendant can change and fill the clamps as the drum goes round. In its
                    revolution the exposed portion of the silk is first combed on one side by a
                    rapidly revolving card-toothed cylinder, from which it passes onwards to meet a
                    second similar cylinder revolving in a contrary direction, which combs the
                    opposite side. In the second revolution of the cylinder the portion of the
                    strick which was previously wound on the rod is similarly combed on both sides,
                    and thus the entire strick is rendered smooth and parallel.</p>
                <p>The above is an outline of the ordinary process of preparing silk waste as
                    practised in Switzerland and in the United Kingdom, &amp;c., the range of
                    machines being that of Messrs Greenwood and Batley of Leeds. In the great
                    Manningham silk mills at Bradford, Mr S. C. Lister, the well-known inventor of
                    wool-combing machinery, while using machinery of the class described, treats by
                    patented methods peculiar to himself a great proportion of his material.
                    According to his original process, scoured, teased, and opened waste is first
                    drawn into a lap on a screw gill box. These laps, containing all the fibres both
                    long and short, are taken to the circular nip combing machine, where the “top”
                    of long fibre is drawn out as a continuous sliver and separated from the “noil"
                    or short fibre, which according to its length is delivered at separate points.
                    In his most recent mode of working, Mr Lister forms his waste into a broad lap
                    on the large drum of a kind of carding engine, the drum being stripped when its
                    teeth are filled with the prepared fibre. These laps are laid on the feeding
                    table of a machine which has an oscillating or rocking filling head. At each
                    oscillation the end of the lap in front of the table is “filled” on to a row of
                    heckle-teeth parallel with it, and just as the feeding-table recedes a knife
                    comes down between the heckles and the table with a sudden stroke and separates
                    from the lap such fibres as have been placed or filled on to the heckle-teeth.
                    These heckle-teeth in the meantime, being fixed on an endless band, are
                    continuously moving forward in a horizontal direction parallel with the front of
                    the feeding machine, and a set of three such machines place a portion of their
                    laps on to the heckle-teeth in their progress, thus filling the teeth with a
                    fair “bite” of silk. Immediately the heckles have passed the machines, the silk
                    is caught and cleaned off the endless comb by pairs of endless revolving nips
                    rising from under and descending from above, and between these nips the stricks
                    are carried forward in the same horizontal line in which they travelled on the
                    heckle-teeth, which here begin their return journey to be again filled. The
                    stricks in their progress are now submitted to the combing action of revolving
                    card-covered cylinders and card-covered cloth. Half way on in its horizontal
                    path a second set of endless nips seize the combed portion of the silk, the
                    uncombed portion held between the first set is released, and it in its turn is
                    submitted to the combing action of cylinders and endless card-bands. In the end
                    the fully dressed stricks of silk fall on a narrow feeding cloth, which has a
                    combined reciprocating and forward motion, so that the material is spread with
                    the utmost regularity and evenness. It passes through a set of screw gills, and
                    is delivered into cans in the form of a most uniform and equal continuous
                    sliver. The great advantage of these machines is the small amount of tending
                    they require and the large quantity of dressed silk they deliver with unerring
                    regularity.</p>
                <p>The spinning proper of dressed waste is done precisely as in the spinning of flax
                    yarn. The flakes are formed into a broad sliver on the spreading frame, and
                    further attenuated and equalized on the set frame and the drawing frame, from
                    which last the silk passes to the roving frame, where it receives its first
                    preliminary twist and is sufficiently condensed to wind on a bobbin. The rovings
                    are finally elongated and spun on the ordinary spinning frame, and for twisting
                    into thread the yarns in two, three, or more strands are wound together on the
                    doubling frame, and finally twisted as in dealing with raw silk spinning.</p>
                <p>Spun silk, as it comes from the spinning frame, shows a good many nibs and
                    irregularities and some roughness of surface. To remove these it is wound from
                    one bobbin to another over an improving or cleaning and gassing machine, which
                    consists of a frame having attached to it a number of small cone rollers, around
                    which the yarn passes in a way which makes the entering portion of the thread
                    rub against the portion running off. In this way, with considerable rubbing, the
                    yarn cleans itself; and in its course over the rollers it rapidly passes through
                    a gas flame, which singes off the fine projecting fibres, leaving the yarn
                    clean, round, and compact. It is submitted to a further examination by eye and
                    hand after being wound into hanks; and some yarns are finally dressed with
                    albumen and gum solutions.</p>
                <p>In the combing of waste silk as much as from 25 to 30 per cent. of waste in a
                    second degree arises, much of which is very short, full of nibs and dust. From
                    this a lower quality of yarn is spun, called noil yarn, and on the Continent
                    “bourette” silk, to distinguish it from the “floret” silk made from first waste.
                    On account of the shortness of staple it is worked up by machinery different
                    from that used in the floret manufacture, being prepared by carding, and combed
                    out with a modification of Heilmann’s or Lister’s combing machines. The finished
                    noil yarn is very lumpy, and requires severe improving and singeing.</p>
                <p>Spun silk lacks the smoothness, brilliance, and strength of raw silk yarn, but
                    still it is an extremely valuable and useful material,<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n79/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0079-0064"/> and its comparative cheapness gives it an
                    important place among the products of textile industry. It is used very largely
                    in mixed fabrics, as well as for the cheaper ribbons, velvets, hat plush, and
                    for many other silk woven fabrics, as also in the hosiery and glove trades and
                    for sewing, knitting, and embroidering yarns.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Silk Weighting.—</hi> Into the dyeing of silk it is not here
                    necessary to enter, except in so far as concerns a nefarious practice, carried
                    on in dye-houses, which has exercised a most detrimental influence on the silk
                    trade. Silk, we have seen, loses about one-fourth of its weight in scouring. To
                    obviate that loss it has long been the practice to dye some dark silks “in the
                    gum,” the dye combining in these cases with the gum or gelatinous coating, and
                    such silks are known as “souples.” Both in the gum and in the boiled-off state
                    silk has the peculiar property of imbibing certain metallic salts largely and
                    combining very firmly with them, the fibre remaining to external appearance
                    undiminished in strength and lustre, but much added to in size and weight. Silk
                    in the gum, it is found, absorbs these salts more freely than boiled-off; so to
                    use it for weighting there are these great inducements—a saving of the costly
                    and tedious boiling-off, a saving of the 25 per cent. weight which would have
                    disappeared in boiling, and a surface on which much greater sophistication can
                    be practised than on scoured silk. In dyeing a silk black a certain amount of
                    weight must be added; and the common practice in former times was to make up on
                    the silk what was lost in the scouring. Up to 1857 the utmost the dyer could add
                    was “weight for weight,” but an accidental discovery that year put dyers into
                    the way of using tin salts in weighting with the result that they can now add 40
                    oz. per lb to scoured silks, 120 oz. to souples, and as much as 150 oz. to spun
                    silks, and yet call these compounds “silk.” Not only so, but the use of tin
                    salts, especially stannic chloride, SnCl <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, enables
                    dyers to weight all colours the same as black. In his “Report on English Silk
                    Industry” to the Royal Commission on Technical Instruction (1885) Mr Thomas
                    Wardle of Leek says:—</p>
                <p>“Colours and white of all possible shades can very easily he imparted to this
                    compound of silk and tin, and this method is becoming extensively used in Lyons.
                    Thus weighting, which was until recently thought to apply only to black silks,
                    and from which coloured silks were comparatively free, is now cheapening and
                    deteriorating the latter in pretty much the same ratio as the former. Thus the
                    proto-and per-salts of iron, as well as the proto-and per-salts of tin,
                    including also a large variety of tannin, sumac, divi-divi, chestnut, valonia,
                    the acacias <hi rend="italic">(Areca Catechu</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Acacia
                        Catechu</hi> from India), from which are obtained cutch and gambier,
                    &amp;c., are no longer used solely as mordants or tinctorial matters, but mainly
                    to serve the object of converting the silk into a greatly-expanded fibre,
                    consisting of a conglomeration of more or less of these substances.”</p>
                <p>Sugar also is employed to weight silk. On this adulterant Mr Wardle remarks:—</p>
                <p>“With a solution of sugar, silk can have its weight augmented from 1 oz. to 3 oz.
                    per lb. I am not quite sure that this method of weighting was not first used by
                    the throwsters, as sugar is known to have been used for adulterating and loading
                    gum silk for a very long time, and then the idea was afterwards applied to silk
                    after the dyeing operations. It is much resorted to for weighting coloured silks
                    by dyers on the Continent, and, though a very clumsy method, no substitute has
                    been found so cheap and easy of application. Bichloride of tin, having chemical
                    affinity for silk fibre, bids fair to extinguish the use of sugar, which, from
                    its hygrometric qualities, has a tendency to ruin the silk to which it is
                    applied, if great care be not taken to regulate the quantity. There is not the
                    slightest use or excuse for the application of sugar, except to cheapen the silk
                    by about 15 to 20 per cent.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wild Silk Dyeing.—</hi> Among the disadvantages under which the
                    silks of the wild moths long laboured one of the most serious was the natural
                    colour of the silks, and the extreme difficulty with which they took on dyes,
                    specially the light and brilliant colours. For success in coping with this
                    difficulty, as well as in dealing with the whole question of the cultivation and
                    employment of wild silks, the unwearying patience and great skill of Mr Thomas
                    Wardle of Leek deserve special mention here. The natural colour of tussur silk
                    is a greyish fawn, and that shade it was found impossible to discharge by any of
                    the ordinary bleaching agents, so as to obtain a basis for light and delicate
                    dyes. Moreover, the chemical character of the tussur silk differs from that of
                    the mulberry silk, and the fibre has much less affinity for tinctorial
                    substances, which it takes up unevenly, requiring a large amount of dye-stuffs.
                    After protracted experimenting Mr Wardle was able in 1873 to show a series of
                    tussurs well-dyed in all the darker shades of colour, but the lighter and bright
                    blues, pinks, scarlets, &amp;c., he could not produce. Subsequently the late M.
                    Tessie du Motay found that the fawn colour of natural tussur could be discharged
                    by solution of permanganate of potash, but the oxidizing action was so rapid and
                    violent that it destroyed the fibre itself. Gentler means of oxidation have
                    since been found for bleaching tussur to a fairly pale ground, but the dyeing of
                    light colours cannot yet be said to be a commercial success. The silk of the
                    eria or castor-oil worm <hi rend="italic">(Attacus ricini)</hi> presents the
                    same difficulties in dyeing as the common tussur. A portion of the eria cocoons
                    are white, while the others are of a lively brown colour, and for the dyeing of
                    light colours the latter require to undergo a bleaching process. The silk takes
                    up colour with difficulty from a strong vat, and is consequently costly to dye.
                    Moonga silk from <hi rend="italic">Antheraea assama</hi> has generally a rather
                    dark brown colour, but that appears to be much influenced by the leaves on which
                    the worm feeds, the cocoons obtained on the champaca tree <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Michclia champaca)</hi> giving a fine white fibre much valued in Assam.
                    The dark colours are very difficult to bleach, but the silk itself takes
                    dye-colours much more freely and evenly than either tussur or eria silk.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Trade and Commerce.</hi></p>
                <p>About the commencement of this century the chief silk-producing regions of the
                    world were the Levant (including Broussa, Syria, and Persia), India, Italy, and
                    France, the two first named sending the low-priced silk, the other two the fine
                    qualities. Between 1840 and 1850, after the opening of trade with China, large
                    quantities of silk were sent from the northern port of Shanghai, and afterwards
                    also from the southern port of Canton. The export became important just at the
                    time when disease in Europe had lessened the production on the Continent. This
                    increased production of medium silk, and the growing demand for fine sorts,
                    induced many of the cocoon-growers in the Levant to sell their cocoons to
                    Europeans, who reeled them in Italian fashion under the name of “Patent Brutia,”
                    thus producing a very fine valuable silk. In 1857 commenced the importation of
                    Japan silk, which became so fierce a competitor with Bengal silk as gradually to
                    displace it in favour; and recently the native silk reeled in Bengal has almost
                    ceased to be made, only the best European filatures, produced under the
                    supervision of skilled Europeans, now-coming forward.</p>
                <p>China and Japan, both of which contribute so largely to the supplies that appear
                    in European and American statistics, only export their excess growth, silk
                    weaving being carried on and native silk worn to an enormous extent in both
                    countries. The other Asiatic exporting countries also maintain native silk
                    manufactures which absorb no inconsiderable proportion of their raw material.
                    The silk production of the world, including only the amount exported from these
                    Oriental countries, amounts on an average to from 20,000,000 lb to 25,000,000 lb
                    yearly; but the crop is subject to great variations.</p>
                <p>The supply available for European consumption during recent years was thus
                    stated, in bales of 100 lb, by the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur des Soies</hi> of
                    Lyons, 25th July 1885:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1854-55.</cell>
                        <cell>1875-76.</cell>
                        <cell>1876-77.</cell>
                        <cell>1877-78.</cell>
                        <cell>1878-79.</cell>
                        <cell>1879-80.</cell>
                        <cell>1880-81.</cell>
                        <cell>1881-82.</cell>
                        <cell>1882-83.</cell>
                        <cell>1883-84.</cell>
                        <cell>1884-85.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">1885-86 (estimates).</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Italy</cell>
                        <cell>92,400</cell>
                        <cell>57,000</cell>
                        <cell>25,000</cell>
                        <cell>40,500</cell>
                        <cell>62,500</cell>
                        <cell>32,000</cell>
                        <cell>68,500</cell>
                        <cell>70,000</cell>
                        <cell>52,000</cell>
                        <cell>73,000</cell>
                        <cell>65,000</cell>
                        <cell><p>Maximum.</p><p>45,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Minimum.</p><p>40,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>France</cell>
                        <cell><p>44,000</p><p>3,300</p></cell>
                        <cell>16,000</cell>
                        <cell>2,000</cell>
                        <cell>19,000</cell>
                        <cell>13,500</cell>
                        <cell>8,500</cell>
                        <cell>9,500</cell>
                        <cell>9,500</cell>
                        <cell>17,500</cell>
                        <cell>14,500</cell>
                        <cell>10,000</cell>
                        <cell>10,000</cell>
                        <cell>8,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Spain</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>2,500</p><p>16,000</p></cell>
                        <cell>1,500</cell>
                        <cell>750</cell>
                        <cell>1,100</cell>
                        <cell>800</cell>
                        <cell>1,500</cell>
                        <cell>1,500</cell>
                        <cell>2,300</cell>
                        <cell>1,750</cell>
                        <cell>1,500</cell>
                        <cell>500</cell>
                        <cell>500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Greece and Asia Minor</cell>
                        <cell>6,600</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>10,000</cell>
                        <cell>6,000</cell>
                        <cell>6,000</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>6,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,000</cell>
                        <cell>10,000</cell>
                        <cell>8,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total bales</cell>
                        <cell>146,300</cell>
                        <cell>91,500</cell>
                        <cell>38,500</cell>
                        <cell>66,250</cell>
                        <cell>83,100</cell>
                        <cell>46,300</cell>
                        <cell>84,500</cell>
                        <cell>86,000</cell>
                        <cell>77,800</cell>
                        <cell>101,250</cell>
                        <cell>88,500</cell>
                        <cell>65,500</cell>
                        <cell>56,500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>China..</cell>
                        <cell>55,000</cell>
                        <cell>68,000</cell>
                        <cell>65,000</cell>
                        <cell>46,000</cell>
                        <cell>53,000</cell>
                        <cell>55,000</cell>
                        <cell>67,000</cell>
                        <cell>44,000</cell>
                        <cell>47,000</cell>
                        <cell>50,000</cell>
                        <cell>50,000</cell>
                        <cell>45,000</cell>
                        <cell>42,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Canton</cell>
                        <cell>19,800</cell>
                        <cell>14,000</cell>
                        <cell>10,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,500</cell>
                        <cell>9,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,500</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>14,500</cell>
                        <cell>11,500</cell>
                        <cell>16,000</cell>
                        <cell>7,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Bengal</cell>
                        <cell>11,000</cell>
                        <cell>8,492</cell>
                        <cell>6,000</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>6,000</cell>
                        <cell>5,000</cell>
                        <cell>4,000</cell>
                        <cell>3,000</cell>
                        <cell>3,000</cell>
                        <cell>3,000</cell>
                        <cell>3,000</cell>
                        <cell>2,000</cell>
                        <cell>2,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Japan</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>14,000</cell>
                        <cell>13,000</cell>
                        <cell>22,000</cell>
                        <cell>22,000</cell>
                        <cell>14,000</cell>
                        <cell>15,000</cell>
                        <cell>15,500</cell>
                        <cell>25,000</cell>
                        <cell>25,000</cell>
                        <cell>20,000</cell>
                        <cell>15,000</cell>
                        <cell>12,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total bales</cell>
                        <cell>85,800</cell>
                        <cell>104,492</cell>
                        <cell>94,000</cell>
                        <cell>85,500</cell>
                        <cell>90,000</cell>
                        <cell>86,500</cell>
                        <cell>91,000</cell>
                        <cell>77,000</cell>
                        <cell>86,500</cell>
                        <cell>94,000</cell>
                        <cell>80,000</cell>
                        <cell>74,000</cell>
                        <cell>68,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Grand total of bales</cell>
                        <cell>232,100</cell>
                        <cell>195,992</cell>
                        <cell>132,500</cell>
                        <cell>151,750</cell>
                        <cell>173,100</cell>
                        <cell>132,800</cell>
                        <cell>175,500</cell>
                        <cell>163,000</cell>
                        <cell>164,300</cell>
                        <cell>195,250</cell>
                        <cell>168,500</cell>
                        <cell>139,500</cell>
                        <cell>124,500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Price of Tsatlee No. 4</cell>
                        <cell>15s.</cell>
                        <cell>15s.</cell>
                        <cell>28s.</cell>
                        <cell>l7s. 6d.</cell>
                        <cell>15s.</cell>
                        <cell>15s. 3d.</cell>
                        <cell>13s. 9d.</cell>
                        <cell>17s.</cell>
                        <cell>14s. 6d.</cell>
                        <cell>16s.</cell>
                        <cell>13s.</cell>
                        <cell>12s. 6d.</cell>
                        <cell>12s. 6d.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n80/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0080-0065"/>
                <p>While these tables indicate remarkable fluctuation of supply they show generally
                    that Asiatic countries, besides supplying their own considerable demands, send
                    to Europe fully one half of the whole silk consumed in Western manufactures.
                    China stands first as a silk-producing country, yielding about 35 per cent. of
                    the entire supply; the whole produce of Italy amounts to nearly the same
                    proportion; the exports of Japan account for about 12 per cent. of the annual
                    supply; while in recent years France and the Levant are credited with about
                    equal proportions.</p>
                <p>In the United Kingdom the trade in raw silks has been in a condition of decline
                    for a considerable number of years, much of the Chinese and Eastern produce
                    which formerly came to London now being unshipped at Marseilles, and sold in the
                    Lyons market, which has become the leading silk mart. But there is a very steady
                    and continuous expansion in the demand for waste silks and cocoons for the spun
                    silk trade. The following figures show the official annual returns of silk
                    imports since 1860, the date of the French commercial treaty, which exposed many
                    branches of the trade to severe and fatal competition :—</p>
                <table cols="5">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Years.</cell>
                        <cell>Raw Silk.</cell>
                        <cell>Knubs or Husks of Silk and Waste.</cell>
                        <cell>Thrown Silk.</cell>
                        <cell>Silk Manufactures.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell>Cwts.</cell>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell>£</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1860-65</cell>
                        <cell>43,137,997</cell>
                        <cell>132,020</cell>
                        <cell>543,679</cell>
                        <cell>30,127,878</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1865-70</cell>
                        <cell>31,645,505</cell>
                        <cell>141,628</cell>
                        <cell>859,251</cell>
                        <cell>49,885,971</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1870-75</cell>
                        <cell>34,220,037</cell>
                        <cell>171,166</cell>
                        <cell>747,505</cell>
                        <cell>55,116,815</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1875-80</cell>
                        <cell>23,003,683</cell>
                        <cell>158,887</cell>
                        <cell>545,247</cell>
                        <cell>62,539,166</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>3,673,949</cell>
                        <cell>55,002</cell>
                        <cell>203,567</cell>
                        <cell>13,324,935</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1881</cell>
                        <cell>2,904,580</cell>
                        <cell>54,119</cell>
                        <cell>131,836</cell>
                        <cell>11,727,397</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1882</cell>
                        <cell>3,377,119</cell>
                        <cell>44,277</cell>
                        <cell>294,207</cell>
                        <cell>11,174,573</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1883</cell>
                        <cell>3,178,593</cell>
                        <cell>62,064</cell>
                        <cell>292,433</cell>
                        <cell>10,523,920</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1884</cell>
                        <cell>4,522,702</cell>
                        <cell>67,239</cell>
                        <cell>323,947</cell>
                        <cell>10,984,073</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The sources whence the English imports of raw silk, the commercial names under
                    which they pass, and their relative importance and values, are exemplified in
                    the following table, extracted from the annual circulars issued by Messrs H. W.
                    Eaton &amp; Sons of London :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Description.</cell>
                        <cell>Imports, 1884.</cell>
                        <cell>Imports, 1885.</cell>
                        <cell>Extreme Prices during 1885.</cell>
                        <cell>Consumption, including Export,1885.</cell>
                        <cell>Prices 1st January 1886.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">China—</cell>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">s. d. s. d.</hi></cell>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">s. d. s. d.</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Tsatlee<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                                    figures relating to Tsatlee comprise Re-reel, Hangchow, and
                                    Yuun-fa.</p></note></cell>
                        <cell rows="2">2,803,572</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">1,001,436</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">9 0 to 14 6</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">1,225,938</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">9 6 to 14 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Haineen, &amp;c.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Taysaam<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                                    figures relating to Taysaam comprise Tussah.</p></note></cell>
                        <cell>416,466</cell>
                        <cell>271,116</cell>
                        <cell>7 6 ,, 15 0</cell>
                        <cell>293,964</cell>
                        <cell>8 0 ,, 14 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Canton</cell>
                        <cell>339,976</cell>
                        <cell>159,328</cell>
                        <cell>8 6 ,, 12 6</cell>
                        <cell>469,456</cell>
                        <cell>9 9 ,, 13 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Szechuen</cell>
                        <cell>23,154</cell>
                        <cell>6,936</cell>
                        <cell>7 0 ,, 11 3</cell>
                        <cell>17,544</cell>
                        <cell>7 0 ,, 11 3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Japan</cell>
                        <cell>388,304</cell>
                        <cell>70,560</cell>
                        <cell>10 6 ,, 15 6</cell>
                        <cell>372,176</cell>
                        <cell>12 0 ,, 15 6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Bengal</cell>
                        <cell>126,450</cell>
                        <cell>114,000</cell>
                        <cell>8 0 „ 14 6</cell>
                        <cell>154,800</cell>
                        <cell>9 6 ,, 15 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Patent Brutia</cell>
                        <cell>8,750</cell>
                        <cell>7,875</cell>
                        <cell>19 0 „ 23 0</cell>
                        <cell>7,700</cell>
                        <cell>19 0 ,, 21 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Persian</cell>
                        <cell>225</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Italian—</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Raw</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">205,610</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">211,700</cell>
                        <cell>17 0 to 21 0</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">208,220</cell>
                        <cell>17 0 to 21 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Novi</cell>
                        <cell>20 0 ,, 24 0</cell>
                        <cell>20 0 ,, 24 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Thrown</cell>
                        <cell>273,760</cell>
                        <cell>310,300</cell>
                        <cell>20 0 ,, 25 0</cell>
                        <cell>307,400</cell>
                        <cell>20 0 ,, 25 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">Total</cell>
                        <cell>4,586,267</cell>
                        <cell>2,153,251</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                        <cell>3,057,198</cell>
                        <cell>...</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In the manufacture of silken fabrics France occupies the most important position
                    among the nations. Not only is the whole of the raw silk produced in France
                    worked up within the country, but a very considerable proportion of that
                    imported from the Levant and from Asia passes into the hands of the French
                    manufacturers. In all, between 8,000,000 and 9,000,000 lb of raw silk are on an
                    average manufactured into various textures in France. Lyons is the headquarters
                    of the trade, and, if the surrounding regions be included, employment is given
                    to about 120,000 looms,—20,000 of which are driven by power,—principally in the
                    production of dress silks, plain and figured, and in other heavy silken fabrics,
                    and at St Etienne and St Chamond in the ribbon trade. There are also important
                    manufactures of silk at Calais, St Pierre les Calais (tulles and passementerie),
                    Paris, Nîmes, Tours, Avignon, and Roubaix. Next to France in the extent and
                    value of manufactures comes Germany, where the principal seat of the silk trade
                    is at Crefeld, nearly one half of the whole production of the empire being
                    manufactured there. The looms of Crefeld and the district it controls numbered
                    in 1881 about 33,000, and the trade was flourishing and expansive. The
                    manufacture of union velvets is the special feature of the industry, about one
                    half of the looms being devoted to that textile; but Crefeld controls also a
                    large trade in union satins, and pure silk broad goods and ribbons of all kinds.
                    The whole value of its trade amounted in 1881 to almost £4,000,000, one-fourth
                    of which found a market in England, and about a quarter of a million went to
                    France. The other principal centres of the silk trade, all in Rhenish Prussia,
                    are Viersen, Barmen, Elberfeld, and Mühlheim. Third on the list of Continental
                    producers is Switzerland, where Zurich takes the lead with broad goods (failles,
                    armures, satins, serges, &amp;c.), and Basel rivals St Étienne in the ribbon
                    trade. The number of looms throughout the country is estimated at 40,000, of
                    which 4000 are powerlooms. Italy—the early home of the silk trade, the land of
                    the gorgeous velvets of Genoa and the damasks and brocades of mediaeval Sicily,
                    Venice, and Florence—has fallen from its high estate, and now employs not more
                    than 30,000 looms, the centre of greatest activity being at Como; but Genoa
                    still makes velvets, and the brocades of Venice are not a thing of the past. In
                    Austria the silk trade has found its principal development in Vienna and its
                    immediate neighbourhood, the number of looms throughout the entire empire being
                    estimated at from 15,000 to 20,000, of which 2000 are power-looms. In Russia
                    there is, with a growing cultivation of raw silk, a considerable and increasing
                    manufacture, the special feature of which is the weaving at Moscow of gold and
                    silver tissues and brocades for sacerdotal use, and for traffic with Central
                    Asia.</p>
                <p>In the United Kingdom all the silk industries—these depending on spun silk alone
                    excepted—have been in a depressed and declining condition ever since 1860. The
                    principal silk manufacturing towns of England have been Coventry, Macclesfield,
                    Congleton, Leek, Derby, London (Spitalfields), Manchester, Middleton, and
                    Nottingham, and it is estimated that at the best period not fewer than 150,000
                    looms found employment in the trade. In 1872 that number was reduced to 65,000,
                    of which 12,500 were power-looms. Spitalfields in her best days (about 1825)
                    kept 24,000 hand-looms occupied; now there are not more than 1200. Manchester
                    once had about 20,000 looms weaving silk; now there are not 6000 so employed.
                    When the French treaty of 1860 came into operation Coventry had about 9000
                    looms, principally employed in ribbon weaving; now not more than one-fourth of
                    that number are in operation. The cause of several of these severe changes is to
                    be found in the introduction of the factory system of working and the extension
                    of power-loom weaving, which crushed out domestic weaving, the original form of
                    the silk industry; but undoubtedly also the English manufacturers were beaten in
                    the battle of free competition brought on by the French treaty. On the other
                    hand, the remarkable development of the <hi rend="italic">Silk and Silk Goods
                        exported from the United Kingdom during the years 1860 to 1884
                        inclusive.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rows="2">Year.</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">Raw Silk.</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">Knubs or Husks of Silk and Waste.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">Thrown Silk.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">Silk Manufactures.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>British.</cell>
                        <cell>Foreign and Colonial.</cell>
                        <cell>British.</cell>
                        <cell>Foreign and Colonial.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell>Cwts.</cell>
                        <cell>£</cell>
                        <cell>lb</cell>
                        <cell>£</cell>
                        <cell>£</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1860</cell>
                        <cell>3,153,993</cell>
                        <cell>1,506</cell>
                        <cell>826,107</cell>
                        <cell>426,866</cell>
                        <cell>1,587,303</cell>
                        <cell>224,366</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1865</cell>
                        <cell>3,137,292</cell>
                        <cell>1,212</cell>
                        <cell>767,058</cell>
                        <cell>306,701</cell>
                        <cell>1,404,381</cell>
                        <cell>166,936</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1870</cell>
                        <cell>2,644,402</cell>
                        <cell>4,167</cell>
                        <cell>1,154,364</cell>
                        <cell>39,771</cell>
                        <cell>1,450,397</cell>
                        <cell>166,297</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1875</cell>
                        <cell>2,551,417</cell>
                        <cell>1,779</cell>
                        <cell>880,923</cell>
                        <cell>87,924</cell>
                        <cell>1,734,519</cell>
                        <cell>328,426</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1876</cell>
                        <cell>3,064,725</cell>
                        <cell>4,210</cell>
                        <cell>1,080,678</cell>
                        <cell>50,202</cell>
                        <cell>1,794,565</cell>
                        <cell>303,054</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1877</cell>
                        <cell>1,652,935</cell>
                        <cell>7,450</cell>
                        <cell>570,999</cell>
                        <cell>17,910</cell>
                        <cell>1,705,153</cell>
                        <cell>229,130</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1878</cell>
                        <cell>1,841,505</cell>
                        <cell>8,012</cell>
                        <cell>565,266</cell>
                        <cell>40,470</cell>
                        <cell>1,922,953</cell>
                        <cell>222,133</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1879</cell>
                        <cell>1,375,608</cell>
                        <cell>5,029</cell>
                        <cell>694,735</cell>
                        <cell>24,461</cell>
                        <cell>1,697,209</cell>
                        <cell>248,495</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1880</cell>
                        <cell>947,165</cell>
                        <cell>9,241</cell>
                        <cell>683,591</cell>
                        <cell>7,553</cell>
                        <cell>2,030,659</cell>
                        <cell>259,023</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1881</cell>
                        <cell>903,997</cell>
                        <cell>4,528</cell>
                        <cell>1,008,272</cell>
                        <cell>5,561</cell>
                        <cell>2,564,730</cell>
                        <cell>263,826</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1882</cell>
                        <cell>915,773</cell>
                        <cell>6,941</cell>
                        <cell>825,572</cell>
                        <cell>6,281</cell>
                        <cell>2,692,275</cell>
                        <cell>341,107</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1883</cell>
                        <cell>524,182</cell>
                        <cell>5,216</cell>
                        <cell>705,825</cell>
                        <cell>5,596</cell>
                        <cell>2,426,299</cell>
                        <cell>340,805</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1884</cell>
                        <cell>377,349</cell>
                        <cell>6,538</cell>
                        <cell>612,951</cell>
                        <cell>50,559</cell>
                        <cell>2,175,410</cell>
                        <cell>644,722</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n81/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0081-0066"/>
                <p>comparatively new trade in spun silk goes far to compensate for the loss of the
                    older trade, and has enabled the exports of silk manufactures from the country
                    to be at least maintained and to show some signs of expansion. The spun-silk
                    industry has chiefly developed in the Yorkshire and Lancashire textile centres,—
                    Bradford, Halifax, Rochdale, &amp;c. But it is highly significant that, while
                    the exports of British silk manufactures have not decreased, the imports in the
                    meantime have shown a marked expansion; and unquestionably, although the use of
                    silken goods has increased very greatly within twenty-five years, the expansion
                    of native silk manufactures has not kept pace with that growth.</p>
                <p>Favoured by the operation of protective duties ranging from 50 to 60 per cent.
                        <hi rend="italic">ad valorem,</hi> the native manufacture of silk in the
                    United States has been nursed into considerable activity and expansion, till now
                    well-nigh one-half of the silken fabrics used in the country are of home
                    manufacture. In 1860 the proportion of native manufacture was 13 per cent., in
                    1880 it reached 38 per cent., and in 1882 it was 40 per cent. of the entire
                    consumption. Reeled silks are principally manufactured at Paterson and Hoboken,
                    N. J., and Brooklyn and New York City, N. Y., and the spun-silk industry
                    flourishes at South Manchester and Hartford, Conn.</p>
                <p>The following estimate of the relative importance of the silk manufacture of
                    various countries was made in 1883 by Mr Peixotto, the United States consul at
                    Lyons :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>France..............</cell>
                        <cell>$85,000,000</cell>
                        <cell>Russia</cell>
                        <cell>16,000,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Germany...........</cell>
                        <cell>45,000,000</cell>
                        <cell>Austria</cell>
                        <cell><p>12,000,000</p><p>12,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>United States.....</cell>
                        <cell>35,000,000</cell>
                        <cell>Italy</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Great Britain.....</cell>
                        <cell>25,000,000</cell>
                        <cell>Spain</cell>
                        <cell>5,000,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Switzerland.......</cell>
                        <cell>18,000,000</cell>
                        <cell>Other countries...</cell>
                        <cell>17,000,000</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>giving a total of $270,000,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
