<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0657-0632-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SULLA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 632</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w66">Cat</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xp3p">Cimbri</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="18" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n657/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SULLA</label> (138-78 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> The
                    life of Lucius Cornelius Sulla makes one of the most important chapters in Roman
                    history. Both as a general and as a politician he stands in the foremost rank of
                    the remarkable figures of all time. It was by his ability and his force of
                    character that Sulla, who had neither great wealth nor noble ancestry<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>He belonged to quite a minor
                    branch of the Cornelian gens.</p></note> to back him up, pushed himself to the
                    front in early manhood, distinguishing himself in the Jugurthine War in 107 and
                    106, and being able with a good show of reason to claim the credit of having
                    terminated that troublesome war by capturing Jugurtha himself. In these African
                    campaigns Sulla showed that he knew how to win the hearts and confidence of his
                    soldiers, and through his whole subsequent career the secret of his brilliant
                    successes seems to have been the enthusiastic devotion of his troops, whom he
                    continued to hold well in hand, while he let them indulge themselves in
                    plundering and in all manner of licence. “Rome’s soldiers from Sulla’s time,”
                    says Sallust <hi rend="italic">(Cat.,</hi> 11), “began to drink, to make love,
                    to have a taste for works of art, to rob temples, and to confound things sacred
                    and profane.” From the year 104 to 101 he served again under Marius in the war
                    with the Cimbri and Teutones and fought in the last great battle near Verona,
                    which annihilated the barbarian host. Marius, it is said, was jealous of him,
                    and any friendly feeling there may have hitherto been between the two now
                    finally ceased. Sulla on his return to Rome lived quietly for some years and
                    took no part in politics. What with his genuine love of letters and his love of
                    gay company he was never at a loss for amusement, and he must always have been a
                    particular favourite with fashionable society at Rome. In 93 he was elected
                    praetor after a lavish squandering of money, and he delighted the populace with
                    an exhibition of a hundred lions from Africa, from the realm of King Bocchus.
                    Next year (92) he went to the East with special authority from the senate to put
                    pressure on the famous Mithradates of Pontus, and make him give back Cappadocia
                    to its petty prince Ariobarzanes, one of Rome’s dependants in Asia, whom he had
                    driven out. Sulla with a small army soon won a victory over the general of
                    Mithradates, and Rome’s client-king was restored. An embassy from the Parthians
                    now came to solicit the honour of alliance with Rome, and Sulla was the first
                    Roman who held diplomatic intercourse with that remote people. In the year 91,
                    which brought with it the imminent prospect of revolution and of sweeping
                    political change, with the enfranchisement of the Italian peoples, Sulla
                    returned to Rome, and it was generally felt that he was the man to head the
                    conservative and aristocratic party. Who was to have the command in the
                    Mithradatic War and be entrusted with the settlement of the East was the
                    question of the day, and the choice lay plainly between Marius and Sulla. The
                    rivalry between the two men and their partisans was as bitter as it could
                    possibly be. Marius was old, but he had by no means lost his prestige with the
                    popular party.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile Mithradates and the East were forgotten in the crisis of the Social or
                    Italic War, which broke out in 91 and threatened Rome’s very existence. The
                    services of both Marius and Sulla were needed, and were given; but Sulla was the
                    more successful, or, at any rate, the more fortunate. Of the Italian peoples
                    Rome’s old foes the Samnites were the most formidable; these Sulla thoroughly
                    vanquished, and took their chief town, Bovianum. But his victories were, after
                    all, followed by the concession of the franchise to the Italian towns and
                    communities generally, though an arrangement which made them vote in separate
                    tribes greatly diminished their political power and became a further source of
                    irritation. It was clear that Rome was on the eve of yet further troubles and
                    revolutionary changes. Her armies, now recruited from the very scum of the
                    population, had not the loyal and honourable spirit of former days, and cared
                    only for licence and plunder. On every side it seemed that public life was
                    demoralized and politics degraded. In 88 Sulla was consul; the revolt of Italy
                    was at an end; and again the question came to the front—who was to go to the
                    East and encounter the warlike king of Pontus, against whom war had been
                    declared. The tribune Publius Sulpicius Rufus moved that Marius should have the
                    command; there was fearful rioting and bloodshed at Rome at the prompting of the
                    popular leaders, Sulla narrowly escaping to his legions in Campania, whence he
                    marched on Rome, being the first Roman who entered the city at the head of a
                    Roman army. Marius now had to fly; and he and his party were crushed for the
                    time.</p>
                <p>Sulla, leaving things quiet at Rome, quitted Italy in 87 for the East, taking
                    Greece on his way, and for the next four years he was winning victory after
                    victory against the armies of Mithradates and accumulating boundless plunder.
                    Athens, the headquarters of the Mithradatic cause, was taken and sacked in 86,
                    and Sulla possessed himself of a library which contained Aristotle’s works. In
                    the same year at Chaeroneia, the scene of Philip of Macedon’s memorable victory
                    more than two and a half centuries before, and in the year following, at the
                    neighbouring Orchomenus, he scattered like chaff, with hardly any loss to
                    himself, immense hosts of the enemy. Crossing the Hellespont in 84 into Asia, he
                    was joined by the troops of Fimbria, who soon deserted their general, a man sent
                    out by the Marian party, now again in the ascendant at Rome. The same year peace
                    was concluded with Mithradates on condition that he should resign all his recent
                    conquests, give up all claim to meddle with Rome’s Asiatic dependencies, and pay
                    a considerable indemnity. In fact the king was to be put back to the position he
                    held before the war; but, as he raised cavils and Sulla’s soldiers wanted better
                    terms and more spoil, he had in the end to content himself with being on the
                    same footing as the other princes of Asia,—simply a vassal of Rome.</p>
                <p>Sulla returned to Italy in 83, landing at Brundusium,<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n658/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0658-0633"/> having previously informed the senate in an
                    official despatch of the result of his campaigns in Greece and Asia, and
                    announced his presence on Italian ground. He complained, too, of the
                    ill-treatment to which his friends and partisans had been subjected during his
                    absence. The revolutionary party, specially represented by Cinna, Carbo, and the
                    younger Marius, had massacred them wholesale, confiscated his property, and
                    declared him a public enemy. They felt they must resist him to the death, and
                    with numerous bodies of troops scattered throughout Italy, and the support of
                    the newly enfranchised Italians, to whom it was understood that Sulla was
                    bitterly hostile, they counted confidently on success, but on Sulla’s advance at
                    the head of his 40,000 veterans many of them lost heart and deserted their
                    leaders, while for the most part the Italians themselves, whom he confirmed in
                    the possession of their new privileges, were won over to his side. Only the
                    Samnites, who were as yet without the Roman franchise, remained his enemies, and
                    it seemed as if the old war between Rome and Samnium had to be fought once
                    again. Several Roman nobles, among them Cneius Pompeius (Pompey the Great),
                    Metellus Pius, Marcus Crassus, Marcus Lucullus, joined Sulla, and in the
                    following year (82) he won a decisive victory over the younger Marius near
                    Praeneste (Palestrina), and then marched straight upon Rome, where again, just
                    before his defeat of Marius, there had been a great massacre of his adherents,
                    in which the famous and learned jurist Mucius Scaevola perished. Rome was at the
                    same time in extreme peril from the advance of a Samnite army, and was barely
                    saved by Sulla, who, after a bloody and very hard-fought battle, routed the
                    enemy before the walls of Rome. With the death of the younger Marius, who killed
                    himself after the surrender of Praeneste to one of Sulla’s officers, the civil
                    war was at an end and Sulla was master of Rome and of the Roman world. Then
                    came, with the object of breaking the neck of the Marian or popular party, the
                    memorable “proscription,” when for the first time in Roman history a list of men
                    declared to be outlaws and public enemies was exhibited in the forum, and a
                    reign of terror— a succession of wholesale murders and confiscations throughout
                    Rome and Italy—made the name of Sulla for ever infamous. The title of “dictator”
                    was revived after a long period and conferred upon him; Sulla was in fact
                    emperor of Rome, with absolute power over the life and fortunes of every Roman
                    citizen. There were of course among them some really honest well-meaning men who
                    looked up to him as the “saviour of society.” After celebrating a splendid
                    triumph for the Mithradatic War, and assuming the surname of “Felix”
                    (“Epaphroditus,” “Venus’s favourite,” he styled himself in addressing Greeks),
                    he carried in 80 and 79 his great political reforms (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Rome,</hi> vol. XX. pp. 761-762). Of these the main object was to invest the
                    senate, the thinned ranks of which he had recruited with a number of his own
                    creatures, with full control over the state, over every magistrate and every
                    province, and the mainstay of his political system was to be the military
                    colonies which he had established with grants of land throughout every part of
                    Italy, to the injury and ruin of the old Italian freeholders and farmers, who
                    from this time dwindled away, leaving whole districts waste and desolate.
                    Sulla’s work had none of the elements of permanence; it was a mere stop-gap
                    purchased at the cost of infinite misery and demoralization.</p>
                <p>In 79 Sulla resigned his dictatorship and retired to Puteoli, where he died in
                    the following year, probably from the bursting of a blood-vessel, though there
                    is a story that he fell a victim to a particularly loathsome disease similar to
                    that which cut off one of the Herods (Acts xii. 23). The half lion, half fox, as
                    his enemies called him, the “Don Juan of politics,” to quote Mommsen’s happy
                    phrase, the man who carried out a policy of “blood and iron” with a grim humour,
                    amused himself in his last days with actors and actresses, with dabbling in
                    poetry, and completing the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> of his strange and
                    eventful life.</p>
                <p>For Sulla and his times, there is his <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by Plutarch,
                    who had his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> for one of his authorities, and there
                    are very numerous references to him in Cicero’s writings. The best and fullest
                    modern account of him is that of Mommsen (vol. iii,, bk. iv. ch. 8, 9,)∙ (W. J.
                    B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
