<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0135-0120-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SKIN DISEASES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 120</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b32s">Scrofula</term>
                    <term n="43" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term n="43" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tq07">Hair</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109411">Scrofula</term>
                    <term n="43" ref="fasttopic:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:952743">Health</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:950358">Hair</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n135/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SKIN DISEASES</label>. These form a large and important
                    class. In number they are very extensive, owing to the varied forms of morbid
                    change which the skin texture may undergo, no less than to the different
                    portions of the structure and its appendages which may be specially affected.
                    Further, the modifications of the typical forms of these diseases which are to
                    be observed have led to arrangements and classifications of very complex
                    character and multiplied greatly their nomenclature. Skin diseases are regarded
                    by the physician as of great importance, not only from the fact that morbid
                    action in this texture must have a powerful influence on the general health and
                    may bring in its train other maladies, but also because they are not
                    unfrequently themselves the expression of constitutional conditions, inherited
                    or acquired, the recognition of which is essential to their effectual treatment.
                    In order to clearness of description it is necessary to make use of some method
                    of classification. Various arrangements have been adopted by writers on the
                    subject, but the following appears sufficient for the present purpose:<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For the structure of the skin
                    see <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> vol. i. p. 897.</p></note> —</p>
                <p>I. Disorders of the secreting apparatus (of the sebaceous and sweat glands);</p>
                <p>II. Disorders specially relating to nutrition (hypertrophies; atrophies; new
                    formations; pigmentary changes);</p>
                <p>III. Inflammatory affections (erythematous; papular; vesicular; pustular;
                    squamous or scaly);</p>
                <p>IV. Neuroses (nervous disorders);</p>
                <p>V. Parasitic affections (animal; vegetable).</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Disorders of the Secreting Apparatus.·</hi> —(1) <hi
                    rend="italic">Of the Sweat Glands.—</hi> The chief morbid conditions are
                    excessive sweating <hi rend="italic">(hyperidrosis)</hi> and foetid sweating <hi
                    rend="italic">(bromidrosis).</hi> Excessive sweating is a symptom observed in
                    various diseases, such as phthisis and rheumatic fever, but it may exist apart
                    from such conditions, and either be general, affecting the whole body, or
                    confined to a part, such as the axillae, head, hands, feet, or, as in some rare
                    instances; the one half of the body. Some persons habitually perspire, often to
                    a great extent, on making any effort, yet never appear to suffer in health,
                    although the discomfort is considerable. Excessive perspiration may often be
                    prevented by the habitual use of the cold bath, and by tonics, such as iron,
                    quinine, strychnia, &amp;c. Locally, the use of astringent lotions of vinegar or
                    a weak solution of lead will also be of service. Bromidrosis or foetid sweating
                    is often associated with the former condition, and it too may be general or
                    local. It most frequently affects the feet, especially in those who have much
                    fatigue, and is a source of much personal discomfort as well as of annoyance to
                    others. It is apparently due to rapid decomposition in the perspiration which
                    has saturated the stockings, and for its treatment it is essential that these
                    should be frequently changed and the feet washed several times a day, dried
                    carefully, and dusted with some antiseptic powder, such as boracic or salicylic
                    acid mixed with starch or French chalk. Hebra recommends the application to the
                    feet of a composition of equal parts of olive oil and litharge plaster spread
                    upon linen and used twice a day.</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Of the Sebaceous Glands.—Seborrhoea</hi> is a term<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n136/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0136-0121"/> applied to describe an accumulation on the skin
                    of the normal sebaceous secretion mixed up with dirt and forming scales or a
                    distinct incrustation. On the head, where it is commonly seen, it may interfere
                    with the nutrition of the hair and cause partial baldness. A form of this
                    disease occurs in young infants. The main treatment is local, consisting in
                    thorough cleansing of the parts. The crusts may be softened with oil and the
                    affected skin regularly washed with soft soap and rectified spirit. The sebum
                    frequently accumulates in the sebaceous ducts, giving rise to the minute black
                    points so often noticed on the face, back, and chest in young adults, to which
                    the term <hi rend="italic">comedones</hi> is applied. A form of this disorder,
                    but of larger size and white appearance, is termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >milium.</hi> These affections may to a large extent be prevented by strict
                    attention to ablution and brisk friction of the skin, which will also often
                    remove them when they begin to appear. The retained secretion may be squeezed
                    out or evacuated by incision and the skin treated with some simple sulphur
                    application.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Acne</hi> is an eruption produced by inflammation of the
                    sebaceous glands and hair follicles. It may occur in connexion with the
                    preceding or independently, and shows itself in the form of red pimples or
                    papules which may become pustular and be attended with considerable surrounding
                    irritation of the skin. This affection is likewise most common in early adult
                    life, and occurs on the chest and back as well as on the face, where it may,
                    when of much extent, produce considerable disfigurement. It is apt to persist
                    for months or even years, but usually in time disappears entirely, although
                    slight traces may remain in the form of scars or stains upon the skin. Eruptions
                    of this kind are sometimes produced by the continued internal use of certain
                    drugs, such as the iodide or bromide of potassium. The treatment is similar to
                    that for the previous affection, viz., brisk friction of the skin, short of
                    producing irritation, and the application of a sulphur lotion or ointment.
                    Attention to the general health by suitable diet, tonics, exercise, &amp;c., is
                    a necessary adjuvant. A variety of this malady, to which the name <hi
                    rend="italic">acne rosacea</hi> is given, is a more severe and troublesome
                    disorder than that already mentioned. It is characterized by great redness of
                    the nose and cheeks, accompanied with nodular enlargements on the surface of the
                    skin, which produce marked disfigurement. Although often seen in persons who
                    live too freely, it is by no means confined to such, but may arise in connexion
                    with disturbances of the general health, especially of the function of
                    digestion, and in females with menstrual disorders. It is apt to be exceedingly
                    intractable to treatment, which is here too, as in the preceding form, partly
                    local and partly constitutional. Of internal remedies preparations of iodine and
                    of arsenic are sometimes found of service.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Molluscum contagiosum</hi> belongs to this class of skin
                    diseases. It consists of an enlargement of the sebaceous glands and occlusion of
                    the ducts, and is seen most commonly on the face, body, or hands in children, or
                    on the breasts in women. It is said to be contagious, but it is a rare form of
                    skin disease.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Disorders affecting Nutrition.</hi> —(1) <hi
                    rend="italic">Hypertrophies.—</hi> A <hi rend="italic">corn (clavus)</hi> is a
                    local thickening of the skin, generally occurring on the toes. There is
                    hypertrophy of the epidermis, and in the centre of the corn there is usually a
                    still denser mass, which, pressing down upon the subjacent sensitive true skin,
                    causes pain and may give rise to inflammation and suppuration in the part. When
                    situated between the toes the corn is softer than when on the free surface of
                    the foot. The treatment consists in maceration of the hardened skin and the use
                    of the knife or strong caustics. Salicylic acid combined with ether and
                    collodion, painted over the part, is said to be useful in the case of soft
                    corns.</p>
                <p>A <hi rend="italic">wart (verruca)</hi> is an excrescence from the surface of the
                    skin due to hypertrophy of the papillary layer of the cutis and of the
                    epidermis. This form of growth may also occur on mucous membranes. Warts
                    occasionally disappear spontaneously, or they may be excised, or carefully
                    touched with some strong caustic acid or alkali.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ichthyosis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">xeroderma</hi> consists of
                    a general thickening of the whole skin and marked accumulation of the epidermic
                    elements, with atrophy of the sebaceous glands, giving rise to a hard, dry,
                    scaly condition. It generally first appears in infancy, and is probably
                    congenital. It differs in intensity and in distribution in different cases, and
                    is generally little amenable to any but palliative remedies, such as the regular
                    application of oily substances, although it is not a fatal malady.</p>
                <p>For <hi rend="italic">elephantiasis Arabum,</hi> see vol. viii. p. 126.</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Atrophies.—</hi> The chief of these relate to the hair. <hi
                    rend="italic">Canities</hi> or whitening of the hair consists in the
                    nonformation of the pigmentary matter which is normally present in the substance
                    of the hair, and occurs generally as a slow senile change. It may, however, take
                    place prematurely, in which case it is often hereditary; or it may be associated
                    with degenerative changes taking place in the system. It is occasionally seen to
                    occur temporarily in very young persons in connexion with some defective
                    condition of the general health. Its development suddenly has not unfrequently
                    been observed as the result of some strong mental emotion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Alopecia,</hi> or baldness, is the loss of hair, which is most
                    commonly a senile change and irremediable, or on the other hand may be
                    premature, occurring either hereditarily or in connexion with some previous
                    constitutional morbid state <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> after fevers or other
                    blood poisons), in which latter case it may be only, although not always,
                    temporary. It appears to depend upon atrophic changes affecting the hair
                    follicle, including obliteration of the capillary vessels,—the result of which
                    is that strong hairs cease to be produced, and only feeble, short, and thin hair
                    <hi rend="italic">(lanugo)</hi> is formed, which soon falls off and is not
                    reproduced. Usually the whole skin of the hairy scalp undergoes thinning and
                    other atrophic changes as well as the hair follicle. Sometimes the loss of hair
                    occurs in distinct circular patches <hi rend="italic">(alopecia areata),</hi>
                    which tend to spread until the whole scalp is denuded. The treatment of
                    temporary or premature baldness bears reference especially to any known
                    conditions affecting the general health; and tonics, baths, and other means to
                    promote a vigorous skin function are useful. Stimulating liniments containing
                    spirits and cantharides, the regular cleansing and moderate brushing of the
                    parts, the application to the scalp of the constant current of electricity, and
                    various other remedies appear to be of service in promoting the growth of
                    hair.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">New Formations.—(a) Lupus</hi> is a disease characterized
                    by the formation in the skin of tubercles or nodules consisting of new cell
                    growth which has no tendency to further development, but to retrograde change,
                    leading to ulceration and destruction of the skin and other tissues in which it
                    exists, and the subsequent formation of permanent white scars. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lupus vulgaris</hi> is most commonly seen in early life, and occurs chiefly on
                    the face, about the nose, cheeks, ears, &amp;c., but it may also affect the skin
                    of the body or limbs. It first shows itself in the form of small, slightly
                    prominent nodules covered with thin crusts or scabs. These may be absorbed and
                    removed at one point, but they tend to spread at another. Their disappearance is
                    followed by a white permanent cicatrix. The disease may be superficial in which
                    case both the<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n137/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0137-0122"/> ulceration and resulting scar are slight (<hi
                    rend="italic">lupus non-exedens)</hi>; or, on the other hand, the ulcerative
                    process may be deep and extensive, destroying a large portion of the tissues of
                    the nose or cheeks, and leaving deep marks with much disfigurement (<hi
                    rend="italic">lupus exedens).</hi> Another form of this disease, termed <hi
                    rend="italic">lupus erythematosus,</hi> is of comparatively mild character, and
                    occurs on the nose and adjacent portions of the cheeks in the form of red
                    patches covered with thin scales, underneath which are seen the widened openings
                    of the sebaceous ducts,—this variety of the disease affecting specially that
                    portion of the skin texture. It is very slow in disappearing, but does not leave
                    any marked scar. Lupus is generally more frequently seen in women than in men,
                    and it is held to be connected with a scrofulous constitution. Its treatment
                    bears reference especially to this condition (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Scrofula).</hi> In the superficial variety the application of soothing
                    ointments when there is much redness, and Squire’s method of slight linear
                    incisions to destroy the increased blood supply, are often serviceable. In the
                    ordinary form the great principle of local treatment is to remove the new tissue
                    growth. This is most readily done either by solid points of caustic, of which
                    the nitrate of silver is perhaps the best, thrust into the tubercles to break
                    them up, or by means of a scoop (Volkmann’s spoon) to scrape away the diseased
                    masses. Only by such means can the ulceration be arrested and healing brought
                    about.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Leprosy (elephantiasis
                    Graecorum)</hi> may be regarded as belonging to this class of skin diseases,
                    inasmuch as it consists in a new growth of cell material, like lupus, but with
                    less tendency to disintegration and with a wider distribution affecting the
                    skin, mucous membranes, nerves, &amp;c., all over the body. For its history and
                    pathology see vol. xiv. p. 468 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> Leprosy is not
                    amenable to treatment, beyond attempts at palliation of the symptoms and by
                    general hygiene.</p>
                <p>(4) <hi rend="italic">Pigmentary Changes.—Chloasma</hi> is an abnormal
                    pigmentation, in the form of brown patches, either generally diffused or
                    confined to one part, such as the forehead and face, and occasionally seen in
                    women suffering from uterine ailments. <hi rend="italic">Addison's disease</hi>
                    is connected with a morbid condition of the suprarenal capsules (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Pathology),</hi> and is accompanied with general bronzing of
                    the skin, together with anaemia and great and increasing prostration. <hi
                    rend="italic">Leucoderma</hi> is a change in the pigmentation of the skin,
                    whereby it becomes white in patches, with a tendency to spread and affect almost
                    the whole surface, until a few dark areas alone remain to represent the original
                    appearance of the skin. It is sometimes called white leprosy, but has no
                    relation to that disease, nor is it of any special significance as regards the
                    health. <hi rend="italic">Albinism</hi> is an entire absence of pigment from the
                    hair, skin, eyes, &amp;c. The hair is usually white, and the skin exceedingly
                    pale; and the eye has a pinkish appearance. This condition is congenital. It
                    occasionally exists to a partial extent in any of the textures named.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Inflammatory Skin Affections.</hi> —These embrace the
                    following chief varieties:—(1) diffuse (erythema); (2) papular (lichen); (3)
                    catarrhal (eczema); (4) vesicular (herpes, pemphigus); (5) pustular (impetigo);
                    and (6) scaly (psoriasis, pityriasis).</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Diffuse.—</hi> This variety includes <hi rend="italic"
                    >erythema</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Erysipelas)</hi> and its forms,
                    particularly <hi rend="italic">erythema nodosum,</hi> which consists of spots
                    and patches of dark red colour and slightly elevated, appearing on the front of
                    the legs and back of the arms in young persons, mostly females. The patches
                    continue for a number of days and then become fainter. It is supposed to be
                    connected with rheumatism, joint pains not unfrequently accompanying it. <hi
                    rend="italic">Urticaria</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nettle-rash</hi> is a diffuse
                    redness of the skin, accompanied with wheals of raised and paler appearance, not
                    unlike the effect produced by the sting of nettles or of insects, and attended
                    with great irritation and itching. Certain kinds of food, such as fruit and
                    fish, produce this eruption in some persons, as also some drugs, such as opium.
                    It is best treated by some soothing application, such as a solution of sal
                    volatile, to which a little chloral has been added, and by attention to the
                    state of the alimentary canal. <hi rend="italic">Roseola,</hi> which consists in
                    the appearance of rose-coloured spots upon the body, is frequently seen in
                    children, and is apt to be mistaken for measles, but has none of the
                    accompanying febrile or catarrhal symptoms of that disorder, and is of brief
                    duration.</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Papular.—Lichen,</hi> an eruption consisting of small,
                    thickly-set, and slightly-elevated red points, more or less widely distributed
                    over the body, and in the young somewhat resembling scarlet fever, but with only
                    slight febrile symptoms and no sore throat, usually results from digestive
                    derangements, but apparently may also arise from exposure to the sun, and it
                    lasts but a short time. Some forms, however <hi rend="italic">{e.g., lichen
                    ruber),</hi> are of chronic character and difficult of treatment. The ordinary
                    form requires little beyond attention to the digestive organs and the
                    application of a soothing lotion or powder. The chronic forms are best treated
                    by the administration of arsenic. <hi rend="italic">Strophulus,</hi> or
                    tooth-rash, or, as it is popularly termed, “red gum,” an affection very common
                    in young infants, belongs to this class of skin disorders.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Catarrhal.—Eczema,</hi> one of the most common and
                    important of all skin diseases, consists of an inflammation of the true skin, of
                    catarrhal character, together with the formation of papules, vesicles, or
                    pustules, attended with more or less discharge, and with itching and other
                    symptoms of irritation. It may be either acute or chronic, and presents itself
                    in a variety of forms. As regards causation, it appears impossible to assign any
                    one condition as giving rise to this disease. It occurs frequently in persons to
                    all appearance in perfect health, and it may in such cases be a permanent or
                    recurring affection during a whole lifetime. Again it is undoubtedly found in
                    persons who possess a morbid constitution, such as the gouty or scrofulous; but
                    apart from any such evident associations it seems in some instances itself
                    distinctly hereditary. Sometimes it is set up as the result of local or general
                    irritation of the skin in certain occupations, and it may exist in connexion
                    with the presence of some other skin disease. It is much more common in men than
                    in women. Numerous varieties of eczema are described, according to its site and
                    duration; only the more important of these can be alluded to. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Acute eczema</hi> shows itself by redness and swelling of the skin, with the
                    formation of minute vesicles, and attended with severe heat and irritation.
                    Should the vesicles rupture, a raw moist surface is formed, from which a
                    colourless discharge oozes, which when it accumulates forms thin crusts. The
                    attack may be general over the greater portion of the body, or it may be
                    entirely localized to a limb or other part. It usually lasts for a few weeks and
                    then passes off, leaving, however, a liability to recurrence. Such attacks may
                    occur as a result of digestive derangements, or in persons of rheumatic or gouty
                    habit, and they tend to appear at certain seasons, such as springtime. They are
                    usually best treated by attention to the general health, and by a simple and
                    carefully-regulated diet, while locally some soothing application, such as a
                    weak lead lotion or a dusting powder of zinc, starch, or boracic acid, will be
                    found of benefit. <hi rend="italic">Chronic eczema</hi> shows itself in various
                    forms, of which we note the most common. In <hi rend="italic">eczema rubrum</hi>
                    the disease affects a part, very often a limb, as a severe form of inflammation,
                    with great redness, and weeping or oozing<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n138/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0138-0123"/> of serous matter from the raw surface. It gives
                    rise to great irritation and. pain, and may cause considerable disturbance of
                    the general health. It may last for years, with intervals of partial recovery,
                    but easily recurring. The skin of the limb becomes in time thickened and the
                    limb itself much swollen. In <hi rend="italic">dry eczema</hi> the skin, though
                    irritable, remains dry and scaly. In <hi rend="italic">pustular eczema,</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">eczema impetiginodes,</hi> in addition to the cutaneous
                    inflammation there occur pustules which break and the purulent matter forms
                    yellow crusts upon the skin. This form is very common on the heads of young
                    children during the period of dentition. The treatment of chronic eczema depends
                    in great measure upon the form it assumes. Where there exists much irritation,
                    soothing lotions or applications similar to those required for acute eczema are
                    necessary; but where irritation has subsided, stimulating ointments, such as
                    those of zinc or white precipitate, are often of service. Constitutional
                    remedies, such as iron, arsenic, &amp;c., are an important and often essential
                    part of successful treatment.</p>
                <p>(4) <hi rend="italic">Vesicular.—Herpes</hi> is an inflammation of the true skin,
                    attended with the formation of isolated or grouped vesicles of various sizes
                    upon a reddened base. They contain a clear fluid, and either rupture or dry up.
                    Two well-marked varieties of herpes are frequently met with. <hi rend="italic"
                    >{a)</hi> In <hi rend="italic">herpes labialis et nasalis</hi> the eruption
                    occurs about the lips and nose. It is seen in cases of certain acute febrile
                    ailments, such as fevers, inflammation of the lungs, or even in a severe cold.
                    It soon passes off. (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) In <hi rend="italic">herpes
                    zoster,</hi> zona, or shingles, the eruption occurs in the course of one or more
                    cutaneous nerves, often on one side of the trunk, but it may be on the face,
                    limbs, or other parts. It may occur at any age, but is probably more frequently
                    met with in elderly people. The appearance of the eruption is usually preceded
                    by severe stinging neuralgic pains for several days, and, not only during the
                    continuance of the herpetic spots, but long after they have dried up and
                    disappeared, these pains sometimes continue and give rise to great suffering.
                    The disease seldom recurs. The most that can be done for its relief is to
                    protect the parts with cotton wool or some dusting powder, while the pain may be
                    allayed by opiates or bromide of potassium. Quinine internally is often of
                    service.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pemphigus</hi> consists in large blebs upon a red base. They
                    contain clear or yellowish fluid. This disease appears to show itself most
                    frequently on the bodies and limbs of unhealthy or neglected children. The blebs
                    give rise to much irritation, and when they burst leave raw ulcerated surfaces
                    which are slow of healing. One variety of this malady (<hi rend="italic"
                    >pemphigus foliaceus)</hi> affects the entire skin of the body, from which there
                    exudes a constant discharge. This form is apt sooner or later to prove fatal
                    from its exhausting effects. The treatment is mainly constitutional,—by good
                    nourishment, iron, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>(5) <hi rend="italic">Pustular.—Impetigo,</hi> consisting of small pustules
                    situated upon a reddened base, mostly occurs in children. There appears to be a
                    contagious form of this malady. <hi rend="italic">Ecthyma</hi> consists of large
                    pustules of similar character on the body and limbs. The treatment of these
                    ailments requires special attention to nutrition, since they usually occur in
                    low states of health.</p>
                <p>(6) <hi rend="italic">Squamous or Scaly.—Psoriasis,</hi> an inflammatory
                    affection of the true skin, attended with the formation of red spots or patches,
                    which are covered with white silvery scales, may affect any portion of the
                    surface of the body, but is most common about the elbows and knees, and on the
                    head. There is as a rule comparatively little irritation except at the outset,
                    but there is an extensive shedding of the scales from the affected spots.
                    Varieties of this disease are described in relation to the size and distribution
                    of the patches. The causes of psoriasis have given rise to much discussion, and,
                    while some authorities regard its appearance as in many instances connected with
                    some constitutional morbid state, such as gout, rheumatism, &amp;c., the
                    majority deny any such relationship, and mention hereditary influence as the
                    only recognizable cause, although it must be admitted that even this evidence is
                    wanting in a large number of cases. The disease appears to be consistent with
                    continued good health. It is usually obstinate to treat, and may, with intervals
                    of comparative immunity, last a lifetime. The remedies most serviceable are
                    arsenic internally and the application externally of preparations of tar.
                    Recently the employment of chrysophanic acid as an ointment or in solution has
                    been resorted to with considerable success.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pityriasis,</hi> a superficial inflammation of the skin, with
                    the formation of minute branny scales, occurs most commonly on the head, and is
                    of chronic duration. The remedies most useful are alkaline lotions and tar
                    preparations. A variety of this disease (<hi rend="italic">pityriasis
                    rubra)</hi> affects the whole body, and is most intractable to treatment.</p>
                <p>IV. <hi rend="smallcaps">Neuroses (</hi><hi rend="italic">Nervous
                    Affections).—</hi> Various disorders of nutrition of the skin occur in persons
                    suffering from organic nervous diseases, such as bedsores, atrophic changes,
                    eruptions, &amp;c., but these belong to the symptoms of the several diseases
                    with which they are associated. The most common of the neuroses of the skin is
                    probably <hi rend="italic">pruritus,</hi> which is an ailment characterized by
                    intense itching of the surface of the body. It may occur in connexion with other
                    morbid conditions, such as jaundice, diabetes, digestive disorders, &amp;c., or
                    as the result of the irritation produced by lice or other skin parasites. The
                    most serious form is <hi rend="italic">pruritus senilis,</hi> which affects old
                    persons, and is often a cause of great suffering, depriving the patient of sleep
                    (the malady being specially troublesome during the night). In such cases it is
                    probably due to atrophic changes in the skin. No eruption is visible, except
                    such marks as are produced by scratching. The treatment consists in the removal
                    of any apparent cause, and measures to strengthen the system, such as the use of
                    quinine, iron, &amp;c. Soothing lotions composed of solutions of alkalis
                    conjoined with chloral, opium, hydrocyanic acid, &amp;c., may be applied to the
                    affected skin at bedtime.</p>
                <p>V. <hi rend="smallcaps">Parasitic Diseases.</hi> —(1) <hi rend="italic">A nimal.
                    —</hi> The following are the chief animal parasitic diseases. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phthiriasis</hi> is produced by the presence of lice <hi rend="italic"
                    >{pediculi),</hi> of which there are three varieties, infesting respectively the
                    head, body, and pubis. The cause is in most instances uncleanliness, but
                    occasionally in the aged, and in persons suffering from chronic diseases, there
                    appears to be a liability to the development of pediculi, notwithstanding every
                    care to prevent it. The irritation produced by the parasite and the scratching
                    thus occasioned may give rise to abrasions of the skin and eczematous
                    conditions. The treatment consists in thorough cleansing of the parts and the
                    use of parasiticides, such as red or white precipitate, carbolic lotions (one in
                    twenty), or a decoction or ointment of stavesacre. Where clothing is infested it
                    should be destroyed or subjected to a strong heat to get rid both of the
                    parasites and their ova. <hi rend="italic">Scabies</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >itch</hi> is a skin affection due to the <hi rend="italic">Acarus scabiei</hi>
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mite).</hi> The female insects burrow into the upper
                    layers of the skin and deposit their eggs in the tract thus made. Great
                    irritation of the skin is set up, and scratching produces eruptions which
                    aggravate the condition, especially at night. The most frequent sites are the
                    parts between the fingers, or the wrists, but by scratching the disease may be
                    conveyed to any part of the body, and in extreme cases the greater portion of
                    the surface of the trunk and limbs may be involved. In infants the feet and
                    buttocks<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n139/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0139-0124"/> are the parts which suffer. The eruption in mild
                    cases has at first the appearance of small raised vesicles with clear fluid, but
                    it may become pustular or eczematous, and extensive excoriations may result. The
                    treatment consists in thorough cleansing of the skin and the inunction of some
                    form of parasiticide,—sulphur ointment being on the whole the best. The
                    application should be discontinued after a few days, otherwise irritation may be
                    produced by its use.</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Vegetable parasites</hi> consist of fungous growths in the
                    texture of the skin and hair, which are characterized microscopically by minute
                    round bodies or spores often coalesced into clusters or bead-like arrangements,
                    and jointed filaments or <hi rend="italic">mycelium</hi> of elongate and
                    branching form. They are readily detected by removing a hair, or scraping a
                    portion of the affected skin, treating it with a strong alkaline solution, and
                    submitting it to microscopic examination, by which the slight differences in
                    form and arrangement of the varieties of the parasite can be easily made out.
                    The common name “tinea” is applied to these parasitic affections. <hi
                    rend="italic">Tinea tonsurans,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ringworm</hi> (parasite
                    <hi rend="italic">Tricophyton tonsurans),</hi> is a very common form of
                    parasitic disease. It occurs as a result of contagion in the heads of children,
                    and begins as circular patches with a scaly appearance and red border, which
                    tend to spread. The hair at the part becomes thin and brittle and is easily
                    removed. It is often extremely obstinate to treatment, and numerous agents have
                    been proposed as specifics, not one of which, however, appears to possess
                    infallible virtues. Among the best are oleate of mercury (5 to 10 per cent.) and
                    other mercurial preparations, all which, however, must be used with care, and
                    carbolic or sulphurous acid with glycerin, iodine, cantharides, &amp;c.; but
                    isolation of the patient as far as possible, together with strict medical
                    supervision, are essential for the effectual treatment of this disorder. <hi
                    rend="italic">Tinea sycosis,</hi> or ringworm affecting the beard, and <hi
                    rend="italic">tinea circinata,</hi> or ringworm affecting the body, require to
                    be dealt with in a similar manner. <hi rend="italic">Tinea favosa,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">favus</hi> (parasite <hi rend="italic">Achorion Schönleinii),</hi>
                    is less frequently seen than the preceding. It occurs mostly on the scalp in
                    unhealthy and neglected children, but it may affect the skin in any part of the
                    body. It is characterized by round, yellow, sulphur-coloured, cup-shaped spots
                    or crusts, which, when occurring extensively upon the scalp, have a peculiar
                    mousy odour. It is very destructive of hair growth, and is most difficult to
                    cure. The best treatment is removal of the hairs by epilation, and the
                    employment of some of the parasiticides already mentioned, together with
                    attention to the healthy nutrition of the patient. <hi rend="italic">Tinea
                    versicolor,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pityriasis versicolor</hi> (parasite <hi
                    rend="italic">Microsporon furfur),</hi> is a brown-coloured rash of scaly
                    character occurring mostly in the form of spots or patches on the skin of the
                    trunk, particularly on the front of the chest or between the shoulders, but
                    sometimes also upon the arms and legs. It affects adults in whom the
                    skin-function is not sufficiently attended to, or those who are in ill-health.
                    The parasite affects the epidermic cells, and is readily made out by the
                    microscope, thus enabling the disease to be distinguished from other skin
                    disorders to which it often bears resemblance. It is best treated by the regular
                    washing and brisk friction of the parts, and by the use of some of the
                    applications above referred to. (<hi rend="smallcaps">j. o. a.</hi>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
