<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0064-0049-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SIGNALS, Naval</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 49</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p30">Flags</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:926942">Flags</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n64/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SIGNALS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Naval</hi></label>. A system of
                    naval signals comprises different methods of conveying orders or information to
                    or from a ship in sight and within hearing, but at a distance too great to
                    permit of hailing,—in other words, beyond the reach of the voice, even when
                    aided by the speaking-trumpet. Signals are divided into classes according to the
                    instruments with which and the circumstances under which they are made. There
                    are sight and sound signals; flag, semaphore, fixed lantern, flashing, firework,
                    horn or steam-whistle, and gun signals; day, night, fog, and distant signals.
                    Besides these, there are other divisions, such as general, vocabulary,
                    evolutionary, &amp;c., which depend upon technical considerations and are
                    matters of arrangement.</p>
                <p>The necessity of some plan of rapidly conveying orders or intelligence to a
                    distance was early recognized. Polybius describes two methods, one proposed by
                    Aeneas Tacitus more than three centuries before Christ, and one perfected by
                    himself, which, as any word could be spelled by it, anticipated the underlying
                    principle of recent systems. The signal codes of the ancients are believed to
                    have been elaborate. Generally some kind of flag was used. Shields were also
                    displayed in a preconcerted manner, and some have imagined that the reflected
                    rays of the sun were flashed from them as with the modern heliograph (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Heliography).</hi> In the Middle Ages flags, banners, and
                    lanterns were used to distinguish particular squadrons, and as marks of rank, as
                    they are at present, also to call officers to the admiral, and to report
                    sighting the enemy and getting into danger. The invention of cannon made an
                    important addition to the means of signalling. In the instructions issued by Don
                    Martin de Padilla in 1597 the use of guns, lights, and fires is mentioned. The
                    introduction of the square rig permitted a further addition, that of letting
                    fall a sail a certain number of times. Before the middle of the 17th century
                    only a few stated orders and reports could be made known by signalling. Flags
                    were used by day, and lights, occasionally with guns, at night. The
                    signification then, and for a long time after, depended upon the position in
                    which the light or flag was displayed. Orders, indeed, were as often as possible
                    communicated by hailing or even by means of boats. As the size of ships
                    increased the inconvenience of both plans became intolerable. Some attribute the
                    first attempt at a regular code to Admiral Penn, but the credit of it is usually
                    given to James II. when duke of York. Notwithstanding the attention paid to the
                    subject by Paul Hoste and others, signals continued strangely imperfect till
                    late in the 18th century. Towards 1780 Admiral Kempenfelt devised a plan of
                    flag-signalling which was the parent of that now in use. Instead of indicating
                    differences of meaning by varying the position of a solitary flag, he combined
                    distinct flags in pairs. About the beginning of the 19th century Sir Home Popham
                    improved a method of conveying messages by flags proposed by Mr Hall Gower, and
                    greatly increased a ship’s power of communicating with others. The number of
                    night and fog signals that could be shown was still very restricted. In 1867 an
                    innovation of prodigious importance was made by the adoption in the British navy
                    of Captain Philip Colomb’s flashing system, on which he had been at work since
                    1858. This is in general use in all fleets, though, oddly enough, on its first
                    trial at sea it was condemned. It is not too much to say that the Colomb system
                    has made it possible to handle, with confidence and safety, in darkness and fog,
                    squadrons composed of the gigantic armour-clads of the day. Its adoption has not
                    only contributed very materially to the increased efficiency of the British
                    fleets but also immensely reduced the risk of accidents; and the saving to the
                    tax-payer since its introduction may probably be estimated in hundreds of
                    thousands of pounds.</p>
                <p>In the British navy, which is copied by most others, sight-signals are made with
                    flags, the semaphore, “flashes,” fixed lanterns, and occasionally with
                    fireworks, and for “distant” signals with flags, balls, and pendants displayed
                    on account of shape but not of colour. Sound-signals are made with horns,
                    steam-whistles, and guns. There are two sets of flags,—one of ten numbered from
                    1 to 10, and another of twenty-one called after letters of the alphabet. There
                    are also pendants and a few special flags. The numbered flags are used with the
                    general signal book, a kind of dictionary in which figures stand opposite
                    sentences conveying orders or announcements. Opposite 123 might stand “hoist in
                    all boats,” which would mean that, when the flag called 1 was hoisted with 2
                    beneath it and 3 beneath 2, the ship or ships addressed—indicated by a special
                    flag or by pendants—were ordered to hoist all boats in. The lettered flags are
                    used with the vocabulary signal book, in which opposite collections of letters
                    are put single words or small groups of words. Thus, if ABC were opposite the
                    word “admiral” and STO opposite “will sail at noon,” when the first three flags
                    were hoisted the signalman on board each ship addressed would note them down
                    with their signification. When all addressed had acknowledged the first “hoist”
                    the flags would be hauled down and STO would be hoisted, to be acknowledged and
                    noted in like manner. The admiral would thus have made known his intention of
                    sailing at a given hour. From this it will appear that the general code is used
                    for words of command and the vocabulary for long communications. The night
                    signal book contains a limited number of definite orders and announcements made
                    known by exhibiting lanterns, never more than four, arranged vertically,
                    horizontally, or in a square. For a few signals some kind of firework is
                    displayed. Fogsignals are made by firing different numbers of guns at fixed
                    intervals. Owing to the slowness of flag-signalling, it is now, especially for
                    the vocabulary and at moderate distances, largely superseded by the semaphore,
                    an upright post with two arms moving in a vertical plane. The changed positions
                    of the arms indicate letters and each word is spelled. Before the adoption of
                    Captain Colomb’s system, at night and in fogs only a few announcements could be
                    made by signal, and sending messages was unknown. By a series of symbols formed
                    of dots and short lines, like those of the Morse alphabet, he represents
                    figures, letters, and special words. Thus ... means 3, and .___ 7. The system
                    can be employed in daylight, at night, and in fogs. In daylight long and short
                    waves of a flag on a staff reproduce the flashes; in fogs long and short blasts
                    on a fog-horn or steam-whistle; and at night the alternate exposure and
                    concealment of the light of a lamp. Every order in the general signal book and
                    every word in the vocabulary—by spelling, indeed, every word in the language—may
                    be communicated by this system. Distant signals, now rarely used, are made by
                    hoisting flags of different shapes at distances at which colours become
                    invisible. The <hi rend="italic">Army and Navy Signal Book</hi> contains the<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n65/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0065-0050"/> code for communications between a ship and its
                    boats or military stations on shore; the <hi rend="italic">International,</hi>
                    with special flags, is for communicating with merchant vessels. In the British
                    navy there is a corps of signalmen rising in grade from boys to chief petty
                    officers. They are selected from the most intelligent and best educated boys in
                    the training-ships, and go through a course of special instruction in their
                    duties. (c. <hi rend="smallcaps">a. g. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
