<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0114-0099-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SISMONDI, Jean Charles Leonard de (9th edition, volume
                    22, page 99)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881352">Countesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n114/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SISMONDI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Charles Leonard
                        de</hi></label> (1773- 1842), whose real name was <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Simonde,</hi> was born at Geneva on May 9, 1773. His father and all his
                    ancestors seem to have borne the name Simonde, at least from the time when they
                    migrated from Dauphiné to Switzerland at the revocation of the edict of Nantes.
                    It was not till after Sismondi had become an author that, observing the identity
                    of his family arms with those of the once flourishing Italian house of the
                    Sismondi, and finding that some members of that house had migrated to France, he
                    assumed the connexion without further proof and called himself De Sismondi. The
                    Simondes, however, were themselves citizens of Geneva of the upper class, and
                    possessed both rank and property, though the father was also a village pastor.
                    The future historian was well educated, but his family wished him to devote
                    himself to commerce rather than literature, and he became a banker’s clerk at
                    Lyons. Then the Revolution broke out, and as it affected Geneva the Simonde
                    family took refuge in England, where they stayed for eighteen months. Disliking,
                    it is said, the climate, they returned to Geneva, but found the state of affairs
                    still unfavourable; there is even a legend that the head of the family was
                    reduced to sell milk himself in the town. The greater part of the family
                    property was sold, and with the proceeds they emigrated to Italy, bought a small
                    farm at Pescia near Lucca, and set to work to cultivate it themselves. Sismondi
                    worked hard here, both with his hands and his mind, and his experiences gave him
                    the material of his first book, <hi rend="italic">Tableau de l'Agriculture
                        Toscane,</hi> which, after returning to Geneva, he published there in 1801.
                    Two years later he published his <hi rend="italic">Traité de la Richesse
                        Commerciale,</hi> his first work on the subject of political economy, which,
                    with some differences of view, continued to interest him to the end of his life
                    (for his position and work in this respect the reader is referred to the article
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Political Economy,</hi> vol. xix. p. 383). Meanwhile he
                    began his great <hi rend="italic">History of the Italian Republics,</hi> and was
                    introduced to Madame de Stael. With her he became very intimate, and after being
                    regularly enrolled in the society of Coppet he was invited or commanded (for
                    Madame de Stael's invitations had something of command) to form one of the suite
                    with which the future Corinne made the journey into Italy, resulting in <hi
                        rend="italic">Corinne</hi> itself during the years 1804-5. Sismondi was not
                    altogether at his ease here, and he particularly disliked Schlegel, who was also
                    of the company. But during this journey he made the acquaintance of the countess
                    of Albany, Louisa of Stolberg, widow of Charles Edward, and all her life long
                    gifted with a singular faculty of attracting the affection (Platonic and other)
                    of men of letters. She was now an old woman, and Sismondi’s relations with her
                    were of the strictly friendly character, but they were close and lasted long,
                    and they produced much valuable and interesting correspondence. In 1807 appeared
                    the first volumes of the above mentioned book on the Italian republics, which
                    (though his essay in political economy had brought him some reputation and the
                    offer of a Russian professorship) first made Sismondi prominent among European
                    men of letters. The completion of this book, which extended to sixteen volumes,
                    occupied him, though by no means entirely, for the next eleven years. He lived
                    at first at Geneva, and delivered there some interesting lectures on the
                    literature of the south of Europe, which were continued from time to time and
                    finally published; and he held an official post,—that of secretary of the
                    chamber of commerce for the then<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n115/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0115-0100"/> department of the Leman. In 1813 he visited
                    Paris for the first time and abode there for some years, mixing much in literary
                    society. Although a Liberal and in his earlier days almost an Anglomaniac, he
                    did not welcome the fall of the empire. During the Hundred Days he defended
                    Napoleon’s constitutional schemes or promises, and had an interview with the
                    emperor himself which is one of the chief events of a not very eventful life.
                    After the Restoration he left Paris. On completing his great book on the Italian
                    republics he undertook a still greater, the <hi rend="italic">Histoire des
                        Français,</hi> which he planned on a vast scale, and of which during the
                    remaining twenty-three years of his life he published twenty-nine volumes. His
                    untiring industry enabled him to compile many other books, but it is on these
                    two that his fame chiefly rests. The earlier displays his qualities in the most
                    favourable light, and has been least injuriously affected by subsequent writings
                    and investigations. The <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Français,</hi> as a
                    careful and accurate sketch on the great scale, has been entirely superseded by
                    that of M. Henri Martin, while it is not to be mentioned, as a work of
                    historical or literary genius, in the same category with that of Michelet.
                    Sainte-Beuve has with benevolent sarcasm surnamed the author “the Rollin of
                    French History,” and the praise and the blame implied in the comparison are both
                    perfectly well deserved. In April 1819 Sismondi married an English lady, Miss
                    Allen, whose sister was the wife of Sir James Mackintosh, and the marriage
                    appears to have been a very happy one. His later years were chiefly spent at
                    Geneva, in the politics of which city he took a great, though as time and
                    changes went on a more and more chagrined, interest. Indeed, in his later days
                    he became a kind of reactionary. He died at Geneva on June 25, 1842. Besides the
                    works above mentioned he had executed many others, his custom for a long period
                    of years being never to work less than eight hours a day. The chief of these are
                        <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux Principes d'Économie Politique</hi> (1819), an
                    historical novel entitled J <hi rend="italic">ulia Severa ou l'An 492</hi>
                    (1822), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Renaissance de la Liberté en
                        Italie</hi> (1832), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Chute de l'Empire
                        Romain</hi> (1835), <hi rend="italic">Précis de l'Histoire des
                        Français,</hi> an abridgment of his own book (1839), with several others,
                    chiefly political pamphlets.</p>
                <p>Sismondi’s literary character has been hinted at in the above remarks on his
                    French history. He was exceedingly laborious, for the most part (though not
                    entirely) free from prejudice, and never violent even when he was prejudiced. He
                    had (with much “sensibility ”) plenty of common sense, though not perhaps any
                    extraordinary amount of acuteness in estimating things uncommon, and he was a
                    little deficient in historical grasp and in the power of taking large views of
                    complicated series of events. His style corresponded to his thought, and
                    (putting aside certain solecisms which French critics usually affect to discover
                    in Swiss writers) lacks point, picturesqueness, and vigour. Of his moral
                    character no one has ever spoken except in terms of praise, and it appears
                    (which is not invariably the case) to have been as attractive as it was
                    estimable. His chief weakness seems to have been a tendency, frequently
                    observable in writers of very great industry, to rank his own productions
                    somewhat too much on a level with those of writers who, if less industrious,
                    were infinitely more gifted. Thus he has somewhere naively observed that “he
                    should not object to signing” a certain proportion of a certain book of
                    Chateaubriand’s. But this overvaluation of self appears to have been merely <hi
                        rend="italic">naïf,</hi> and not in the least arrogant.</p>
                <p>Sismondi’s journals and his correspondence with Channing, with the countess of
                    Albany, and others have been published chiefly by Mlle. Mongolfier (Paris, 1863)
                    and M. de Saint-René Taillandier. The latter work serves as the chief text of
                    two admirable <hi rend="italic">Lundis</hi> of Sainte-Beuve (September 1863),
                    republished in the <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux Lundis,</hi> vol. vi.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
