<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0198-0183-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMOLENSK (9th edition, volume 22, page 183)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068347">Poles</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n198/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMOLENSK</label>, a government of middle Russia, belonging
                    partly to Great Russia and partly to White Russia, is bounded by Moscow and
                    Kaluga on the E., Orel and Tchernigoff on the S., Moghileff and Vitebsk on the
                    W., and Pskoff and Tver on the N. It covers an area of 21,638 square miles in
                    the west of the great central plateau, its northern districts extending towards
                    the hilly region of the Valdais, where the flat-topped gentle declivities reach
                    about 1000 feet above the sea. The rivers being deeply cut in the plateau, the
                    surface is also hilly in the western districts (Smolensk, Dorogobuzh), whence it
                    slopes away gently towards immense plains on the east and south. Carboniferous
                    limestones, containing a few layers of coal (in Yuchnoff) and quarried for
                    building purposes, occupy the east of Smolensk; white Chalk appears in the
                    southern extremity; while Tertiary sands, marls, and ferruginous clays cover all
                    the west. The whole is overlain with a thick sheet of boulder clay, with
                    irregular extensions to the north; Post-Tertiary sands are spread over wide
                    surfaces; and peat-bog fills the marshy depressions. The soil, mostly clay, is
                    generally unfertile, and stony and sandy in several districts. Many large rivers
                    belonging to the basins of the Volga, the Oka, the Dnieper, and the Dwina have
                    their origin in Smolensk. The Vazuza and the Gzhat, both flowing into the Volga,
                    and the Moskva and the Ugra, tributaries of the Oka, are channels for floating
                    timber. The two tributaries of the Dwina—the Kasplya and the Mezha—are of much
                    more importance, as they and their affluents carry considerable numbers of boats
                    to Riga. The Dnieper takes its origin in Smolensk and waters it for more than
                    300 miles; but neither this river nor its tributaries (Vop, Vyazma, Sozh, and
                    Desna), whose upper courses belong to Smolensk, are navigable; timber only is
                    floated down some of them. Many small lakes and extensive marshes occur in the
                    northwest. One-third of the area is under forests. The population of Smolensk
                    reached 1,191,172 in 1882, of whom only 106,133 lived in towns, and consists of
                    White Russians in the west (46∙7 per cent.), Great Russians in the east (42∙6),
                    and of a mixed population of both (10∙4). Nearly 1000 Jews and 1000 Poles are
                    scattered through the towns.</p>
                <p>The climate is like that of middle Russia generally, although the moderating
                    influence of the wet climate of western Europe is felt to some extent. The
                    average yearly temperature at Smolensk is 45°∙5 Fahr. (January, 13°∙5; July,
                    67°∙2). Notwithstanding the unproductive soil and the frequent failures of crops
                    (especially in the north-west), the chief occupation is agriculture. In 1884
                    3,040,000 acres were under crops, and 2,379,600 quarters of grain of various
                    kinds were raised (2,930,400 in 1883),—the potato crop yielding 5,498,400
                    bushels. Nearly all the land is cultivated by the peasant communes,—only 766,500
                    acres (out of 6,868,900) in the hands of single individuals being under
                    cultivation. Oats are an important crop. Hemp and flax are largely raised and
                    exported. Cattle-breeding stands at a low level; the cattle of the peasantry
                    suffer from a want of meadow and pasture land, which is mostly in private
                    ownership. In 1882 there were 329,850 horses, 349,000 horned cattle, 401,000
                    sheep, and 162,000 pigs. The peasantry are mostly very poor, in consequence not
                    only of the desolation inflicted on Smolensk in 1812, the effects of which are
                    still felt, but also of insufficient allotments and want of meadows. Gardening
                    and bee - keeping, which formerly flourished, have almost disappeared. The
                    timber trade and boat-building are important sources of income, but do not
                    furnish employment for all who are in need of it; more than one-half of the male
                    population of west Smolensk leave their homes every year in search of work,
                    principally as navvies throughout Russia. The manufactures are developing but
                    slowly, and in 1882 employed only about 5100 workmen,—their annual production
                    being valued at £328,800; of this amount the distilleries yielded nearly
                    one-third. A few cotton-mills in the east have a production valued at £62,160
                    per annum. A lively traffic is carried on on the rivers, principally the
                    Kasplya, the Obzha, and the Ugra, where corn, hemp, hempseed, linseed; and
                    especially timber are shipped to the amount of nearly £400,000 annually. A
                    considerable quantity of corn is imported into the western districts. Smolensk
                    is crossed by two important railways, from Moscow to Warsaw and from Riga to
                    Saratoff; a branch-line connects Vyazma with Kaluga. The educational
                    institutions embrace eleven gymnasia and progymnasia (830 boys and 1402 girls),
                    and 394 primary schools (15,031 boys and 2142 girls). Smolensk is divided into
                    twelve districts, the chief towns of which, with their populations in 1882,
                    are—Smolensk (see below), Byełyi (7150), Dorogobuzh (8400), Duhovshina (3660),
                    Elnya (4850), Gzhatsk (7050), Krasnyi (3550), Poryetchie (4650), Rosłavl (9050),
                    Sytchevka (5720), Vyazma (13,000), and Yuchnoff (3230).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
