<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0839-0804-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SWORD-FISH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 804</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4g737392">Sword</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j97x">Fins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1140675">Swords</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:925154">Fins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1120047">Skin</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n839/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SWORD-FISH</label>. Sword-fishes are a small family of
                    spiny-rayed fishes <hi rend="italic">(Xiphiidx),</hi> the principal
                    characteristic of which consists in the prolongation of the upper jaw into a
                    long pointed sword-like weapon. The “sword” is formed by the coalescence of the
                    intermaxillary and maxillary bones, which possess an extremely hard texture; it
                    has the shape of a much elongate cone, more or less flattened throughout its
                    whole length; the end is sharply pointed. It is smooth above and on the upper
                    part of the sides, and rough below owing to the presence of innumerable
                    rudimentary teeth, which have no function.</p>
                <p>The general form of the body is well proportioned, somewhat elongate, and such as
                    is always found in fishes with great power of swimming, as, for in stance, in
                    the mackerel and tunny, and the tail terminates in a powerful bi-</p>
                <p>lobed caudal fin. A long fiu occupies nearly the whole length of the back, whilst
                    the anal fin is generally interrupted in the middle, and consequently appears to
                    be double. The skin is very firm, partly naked, partly with small lanceolate
                    scales deeply imbedded in the skin. The teeth of the lower jaw are, like those
                    of the upper, merely rudimentary structures, which render the surface of the
                    bone rough without possessing any special function.</p>
                <p>Sword-fishes have been divided into three generic groups :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">a. Histiophorus,</hi> with a high dorsal fin which can be
                    spread out like a sail, and with ventral fins which are reduced to a pair of
                    long styliform appendages.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">b. Tetrapturus,</hi> with a dorsal fin of which the anterior
                    rays only are elongate, the remainder of the fin being low or partly obsolete,
                    and with styliform ventral fins as in the preceding genus.</p>
                <p>c. <hi rend="italic">Xiphias,</hi> with the dorsal fin shaped as in <hi
                    rend="italic">Tetrapturus,</hi> but without ventral fins.</p>
                <p>Sword-fishes are truly pelagic fishes, which either singly or in pairs or in
                    smaller or larger companies roam over the oceans of the tropical and subtropical
                    zones of both hemispheres. Some species wander regularly or stray far into the
                    temperate seas. Some of the tropical forms are the largest of Acanthopterygian
                    fishes, and not exceeded in size by any other Teleostean; such species attain to
                    a length of from 12 to 15 feet, and swords have been preserved more than 3 feet
                    long and with a diameter of at least 3 inches at the base. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histiophori,</hi> which inhabit chiefly the Indo-Pacific Ocean, but occur also
                    in the Atlantic, seem to possess in their high dorsal fin an additional aid for
                    locomotion. During the rapid movements of the fish this fin is folded downwards
                    on the back, as it would impede the velocity of progress by the resistance it
                    offers to the water; but, when the fish is swimming in a leisurely way, it is
                    frequently seen with the fin erected and projecting out of the water, and when
                    quietly floating on the surface it can sail by the aid of the fin before the
                    wind, like a boat.</p>
                <p>The food of the sword-fishes is the same as that of tunnies, and consists of
                    smaller fish, and probably also in great measure of pelagic cuttle-fishes. It
                    has been ascertained by actual observation that sword-fishes procure their food
                    by dashing into a school of fishes, piercing and killing a number of them with
                    their swords; and this kind of weapon would seem to be also particularly
                    serviceable in killing large cuttle-fish, like the saw of saw-fishes, which is
                    used for the same purpose. But the swords of the large species of <hi
                    rend="italic">Histiophorus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tetrapturus</hi> are,
                    besides, most formidable weapons of aggression. These fishes never hesi tate to
                    attack whales and other large cetaceans, and, by repeatedly stabbing them,
                    generally retire from the combat victorious. That they combine in these attacks
                    with the thresher-shark is an often-repeated story which has its foundation in
                    the imagination of the observer, and which is fully disproved by the fact that
                    the dentition of the thresher-shark is much too weak to make an impression on
                    the skin of any cetacean. The cause which excites swordfishes to such attacks is
                    unknown; but they follow the instinct so blindly that they not rarely assail
                    boats and ships in a similar manner, evidently mistaking them for cetaceans.
                    They easily pierce the light canoes of the natives of the Pacific islands and
                    the heavier boats of the professional sword-fish fishermen, often dangerously
                    wounding the persons sitting in them. Attacks by sword-fishes on ocean-going
                    ships are so common as to be included among sea-risks: they are known to have
                    driven their weapon through copper-sheathing, oak-plank, and timber to a depth
                    of nearly 10 inches, part of the sword projecting into the inside of the ship;
                    and the force required to produce such an effect has been described by Prof.
                    Owen in a court of law as equal to “the accumulated force of fifteen
                    double-handed hammers,” and the velocity as “equal to that of a swivel-shot,”
                    and “as dangerous in its effects as a heavy artillery projectile.” Among the
                    specimens of planking pierced by sword-fishes which are preserved in the British
                    Museum there is one less than a foot square which encloses the broken ends of
                    three swords, as if the fishes had had the object of concentrating their attack
                    on the same vulnerable point of their supposed enemy. The part of the sword
                    which penetrates a ship’s side is almost always broken off and remains in the
                    wood, as the fish is unable to execute sufficiently powerful backward movements
                    to free itself by extracting the sword.</p>
                <p>In the Mediterranean and on the Atlantic coasts of the United States the capture
                    of sword-fishes forms a regular branch of the fishing-industry. The object of
                    the fishery in the Mediterranean is the common European sword-fish <hi
                    rend="italic">(Xiphias gladius),</hi> the average weight of which is about one
                    cwt., and which is abundant off the Sicilian coasts and on the opposite coast of
                    Calabria. Two methods are employed,—that by harpoons, chiefly used for larger
                    fish, and that by peculiarly constructed nets called <hi rend="italic"
                    >palamitare.</hi> This fishery is very productive: a company of fishermen
                    frequently capture from twenty to fifty fish in a single day, and the average
                    annual catch in Sicily and Calabria is reported to be 140,000 kilogrammes (138
                    tons). The products of the fishery are consumed principally in a fresh state,
                    but a portion is preserved in salt or oil. The flesh of the sword-fish is much
                    preferred to that of the tunny, and always commands a high price. This species
                    is occasionally captured on the British coast.</p>
                <p>On the coast of the United States a different species, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histiophorus gladius,</hi> occurs; it is a larger fish than the Mediterranean
                    sword-fish, attaining to a length of from 7 to 12 feet, and an average weight of
                    300 or 400 lb. It is captured only by the use of the harpoon. From forty to
                    fifty vessels, schooners of some 50 tons, are annually engaged in this fishery,
                    with an aggregate catch amounting annually to about 3400 sword-fishes, of a
                    value of $45,000. The flesh of this species is inferior in flavour to that of
                    the Mediterranean species, and is principally consumed after having been
                    preserved in salt or brine.</p>
                <p>Useful and detailed information on the sword-fish fishery can be obtained from A.
                    T. Tozzetti, “La Pesca nei Mari d’Italia e la Pesca all’ Estero esercitata da
                    Italiani,” in <hi rend="italic">Catalogo Esposizione Internazionale di Pesca in
                    Berlino,</hi> 1880; also from <hi rend="italic">La Pesca del Pesce-Spada nello
                    Stretto di Messina</hi> (Messina, 1880), and from G. Brown Goode, “Materials for
                    a History of the Sword-fish,” in <hi rend="italic">Report of the Commissioner of
                    Fish and Fisheries,</hi> part viii., Washington, 1883. (A. C. G.)<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n840/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0840-0805"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
