<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0119-0104-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SIXTUS V</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 104</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:806713">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:887231">Dalmatians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br3k">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z60c31q">Robbers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SIXTUS V</label>. (Felice Peretti), pope from 1585 to 1590,
                    was born 13th December 1521 at Grottamarina, in the district of Fermo, of a
                    family said to be of Dalmatian extraction. His parents were undoubtedly in
                    humble circumstances, but the story of his having been a swineherd in his youth
                    seems to be a mere legend. He entered the Franciscan order at an early age, and
                    obtained great celebrity as a preacher. After having been successively professor
                    at Rimini and at Siena, he became inquisitor-general in Venice (where his
                    firmness in controversy with the Venetian Government exposed him to personal
                    danger), theologian at the council of Trent, and ultimately vicargeneral of his
                    order. In 1565 he accompanied the papal legate to Spain, and in 1570 was created
                    cardinal by Pius V., and entrusted with the publication of a correct edition of
                    the works of St Ambrose, which appeared in 1579-1585. Finding himself out of
                    favour with Pius’s successor, Gregory XIII., he withdrew to a villa which he had
                    purchased, and lived in strict retirement, affecting, it is said, to be in a
                    precarious state of health. According to the usual story, which is probably at
                    least exaggerated, this dissimulation greatly contributed to his unexpected
                    elevation to the papacy on the next vacancy, 24th April 1585. If the electors
                    had indeed anticipated a weak or ephemeral pontificate, they were grievously
                    disappointed. Sixtus speedily proved himself one of the most vigorous popes,
                    both in body and mind, that had ever occupied the chair of St Peter. Within two
                    years he issued seventy-two bulls for the reform of religious orders alone.
                    Ardent, despotic, indefatigable, he did everything by himself, rarely invited
                    advice and still more rarely followed it, and manifested in all his actions a
                    capacious and highly original genius, in most respects eminently practical, but
                    swayed in some things towards the visionary and fantastic by the inevitable
                    effects of a monastic training. His first great aim was to purge the papal
                    dominions of the robbers who had overrun them under the weak administration of
                    his predecessor. This salutary undertaking was effectually accomplished, not
                    without many instances of tyranny and cruelty which have left a stain upon his
                    name; but security of life and property returned. Sixtus’s financial management
                    seemed on a superficial view equally brilliant; he had found the exchequer
                    empty, and speedily accumulated an immense treasure. But this end was obtained
                    partly by excessive taxation, partly by the sale of offices which had never
                    before been venal; and the withdrawal of such an amount of specie from
                    circulation impoverished the community. His intention was to amass a fund for
                    use in special emergencies, such as a crusade or a hostile invasion, which never
                    arose. Much, nevertheless, was expended by Sixtus in the encouragement of
                    agriculture and commerce, and in public works, either of signal utility, like
                    his supply of Rome with water, or such at least as impressed the popular
                    imagination with his munificence, as the completion of the cupola of St Peter’s,
                    the construction of six new streets, and the elevation of four Egyptian obelisks
                    in various parts of Rome. Though a scholar, Sixtus was no humanist, and did much
                    mischief to the monuments of antiquity, ruthlessly destroying some, and
                    disfiguring those which he repaired by the addition of Christian attributes. In
                    his ecclesiastical and foreign policy good sense contended with eccentricity but
                    usually obtained the upper hand. He thought of attacking Turkey with the
                    alliance of Poland and Russia, of subjugating Egypt by his own forces, of making
                    a descent into Syria and carrying off the Holy Sepulchre. But he never attempted
                    to realize these projects, and his conduct of the affairs which imperatively
                    required his attention evinced more moderation than could have been expected.
                    After having strongly sided with Spain and the League, he allowed himself to be
                    convinced by the Venetian ambassador of the evil consequences of Spanish
                    preponderance in Italy, and showed a manifest disposition to acknowledge Henry
                    IV. as king of France, on condition of his abjuration. This led to violent
                    altercations with the Spanish ambassador, and the death of the pope on 27th
                    August 1590 was attributed by many to poison, though without sufficient ground.
                    He was succeeded by Urban VII. Sixtus V. left the reputation of a zealous and
                    austere pope,—with the pernicious qualities inseparable from such a character in
                    his age,—of a stern and terrible but just and magnanimous temporal magistrate,
                    of a great sovereign in an age of great sovereigns, of a man always aiming at
                    the highest things and whose great faults were but the exaggeration of great
                    virtues.</p>
                <p>The best view of his character and government is that given by Ranke. Leti’s
                    well-known biography is full of fables; Tempesti is too panegyrical; and Lorentz
                    is little more than a compiler from the two. The most valuable part of Baron von
                    Huebner’s <hi rend="italic">Sixte Quint</hi> (Paris, 1870) is the rich appendix
                    of documents. Sixtus’s note-books and drafts of letters in the Chigian library,
                    frequently referred to by Tempesti and Ranke, were published by Cugnoni in 1882.
                    (R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
