<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0060-0045-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SIEYÈS, Emmanuel Joseph (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    45)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hw9j">Girondists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f1p">Jacobins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tb0xx74">Riots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942930">Girondists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:981035">Jacobins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098069">Riots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n60/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SIEYÈS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Emmanuel Joseph</hi></label>
                    (1748-1836), one of the chief political thinkers and writers of the period of
                    the French Revolution and the first empire, was born at Fréjus (Var) on 3d May
                    1748. He was destined for the church, was educated by the Jesuits, became a
                    licentiate of the canon law, and, having early distinguished himself by the
                    astuteness and originality of his ideas, was appointed vicar-general by the
                    bishop of Chartres. He shared the political fervour of the party of advance, and
                    was fearlessly logical in working out the new and as yet indistinct princi-<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n61/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0061-0046"/> ples of reform. An excellent opportunity was
                    provided for the inculcation of his views by the invitation which Necker
                    addressed to all French writers to publish their opinions upon the mode of
                    convening the states-general. Sieyès startled his countrymen by the issue of
                    various pamphlets upon the political situation, and particularly by his daring
                    and original treatise upon the Third Estate, with its three famous divisions in
                    question and answer:—“1st, What is the Third Estate?—Everything. What has it
                    hitherto been in the political order?—Nothing. What does it demand?—To become
                    something.” He attacked unsparingly the privileged classes, and indeed in this
                    his most famous work he constructed, single-handed and at once, a programme for
                    the Revolution. The influence of the book and of its author soon became
                    enormous, and in 1789 the Abbé Sieyès was elected by the city of Paris as a
                    representative to the states-general, where he was the first to propose that the
                    three estates should meet together in one assembly. On the rejection of his
                    motion he boldly suggested the formation of an “assembly of representatives of
                    France already verified.” He was not, however, successful as a speaker, his
                    style being obscure and his matter too compressed for oral expression,—faults
                    which disappeared when he committed his thoughts to writing. Yet he was one of
                    the leaders of the assembly, and was appointed a member of the committee on the
                    constitution. His published speech in opposition to the power of absolute veto
                    by the king brought him still further into notice. But he recognized his
                    inaptitude for public speaking, and, although even Mirabeau declared that the
                    silence of Sieyès was a public calamity, he stood aside while his own ideas were
                    being developed amidst violence and riot both within and without the constituent
                    and afterwards the legislative assembly. As excess followed upon excess in the
                    wild course of the Revolution Sieyès had neither the courage nor the power to
                    quell the riot. In danger of becoming a suspect, and fearful of his life, he
                    emerged from obscurity in November 1793, on the occasion of the installation of
                    Reason in Notre Dame. Before the national convention he denied his faith,
                    abjuring the title of priest, professing that his only worship was that of
                    liberty and equality and his only religion the love of humanity and country, and
                    concluding by formally renouncing to the state the commuted pension which he
                    enjoyed in lieu of his former benefice. The overthrow of the Jacobins at last
                    overcame his fears and in March 1795 he is found publicly lauding the memory of
                    those guillotined Girondists in whose defence he, two years before, had never
                    once lifted his voice.</p>
                <p>In the same year (1795) the ex-abbé was commissioned by the Convention to The
                    Hague, where he successfully concluded an offensive and defensive alliance
                    between the United Provinces and France. Without Sieyès no framing of a
                    constitution could be attempted, and he was accordingly appointed member of a
                    commission to draw up organic laws, the constitution of 1793 having been found
                    unworkable. When the commission brought forward its report Sieyès did not
                    dissent; but he proposed to the Convention a separate scheme of his own, the
                    specialty of which was the provision for the appointment of a constitutional
                    jury which should be charged with the duty of revising all legislative decrees
                    against which the challenge was brought that they were themselves at variance
                    with the constitution. His scheme was, however, rejected in favour of the new
                    constitution, and from that moment he became its secret enemy. He was elected
                    one of the first directory of five, but he declined the honour. In 1798 he was
                    appointed the plenipotentiary of France to Prussia, where he was received with
                    great honour and where he speedily began to plot against the Government he
                    represented.</p>
                <p>He communicated his views to Napoleon, then in Egypt. Meanwhile (1799) he was
                    again elected to the directory, and, his plans being ripe, he accepted office.
                    Then came the <hi rend="italic">coup d'état</hi> of 18th Brumaire (9th November
                    1799), in which Sieyès took so important a part, but in which he was
                    unquestionably overborne by the genius and audacity of Bonaparte. The
                    provisional consulate composed of Napoleon, Sieyès, and Ducos lasted but a few
                    weeks. After a little Sieyès is a count of the empire and the proprietor of
                    Crosne (Seine-et-Oise), while Napoleon is able to boast of how he has bribed the
                    ex-abbé out of his constitutional views. Amid the political changes of France,
                    Sieyès on the second return of the Bourbons fled to Brussels; but after the
                    revolution of 1830 he felt it safe to return to Paris, where he died on 20th
                    June 1836.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
