<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0806-0775-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SWITHUN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 775</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1006241">Majorities</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:995592">Legends</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:825070">Back</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j62t">Legends</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n806/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SWITHUN</label>, Sτ, bishop of Winchester from 852 to 862.
                    The name of St Swithun, patron saint of Winchester cathedral from the 10th to
                    the 16th century, is scarcely to be found in any contemporary document. His
                    death is entered in the <hi rend="italic">Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</hi> under the
                    year 861; and his signature is appended to several charters in Kemble’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Codex Diplomaticus.</hi> Of these charters three belong to 833,
                    838, and some year between 860 and 862. In the first the saint signs as
                    “Swithunus presbyter regis Egberti,” in the second as “Swithunus diaconus,” and
                    in the third as “Swithunus episcopus.” Hence if the second charter be genuine
                    the first must be spurious, and is so marked in Kemble.</p>
                <p>More than a hundred years later, when Dunstan and Ethelwold of Winchester were
                    inaugurating their church reform and supplanting the secular canons of the
                    degenerate English foundations by monks, St Swithun was adopted as patron of the
                    restored church at Winchester, formerly dedicated to St Peter and St Paul. His
                    body was taken up from its almost forgotten grave outside the old monastery and
                    transplanted to Ethelwold’s new basilica on 15th July 971. Numerous miracles
                    preceded and followed this translation. “We have seen,” saysone contemporary
                    writer, “the precincts of the monastery so thronged with crowds of ailing folk
                    that a traveller could scarcely make his way to the shrine; and yet, after some
                    days, so numerous were the cures that even within the church itself there were
                    scarcely five sick people to be seen.” Another writer, likewise a contemporary,
                    claims to the saint’s credit two hundred cures in the short space of ten
                    days.</p>
                <p>The revival of St Swithun’s fame gave rise to a mass of legendary literature,
                    from which it can only be deduced that towards the end of the 10th century very
                    little was known concerning his career. The so-called <hi rend="italic">Vitae
                    Swithuni</hi> of Lantfred and Wulstan, written about this time, hardly contain
                    the very smallest kernel of biographical fact; and all that has in later years
                    passed for authentic detail of St Swithun’s life is extracted from a biography,
                    ascribed with much probability to Gotzelin, a monk who came over to England with
                    Hermann, bishop of Salisbury from 1058 to 1078. From this writer, who has
                    perhaps preserved some fragments of genuine tradition, we learn that St Swithun
                    was born in the reign of Egbert, and was ordained priest by Helmstan, bishop of
                    Winchester (838-c. 852). His fame reached the king’s ears, who appointed him
                    tutor of his son Adulphus (Ethelwulf) and numbered him amongst his chief
                    friends. Under Ethelwulf he was appointed bishop of Winchester, to which see he
                    was consecrated by Archbishop Ceolnoth. In his new office he was remarkable for
                    his piety and his zeal in building new churches or restoring old ones. At his
                    request Ethelwulf gave the tenth of his royal lands to the church. His humility
                    was such that he made his diocesan journeys on foot; and when he gave a banquet
                    he invited the poor aud not the rich. He built near the eastern gate of his
                    cathedral city a bridge whose stone arches were so strongly constructed that in
                    Gotzelin’s time they seemed a work “non leviter ruiturus.” He died 2d July 862,
                    and gave orders that he was not to be buried within the church but outside in “a
                    vile and unworthy place.”</p>
                <p>William of Malmesbury adds that, as Bishop Alhstan of Sherborne was Ethelwulf’s
                    minister for temporal, so St Swithun was for spiritual matters. The same
                    chronicler uses a remarkable phrase in recording the bishop’s prayer that his
                    burial might be “ubi et pedibus praetereuntium et stillicidiis ex alto
                    rorantibus esset obnoxius.” This expression has been taken as indicating that
                    the well-known weather myth contained in the doggrel lines—</p>
                <p>St Swithin’s day if thou dost rain For forty days it will remain;</p>
                <p>St Swithin’s day if thou be fair For forty days ’twill rain na mair—</p>
                <p>had already, in the 12th century, crystallized round the name of St Swithun; but
                    it is doubtful if the passage lends itself by any straining to this
                    interpretation. Mr Raine has suggested that the legend is derived from the
                    tremendous downpour of rain that occurred, according to the Durham chroniclers,
                    on St Swithun’s day, 1315 (<hi rend="italic">Hist. Dunelm.,</hi> pp. xiii.
                    96-7). Another theory, more plausible, but historically worthless, traces it to
                    a heavy shower by which, on the day of his translation, the saint marked his
                    displeasure towards those who were removing his remains. This story, however,
                    cannot be traced farther back than some two or three centuries at the outside,
                    and is at variance with the 10th-century writers, who are all agreed that the
                    translation took place in accordance with the saint’s desire as expressed by
                    vision. More probable is Mr Earle’s suggestion that in the legend as now
                    current<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n807/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0807-0776"/> we have the survival of some pagan or possibly
                    prehistoric day of augury, which has sheltered itself and preserved its vitality
                    under the protection of an ecclesiastical saint. This view is supported by the
                    fact adduced in <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> (1st ser., xii. p. 137)
                    that in France St Médard (June 8) and St Gervase and St Protais (June 19) are
                    accredited with an influence on the weather almost identical with that
                    attributed to St Swithun in England. Mr Parker professes to detect a shower of
                    rain as the symbol of St Swithun in the clog almanacs (of Queen Elizabeth’s
                    time), but Mr Earle doubts the resemblance. Of other stories connected with St
                    Swithun the two most famous are those of the Winchester egg-woman and Queen
                    Emma’s ordeal. The former is be found in Gotzelin’s life (c. 1100), the latter
                    in Rudborne’s <hi rend="italic">Historia Major</hi></p>
                <p>(15th century),—a work which is also responsible for the not improbable legend
                    that this prelate accompanied Alfred on his visit to Rome in 856.</p>
                <p>The so-called lives of St Swithun written by Wulstan, Lantfred, and perhaps
                    others towards the end of the 10th century may be found in Bollandus’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Acta Sanctorum</hi> (July), i. 321-327; Mabillon’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Acta SS. o. B.,</hi> vi. 70, &amp;c., vii. 628, &amp;c.; and
                    Earle’s <hi rend="italic">Life and Times of St Swithun,</hi> 59, &amp;c. See
                    also william of Malmesbury, <hi rend="italic">Gest. Reg.,</hi> i. 150, and <hi
                    rend="italic">De Gest. Pont.,</hi> 160 <hi rend="italic">,</hi> 167, 179;
                    Florence of Worcester, i. 168; Rudborne ap. wharton’s <hi rend="italic">Anglia
                    Sacra,</hi> i. 287; Hardy's <hi rend="italic">Cat. of MSS.,</hi> i. 513-17;
                    Brand's <hi rend="italic">Popular Antiquities',</hi> Chambers’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Book of Days.</hi> Ethelwulf’s <hi rend="italic">Tithe
                    Charters,</hi> nearly all of which refer to St Swithun in the body of the text,
                    may be studied in Haddon and Stubbs’s <hi rend="italic">Councils,</hi> iii.
                    636-45; a comparison of the charter on page 642 with Gotzelin’s life (ap. Earle,
                    69) and william of Malmesbury <hi rend="italic">(Gest. Reg.,</hi> 150; <hi
                    rend="italic">De Gest. Pont.,</hi> 160) seems to show that these charters, even
                    if forgeries, date back at least to the 11th century, as well as the story of
                    his being Ethelwulf’s “altor et ductor.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
