<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0617-0594-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">STRENGTH OF MATERIALS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 594</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="39" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xj9j">Steel</term>
                    <term n="42" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gr12">Testing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="29" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n694">Stresses</term>
                    <term n="28" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="26" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="39" ref="fasttopic:1132472">Steel</term>
                    <term n="42" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1017914">Metallizing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1018047">Metals</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1148240">Testing</term>
                    <term n="26" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="fasttopic:899352">Dues</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n617/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STRENGTH OF MATERIALS</label></p>
                <p>1. The name “strength of materials” is given to that part of the theory of
                    engineering which deals with the nature and effects of stresses in the parts of
                    engineering structures. Its principal object is to determine the proper size and
                    form of pieces which have to bear given loads, or, conversely, to determine the
                    loads which can be safely applied to pieces whose dimensions and arrangement are
                    already given. It also treats of the relation between the applied loads and the
                    changes of form which they cause.</p>
                <p>The subject comprises experimental investigation of the properties of materials
                    as to strength and elasticity, and mathematical discussion of the stresses in
                    ties, struts, beams, shafts, and other elements of structures and machines.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stress</hi> is the mutual action at the surface of
                    contact between two bodies, or two imaginary parts of a body, whereby each of
                    the two exerts a force upon the other. Thus, when a stone lies on the ground
                    there is at the surface of contact a stress, one aspect of which is the force
                    directed downwards with which the stone pushes the ground, and the other aspect
                    is the equal force directed upwards with which the ground pushes the stone. A
                    body is said to be in a state of stress when there is a stress between the two
                    parts which lie on opposite sides of an imaginary surface of section. A pillar
                    or block supporting a weight is in a state of stress because at any cross
                    section the part above the section pushes down against the part below, and the
                    part below pushes up against the part above. A stretched rope is in a state of
                    stress, because at any cross section the part on each side is pulling the part
                    on the other side with a force in the direction of the rope’s length. A plate of
                    metal that is being cut in a shearing machine is in a state of stress, because
                    at the plane which is about to become the plane of actual section the portion of
                    metal on each side is tending to drag the portion on the other side with a force
                    in that plane.</p>
                <p>3. In a solid body which is in a state of stress the direction of stress at an
                    imaginary surface of division may be normal, oblique, or tangential to the
                    surface. When oblique it is often conveniently treated as consisting of a normal
                    and a tangential component. Normal stress may be either push (compressive
                    stress) or pull (tensile stress). Stress which is tangential to the surface is
                    called shearing stress. Oblique stress may be regarded as so much push or pull
                    along with so much shearing stress. The amount of stress per unit of surface is
                    called the intensity of stress. Stress is said to be uniformly distributed over
                    a surface when each fraction of the area of surface bears a corresponding
                    fraction of the whole stress. If a stress P is uniformly distributed over a
                    plane surface of area S, the intensity is P/S. If the stress is not uniformly
                    distributed, the intensity at any point is δP∕δS, where δP is the amount of
                    stress on an indefinitely small area δS at the point considered. For practical
                    purposes intensity of stress is usually expressed in tons weight per square
                    inch, pounds weight per square inch, or kilogrammes weight per square millimetre
                    or per square centimetre. <hi rend="superscript"><note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Οne ton per sq. in.=2240 lb per sq. in.=
                    1·511 kilos. per sq. mm.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p>4. The simplest possible state of stress is that of a short pillar or block
                    compressed by opposite forces applied at its ends, or that of a stretched rope
                    or other tie. In these cases the stress is wholly in one direction, that of the
                    length. These states may be distinguished as simple longitudinal push and simple
                    longitudinal pull. In them there is no stress on planes parallel to the
                    direction of the applied forces.</p>
                <p>A more complex state of stress occurs if the block is compressed or extended by
                    forces applied to a pair of opposite sides, as well as by forces applied to its
                    ends,—that is to say, if two simple longitudinal stresses in different
                    directions act together. A still more complex state occurs if a third stress be
                    applied to the remaining pair of sides. It may be shown that any state of stress
                    which can possibly exist at any point of a body may be produced by the joint
                    action of three simple pull or push stresses in three suitably chosen directions
                    at right angles to each other.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> vol. vif. p.
                    819.</p></note> These three are<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n618/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0618-0595"/> called principal stresses, and their directions
                    are called the axes of principal stress. These axes have the important property
                    that the intensity of stress along one of them is greater, and along another it
                    is less, than in any other direction.</p>
                <p>These are called respectively the axes of greatest and least principal
                    stress.</p>
                <p>5. Returning now to the case of a single simple longitudinal stress, let AB (fig.
                    1) be a portion of a tie or a strut which is being pulled or pushed in the
                    direction of the axis AB with a total stress P. On any plane CD taken at right
                    angles to the axis we have a normal pull or push of intensity <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi> =P∕S, S being the area of the normal cross-section. On a plane EF whose
                    normal is inclined to the axis at an angle θ we have a stress still in the
                    direction of the axis, and therefore oblique to the plane EF, of intensity P∕S',
                    where S' is the area of the surface EF, or S/cos <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi> The
                    whole stress P on EF may be resolved into two components, one normal to EF, and
                    the other a shearing stress tangential to EF. The normal component (P <hi
                    rend="subscript"> n</hi>, fig. 2) is PcosØ; the tangential component (P <hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> t</hi>) is Psin <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>. Hence the
                    intensity of normal pull or push on EF, or <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> n</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> is <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">θ</hi>, and the
                    intensity of shearing stress EF, or <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> t</hi>, is <hi rend="italic">p</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> cos
                    <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>.</p>
                <p>This expression makes <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi>
                    a maximum when 0 = 45°: planes inclined at 45° to tho axis are called planes of
                    maximum shearing stress; the intensity of shearing stress on them is ½ <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi>.</p>
                <p>6. Shearing stress in one direction is necessarily accompanied by an equal
                    intensity of shearing stress in another direction at right angles to the first.
                    To prove this it is sufficient to consider the equilibrium of an indefinitely
                    small cube (fig. 3), with one pair of sides parallel to the direction of the
                    shearing stress P <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi>. This stress, acting on
                    two opposite sides, produces a couple which tends to rotate the cube. No
                    arrangement of normal stresses on any of the three pairs of sides of the cube
                    can balance this couple; that can be done only by a shearing stress Q <hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> whose direction is at right angles to the first
                    stress P <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> and to the surface on which P <hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> acts, and whose intensity is the same as that of
                    P <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi>. The shearing stresses P <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> t</hi> and Q <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> may exist alone, or
                    as components of oblique stress.</p>
                <p>7. If they exist alone, the material is said to be in a state of simple shearing
                    stress. This state of stress may be otherwise described by reference to the
                    stresses on diagonal planes of the cube ABCD. Thus P <hi rend="italic subscript"
                    > t</hi> aud Q <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> produce a normal stress R on
                    a diagonal plane, and the equilibrium of the triangular prism</p>
                <p>(fig. 4) requires that</p>
                <p>R=P <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> √2. But R acts on a surface which is
                    greater than each of the sides in the ratio of √2: 1. The inten sity of normal
                    stress on the diagonal plane</p>
                <p>AC is therefore the same as the intensity of shearing stress on AB or BC. The
                    same considerations apply to the other diagonal plane BD at right angles to AC,
                    with this difference, that the stress on it is normal pull instead of push.
                    Hence we may regard a state of simple shearing stress as compounded of two
                    simple longitudinal stresses, one of push and one of pull, at right angles to
                    each other, of equal intensity, and inclined at 45° to the direction of the
                    shearing stress.</p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="smallcaps">Strain</hi> is the change of shape produced by stress. If
                    the stress is a simple longitudinal pull, the strain consists of lengthening in
                    the direction of the pull, accompanied by contraction in both directions at
                    right angles to the pull. If the stress is a simple push, the strain consists of
                    shortening in the direction of the push and expansion in both directions at
                    right angles to that; the stress and the strain are then exactly the reverse of
                    what they are in the case of simple pull. If the stress is one of simple
                    shearing, the strain consists of a distortion such as would be produced by the
                    sliding of layers in the direction of the shearing stresses.</p>
                <p>A material is elastic with regard to any applied stress if the strain disappears
                    when the stress is removed. Strain which persists after the stress that produced
                    it is removed is called permanent set. For brevity, it is convenient to speak of
                    strain which disappears when the stress is removed as elastic strain.</p>
                <p>9. Actual materials are generally very perfectly elastic with regard to small
                    stresses, and very imperfectly elastic with regard to great stresses. If the
                    applied stress is less than a certain limit, the strain is in general small in
                    amount, and disappears wholly or almost wholly when the stress is removed. If
                    the applied stress exceeds this limit, the strain is, in general, much greater
                    than before, and the principal part of it is found, when the stress is removed,
                    to consist of permanent set. The limits of stress within which strain is wholly
                    or almost wholly elastic are called limits of elasticity.</p>
                <p>For any particular mode of stress the limit of elasticity is much more sharply
                    defined in some materials than in others. When well defined it may readily be
                    recognized in the testing of a sample from the fact that after the stress
                    exceeds the limit of elasticity the strain begins to increase in a much more
                    rapid ratio to the stress than before. This characteristic goes along with the
                    one already mentioned, that up to the limit the strain is wholly or almost
                    wholly elastic.</p>
                <p>10. Within the limits of elasticity the strain produced by a stress of any one
                    kind is proportional to the stress producing it. This is Hooke’s law, enunciated
                    by him in 1676.</p>
                <p>In applying Hooke’s law to the case of simple longitudinal stress, —such as the
                    case of a bar stretched by simple longitudinal pull,— we may measure the state
                    of strain by the change of length per unit of original length which the bar
                    undergoes when stressed. Let the original length be <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>
                    and let the whole change of length be δ <hi rend="italic">l</hi> when a stress
                    is applied whose intensity <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is within the elastic limit.
                    Then the strain is measured by <hi rend="italic">Sl∕l,</hi> and this by Hooke’s
                    law is proportional to <hi rend="italic">ρ.</hi> This may be written <hi
                    rend="italic">δl: l :: p</hi>: E, where E is a constant for the particular
                    material considered. The same value of E applies to push and to pull, these
                    modes of stress being essentially continuous, and differing only in sign.</p>
                <p>11. This constant E is called the modulus of longitudinal extensibility, or
                    Young’s modulus. Its value, which is expressed in the same units as are used to
                    express intensity of stress, may be measured directly by exposing a long sample
                    of the material to longitudinal pull and noting the extension, or indirectly by
                    measuring the flexure of a loaded beam of the material, or by experiments on the
                    frequency of vibrations. It is frequently spoken of by engineers simply as the
                    modulus of elasticity, but this name is too general, as there are other
                    moduluses applicable to other modes of stress. Since E <hi rend="italic"
                    >=pl/δl,</hi> the modulus may be defined as the ratio of the intensity of stress
                    <hi rend="italic">p</hi> to the longitudinal strain <hi rend="italic"
                    >δl∕l</hi>.</p>
                <p>12. In the case of simple shearing stress, the strain may be measured by the
                    angle by which each of the four originally right angles in the square prism of
                    fig. 3 is altered by the distortion of the prism. Let this angle be <hi
                    rend="italic">φ</hi> in radians; then by Hooke’s law <hi rend="italic"
                    >p∣φ=C,</hi> where <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is the intensity of shearing stress
                    and C is a constant which measures the rigidity of the material. C is called the
                    modulus of rigidity, and is usually determined by experiments on torsion.</p>
                <p>13. When three simple stresses of equal intensity <hi rend="italic">p</hi> and of
                    the same sign (all pulls or all pushes) are applied in three directions, the
                    material (provided it be isotropic, that is to say, provided its properties are
                    the same in all directions) suffers change of volume only, without distortion of
                    form. If the volume is V and the change of volume δV, the ratio of the stress
                    <hi rend="italic">p</hi> to the strain δV∕Y is called the modulus of cubic
                    compressibility, and will be denoted by K. The state of stress here considered
                    is the only one possible in a fluid at rest. The intensity of stress is equal in
                    all directions.</p>
                <p>14. Of these three moduluses the one of most importance in engineering
                    applications is Young’s modulus E. When a simple longitudinal pull or push of
                    intensity <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is applied to a piece, the longitudinal
                    strain of extension or compression is <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">∕E.</hi> This is accompanied by a lateral contraction or
                    expansion, in each transverse direction, whose amount may be written <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi> ∕σE, where σ is the ratio of longitudinal to lateral
                    strain. It is shown in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> § 47,
                    that E= <hi rend="superscript"> 9CK</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3K+C</hi> and
                    σ= <hi rend="superscript"> 2(3K+C)</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3K-2C</hi></p>
                <p>15. Beyond the limits of elasticity the relation of strain to stress becomes very
                    indefinite. Materials then exhibit, to a greater or less degree, the property of
                    plasticity. The strain is much affected by the length of time during which the
                    stress has been in operation, and reaches its maximum, for any assigned stress,
                    only after a long (probably an indefinitely long) time. Finally, when the stress
                    is sufficiently increased, the ratio of the increment of strain to the increment
                    of stress becomes indefinitely great if time is given for the stress to take
                    effect. In other words, the substance then assumes what may be called a
                    completely plastic state; it <hi rend="italic">flows</hi> under the applied
                    stress like a viscous liquid.</p>
                <p>16. The <hi rend="italic">ultimate strength</hi> of a material with regard to any
                    stated mode of stress is the stress required to produce rupture. In reckoning
                    ultimate strength, however, engineers take, not the actual intensity of stress
                    at which rupture occurs, but the value which this intensity would have reached
                    had rupture ensued without previous alteration of shape. Thus, if a bar whose
                    original cross-section is 2 square inches breaks under a uniformly distributed
                    pull of 60 tons, the ultimate tensile strength of the material is reckoned to be
                    30 tons per square inch, although the actual intensity of stress which produced
                    rupture may have been much greater than this, owing to the contraction of the
                    section previous to fracture. The convenience of this usage will be obvious from
                    an example. Suppose that a piece<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n619/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0619-0596"/> of material of the same quality he used in a
                    structure under conditions which cause it to bear a simple pull of 6 tons per
                    square inch; we conclude at once that the actual load is one-fifth of that which
                    would cause rupture, irrespective of the extent to which the material might
                    contract in section if overstrained. The stresses which occur in engineering
                    practice are, or ought to be, in all cases within the limits of elasticity, and
                    within these limits the change of cross-section caused by longitudinal pull or
                    push is so small that it may be neglected in reckoning the intensity of
                    stress.</p>
                <p>Ultimate tensile strength and ultimate shearing strength are well defined, since
                    these modes of stress (simple pull and simple shearing stress) lead to distinct
                    fracture if the stress is sufficiently increased. Under compression some
                    materials yield so continuously that their ultimate strength to resist
                    compression can scarcely be specified; others show so distinct a fracture by
                    crushing (§ 43 below) that their compressive strength may be determined with
                    some precision. In what follows, the three kinds of ultimate strength will be
                    designated by the symbols <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    t</hi><hi rend="italic">, f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> s</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    c</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> for tension, shearing, and crushing
                    respectively.</p>
                <p>Some of the materials used in engineering, notably timber and wrought-iron, are
                    so far from being isotropic that their strength is widely different for stresses
                    in different directions. In the case of wrought-iron the process of rolling
                    develops a fibrous structure on account of the presence of streaks of slag which
                    become interspersed with the metal in puddling; and the tensile strength of a
                    rolled plate is found to be considerably greater in the direction of rolling
                    than across the plate. Steel plates, being rolled from a nearly homogeneous
                    ingot, have nearly the same strength in both directions.</p>
                <p>17. In applying a knowledge of the ultimate strength of materials to determine
                    the proper sizes of parts in an engineering structure, these parts are
                    proportioned so that the greatest intensity of stress (which for brevity is
                    called the working stress) will be only a certain fraction of the ultimate
                    strength. The ratio <hi rend="superscript"> ultimate strength</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> working stress</hi> is called the factor of safety.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>French engineers usually
                    estimate the permissible working stress as a certain fraction of the elastic
                    strength (that is, of the stress which reaches the limit of elasticity), instead
                    of estimating it as a certain fraction of the ultimate strength.</p></note> The
                    choice of a factor of safety depends on many considerations, such as the
                    probable accuracy of the theory on which the calculation of working stress has
                    been based; the uniformity of the material dealt with, and the extent to which
                    its strength may be expected to conform to the assumed value or to the values
                    determined by experiments on samples; the deviations from the specified
                    dimensions which may be caused by bad workmanship; the probable accuracy in the
                    estimation of loads; the extent to which the materials will deteriorate in time.
                    The factor is rarely less than 3, is very commonly 4 or 5, and is sometimes as
                    much as 12, or even more.</p>
                <p>The ultimate strength for any one mode of stress, such as simple pull, has been
                    found to depend on the time rate at which stress is applied; this will be
                    noticed more fully later (§§ 28-34). It has also been found to depend very
                    greatly on the extent and frequency of variation in the applied stress. A stress
                    considerably less than the normal ultimate strength will suffice to break a
                    piece when it is frequently applied and removed; a much smaller stress will
                    cause rupture if its sign is frequently reversed; and hence in a structure which
                    has to bear what is called live load the permissible intensity of stress is less
                    than in a structure which has to bear only load and also on its frequency of
                    variation (§§ 45, 46 below).</p>
                <p>18. From an engineering point of view, the structural merit of a material,
                    especially when live loads and possible shocks have to be sustained, depends not
                    only on the ultimate strength but also on the extent to which the material will
                    bear deformation without rupture. This characteristic is shown in tests made to
                    determine tensile strength by the amount of ultimate elongation, and also by the
                    contraction of the cross-section which occurs through the flow of the metal
                    before rupture. It is often tested in other ways, such as by bending and
                    unbending bars in a circle of specified radius, or by examining the effect of
                    repeated blows. Tests by impact are generally made by causing a weight to fall
                    through a regulated distance on a piece of the material supported as a beam.</p>
                <p>19. Ordinary tests of strength are made by submitting the piece to direct pull,
                    direct compression, bending, or torsion. Testing machines are frequently
                    arranged so that they may apply any of these four modes of stress; tests by
                    direct tension are the most common, and next to them come tests by bending. When
                    the samples to be tested for tensile strength are mere wires, the stress may be
                    applied directly by weights; for pieces of larger section some mechanical
                    multiplication of force becomes necessary. Owing to the plasticity of the
                    materials to be tested, the applied loads must be able to follow considerable
                    change of form in the test-piece: thus in testing the tensile strength of
                    wrought-iron or steel provision must be made for taking up the large extension
                    of length which occurs before fracture. In most modern forms of large testing
                    machines the loads are applied by means of hydraulic pressure acting on a piston
                    or plunger to which one end of the specimen is secured, and the stress is
                    measured by connecting the other end to a lever or system of levers provided
                    with adjustable weights. In small machines, and also in some large ones, the
                    stress is applied by screw gearing instead of by hydraulic pressure. Springs are
                    sometimes used instead of weights to measure the stress, and another plan is to
                    make one end of the specimen act on a diaphragm forming part of a hydrostatic
                    pressure-gauge (§ 23 below).</p>
                <p>20. Figs. 5 and 6 show an excellent form of single-lever testing machine designed
                    by Mr J. H. Wicksteed,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng.,</hi> August 1882.</p></note> in
                    which the stress is applied by an hydraulic plunger and is measured by a lever
                    or steelyard and a movable weight. The illustration shows a 30-ton machine, but
                    machines of similar design have been built to exert a force of 100 tons or more.
                    AA is the lever, on which there is a graduated scale. The stress on the
                    test-piece T is measured by a weight W of 1 ton (with an attached vernier
                    scale), which is moved along the lever by a screw-shaft S; this screw-shaft is
                    driven by a belt from a parallel shaft R, which takes<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n620/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0620-0597"/> its motion, through bevel-wheels and a Hooke’s
                    joint in the axis of the fulcrum, from the hand-wheel H. (The Hooke’s joint in
                    the shaft R is shown in a separate sketch above the lever in fig. 6.) The holder
                    for the upper end of the sample hangs from a knife-edge three inches from the
                    fulcrum of the lever. The lower holder is jointed to a crosshead C, which is
                    connected by two vertical screws to a lower crosshead B, upon which the
                    hydraulic plunger P, shown in section in fig. 5, exerts its thrust. G is a
                    counterpoise which pushes up the plunger, when the water is allowed to escape.
                    Hydraulic pressure may be applied to P by pumps or by an accumulator. In the
                    present instance it is applied by means of an auxiliary plunger Q, which is
                    pressed by screw gearing into an auxiliary cylinder. Q is driven by a belt on
                    the pulley D. This puts stress on the specimen, and the weight W is then run out
                    along the lever so that the lever is just kept floating between the stops E, E.
                    Before the test-piece is put in, the distance between the holders is regulated
                    by means of the screws connecting the upper and lower crossheads C and B, these
                    screws being turned by a handle applied at F. Fig. 7 is a section of one of the
                    holders, showing how the test-piece T is gripped by serrated wedges. The
                    knife-edges are made long enough to prevent the load on them ever exceeding 5
                    tons to the linear inch.</p>
                <p>21. Another example of the single-lever type is the Werder testing machine, much
                    used on the continent of Europe. In it the specimen is horizontal; one end is
                    fixed, the other is attached to the short vertical arm of a bell-crank lever,
                    whose fulcrum is pushed out horizontally by an hydraulic ram.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Maschine
                    zum Prüfen d. Festigkeit d. Materialen,</hi> &amp;c., Munich, 1882.</p></note>
                    In many other testing machines a system of two, three, or more levers is
                    employed to reduce the force between the specimen and the measuring weight.
                    Probably the earliest machine of this class was that of Major Wade,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Report of
                    Experiments on Metals for Cannon,</hi> Philadelphia, 1856; also Anderson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Strength of Materials,</hi> p. 15.</p></note> in which one end of
                    the specimen was held in a fixed support, and the stretch was taken up by
                    screwing up the fulcrum plate of one of the levers. In most multiple-lever
                    machines, however, the fulcrums are fixed, and the stress is applied to one end
                    of the specimen by hydraulic power or by screw gearing, which of course takes up
                    the stretch, as in the single-lever machines already described. Mr Kirkaldy, who
                    was one of the earliest as well as one of the most assiduous workers in this
                    field, applies in his 1,000,000 fb machine a horizontal hydraulic press directly
                    to one end of the horizontal test-piece. The other end of the piece is connected
                    to the short vertical arm of a bell-crank lever; the long arm of this lever is
                    horizontal, and is connected to a second lever to which weights are applied. In
                    some of Messrs Fairbanks’s machines the multiple-lever system is carried so far
                    that the point of application of the weight moves 24,000 times as far as the
                    point of attachment to the test-piece. The same makers have employed a plan of
                    adjusting automatically the position of the measuring weight, by making the
                    scale lever complete an electric circuit when it rises or falls so that it
                    starts an electric engine which runs the weight out or in.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Abbott, <hi rend="italic">On Testing
                    Machines,</hi> New York, 1884, or <hi rend="italic">Van Nostrand's Engineering
                    Mag.,</hi> 1884.</p></note> Generally the measuring weight is adjusted by hand.
                    In some, chiefly small, machines, the weight adjusts itself by means of another
                    device. It is fixed at one point of a lever which is arranged as a pendulum, so
                    that, when the test-piece is pulled by force applied at the other end, the
                    pendulum lever is deflected from its originally vertical position and the weight
                    acts with increasing leverage.</p>
                <p>Multiple-lever machines have the advantage that the measuring weight is reduced
                    to a conveniently small value, and that it can be easily varied to suit
                    test-pieces of different strengths. On tho other hand, their multiplicity of
                    joints makes the leverage somewhat uncertain and increases friction. Another
                    drawback is the inertia of the working parts. It is impossible to avoid
                    oscillations of the levers: and, to prevent them from producing important errors
                    in the recorded stress, the inertia of the oscillating system should be
                    minimized. In a testing machine in which the specimen is directly loaded the
                    inertia is simply that of the suspended weight M. In a lever machine, which
                    multiplies the weight <hi rend="italic">n</hi> times, the weight applied to the
                    lever is reduced to M <hi rend="italic">∕n</hi>, but its inertia, when referred
                    to the test-piece, is (M <hi rend="italic">/n)</hi> × <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> or Mn. The inertia which is effective for
                    producing oscillation is thus increased <hi rend="italic">n</hi> times, so far
                    as the weight alone is concerned, and this detrimental effect of leverage is
                    increased by the inertia of the levers themselves. Tho effect will be more
                    serious the greater is the leverage n.</p>
                <p>22. Whitworth and others employ machines in which one end of the specimen is held
                    in a fixed support; an hydraulic press acts on the other end, and the stress is
                    calculated from the pressure of fluid in the press, this being observed by a
                    pressure-gauge. Machines of this class are open to the obvious objection that
                    the friction of the hydraulic plunger causes a large and very uncertain
                    difference between the force exerted by the fluid on the plunger and the force
                    exerted by the plunger on the specimen. It appears, however, that in the
                    ordinary conditions of packing the friction is very nearly proportional to the
                    fluid pressure, and its effect may therefore be allowed for with some exactness.
                    The method is not to be recommended for work requiring precision, unless the
                    plunger be kept in constant rotation on its own axis during the test, in which
                    case the effects of friction are almost entirely eliminated.</p>
                <p>23. In another important class of testing machines the stress (applied as before
                    to one end of the piece, by gearing or by hydraulic pressure)</p>
                <p>is measured by con necting the other end to a flexible diaphragm, on which a
                    liquid acts whose pressure is determined by a gauge.</p>
                <p>Fig. 8 shows a simple machine of this class (used in 1873 for testing wire by Sir
                    W. Thomson and the late Prof. F.</p>
                <p>Jenkin). The wire is stretched by means of a screw at the top, and pulls up the
                    lower side of a hydrostatic bellows; water from the bellows rises in the
                    gauge-tube G, and its height measures the stress. Fig. 9 is Thomasset's testing
                    machine, in which one end of the specimen is pulled by an hydraulic press A. The
                    other end acts through a bell-crank lever B on a horizontal diaphragm C,
                    consisting of a metallic plate and a flexible ring of india-rubber. The pressure
                    on the diaphragm causes a column of mercury to rise in the gauge-tube D. The
                    same principle is made use of in the testing machines of Chauvin and Marin-</p>
                <p>Darbel, Maillard,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For
                    descriptions of several of these machines, see a paper by MM. Denizeau and
                    Lechien, <hi rend="italic">Mémorial de l’Artillerie et de Ia Marine,</hi>
                    l883.</p></note> and Bailey. It has found its most important application in the
                    remarkable testing machine of Watertown arsenal, built in 1879 by the U.S.
                    Government to the designs of Mr A. H. Emery. This is a horizontal machine,
                    taking specimens of any length up to 30 feet, and exerting a pull of 360 tons or
                    a push of 480 tons by an hydraulic press at one end. The stress is taken at the
                    other end by a group of four large vertical diaphragm presses, which communicate
                    by small tubes with four similar small diaphragm presses in the scale case. The
                    pressure of these acts on a system of levers which terminates in the scale beam.
                    The joints and bearings of all the levers are made frictionless by using
                    flexible steel connecting plates instead of knife-edges. The total
                    multiplication at the end of the scale beam is 420,000.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Report of the U.S.
                    Board appointed to test Iron, Steel, and other Metals</hi> 2 vols 1881 For full
                    details of the Emery machine, see <hi rend="italic">Report of the U.S. Chief of
                    Ordnance, 1883, appendix 24.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>24. The results of tests are very commonly exhibited by means of stress-strain
                    diagrams, or diagrams showing the relation of strain to stress. A few typical
                    diagrams for wrought-iron and steel in tension are given in fig. 10, the data
                    for which are taken from tests of long rods by Mr Kirkaldy.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Experiments on the
                    Mechanical Properties of Steel by a Committee of Civil Engineers,</hi> London,
                    1868 and 1870.</p></note> Up to the elastic limit these diagrams show sensibly
                    the same rate of extension tor all the materials to which they refer. Soon after
                    the limit of elasticity is passed, a point, which has been called by Prof.
                    Kennedy the yield-point, is reached, which is marked by a very sudden extension
                    of<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0621-0598"/> the specimen. After this the extension becomes
                    less rapid; then it continues at a fairly regular and gradually increasing rate;
                    near the point of rupture the metal again begins to draw out rapidly.</p>
                <p>When this stage is reached rupture will occur through the flow of the metal, even
                    if the load be somewhat decreased. The diagram may in this way be made to come
                    back towards the line of no load, by withdrawing a part of the load as the end
                    of the test is approached (§ 29 below).</p>
                <p>25. Fig. 11 is a stress-strain diagram for cast-iron in extension and
                    compression, taken from Hodgkinson’s experiments.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Report of the Commissioners
                    on the Application of Iron to Railway Structures,</hi></p></note> The extension
                    was measured on a rod 50 feet long; the compression was also measured on a long
                    rod, which was prevented from buckling by being supported in a trough with
                    partitions. The full line gives the strain produced by loading; it is continuous
                    through the origin, showing that Young’s modulus is the same for pull and push.
                    (Similar experiments on wrought-iron and steel in extension and compression have
                    given the same result.)</p>
                <p>The broken line shows the set produced by each load. Hodgkinson found that some
                    set could be detected after even the smallest loads had been applied. This is
                    probably due to the existence of initial internal stress in the metal, produced
                    by unequally rapid cooling in different portions of the cast bar. A second
                    loading of the same piece showed a much closer approach to perfect elasticity.
                    The elastic limit is, at the best, ill defined; but by the time the ultimate
                    load is reached the set has become a more considerable part of the whole strain.
                    The pull curves in the diagram extend to the point of rupture; the compression
                    curves are drawn only up to a stage at which the bar buckled (between the
                    partitions) so much as to affect the results.</p>
                <p>26. Testing machines are now frequently fitted with autographic appliances for
                    drawing strain diagrams. When the load is measured by a weight travelling on a
                    steelyard, the diagram may be drawn by connecting the weight with a drum by
                    means of a wire or cord, so that the drum is made to revolve through angles
                    proportional to the travel of the weight. At the same time another wire,
                    fastened to a clip near one end of the specimen, and passing over a pulley near
                    the other end, draws a pencil through distances proportional to the strain, and
                    so traces a diagram of stress and strain on a sheet of paper stretched round the
                    drum. Apparatus of this kind has been used by Messrs Fairbanks, Unwin, Aspinall,
                    and others.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For
                    descriptions of these and other types of autographic recorder, see a paper by
                    Prof. Unwin, “On the Employment of Autographic Records in Testing Materials,”
                    <hi rend="italic">Jour. Soc. Arts,</hi> Feb., 1886; also Prof. Kennedy’s
                    comprehensive paper, “Οn the Use and Equipment of Engineering Laboratories,” <hi
                    rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> 1886, which contains much valuable
                    information on the whole subject of testing and testing machines.</p></note> In
                    Mr Wicksteed’s autographic recorder the stress is determined by reference, not
                    to the load on the lever, but to the pressure in the hydraulic cylinder by which
                    stress is applied. The main cylinder is in communication with a small auxiliary
                    hydraulic cylinder, the plunger of which is kept rotating to avoid friction at
                    its packing. This plunger abuts against a spring, so that the distance through
                    which it is pushed out varies with the pressure in the main cylinder. A drum
                    covered with paper moves with the plunger under a fixed pencil, and is also
                    caused to rotate by a wire from the specimen through distances proportional to
                    the strain. The scale of loads is calibrated by occasional reference to the
                    weighted lever.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng.,</hi> 1S86. An interesting feature of this
                    apparatus is a device for preventing error in the diagram through motion of the
                    test-piece as a whole.</p></note> In Prof. Kennedy’s machine autographic
                    diagrams are drawn by applying the stress to the test-piece through an elastic
                    master-bar of larger section. The master-bar is never strained beyond its
                    elastic limit, and within that limit its extension furnishes an accurate measure
                    of the stress; this gives motion to a pencil, which writes on a paper moved by
                    the extension of the test-piece.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng.,1886;</hi> also <hi
                    rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> vol.lxxxviii., 1886, pl. 1.</p></note>
                    In Prof. Thurston’s pendulum machine for torsion tests, a cam attached to the
                    pendulum moves a pencil through distances proportional to the stress, while a
                    paper drum attached to the other end of the test-piece turns under the pencil
                    through distances proportional to the angle of twist.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Thurston's <hi rend="italic">Materials of
                    Engineering,</hi> part ii. For accounts of work done with this machine, see <hi
                    rend="italic">Trans. Amer. Soc. Civ. Eng.,</hi> from 1876; also, <hi
                    rend="italic">Report</hi> of the American Board, cited above.</p></note></p>
                <p>27. The elastic extension or compression of a test-piece of ordinary dimensions
                    is so small as to require for its measurement refined methods which are seldom
                    employed in everyday practical testing. Measurements of this class must be made
                    simultaneously on opposite sides of the test-piece, to guard against error
                    through the bending of the piece. Microscopes and also various forms of
                    micrometer calipers are used for the purpose.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See a paper by Prof. Unwin, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phil. Mag.,</hi> March, 1887.</p></note> A method capable of great delicacy,
                    which has been used by Bauschinger<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Mitth. aus dem Mech.-Tech. Lab. in
                    München,</hi> Heft 5.</p></note> and others, is to measure the strain by light
                    reflected from a pair of small mirrors attached to rollers which turn as the
                    specimen extends or contracts. With apparatus of this kind it may be shown that
                    iron, steel, or other materials with a well-defined yield-point begin to show a
                    marked defect of elasticity at a somewhat lower stress. The true elastic limit
                    comes considerably earlier in the test than the point which usually passes by
                    that name.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Cf.</hi> Bauschinger, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.;</hi> Kennedy,
                    <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.;</hi> Jenny <hi rend="italic">Festigkeits
                    Versuche,</hi> Vienna, 1878.</p></note></p>
                <p>28. In testing a plastic material such as wrought-iron or mild steel it is found
                    that the behaviour of the metal depends very materially on the time rate at
                    which stress is applied. When once the elastic limit is passed the full strain
                    corresponding to a given load is reached only after a perceptible time,
                    sometimes even a long time. If the load be increased to a value exceeding the
                    elastic limit, and then kept constant, the metal will be seen to draw out (if
                    the stress be one of pull), at first rapidly and then more slowly. When the
                    applied load is considerably less than the ultimate strength of the piece (as
                    tested in the ordinary way by steady increment of load), it appears that this
                    process of slow extension comes at last to an end. On the other hand, when the
                    applied load is nearly equal to the ultimate strength, the flow of the metal
                    continues until rupture occurs. Then, as in the former case, extension goes on
                    at first quickly, then slowly, but, finally, instead of approaching an
                    asymptotic limit, it quickens again as the piece approaches rupture. The same
                    phenomena are observed in the bending of timber and other materials when in the
                    form of beams. If, instead of being subjected to a constant load, a test-piece
                    is set in a constant condition of strain, it is found that the stress required
                    to maintain this constant strain gradually decreases.</p>
                <p>29. The gradual flow which goes on under, constant stress— approaching a limit if
                    the stress is moderate in amount, and continuing without limit if the stress is
                    sufficiently great—will still go on at a diminished rate if the amount of stress
                    be reduced. Thus, in the testing of soft iron or mild steel by a machine in
                    which the stress is applied by hydraulic power, a stage is reached soon after
                    the limit of elasticity is passed at which the metal begins to flow with great
                    rapidity. The pumps often do not keep pace with this, and the result is that, if
                    the lever is to be kept floating, the weight on it must be run back. Under this
                    reduced stress the<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0622-0599"/> flow continues, more slowly than before, until
                    presently the pumps recover their lost ground and the increase of stress is
                    resumed. Again, near the point of rupture, the flow again becomes specially
                    rapid; the weight on the lever has again to be run back, and the specimen
                    finally breaks under a diminished load.</p>
                <p>These features are well shown by fig. 12, which is copied from the autographic
                    diagram of a test of mild steel.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The increase of strain without increase of stress, which
                    goes on without limit when a test-piece under tension approaches rupture, is a
                    special case of the general phenomenon of “flow of solids,” which has been
                    exhibited, chiefly for compressive stresses, in a series of beautiful
                    experiments by Tresca <hi rend="italic">(Mémoires sur l'Écoulement des Corps
                    Solides,</hi> also <hi rend="italic">Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng.,</hi> 1S67 and
                    1878).</p></note></p>
                <p>30. But it is not only; through what we may call the viscosity of materials that
                    the time rate of loading affects their behaviour under test. In iron and steel,
                    and probably in some other metals, time has another effect of a very remarkable
                    kind. Let the test be carried to any point <hi rend="italic">a</hi> (fig. 13)
                    past the original limit of elasticity. Let the load then be removed; during the
                    first stages of this removal the material continues to stretch slightly, as has
                    been explained above. Let the load then be at once replaced and loading
                    continued. It will then be found that there is a new yield-point <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> at or near the value of the load formerly reached; up to
                    this point there is little other than elastic strain.</p>
                <p>The full line <hi rend="italic">be</hi> in fig. 13 shows the subsequent behaviour
                    of the piece. But now let the experiment be repeated on another sample, with
                    this difference, that an interval of time, of a few hours or more, is allowed to
                    elapse after the load is removed and before it is replaced. It will then be
                    found that a process of hardening has been going on during this interval of
                    rest; for, when the loading is continued, the new yield-point appears, not at
                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi> as formerly, but at a higher load <hi rend="italic"
                    >d.</hi></p>
                <p>Other evidence that a change has taken place is afforded by the fact that the
                    ultimate extension is reduced and the ultimate strength is increased (c, fig.
                    13).</p>
                <p>31. A similar aud even more marked hardening occurs when a load (exceeding the
                    original elastic limit), instead of being removed and replaced, is kept on for a
                    sufficient length of time without change. When loading is resumed a new
                    yield-point is found only after a considerable addition has been made to the
                    load. The result is, as in the former case, to give greater ultimate strength
                    and less ultimate elongation, Fig. 14 exhibits two experiments of this kind,
                    made with annealed iron wire. A load of 23½ tons per square inch was reached in
                    both cases; <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> shows the result of continuing to load
                    after an interval of five minutes, and <hi rend="italic">acd</hi> after an
                    interval of 45½ hours, the stress of 23½ tons being maintained during the
                    interval in both cases.</p>
                <p>32. It must not be supposed that in a material hardened by strain the elasticity
                    is perfect up to the yield-points which are shown in fig. 13 at <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> or in fig. 14 at <hi
                    rend="italic">c.</hi> In experiments made for this article, it has been found
                    that, after a piece of very soft iron wire has been hardened (as in fig. 14) by
                    the continued application of a load which had caused stretching, if a small
                    addition be made to the load (bringing it to a value between <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi> and the new yield-point), although there is at first no apparent drawing
                    out, nevertheless if time be given the wire begins again to draw, and a large
                    amount of stretching at an increased pace may ensue. In this way wires have been
                    broken with loads considerably short of those which would have been required had
                    the process of loading, from the point <hi rend="italic">a</hi> onward, been
                    continued at a moderately rapid rate. A slow process of viscous deformation may
                    in fact be occurring at the same time that the metal shows a quasi-elasticity
                    with respect to rapid alteration of stress. Bauschinger’s micrometric
                    experiments have shown that after a piece has been hardened by rest the true
                    limit of elasticity, or the point at which Hooke’s law begins to fail, comes far
                    short of the yield-point. He has also shown that a long interval of rest after
                    the set has taken place produces a slow rise of the true limit of
                    elasticity,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Mitth. aus dem Mech.-Tech. Lab. in München,</hi> Heft 13,
                    1886.</p></note> apparently a slower rise than the lapse of time causes in the
                    yield-point itself.</p>
                <p>33. In the testing of iron and steel the time during which any state of (pull)
                    stress (exceeding the original elastic limit) exists affects the result in two
                    somewhat antagonistic ways. It augments extension, by giving the metal leisure
                    to flow. This may be called the viscous effect. But, on the other hand, it
                    reduces the amount of extension which subsequent greater loads will cause, and
                    it increases the amount of load required for rupture in the way which has just
                    been described. This may be called the hardening effect. When a piece is broken
                    by continuous gradual increment of load, these two effects are occurring at all
                    stages of the test. If the viscous effect existed alone, or if the hardening
                    effect were small, the material would show to greater advantage as regards
                    elongation, and to less advantage as regards ultimate strength, the more slowly
                    the load were applied. Tin and lead may be cited as materials for which this is
                    the case. But when the hardening effect is relatively great, as in iron and
                    steel, the material shows less elongation and a higher breaking strength the
                    more slowly it is tested. An excellent illustration of this is given by the
                    following experiment of Mr Bottomley. Pieces of iron wire, annealed and of
                    exceptionally soft quality, when loaded at the rate of 1 lb in 5 minutes, broke
                    with 44¼lb and stretched 27 per cent. of their original length. Other pieces of
                    the same wire, loaded at the rate of 1 lb in 24 hours, broke with 47 lb and
                    stretched less than 7 per cent.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1879, p. 221. See
                    also <hi rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> § 80 .</p></note> Again, it has been
                    found that an excessively rapid application of stress (by the explosion of
                    gun-cotton) makes soft steel stretch twice as much as in ordinary testing.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See remarks by Col. Maitland,
                    <hi rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> vol. lxxvi. p. 104.</p></note> The
                    case is very different, however, if the material has been previously hardened by
                    strain. It does not appear that such variations in the rate of loading as are
                    liable to occur in practical tests of iron or steel have much influence on the
                    extension or the strength, great as the effects of time are when the metal is
                    loaded either much more slowly or much more quickly. In fig. 15 the results are
                    shown of tests of two similar pieces of soft iron wire, one loaded to rupture in
                    4 minutes and the other at a rate about 5000 times slower.</p>
                <p>34. The hardening effect which intervals of rest ... , . from load or of constant
                    load produce, once the primitive elastic limit is passed, has been examined by
                    Beardsley,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi
                    rend="italic">Report of the U.S. Board on Tests of Metals,</hi> vol. i. section
                    4.</p></note> Thurston,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>See <hi rend="italic">Report of the U.S. Board on Tests of Metals,</hi> vol.
                    i. section 4.</p></note> Bauschinger,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Loc. cit.</hi></p></note> Ewing,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy.
                    Soc.,</hi> June 1870. The autographic diagrams given in figs. 13 aud 14 are
                    taken from these tests.</p></note> and others. The effect of even a few minutes
                    pause is perceptible, an hour or two of constant stress has a very marked
                    influence, and after 24 hours or so there appears to be little further
                    hardening. The American Board found that iron bars, previously stressed to about
                    50,000 lb per square inch, gained in strength, by intervals of rest from stress,
                    to the extent of about 9 per cent. in one day, 16 per cent. in three days, and
                    18 per cent. in six months.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Loc. cit</hi>., p. 111.</p></note></p>
                <p>35. It may be concluded that, when a piece of metal has in any way received a
                    permanent set by stress exceeding its limits of<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n623/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0623-0600"/> elasticity, it is hardened, and (in some cases at
                    least) its physical properties go on slowly changing for days or even months.
                    Instances of the hardening effect of permanent set occur when plates or bars are
                    rolled cold, hammered cold, or bent cold, or when wire is drawn. When a hole is
                    punched in a plate the material contiguous to the hole is severely distorted by
                    shear, and is so much hardened in consequence that when a strip containing the
                    punched hole is broken by tensile stress the hardened portion, being unable to
                    extend so much as the rest, receives an undue proportion of the stress, and the
                    strip breaks with a smaller load than it would have borne had the stress been
                    uniformly distributed. This bad effect of punching is especially noticeable in
                    thick plates of mild steel. It disappears when a narrow ring of material
                    surrounding the hole is removed by means of a rimer, so that the material that
                    is left is homogeneous. Another remarkable instance of the same kind of action
                    is seen when a mild-steel plate which is to be tested by bending has a piece cut
                    from its edge by a shearing machine. The result of the shear is that the metal
                    close to the edge is hardened, and, when the plate is bent, this part, being
                    unable to stretch like the rest, starts a crack or tear which quickly spreads
                    across the plate on account of the fact that in the metal at the end of the
                    crack there is an enormously high local intensity of stress (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> § 72). By the simple expedient of planing off
                    the hardened edge before bending the plate homogeneity is restored, and the
                    plate will then bend without damage.</p>
                <p>36. The hardening effect of strain is removed by the process of annealing, that
                    is, by heating to redness and cooling slowly. In iron, very mild steel, and most
                    other metals the rate of cooling is a matter of indifference; but in steel that
                    contains more than about 0·2 per cent. of carbon another kind of hardening is
                    produced if the metal, after being heated to redness, is cooled suddenly. When
                    the proportion of carbon is considerably greater than this, steel may be
                    rendered excessively hard and brittle (“glass-hard ”) by sudden cooling from a
                    red heat. Further, by being subsequently heated to a moderate temperature, it
                    may be deprived of some of this hardness and rendered elastic through a wide
                    range of strain. This process is called the tempering of steel; its effects
                    depend on the temperature to which the steel is heated after being hardened, and
                    the grade of temper which is acquired is usually specified by the colour (blue,
                    straw, &amp;c.) which appears on a clean surface of the metal during this
                    heating, through the formation of a film of oxide. In the ordinary process of
                    rolling plates or bars of iron or mild steel the metal leaves the rolls at so
                    high a temperature that it is virtually annealed, or pretty nearly so.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In several of Mr Kirkaldy’s
                    papers, a comparison is given of the elastic limit, ultimate strength, and
                    ultimate extension of samples which were annealed before testing, and of samples
                    which were tested in the commercial state; in general the annealed samples are
                    distinctly, though not very materially, softer than the others <hi rend="italic"
                    >(on the Relative Properties of Wrought-Iron Plates from Essex and
                    Yorkshire,</hi> London, 1876; also <hi rend="italic">Experiments on Fagersta
                    Steel,</hi> London, 1873).</p></note> The case is different with plates and bars
                    that are rolled cold: they, like wire supplied in the hard-drawn state (that is,
                    without being annealed after it leaves the draw-plate), exhibit the higher
                    strength and greatly reduced plasticity which result from permanent set.</p>
                <p>37. The extension which occurs when a bar of uniform section is pulled is at
                    first general, and is distributed with some approach to uniformity over the
                    length of the bar. Before the bar breaks, however, a large additional amount of
                    local extension occurs at and near the place of rupture. The material flows in
                    that neighbourhood much more than in other parts of the bar, and the section is
                    much more contracted there than elsewhere. The contraction of area at fracture
                    is frequently stated as one of the results of a test, and is a useful index to
                    the quality of materials. If a flaw is present sufficient to determine the
                    section at which rupture shall occur the contraction of area will in general be
                    distinctly diminished as compared with the contraction in a specimen free from
                    flaws, although little reduction may be noted in the total extension of the
                    piece. Local extension and contraction of area are almost absent in cast-iron
                    and hard steel; on the other hand they are specially prominent in wrought-iron,
                    mild steel, and other metals that combine plasticity with high tensile strength.
                    An example is shown in fig. 16, which is copied from a photograph of a broken
                    test-piece of Whitworth soft fluid-compressed steel.</p>
                <p>38. Experiments with long rods show that the general extension which occurs in
                    parts of the bar not near the break is somewhat irregular;<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Kirkaldy’s <hi rend="italic">Experiments
                    on Fagersta Steel,</hi> London, 1873; also <hi rend="italic">Report of the Steel
                    Committee,</hi> part i.</p></note> it exhibits here and there incipient local
                    stretching, which has stopped without leading to rupture. This is of course due
                    in the first instance to want of homogeneity. It may be supposed that when local
                    stretching begins at any point in the earlier stages of the test it is checked
                    by the hardening effect of the strain, until, finally, under greater load, a
                    stage is reached in which the extension at one place goes on so fast that the
                    hardening effect cannot keep pace with the increase in intensity of stress which
                    results from diminution of area; the local extension is then unstable, and
                    rupture ensues. Even at this stage a pause in the loading, and an interval of
                    relief from stress, may harden the locally stretched part enough to make rupture
                    occur somewhere else when the loading is continued.</p>
                <p>39. Local stretching causes the percentage of elongation which a test-piece
                    exhibits before rupture (an important quantity in engineers’ specifications) to
                    vary greatly with the length and section of the piece tested. It is very usual
                    to specify the length which is to exhibit an assigned percentage of elongation.
                    This, however, is not enough; the percentage obviously depends on the relation
                    of the transverse dimensions to the length. A fine wire of iron or steel, say 8
                    inches long, will stretch little more in proportion to its length than a very
                    long wire of the same quality. An 8-inch bar, say 1 inch in diameter, will show
                    something like twice as much the percentage of elongation as a very long rod.
                    The experiments of M. Barba<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Mém. de la Soc. des Ing. Civ..</hi> 1880; see also a paper
                    by Mr W. Hackney, “Οn the Adoption of Standard Forms of Test-Pieces,” <hi
                    rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> 1884.</p></note> show that, in
                    material of uniform quality, the percentage of extension is constant for
                    test-pieces of similar form, that is to say, for pieces of various size in which
                    the transverse dimensions are varied in the same proportion as the length. It is
                    to be regretted that in ordinary testing it is not practicable to reduce the
                    pieces to a standard form, with one proportion of transverse dimensions to
                    length, since an arbitrary choice of length and cross-section gives results
                    which are incapable of direct comparison with one another.</p>
                <p>40. The form chosen for test-pieces in tension tests affects not only the
                    extension but also the ultimate strength. In the first place, if there is a
                    sudden or rapid change in the area of cross section at any part of the length
                    under tension (as at AB, fig. 17), the stress will not be uniformly distributed
                    there.</p>
                <p>The intensity will be greatest at the edges A and B, and the piece will, in
                    consequence, pass its elastic limit at a less value of the total load than would
                    be the case if the change from the larger to the smaller section were gradual.
                    In a non-ductile material, rup ture will for the same reason take place at AB,
                    with a less total load than would otherwise be borne. On the other hand, with a
                    sufficiently ductile material, although the section AB is the first to be
                    permanently deformed, rupture will preferably take place at some section not
                    near AB, because at and near AB the con traction of sectional area which
                    precedes rupture is partly prevented by the presence of the projecting portions
                    C and D. Hence, too, with a ductile material samples such as those of fig. 18,
                    in which the part of smallest section between the shoulders or enlarged ends of
                    the piece is short, will break with a greater load than could be borne by long
                    uni form rods of the same section. In good wrought-iron and mild steel the flow
                    of metal pre ceding rupture and causing local con traction of section extends
                    over a length six or eight times the width of the piece; and, if the length
                    throughout which the section is uniform be materially less than this, the
                    process of flow will be rendered more difficult and the breaking load of the
                    sample will be raised.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The greater strength of nicked or grooved specimens seems to have been first
                    remarked by Mr Kirkaldy <hi rend="italic">(Experiments on Wrought Iron and
                    Steel,</hi> p. 74, also <hi rend="italic">Experiments on Fagersta Steel,</hi> p.
                    27). See also a paper by Mr E. Richards, on tests of mild steel, <hi
                    rend="italic">Jour. Iron and Steel Inst.,</hi> 1882.</p></note></p>
                <p>These considerations have of course a wider application than to the mere
                    interpretation of special tests. An important practical case is that of riveted
                    joints, in which the metal left between the rivet-holes is subjected to tensile
                    stress. It is found to bear, per square inch, a greater pull than would be borne
                    by a strip of the same plate, if the strip were tested in the usual way with
                    uniform section throughout a length great enough to allow complete freedom of
                    local flow.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Kennedy’s “Reportson Rivetted Joints," <hi rend="italic">Proc. Inst. Mech.
                    Eng.,</hi> 1881-5. In the case of mild steel plates a drilled strip may have as
                    much as 12 per cent. more tensile strength per square inch than an undrilled
                    strip. with punched holes, on the other hand, the remaining metal is much
                    weakened, for the reason referred to in § 35.</p></note></p>
                <p>41. The tensile strength of long rods is affected by the length in quite a
                    different way. With a perfectly homogeneous material, no difference should be
                    found in the strength of rods of equal<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n624/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0624-0601"/> sectional area and of different lengths, provided
                    the length of both were great enough to prevent tho action described in § 40
                    from affecting the result. But, since no material is perfectly homogeneous, the
                    longer rod will in general be the weaker, offering as it does more chances of a
                    weak place; and the probable defect of strength in the long rod will depend on
                    the degree of variability of the material. When this has been established by
                    numerous tests of short samples, the strength which a rod of any assigned length
                    may be expected to possess can be calculated by an application of the theory of
                    probabilities. A theory of the strength of long bars has been worked out on this
                    basis by Prof. Chaplin,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Van Nostrand's Engineering Magazine,</hi> Dec. 1880; <hi
                    rend="italic">Proc. Engineers' Club of Philadelphia,</hi> March,
                    1882.</p></note> and has been experimentally confirmed by tests of long and
                    short samples of wire. The theory does not apply when the length is so small
                    that the action of § 40 enters into the case, and the experimental data on which
                    it is based must be taken from tests of samples long enough to exclude that
                    action.</p>
                <p>42. In tension tests, rupture may occur, as in fig. 19, by direct separation over
                    a surface which is nearly plane and normal to the line of stress. This is usual
                    in hard steel aud other comparatively non-ductile materials. Or it may occur by
                    shearing along an oblique plane, as in fig. 20, which shows the fracture of a
                    piece of steel softer than the specimen of fig. 19. In very ductile samples
                    these two modes of rupture are frequently found in combination, as in fig. 21,
                    where a central core is broken by direct tension while round it is a ring over
                    which separation has taken place by shearing. In this instance the ring is in
                    two parts, one above and one below the surface of rupture of the central flat
                    core. In other instances, such as that of the sample shown in fig. 16, the shorn
                    ring forms a continuous cone or crater round a flat core.</p>
                <p>43. In compression tests of a plastic material, such as mild steel, a process of
                    flow may go on without limit; the piece (which must of course be short, to avoid
                    buckling) shortens and bulges out in the form of a cask. This is illustrated by
                    fig. 22 (from one of Fairbairn’s experiments), which shows the compression of a
                    round block of steel (the original height and diameter of which are shown by the
                    dotted lines) by a load equal to 100 tons per square inch of original sectional
                    area. The surface over which the stress is distributed becomes enlarged, and the
                    total load must be increased in a corresponding degree to maintain the process
                    of flow.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For examples,
                    see Fairbairn’s experiments on steel, <hi rend="italic">Pep. Brit. Ass.,</hi>
                    1867.</p></note> The bulging often produces longitudinal cracks, as in the
                    figure, especially when the material is fibrous as well as plastic (as in the
                    case of wrought-iron). A brittle material, such as cast-iron brick, or stone,
                    yields by shearing on inclined planes as in figs. 23 and 24, which are taken
                    from Hodgkinson’s experiments on cast-iron.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Report of the Royal Commissioners on the
                    Application of Iron to Railway Structures,</hi> 1849; see also <hi rend="italic"
                    >Brit. Ass. Rep.,</hi> 1837.</p></note> The simplest fracture of this kind is
                    exemplified by fig. 23, where a single surface (approximately a plane) of shear
                    divides the compressed block into two wedges. With cast-iron the slope of the
                    plane is such that this simple mode of fracture can take place only if the
                    height of the block is not less than about <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> the width of the base. When the height is less the
                    action is more complex. Shearing must then take place over more than one plane,
                    as in fig. 24, so that cones or wedges are formed by which the surrounding
                    portions of the block are split off. The stress required to crush the block is
                    consequently greater than if the height were sufficient for shearing in a single
                    plane.</p>
                <p>44. The inclination of the surfaces of shear, when fracture takes place by
                    shearing under a simple stress of pull or push, is a matter of much interest,
                    throwing some light on the question of how the resistance whieh a material
                    exerts to stress of one kind is affected by the presence of stress of another
                    kind,—a question scarcely touched by direct experiment. At the shorn surface
                    there is, in the case of tension tests, a normal pull as well as a shearing
                    stress, and in the case of compression tests a normal push as well as shearing
                    stress. If this normal component were absent the material (assuming it to be
                    isotropic) would shear in the surface of greatest shearing stress, which, as we
                    have seen in § 5, is a surface inclined at 45° to the axis. In fact, however, it
                    does not shear on this surface. Hodgkinson’s experiments on the compression of
                    castiron give surfaces of shear whose normal is inclined at about 55° to the
                    axis of stress,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Op. cit.</hi></p></note> and Kirkaldy’s, on the tension of steel,
                    show that when rupture takes place by shear the normal to the surface is
                    inclined at about 25° to the axis.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Op. cit.</hi></p></note> These results
                    show that normal pull diminishes resistance to shearing and normal push
                    increases resistance to shearing. In the case of cast-iron under compression,
                    the material prefers to shear on a section where the intensity of shearing
                    stress is only 0·94 of its value on the surface of maximum shearing stress
                    (inclined at 45°), but where the normal push is reduced to 0·66 of its value on
                    the surface of maximum shearing stress.</p>
                <p>45. <hi rend="italic">Fatigue of Metals.—</hi> A matter of great practical as
                    well as scientific interest is the weakening which materials undergo by repeated
                    changes in their state of stress. It appears that in some if not in all
                    materials a limited amount of stress-variation may be repeated time after time
                    without appreciable deterioration in the strength of the piece; in the
                    balance-spring of a watch, for instance, tension and compression succeed each
                    other some 150 millions of times in a year, and the spring works for years
                    without apparent injury. In such cases the stresses lie well within the elastic
                    limits. On the other hand, the toughest bar breaks after a small number of
                    bendings to and fro, when these pass the elastic limits, although the stress may
                    have a value greatly short of the normal ultimate strength. A laborious research
                    by Wohler,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Die Festigkeits-Versuche mit Eisen und Stahl,</hi> Berlin, 1870,
                    or <hi rend="italic">Zeitschr. für Bauwesen,</hi> 1860-70; see also <hi
                    rend="italic">Engineering,</hi> vol. xi., 1871. For early experiments by
                    Fairbairn on the same subject, see <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi>
                    1864.</p></note> extending over twelve years, has given much important
                    information regarding the effects on iron and steel of very numerous repeated
                    alternations of stress from positive to negative, or between a higher and a
                    lower value without change of sign. By means of ingeniously contrived machines
                    he submitted test-pieces to direct pull, alternated with complete or partial
                    relaxation from pull, to repeated bending in one direction and also in opposite
                    directions, and to repeated twisting towards one side and towards opposite
                    sides. The results show that a stress greatly less than the ultimate strength
                    (as tested in the usual way by a single application of load continued to
                    rupture) is sufficient to break a piece if it be often enough removed and
                    restored, or even alternated with a less stress of the same kind. In that case,
                    however, the variation of stress being less, the number of repetitions required
                    to produce rupture is greater. In general, the number of repetitions required to
                    produce rupture is increased by reducing the range through which the stress is
                    varied, or by lowering the upper limit of that range. If the greatest stress be
                    chosen small enough, it may be reduced, removed, or even reversed many million
                    times without destroying the piece. Wohler’s results are best shown by quoting a
                    few figures selected from his experiments. The stresses are stated in centners
                    per square zoll;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>According to Bauschinger (<hi rend="italic">loc</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                    >cit.,</hi> p. 44), the centner per square zoll in which Wöhler gives his
                    results is equivalent to 6·837 kilos per square cm., or 0·0434 ton per square
                    inch.</p></note> in the case of bars subjected to bending they refer to the top
                    and bottom sides, which are the most stressed parts of the bar.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1">I. Iron bar in direct tension :—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1">Stress. Number of Applications</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stress.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Applications</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Max. Min</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">causing Rupture.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Max. Min.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">causing Rupture.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">480 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">800</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">320 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">10,141,645</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">440 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">106,901</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">400 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">340,853</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">440 200</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2,373,424</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">360 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">480,852</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">440 240</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Not broken with 4 millions.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1">II. Iron bar bent by transverse load
                            :—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stress.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Bendings</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stress.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Bendings</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Max. Min.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">causing Rupture.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Max. Min.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">causing Rupture.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">530 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">169.750</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">400 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,320,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">500 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">420,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">350 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4,035,400</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">450 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">481.950</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">300 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Not broken with 48 millions.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1">III. Steel bar bent by transverse load:
                            —</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stress.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Bendings</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stress.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Bendings</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Max. Min.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">causing Rupture.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Max. Min</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">causing Rupture.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">900 0</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">72,459</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">900 400</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">225,300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">900 200</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">81,200</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">900 500</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">764,900—mean of two trials.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">900 300</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">156,200</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">900 600</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Not broken with 33 J mills.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0625-0602"/>
                <p>IV. Iron bar bent by supporting at one end, the other end being loaded;
                    alternations of stress from pull to push caused by rotating the bar :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Stress.</p><p>From + to —</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Rotations causing
                            Rupture.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Stress.</p><p>From + to —</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Number of Rotations causing
                            Rupture.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">320</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">56,430</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">220</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">3,632,588</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">300</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">99,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">200</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4,917,992</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">280</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">183,145</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">180</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">19,186,791</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">260</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">479,490</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">160</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Not broken with 132¼</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">210</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">909,810</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">millions.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Stress.</p>
                <p>From + to —</p>
                <p>Stress.</p>
                <p>From + to —</p>
                <p>46. From these and other experiments Wohler concluded that the wrought-iron to
                    which the tests refer could probably bear an indefinite number of stress changes
                    between the limits stated (in round numbers) in the following table (the
                    ultimate tensile strength was about 19½ tons per square inch) :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stress in Tons per Sq. Inch.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">From pull to push</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">From pull to no stress</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">13 to 0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">From pull to less pull</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">19 to 10½</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Hence it appears that the actual strength of this material varies in a ratio
                    which may be roughly given as 3: 2: 1 in the three cases of (<hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi>) steady pull, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) pull alternating with no
                    stress, very many times repeated, and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) pull
                    alternating with push, very many times repeated. Factors of safety applicable to
                    the three cases might therefore rationally stand to one another in the ratio of
                    1: 2: 3. For steel Wohler obtained results of a generally similar kind. His
                    experiments were repeated by Spangenberg, who extended the inquiry to brass,
                    gun-metal, and phosphor-bronze.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Ueber das Verhalten der Metalle bei
                    weiderholten Anstrengungen,</hi> Berlin, 1875.</p></note> On the basis of
                    Wohler’s results formulas have been devised by Launhardt, Weyrauch, and others
                    to express the probable actual strength of metals under assigned variations of
                    stress; these are, of course, of a merely empirical character, and the data are
                    not yet extensive enough to give them much value.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Weyrauch, “Οn the Calculation of
                    Dimensions as depending on the Ultimate Working Strength of Materials," <hi
                    rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. C.E,,</hi> vol. lxiii. p. 275; also a
                    correspondence in <hi rend="italic">Engineering,</hi> vol. xxix., and Unwin's
                    <hi rend="italic">Machine Design,</hi> chap. ii.</p></note></p>
                <p>47. Wohler’s experiments, dealing, as all experiments must, with a finite number
                    of stress-changes, leave it an open question whether there are any limits within
                    which a state of stress might be indefinitely often varied without finally
                    destroying the material. It is natural to suppose that a material possessing
                    perfect elasticity would suffer no deterioration from stress-changes lying
                    within limits up to which the elasticity is perfect. But these limits, if they
                    exist at all, are probably very narrow. Indeed, in the case of iron, there is
                    indirect evidence that all alteration of stress whatsoever affects the molecular
                    structure in a way not consistent with the notion of perfect elasticity. When
                    the state of stress in iron is varied, however slowly aud however little, the
                    magnetic and thermo-electric qualities of the metal are found to change in an
                    essentially irreversible manner.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Ewing, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1885,
                    1886.</p></note> Every variation leaves its mark on the quality of the piece;
                    the actual quality at any time is a function of all the states of stress in
                    which the piece has previously been placed. It can scarcely be doubted that
                    sufficiently refined methods of experiment would detect a similar want of
                    reversibility in the mechanical effects of stress, even when alterations of
                    stress occur slowly enough to escape the effects of viscosity which have been
                    examined by Sir William Thomson and discussed under <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Elasticity</hi> (vol. vii. pp. 802 <hi rend="italic">sq. ).</hi> In any case,
                    the viscosity investigated by Thomson causes such stress-changes as occur
                    rapidly to do work on the material, and the destructive effect of repeated
                    changes may be due in great part to this cause. His experiments show that rapid
                    stress-changes often repeated do produce a cumulative effect in reducing the
                    modulus of elasticity; and it is very probable that this fatigue of elasticity
                    is associated with fatigue of strength.</p>
                <p>There are as yet no experiments showing how far fatigue of strength is affected
                    by the frequency, as distinguished from the mere number, of the stress-changes,
                    nor whether a period of rest, after fatigue has been induced, restores strength.
                    That it does so may be conjectured from Thomson’s discovery that rest restores
                    elasticity after elastic fatigue. The conjecture is strengthened by
                    Bauschinger’s discovery that, after a permanent set has been produced and a
                    period of rest follows, the apparent limit of elasticity (in the strict sense of
                    that term) rises slowly with the lapse of time. Both questions are of obvious
                    practical interest.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For
                    interesting notices of the fatigue of metals in railway axles, bridge ties,
                    &amp;c., and results of experiments showing reduced plasticity in fatigued
                    metal, see Mr B. Baker’s address to the Mechanical Section of the British
                    Association, 1885. In most cases where the fatigue of metals occurs in
                    engineering practice the phenomenon is complicated by the occurrence of blows or
                    shocks whose energy is absorbed in producing strains often exceeding the elastic
                    limits, sometimes of a very local character in consequence of the inertia of the
                    strained pieces. Such shocks may cause an accumulation of set which finally
                    leads to rupture in a way that is not to be confused with ordinary fatigue of
                    strength. It appears that the effects of fatigue may be removed by
                    annealing.</p></note></p>
                <p>48. When a strain is produced within the limits to which Hooke’s law applies, the
                    work done in producing it is half the product of the stress into the strain. A
                    load applied to a piece suddenly, but without impact, does an amount of work in
                    straining the piece which is measured by the weight of the load into the
                    distance it sinks in consequence of the strain. Hence, provided this strain
                    falls within the elastic limit, the strain and the stress are twice as great as
                    the same load would produce when in equilibrium. Instances of load applied with
                    complete suddenness, and yet without shock, are rare; but it is a common case
                    for loads to be applied so rapidly that the stress reaches a value intermediate
                    between that due to a static load and the double stress due to the same load
                    applied at once. Thus the Railway Commissioners found that certain bridges were
                    deflected by a train passing at a speed of 50 miles per hour <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> /7 more than by the same load at rest.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Report of
                    Commissioners on the Application of Iron to Railway Structures,</hi> 1849. A
                    mathematical investigation of this effect of rolling load is given in an
                    appendix to the Report.</p></note> The fact that a “live” load produces greater
                    stress than a dead load is of course to be distinguished from the question
                    Wohler’s experiments deal with—the greater destructiveness of the intermitted or
                    varied stress which a live load causes. In many cases engineers allow in one
                    operation for these quite independent influences of a live load by choosing a
                    higher factor of safety for the live than for the dead part of the whole load on
                    a structure, or (what is the same thing) by multiplying the live load by a
                    coefficient (often 1½), adding the product to the dead load, and treating the
                    sum as if all were dead load.</p>
                <p>49. A useful application of diagrams showing the relation of strain to stress is
                    to determine the amount of work done in straining a piece in any assigned way.
                    The term “resilience” is conveniently used to specify the amount of work done
                    when the strain just reaches the corresponding elastic limit. Thus a rod in
                    simple tension or simple compression has a resilience per unit of volume = <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕2E, where <hi rend="italic"
                    >f</hi> is the greatest elastic pull or push. A blow whose energy exceeds the
                    resilience (reckoned for the kind of stress to which the blow gives rise) must
                    in the most favourable case produce a permanent set; in less favourable cases
                    local permanent set will be produced although the energy of the blow is less
                    than the resilience, in consequence of the strain being unequally distributed.
                    In a plastic material a strain exceeding the limit of elasticity absorbs a
                    relatively large amount of energy, and generally increases the resilience for
                    subsequent strains. Fracture under successive blows, as in the testing of rails
                    by placing them as beams on two supports, and allowing a weight to fall in the
                    middle from a given height, results from the accumulated set which is brought
                    about by the energy of each blow exceeding the resilience</p>
                <p>50. In an important paper<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Camb. and Dub. Math. Journ.,</hi> Nov., 1848.</p></note>
                    which is reprinted in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> and
                    should be carefully studied in this connexion, Prof. James Thomson has pointed
                    out that the effect of any externally applied load depends, to a very material
                    extent, on whether there is or is not initial internal stress, or, in other
                    words, whether the loaded piece is initially in what Prof. Hearson has called a
                    state of ease. Internal stress, existing without the application of force from
                    without the piece, must satisfy the condition that its resultant vanishes over
                    any complete cross-section. It may exist in consequence of set caused by
                    previously applied forces (a case of which instances are given below), or in
                    consequence of previous temperature changes, as in cast-iron, which is thrown
                    into a state of internal stress by unequally rapid cooling of tho mass. Thus in
                    (say) a spherical casting an outside shell solidifies first, and has become
                    partially contracted by cooling by the time the inside has become solid. The
                    inside then contracts, and its contraction is resisted by the shell, which is
                    thereby compressed in a tangential direction, while the metal in the interior is
                    pulled in the direction of the radius. Allusion has already been made to the
                    fact, pointed out by J. Thomson, that the defect of elasticity under small loads
                    which Hodgkinson discovered in cast-iron is probably due to initial stress. In
                    plastic metal a nearly complete state of ease is brought about by annealing;
                    even annealed pieces, however, sometimes show, in the first loading, srnall
                    defects of elasticity, which are probably due to initial stress, as they
                    disappear when the load is reapplied.</p>
                <p>51. Little is exactly known with regard to the effect of temperature on the
                    strength of materials. Some metals, notably iron or steel containing much
                    phosphorus, show a marked increase in brittleness at low temperatures, or “cold
                    shortness.” Experiments on the tensile strength of wrought-iron and steel show
                    in general little variation within the usual atmospheric range of heat and cold.
                    The tensile strength appears to be slightly reduced at very low temperatures,
                    and to reach a maximum when the metal is warmed to a temperature between 100° C.
                    and 200° C. When the temperature exceeds 300° C. the tensile strength begins to
                    fall off rapidly, and at 1000° C. it is less than one-tenth of the normal
                    value.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi
                    rend="italic">Report of a Committee of the Franklin Institute,</hi> 1837;
                    Fairbairn, <hi rend="italic">Brit. Ass. Rep.,</hi> 1856; Styffe on <hi
                    rend="italic">Iron and Steel,</hi> trans. by C. P. Sandberg. Notices of these
                    and other experiments will be found in Thurston's <hi rend="italic">Materials of
                    Engineering,</hi> ii. chap. x., and in papers by J. J. Webster, <hi
                    rend="italic">Min</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> vol. lx,, and
                    A. Martens, <hi rend="italic">Zeitschr. des Ver. Deutsch. Ing.,</hi>
                    1883.</p></note> Reference may be made, in this connexion, to the effect which a
                    “blue heat,” or temperature short of red heat, is believed to have on the
                    plasticity and strength of iron, and more especially of mild steel. It appears
                    that steel plates and bars bent or otherwise<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0626-0603"/> worked at a blue heat not only run a much more
                    serious risk of fracture in the process than when worked either cold or red-hot,
                    but become deteriorated so that brittleness may afterwards show itself when the
                    metal is cold.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Stromeyer, “The Injurious Effect of a Blue Heat on Steel and Iron,” <hi
                    rend="italic">Jiin. Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> vol. lxxxiv., 1886.</p></note></p>
                <p>52. The following table gives a few representative data regarding the strength of
                    the more important materials used in engineering (the figures are gathered from
                    the writings of Barlow, Hodgkinson, Kirkaldy, Thurston, Rankine, Unwin, Clark,
                    and others) :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ultimate Strength.</p><p>Tons per
                            Square Inch.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1">Elasticity. Tons. per sq. in.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Young's</p><p>Modulus</p><p>E.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Mod. of Rigidity C.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><hi rend="italic">ft</hi></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic
                            subscript"> c</hi></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi
                            rend="subscript"> 8</hi></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Cast-iron</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5½ to 10½</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">25 to 65 I</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">9 to 13</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, average</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">42</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">11</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, American (ordnance)...</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">14</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">36 to 58</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">to</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">to</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, ,, strengthened</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">15 to 20</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">60 to 75</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">6000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">by successive fusions.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Wrought-iron—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Finest Lowmoor and York-</cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1">27 to 29 along the fibre</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">shire plates (</cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1">24 across the fibre</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Staffordshire</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">26 along</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">18 to</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1">24 across ,,</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">12,000 to</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Bridge iron</cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>22 along ,,</p><p>19
                            across</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">22, or about</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Bars, finest</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">27 to 29</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> / <hi
                            rend="subscript"> 5</hi> of <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic
                            subscript"> t</hi></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">13,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Ordinary good</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">25</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">20</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Soft Swedish</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">19 to 24</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Wrought-iron wire</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">25 to 50</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, ,, average about</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">35</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">...</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Steel—</p><p>Mild steel plates
                            (Siemens or</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">26 to 32</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">...</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Bessemer)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">about 30</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><hi rend="italic">about</hi><hi
                            rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">/</hi><hi
                            rend="italic subscript"> 4</hi></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Axle and rail steel (do.)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">30 to 45</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">of <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi
                            rend="italic subscript"> t</hi></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Crucible tool steel</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">40 to 65</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">12,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Steel castings</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">about 28</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Chrome steel</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">80</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">to</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">to</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Tungsten steel</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">72</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">13,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5200</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Whitworth's fluid-compressed</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">steel (mild)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">40</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, ,, (hard)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">48 to 68</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Steel wire, ordinary,
                            about</p><p>Tempered steel rope wire</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">70</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">(highest)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">124</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>13,000</p><p>13,000</p><p>7000</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Pianoforte steel wire</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">150</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Copper, cast</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">10 to 14</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">35</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">10 to 14</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, rolled</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">15 to 16</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, wire, hard-drawn</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">28</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">8000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2800</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Brass</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">8 to 13</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5500</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1500</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, wire</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">22</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">6400</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2200</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Muntz metal</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">22</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Gun metal</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">11 to 23</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4500 to</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1700</p><p>2400</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Phosphor bronze</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">15 to 26</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">6500 6000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, wire</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">33 to 70</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Manganese bronze</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">28 to 32</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Zinc, cast</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2 to 3</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, rolled</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">7 to 10</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5500</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Tin</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Lead</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">0∙9</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">3</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Timber—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Oak</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">3 to 7</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">800</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">White pine</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1½ to 3½ 4</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2½</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">600</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Pitch pine</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">950</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Riga fir</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2½ to 51/ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> 4
                            to 7</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Ash</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2 to 4</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">750</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Beech</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Teak</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4 to 7</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">950</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Spanish mahogany</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4 to 7</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">3½</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">650</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stone—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Granite</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2½ to 5 1½ to 2 ½ 2 to 2½ 1½ to 3 ¼ to
                            ¾</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Sandstone</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Limestone</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Slate</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">7000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Brick</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Ultimate Strength.</p>
                <p>Tons per Square Inch.</p>
                <p>Young's</p>
                <p>Modulus</p>
                <p>E.</p>
                <p>22 along ,,</p>
                <p>19 across</p>
                <p>Steel—</p>
                <p>Mild steel plates (Siemens or</p>
                <p>Steel wire, ordinary, about</p>
                <p>Tempered steel rope wire</p>
                <p>13,000</p>
                <p>13,000</p>
                <p>7000</p>
                <p>1700</p>
                <p>2400</p>
                <p>53. Space admits of no more than a short and elementary account of some of the
                    more simple straining actions that occur in machines and engineering
                    structures.</p>
                <p>The stress which acts on any plane surface AB (fig. 25), such as an imaginary
                    cross-section of a strained piece, may be represented by a figure formed by
                    setting up ordinates A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, B5,</p>
                <p>&amp;c., from points on the surface, the length of these being made proportional
                    to the intensity of stress at each point.</p>
                <p>This gives an ideal solid, which may be called the stress figure, whose height
                    shows the distribution of stress over the surface which forms its base. A line
                    drawn from <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> the centre of gravity of the stress figure,
                    parallel to the ordinates A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, &amp;c., determines the
                    point C, which is called the centre of stress, and is the point through which
                    the resultant of the distributed stress acts. In the case of a uniformly
                    distributed stress, <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> is a plane surface parallel to AB,
                    and C is the centre of gravity of the surface AB. When a bar is subjected to
                    simple pull applied axially—that is to say, so that the resultant stress passes
                    through the centre of gravity of every cross-section,—the stress may be taken as
                    (sensibly) uniformly distributed over any section not near a place where the
                    form of the cross-section changes, provided the bar is initially in a state of
                    ease and the stress is within the limits of elasticity.</p>
                <p>54. Uniformly varying stress is illustrated by fig. 26. It occurs (in each case
                    for stresses within the elastic limit) in a bent beam, in a tie subjected to
                    non-axial pull, and in a long strut or column where buckling makes the stress
                    become non-axial. In uniformly varying stress the intensity <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi> at any point P is proportional to the distance of P from a line MN,
                    called &lt; the neutral axis, whieh lies in the plane of the stressed surface
                    and at right angles to the direction AB, which is assumed to be that in which
                    the intensity of stress varies most rapidly. There is no varia tion of stress
                    along lines parallel to MN. If MN passes through</p>
                <p>C, the centre of gravity of the sur face, as in fig. 27, it may easily be shown
                    that the total pull stress on one side of the neutral axis is equal to the total
                    push stress on the other side, whatever be the form of the surface AB. The
                    resultant of the whole stress on AB is in that case a couple, whose moment may
                    be found as follows. Let <hi rend="italic">d</hi> S be an indefinitely small
                    part of the surface at a distance <hi rend="italic">x</hi> from the neutral axis
                    through C, and let <hi rend="italic">p</hi> be the intensity of stress on <hi
                    rend="italic">d</hi> S. The moment of the stress on <hi rend="italic">d</hi> S
                    is <hi rend="italic">xpd</hi> S But <hi rend="italic">p=p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">x∕x</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">=p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >x/x</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (see fig. 27). The whole moment of the
                    stress on AB is <hi rend="italic">∫xpd</hi> S = (<hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi>
                    ∫ <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi>
                    S= <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> I∕ <hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> or <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> I∕ <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>, where I is the moment of inertia of the surface AB about the neutral
                    axis through C.</p>
                <p>55. A stress such as that shown in fig. 26 or fig. 28 may be regarded as a
                    uniformly distributed stress of intensity <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi> (which is the intensity at the centre of gravity of the
                    surface C) and a stress of the kind shown in fig. 27. The resultant is <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> S, where S is the whole area of
                    the surface, and it acts at a distance CD from C such that the moment <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> S . CD =</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>- <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi>)I/ <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = (<hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>
                    + <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi>)I∕ <hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. Hence <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> = <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi>
                    (1+ <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S . CD∕I), and <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi> (1- <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> S. CD∕I).</p>
                <p>56. Simple bending occurs when a beam is in equilibrium under equal and opposite
                    couples in the plane of the beam. Thus if a beam (fig. 29), supported at its
                    ends, be loaded at two points so that W <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">l</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = W <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, the por tion of the
                    beam lying between W <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and W <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> is subjected to a simple bending stress. On any section AB the only
                    stress consists of pul 1 and push, and has for its resultant a couple whose
                    moment M=W <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> Z <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =W <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Z <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. This is called the <hi
                    rend="italic">bending moment</hi> at the section. If the stress be within the
                    elastic limits it will be distributed as in fig.</p>
                <p>30, with the neutral axis at the centre of gravity of the section. The greatest
                    intensities of push and of pull, at the top and bottom edge respectively, are
                    (by § 54) <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = M <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕I and <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> M <hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> /I <hi rend="italic">,</hi> and the
                    intensity at any point at a distance <hi rend="italic">y</hi> above or below C
                    is p=M <hi rend="italic">y</hi> ∕I.</p>
                <p>57. Let the bending moment now be increased; non-elastic strain will begin as
                    soon as either <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> exceeds the corresponding limit
                    of elasticity, and the distribution of stress will be changed in consequence of
                    the fact that the outer layers of the beam are taking set while the inner layers
                    are still following Hooke’s law. As a simple instance we may consider the case
                    of a material strictly elastic up to a certain stress, and then so plastic that
                    a relatively very large amount of strain is produced without further change of
                    stress, a case not very far from being realized by soft wrought-iron and mild
                    steel. The diagram of stress will now take the form sketched in fig. 31. If the
                    elastic limit is (say) less for compression than for tension, the diagram will
                    be as in fig. 32, with the neutral axis shifted towards the tension side. When
                    the beam is relieved from external load it will be left in a state of internal
                    stress, represented, for the case of fig. 31, by the dotted lines in that
                    figure.</p>
                <p>58. In consequence of the action which has been illustrated (in a somewhat crude
                    fashion) by figs. 31 and 32, the moment required<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n627/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0627-0604"/> to break the beam (M <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi>) cannot be calculated from the ultimate tensile or compressive strength
                    of the material by using the formula M <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> I∕ <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    c</hi> I∕ <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. When experiments
                    are made on the ultimate strength of bars to resist bending, it is not unusual
                    to apply a formula of this form to calculate an imaginary stress <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> which receives the name of the modulus of trans verse
                    rupture. Let the section be such that y <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =</p>
                <p>y <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. Then the modulus of transverse rupture is defined
                    as <hi rend="italic">f</hi> = M <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕I.</p>
                <p>This mode of stating the results of experiment on transverse strength is
                    unsatisfactory, inasmuch as the modulus of rup ture thus determined will vary
                    with different forms of section. Thus a plastic material for which <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> t</hi> are equal, if tested in the form of an I beam in which
                    the flanges form practically the whole area of section, will have a modulus of
                    rapture sensibly equal to <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> t</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> On the other hand, if the material be tested in the form of a
                    rectangular bar, the modulus of rupture may approach a value one and a half
                    times as great. For in the latter case the distribution of stress may approach
                    an ultimate condition in which half the section is in uniform tension <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                    and the other half in uniform compression of the same intensity. The moment of
                    stress is then ¼ <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">bh</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">, b</hi> being the breadth and <hi rend="italic">h</hi>
                    the depth of the section; but by definition of the modulus of rupture <hi
                    rend="italic">f,</hi> M= <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    6</hi><hi rend="italic">fbh</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. In tables of the
                    modulus of transverse rupture the values are generally to be understood as
                    referring to bars of rectangular section. Values of this modulus for some of the
                    principal materials of engineering are given in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Bridges,</hi> vol. iv. p. 292.</p>
                <p>59. The strain produced by bending stress in a bar or beam is, as regards any
                    imaginary filament taken along the length of the piece, sensibly the same as if
                    that filament were directly pulled or compressed by itself. The resulting
                    deformation of the piece consists, in the first place and chiefly, of curvature
                    in the direction of the length, due to the longitudinal extension and
                    compression of the filaments, and, in the second place, of transverse flexure,
                    due to the lateral compression and extension which go along with their
                    longitudinal extension and compression (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Elasticity,</hi> § 57). Let <hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi>, fig. 33, be a short portion of the length of a beam strained by a
                    bending moment M (within the limits of elasticity). The beam, which we assume to
                    be originally straight, bends in the direction of its length to a curve of
                    radius R, such that R∕Z = y <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic"
                    >δl</hi>, <hi rend="italic">δl</hi> being the change of <hi rend="italic">l</hi>
                    by extension or compression, at a distance <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> from the neutral axis. But <hi rend="italic">δl</hi> =
                    <hi rend="italic">lp</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕E by § 10, and <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =M <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕I. Hence R = EI∕M. The transverse flexure is not, in
                    general, of practical importance. The centre of curvature for it is on the
                    opposite side from the centre for longitudinal flexure, and the radius is Rσ,
                    where <hi rend="italic">σ</hi> is the ratio of longitudinal extension to lateral
                    contraction under simple pull.</p>
                <p>60. Bending combined with shearing is the mode of stress to which beams are
                    ordinarily subject, the loads, or externally applied forces, being applied at
                    right angles to the direction of the length. Let AB, fig. 34, be any
                    cross-section of a beam in equilibrium. The portion V of the beam, whieh lies on
                    one side of AB, is in equi librium under the joint action of the external forces
                    F <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, F <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, F <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, &amp;c., and the forces which the other por tion U
                    exerts on V in consequence of the state of stress at AB. The forces F <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, F <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, F <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 3</hi>, &amp;c. may be referred to AB by introducing couples whose moments are
                    F <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi>, F <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, F <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, &amp;c. Hence the stress at AB must
                    equilibrate, first, a couple whose moment is ΣF <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, and,
                    second, a force whose value is 2F, which tends to shear V from U. In these
                    summations regard must of course be had to the sign of each force; in the
                    diagram the sign of F <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> is opposite to the sign of F
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and F <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, Thus the stress
                    at AB may be regarded as that due to a bending moment M equal to the sum of the
                    moments about the section of the externally applied forces on one side of the
                    section (ΣF <hi rend="italic">x</hi>), and a shearing force equal to the sum of
                    the forces about one side of the section (2F). It is a matter of convenience
                    only whether the forces on V or on U be taken in reckoning the bending moment
                    and the shearing force. The bending moment causes a uniformly varying normal
                    stress on AB of the kind already discussed in § 56; the shearing force causes a
                    shearing stress in the plane of the section, the distribution of which will be
                    investigated later. This shearing stress in the plane of the section is (by § 6)
                    accompanied by an equal intensity of shearing stress in horizontal planes
                    parallel to the length of the beam.</p>
                <p>61. The stress due to the bending moment, consisting of longitudinal push in
                    filaments above the neutral axis and longitudinal pull in filaments below the
                    neutral axis, is the thing chiefly to be considered in practical problems
                    relating to the strength of beams. The general formula <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = M <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕I becomes, for a beam of rectangular section of
                    breadth <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and depth <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 6M∕ <hi rend="italic"
                    >bh</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 6M∕SA, S being the area of section. For
                    a beam of circular section it becomes <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 32M∕π <hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi> = 8M <hi rend="italic">∕Sh.</hi> The material of a beam is disposed to
                    the greatest advantage as regards resistance to bending when the form is that of
                    a pair of flanges or booms at top and bottom, held apart by a thin but stiff web
                    or by cross-bracing, as in I beams and braced trusses. In such cases sensibly
                    the whole bending moment is taken by the flanges; the intensity of stress over
                    the section of each flange is very nearly uniform, and the areas of section of
                    the tension and compression flanges (S <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and S <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> respectively) should be proportioned to the value of
                    the ultimate strengths <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    t</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> c</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> so that S <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> =S <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> c</hi>. Thus for cast-iron
                    beams Hodgkinson has recommended that the tension flange should have six times
                    the sectional area of the compression flange. The intensity of longitudinal
                    stress on the two flanges of an I beam is approximately M∕S <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 1</hi><hi rend="italic">h</hi> and M∕S <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">h</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h</hi> being the depth from centre to
                    centre of the flanges.</p>
                <p>62. In the examination of loaded beams it is convenient to represent graphically
                    the bending moment and the shearing force at various sections by setting up
                    ordinates to represent the values of these quantities. Curves of bending moment
                    and shearing force for a number of important practical cases of beams supported
                    at the ends will be found in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Bridges,</hi> with
                    expressions for the maximum bending moment and maximum shearing force under
                    various distributions of load. The subject may be briefly illustrated here by
                    taking the case of a cantilever or projecting bracket—(1) loaded at the end only
                    (fig. 35); (2) loaded at the end and at another point (fig. 36); (3) loaded over
                    the whole length with a uniform load per foot run. Curves of bending moment are
                    given in full lines and curves of shearing force in dotted lines in the
                    diagrams.</p>
                <p>The area enclosed by the curve of shearing force, up to any ordinate, such as <hi
                    rend="italic">ab</hi> (fig. 37), is equal to the bending moment at the same
                    section, represented by the ordinate <hi rend="italic">ac.</hi> For let <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi> be increased to <hi rend="italic">x + δx,</hi> the bending
                    moment changes to 2F(<hi rend="italic">x</hi> + δ <hi rend="italic">x</hi>), or
                    δM = δ <hi rend="italic">xΣ</hi> F. Hence the shearing force at any section is
                    equal to the rate of change of the bending moment there per unit of the length,
                    and the bending moment is the integral of the shearing force with respect to the
                    length. In the case of a continuous distribution of load, it should be observed
                    that, when <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is increased to <hi rend="italic">x</hi> +δ
                    <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, the moment changes by an additional amount which
                    depends on (δx) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> and may therefore be
                    neglected.</p>
                <p>63. To examine the distribution of shearing stress over any vertical section of a
                    beam, we may consider two closely adjacent sections AB and DE (fig. 38), on
                    which the bending moments are M and M + δM respectively. The resultant
                    horizontal force due to the bending stresses on a piece ADHG enclosed between
                    the adjacent sections, and bounded by the horizontal plane GH at a distance <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> from the neutral axis, is shown
                    by the shaded figure. This must be equilibrated by the horizontal shearing
                    stress on GH, which is the only other horizontal force acting on the piece. At
                    any height <hi rend="italic">y</hi> the intensity of resultant horizontal stress
                    due to the difference of the bending moments is <hi rend="italic">y</hi> δM∕I,
                    and the whole horizontal force on GH is <hi rend="italic">⅛lfP</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> vι</hi><hi rend="italic">yzdy, z</hi> being the
                    breadth. If <hi rend="italic">q</hi> be the intensity of horizontal shearing
                    stress on the section GH, whose breadth is <hi rend="italic">z</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi>, we have <hi rend="italic">qzjδx=^-∕ yzdy .</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> √i'o<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n628/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0628-0605"/> But δM∕δ <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is the whole
                    shearing force Q on the section of the beam. Hence <hi rend="strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> Q</hi><hi rend="italic                     strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> Γ</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript
                    strikethrough smallcaps"> Vl</hi><hi rend="italic strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> j</hi><hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> 9</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript strikethrough                     smallcaps"> ,</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> =∑⅞ ∕</hi><hi rend="italic strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> y-dy;</hi> and this is also the intensity of vertical shearing
                    stress at the distance <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> from
                    the neutral axis. This expression may conveniently be written <hi rend="italic"
                    >q =</hi> QA <hi rend="italic">y∕z</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> I <hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> where A is the area of the surface AG and <hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi> the distance of its centre of gravity from the neutral axis. The
                    intensity <hi rend="italic">q</hi> is a maximum at the neutral axis and
                    diminishes to zero at the top and bottom of the beam. In a beam of rectangular
                    section the value of the shearing stress at the neutral axis is <hi
                    rend="italic">q</hi> max. = <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Q/ <hi rend="italic">bh.</hi> In other words, the
                    maximum intensity of shearing stress on any section is ⅜ of the mean intensity.
                    Similarly, in a beam of circular section the maximum is 4/ <hi rend="subscript">
                    3</hi> of the mean. This result is of some importance in application to the pins
                    of pin-joints, which may be treated as very short beams liable to give way by
                    shearing.</p>
                <p>In the case of an I beam with wide flanges and a thin web, the above expression
                    shows that in any vertical section <hi rend="italic">q</hi> is nearly constant
                    in the web, and insignificantly small in the flanges. Practically all the
                    shearing stress is borne by the web, and its intensity is very nearly equal to Q
                    divided by the area of section of the web.</p>
                <p>64. The foregoing analysis of the stresses in a beam, which resolves them into
                    longitudinal pull and push, due to bending moment, along with shear in
                    longitudinal and transverse planes, is generally sufficient in the treatment of
                    practical cases. If, however, it is desired to find the direction and greatest
                    intensity of stress at any point in a beam, the planes of principal stress
                    passing through the point must be found by an application of the general method
                    given in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> chapter iii. In the
                    present case the problem is excep tionally simple, from the fact that the
                    stresses on two planes at right angles are known, and the stress on one of these
                    planes is wholly tan gential. Let AC (fig. 39) be an indefinitely small portion
                    of the horizontal section of a beam, on which there is only shearing stress, and
                    let AB be an indefinitely small portion of the vertical section at the same
                    place, on which there is shearing and normal stress. Let <hi rend="italic"
                    >q</hi> be the intensity of the shearing stress, which is the same on AB and AC,
                    and let <hi rend="italic">p</hi> be the in tensity of normal stress on AB: it is
                    required to find a third plane BC, such that the stress on it is wholly normal,
                    and to find <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> the in tensity of that stress. Let <hi
                    rend="italic">θ</hi> be the angle (to be determined) which BC makes with AB.
                    Then the equilibrium of the triangular wedge ABC requires that <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi> BC cos <hi rend="italic">θ=p.</hi> AB+ <hi rend="italic">q.</hi> AC, and
                    rBC sin <hi rend="italic">θ=q</hi>. AB; or <hi rend="italic">(r-p)</hi> cos <hi
                    rend="italic">θ</hi> = <hi rend="italic">q</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">θ,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">r</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> = <hi rend="italic"
                    >q</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi></p>
                <p>Hence, <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=r(r-p),</hi> tan <hi rend="italic">2θ = 2q∕p, r</hi> = ½ <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi> ±√ <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    +¼ <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>The positive value of <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is the greater principal stress,
                    and is of the same sign as <hi rend="italic">p</hi>. The negative value is the
                    lesser principal stress, which occurs on a plane at right angles to the former.
                    The equation for <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> gives two values corresponding to the
                    two planes of principal stress. The greatest intensity of shearing stress occurs
                    on the pair of planes inclined at 45° to the planes of principal stress, and its
                    value is √ <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">+</hi> ¼ <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    (by § 5).</p>
                <p>65. The above determination of <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> the greatest intensity
                    of stress due to the combined effect of simple bending and shearing, is of some
                    practical importance in the case of the web of an I beam. We have seen that the
                    web takes practically the whole shearing force, distributed over it with a
                    nearly uniform intensity <hi rend="italic">q.</hi> If there were no normal
                    stress on a vertical section of the web, the shearing stress <hi rend="italic"
                    >q</hi> would give rise to two equal principal stresses, of pull and push, each
                    equal to <hi rend="italic">q,</hi> in directions inclined at 45° to the section.
                    But the web has further to suffer normal stress due to bending, the intensity of
                    which at points near the flanges approximates to the intensity on the flanges
                    themselves. Hence in these regions the greater principal stress is increased,
                    often by a considerable amount, which may easily be calculated from the
                    foregoing formula. What makes this specially important is the fact that one of
                    the principal stresses is a stress of compression, which tends to make the web
                    yield by buckling, and must be guarded against by a suitable stiffening of the
                    web.</p>
                <p>The equation for <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> allows the lines of principal stress in
                    a beam to be drawn when the form of the beam and the distribution of loads are
                    given. An example has been shown in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Bridges</hi> (§ 13, fig. 12), vol. iv. p. 290.</p>
                <p>66. The deflexion of beams is due partly to the distortion caused by shearing,
                    but chiefly to the simple bending which occurs at each vertical section. As
                    regards the second, which in most cases is the only important cause of
                    deflexion, we have seen (§ 59) that the radius of curvature R at any section,
                    due to a bending moment M, is EI∕M, which may also be written E <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. Thus beams of uniform strength and depth (and, as a
                    particular case, beams of uniform section subjected to a uniform bending moment)
                    bend into a circular arc. In other cases the form of the bent beam, and the
                    resulting slope and deflexion, may be determined by integrating the curvature
                    throughout the span, or by a graphic process (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Bridges,</hi> § 25), which consists in drawing a curve to represent the beam
                    with its curvature greatly exaggerated, after the radius of curvature has been
                    determined for a sufficient number of sections. In all practical cases the
                    curvature is so small that the arc and chord are of sensibly the same length.
                    Calling <hi rend="italic">i</hi> the angle of slope, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >u</hi> the dip or deflexion from the chord, the equation to the curve into
                    which an originally straight beam bends may be written</p>
                <p>&lt;ύί_ .. d <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> w <hi rend="italic">di</hi> El <hi
                    rend="italic">dx ’ dx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dx~</hi> M</p>
                <p>Integrating this for a beam of uniform section, of span L, supported at its ends
                    and loaded with a weight W at the centre, we have, for the greatest slope and
                    greatest deflexion, respectively, <hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> = WL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕16EI, <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =WL <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∕48EI. If the load W
                    is uniformly distributed over L, <hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> = WL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕24EI and <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 5WL <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∕384EI. For other
                    cases, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bridges,</hi> §24.</p>
                <p>The additional slope which shearing stress produces in any originally horizontal
                    layer is <hi rend="italic">q</hi> ∕C, where <hi rend="italic">q</hi> is, as
                    before, the intensity of shearing stress and C is the modulus of rigidity. In a
                    round or rectangular bar the additional deflexion due to shearing is scarcely
                    appreciable. In an I beam, with a web only thick enough to resist shear, it may
                    be a somewhat considerable proportion of the whole.</p>
                <p>67. <hi rend="italic">Torsion</hi> occurs in a bar to which equal and opposite
                    couples are applied, the axis of the bar being the axis of the couples, and
                    gives rise to shearing stress in planes perpendicular to the axis. Let AB (fig.
                    40) be a uniform circular shaft held fast at the end A, and twisted by a couple
                    applied in the plane BB. As suming the strain to be within the limits of
                    elasticity, a radius</p>
                <p>CD turns round to</p>
                <p>CD', and a line AD</p>
                <p>drawn at any dis tance <hi rend="italic">r</hi> from the axis, and originally
                    straight, changes into the helix AD'. Let <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> be the angle
                    which this helix makes with lines parallel to the axis, or in other words the
                    angle of shear at the distance <hi rend="italic">r</hi> from the axis, and let
                    <hi rend="italic">i</hi> be the angle of twist DCD'. Taking two sections at a
                    distance <hi rend="italic">dx</hi> from one another, we have the arc <hi
                    rend="italic">θdx = rdi.</hi> Hence <hi rend="italic">q,</hi> the intensity of
                    shearing stress in a plane of cross-section, varies as r, <hi rend="italic">.
                    di</hi> since <hi rend="italic">q</hi> =C <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> = Cr <hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> di</hi> / <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> dx</hi>. The resultant moment of the whole shearing stress on each
                    plane of cross-section is equal to the twisting moment M. Thus <hi rend="italic"
                    >∫2πr</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">qdr =</hi> M <hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p>Calling <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> the outside radius
                    (where the shearing stress is greatest) and <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> its intensity there, we have <hi rend="italic">q =
                    rq</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">/r</hi><hi rend="subscript"
                    > 1</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> and hence, for a solid shaft, <hi rend="italic"
                    >q</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 2M∕π <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. For a hollow shaft with
                    a central hole of radius <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    the same reasoning applies: the limits of integration are now r <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and r <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ιr</hi> (<hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ι <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 4 - r</hi> 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi>)</p>
                <p>The lines of principal stress are obviously helices inclined at 45° to the
                    axis.</p>
                <p>If the shaft has any other form of section than a solid or symmetrical hollow
                    circle, an originally straight radial line becomes warped when the shaft is
                    twisted, and the shearing stress is no longer proportional to the distance from
                    the axis. The twisting of shafts of square, triangular, and other sections has
                    been investigated by M. de St Venant (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi>
                    § 66-71, where a comparison of torsional rigidities is given). In a square shaft
                    (side = <hi rend="italic">h</hi>) the stress is greatest at the middle of each
                    side, and its intensity there<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Rankine, <hi rend="italic">Applied Mechanics,</hi> §
                    324.</p></note> is <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =
                    M∕0∙281 <hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>.</p>
                <p>For round sections the angle of twist per unit of length is <hi rend="italic"
                    >i</hi> = .-γL = in solid and <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>,. —- in hollow
                    shafts.</p>
                <p>68. In what has been said above it is assumed that the stress is within the limit
                    of elasticity. When the twisting couple is increased so that this limit is
                    passed, plastic yielding begins in the outermost layer, and a larger proportion
                    of the whole stress falls to be borne by layers nearer the centre. The case is
                    similar to that of a beam bent beyond the elastic limit, described in § 57. If
                    we suppose the process of twisting to be continued, and that after passing the
                    limit of elasticity the material is capable of much distortion without further
                    increase of shearing stress, the distribution of stress on any cross section
                    will finally have an approximately <hi rend="italic">f*</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> y</hi> *l uniform value <hi rend="italic">q</hi> ’ <hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> and the moment of torsion will be ^. <hi rend="italic"
                    >2πr~qdr</hi> = f^'(<hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ι <hi rend="superscript">
                    3-r</hi> 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)∙ In the case of a solid shaft this
                    gives for M a<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n629/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0629-0606"/> value greater than it has when the stress in the
                    outermost layer only reaches the intensity <hi rend="italic">q'</hi>, in the
                    ratio of 4 to 3.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Elasticity,</hi> §§ 10-20.</p></note> It is obvious from this
                    consideration that the ultimate strength of a shaft to resist torsion is no more
                    deducible from a knowledge of the ultimate shearing strength of the material
                    than the ultimate strength of a beam to resist bending is deducible from a
                    knowledge of <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> c</hi>. It should be noticed
                    also that as regards ultimate strength a solid shaft has an important advantage
                    over a hollow shaft of the same elastic strength, or a hollow shaft so
                    proportioned that the greatest working intensity of stress is the same as in the
                    solid shaft.</p>
                <p>69. <hi rend="italic">Twisting combined with Longitudinal Stress.—</hi> When a
                    rod is twisted and pulled axially, or when a short block is twisted and
                    compressed axially, the greatest intensity of stress (the greater principal
                    stress) is to be found by compounding the longitudinal and shearing stresses as
                    in § 64. In a circular rod of radius <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, a total longitudinal force P in the direction of the
                    axis gives a longitudinal normal stress whose intensity <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =P∕π <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. A twisting couple M
                    applied to the same rod gives a shearing stress whose greatest intensity <hi
                    rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =2M∕π <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. The two
                    together give rise to a pair of principal stresses of intensities r = P∕2π <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    ±∖∕(2M∕π <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +(P∕2π <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, their inclinations to the axis being defined by
                    the equation tan 20 = 2M∕r <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> P, and the term under
                    the square root is the greatest intensity of shearing stress.</p>
                <p>70. <hi rend="italic">Twisting combined with Bending.—</hi> This important
                    practical case is realized in a crank-shaft (fig. 41). Let a force P be applied
                    at the crank-pin A at right angles to the plane of the crank.</p>
                <p>At any section of the shaft C</p>
                <p>(between the crank and the bearing) there is a twisting mo ment M <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = P . AB, and a bend ing moment M <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> =P. BC. There is also a direct shearing force P, but this does not
                    require to be taken into account in calculating the stress at points at the top
                    or bottom of the circumference (where the intensity is greatest), since (by §
                    63) the direct shearing stress is dis tributed so that its intensity is zero at
                    these points. The stress there is consequently made up of longitudinal normal
                    stress (due to bending), <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =
                    4M <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∕πr <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, and shearing stress (due to torsion), <hi
                    rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 2M <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> ∕π <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. Combining these, as in § 64, we find for the
                    principal stresses r=2(M <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ±∖∕M <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + M <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)∕π <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, or r = 2P(BC±AC)∕π <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. The greatest
                    shearing stress is 2P . AC∕πr <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"
                    > 3</hi> ∙, and the axes of principal stress are inclined so that tan 20 = M <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕M <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> = AB∕BC. The axis of
                    greater principal stress bisects the angle ACB.</p>
                <p>71. <hi rend="italic">Long Columns and Struts—Compression and Bending.—</hi> A
                    long strut or pillar, compressed by forces P applied at the ends in the
                    direction of the axis, becomes unstable as regards flexure when P exceeds a
                    certain value. Under no circumstances can this value of P be exceeded in loading
                    a strut. But it may happen that the intensity of stress produced by smaller
                    loads exceeds the safe compressive strength of the material, in which case a
                    lower limit of load must be chosen. If the applied load is not strictly axiai,
                    if the strut is not initially straight, if it is subject to any deflexion by
                    transverse forces, or if the modulus of elasticity is not uniform over each
                    cross-section,—then loads smaller than the limit which causes instability will
                    produce a certain deflexion which increases with increase of load, and will give
                    rise to a uniformly varying stress of the kind illustrated in figs. 26 and 28.
                    We shall first consider the ideal case in which the forces at the ends are
                    strictly axial, the strut perfectly straight and free from transverse loads and
                    perfectly symmetrical as to elasticity. Two conditions have to be
                    distinguished—that in which the ends are left free to bend, and that in which
                    the ends are held fixed. In what follows, the ends are supposed free to bend.
                    The value of the load which causes instability will be found by considering what
                    force P applied to each end would suffice to hold an originally straight strut
                    in a bent state, supposing it to have received a small amount of elastic
                    curvature in any way. Using <hi rend="italic">u</hi> as before to denote the
                    deflexion at any part of the length, the bending moment is <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pu,</hi> and (taking the origin at the middle of tho chord) the equation to the
                    elastic curve is <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u _ - Pu</hi></p>
                <p>&lt;‰Γ <hi rend="superscript"> 2-</hi> ^~ËÎ’</p>
                <p>from which, for a strut of uniform section, <hi rend="italic">u</hi> = <hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">x</hi>
                    √P∕EI, <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> being the
                    deflexion at the centre, Now <hi rend="italic">u</hi> = 0 when <hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi> =½L (the half length), and therefore ½L∖∕P∕EI = <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi> /2πr or an integral multiple of ½π. The smallest value (½π) corresponds
                    to the least force P. Thus the force required to maintain the strut in its
                    curved state is P = π <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> EI∕L <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 2</hi>, and is independent of <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> This means that with this particular value of P
                    (which for brevity we shall write P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>) the strut will
                    be in neutral equilibrium when bent; with a value of P less than P <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> it will be stable: with a greater value it will be
                    unstable. Hence a load exceeding P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> will certainly
                    cause rupture. The value</p>
                <p>π <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> EI∕L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> applies to
                    struts with round ends, or ends free to turn. If the ends are fixed the
                    effective length for bending is reduced by one half, so that P <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> then is 4π <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> EI∕L <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. When one end is fixed and the other is free P <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> has an intermediate value, probably about 9π <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> EI∕4L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>72. The above theory, which is Euler’s, assigns P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> as
                    a limit to the strength of a strut on account of flexural instability; but a
                    stress less than P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> may cause direct crushing. Let S
                    be the area of section, and <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    c</hi> the strength of the material to resist crushing. Thus a strut which
                    conforms to the ideal conditions specified above will fail by simple crushing if
                    <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> S is less than P <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, but by bending if <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> c</hi> S is greater than P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. Hence
                    with a given material and form of section the ideal strut will fail by direct
                    crushing if the length is less than a certain multiple of the least breadth
                    (easily calculated from the expression for P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>), and
                    in that case its strength will be independent of the length; when the length is
                    greater than this the strut will yield by bending, and its strength diminishes
                    rapidly as the length is increased.</p>
                <p>But the conditions which the above theory assumes are never realized in practice.
                    The load is never strictly axial, nor the strut absolutely straight to begin
                    with, nor the elasticity uniform. The result is that the strength is in all
                    cases less than either <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> S or
                    P <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. The effect of deviations from axiality, from
                    straightness, and from uniformity of elasticity may be treated by introducing a
                    term expressing an imaginary initial deflexion, and in this way Euler’s theory
                    may be so modified as to agree well with experimental results on the fracture of
                    struts,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See papers by
                    Profs. Ayrton and Perry, <hi rend="italic">The Engineer,</hi> Dec. 10 and 24,
                    1886, and by T. C. Fidler, <hi rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. C.E.,</hi> vol.
                    lxxxvi. p. 2C1.</p></note> and may be reconciled with the observed fact that the
                    deflexion of a strut begins gradually and passes through stable values before
                    the stage of instability is reached. In consequence of this stable deflexion the
                    stress of compression on the inside edge becomes greater than P∕S, the stress on
                    the outside edge becomes less than P∕S, and may even change into tension, and
                    the strut may yield by one or the other of these stresses becoming greater than
                    <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> c</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> respectively. As regards the
                    influence of length and moment of inertia of section on the deflexion of struts,
                    analogy to the case of beams suggests that the greatest deflexion consistent
                    with stability will vary as L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic"
                    >b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b</hi> being the least breadth, and the greatest and
                    least stress, at opposite edges of the middle section, will consequently be</p>
                <p>J√ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>,∈U∖ n <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> (<hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ± <hi rend="subscript"> &amp;a</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >j,</hi> where <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is a coefficient depending on the
                    material and the form of the section. This gives, for the breaking load, P = S
                    <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> ∕(1 + <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi> L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) or -S <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> t</hi> ∕(1 <hi rend="italic">-a</hi> L <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">/b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">),</hi> the smaller of the two being taken.</p>
                <p>This formula, which is generally known as Gordon’s, can be made to agree fairly
                    with the results of experiments on struts of ordinary proportions, when the
                    values of <hi rend="italic">f</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">a</hi> are
                    treated as empirical constants to be determined by trial with struts of the same
                    class as those to which the formula is to be applied. Gordon’s formula may also
                    be arrived at in another way. For very short struts we have seen that the
                    breaking load is <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> S, and for
                    very long struts it is π <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> EI∕L <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. If we write P=∕S∕(1+ <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> c</hi> SL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕π <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> EI), we have a formula which gives correct values in
                    these two extreme cases, and intermediate values for struts of medium length. By
                    writing this P=√S∕(1 <hi rend="italic">+ c</hi> SL <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> /I), and treating <hi rend="italic">f</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                    as empirical constants, we have Gordon’s formula in a slightly modified shape.
                    Gordon’s formula is largely used; it is, however, essentially empirical, and it
                    is only by adjustment of both constants that it can be brought into agreement
                    with experimental results.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>For experiments on the breaking strength of struts, see papers by
                    Hodgkinson, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1840; Berkeley, <hi
                    rend="italic">Min. Proc. Inst. O.E.,</hi> vol. xxx.; Christie, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Trans. Amer. Soc. Civ. Eng.,</hi> 1884.</p></note> For values of the constants,
                    see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bridges.</hi> In the case of fixed ends, <hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi> is to be divided by 4.</p>
                <p>73. <hi rend="italic">Bursting Strength of Circular Cylinders and Spheres.—</hi>
                    Space remains for the consideration of only one other mode of stress, of great
                    importance from its occurrence in boilers, pipes, hydraulic and steam cylinders,
                    and guns.</p>
                <p>The material of a hollow cylinder, subjected to pressure from within, is thrown
                    into a stress of circumferential pull. When the thickness <hi rend="italic"
                    >t</hi> is small compared with the radius R, we may treat this stress as
                    uniformly distributed over the thickness. Let <hi rend="italic">p</hi> be the
                    intensity of fluid pres sure within a hollow circular cylinder, and let <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> be the intensity of circumferential stress.</p>
                <p>Consider the forces on a small rectangular plate</p>
                <p>(fig. 42), with its sides parallel and perpen dicular to the direction of the
                    axis, of length <hi rend="italic">l</hi> and width Rδ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>,
                    δ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> being the small angle it subtends at the axis.
                    Whatever forces act on this plate in the direction of the axis are equal and
                    opposite. The remaining forces, which are in equilibrium, are P, the total
                    pressure from within, and a force Tat each side due to the circumferential
                    stress. P= <hi rend="italic">pl</hi> Rδ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n630/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0630-0607"/> and T= <hi rend="italic">flt</hi>. But by the
                    triangle of forces (fig. 43) P = Tδ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>. Hence <hi
                    rend="italic">f=p</hi> R <hi rend="italic">∣t.</hi></p>
                <p>The ends of the cylinder may or may not be held together by longitudinal stress
                    in the cylinder sides; if they are, then, whatever be the form of the ends, a
                    transverse section, the area of which is 2πR <hi rend="italic">t</hi>, has to
                    bear a total force <hi rend="italic">p</hi> πR <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.
                    Hence, if <hi rend="italic">f'</hi> be the intensity of longitudinal stress, <hi
                    rend="italic">f' =p</hi> R <hi rend="italic">∣</hi> 2 <hi rend="italic">t =</hi>
                    ½ <hi rend="italic">f.</hi></p>
                <p>74. A thin hollow sphere under internal pressure has equal circumferential pull
                    in all directions. To find its value consider the plate of fig. 42. There are
                    now four equal forces T, on each of the four sides, to equilibrate the radial
                    force P. Hence P = 2Tδ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f=p</hi>
                    R/2 <hi rend="italic">t</hi></p>
                <p>75. When the thickness is not small compared with the radius, the radial pressure
                    is transmitted from layer to layer with reduced intensity, and the
                    circumferential pull diminishes towards the outside. In the case of a thick
                    cylinder with free ends<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>This condition is realized in practice when the fluid causing internal
                    pressure is held in by a piston, and the stress between this piston and the
                    other end of the cylinder is taken by some other part of the structure than the
                    cylinder sides.</p></note> we have to deal at any point with two principal
                    stresses, radial and circumferential, which may be denoted by <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> ’ respectively. Supposing (as we may
                    properly do in dealing with a cylinder which is not very short) that a
                    transverse section originally plane remains plane, the longitudinal strain is
                    uniform. Since there is no longitudinal stress this strain is due entirely to
                    the lateral action of the stresses <hi rend="italic">p</hi> and p', and its
                    amount is (<hi rend="italic">p +p')∕σE</hi>. Hence at all points <hi
                    rend="italic">p + p'≈</hi> constant.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The solution which follows in the text is applicable even
                    when there is longitudinal stress, provided that the longitudinal stress is
                    uniformly distributed over each transverse section. If we call this stress <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi> ", the longitudinal strain is <hi rend="italic">p</hi>
                    "∕E+(<hi rend="italic">p</hi> + <hi rend="italic">p</hi> ')∕σE. Since the whole
                    strain is uniform, and <hi rend="italic">p"</hi> is uniform, the sum of <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p'</hi> is constant at all points, as
                    in the case where the ends are free.</p></note> Further, by considering the
                    equilibrium of any thin layer, as we have already considered that of a thin
                    cylinder, we have <hi rend="italic superscript"> d</hi> / <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> dx</hi> (<hi rend="italic">pr</hi>)= <hi rend="italic">p'.</hi></p>
                <p>These two equations give by integration, p = C + C'∕ <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> ' = C - C'∕ <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>If <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> be the external and <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> the internal radius, and <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> the pressure on the inner
                    surface, the conditions that <hi rend="italic">p=p</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    0</hi> when <hi rend="italic">r</hi> = <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0 when <hi rend="italic"
                    >r=r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> give C = - <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕(<hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) and C' = -C <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.
                    Hence the circumferential stress at any radius <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is <hi
                    rend="italic">p'</hi> = <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    (l+ <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> / <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)∕(<hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-
                    r <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>). At the inside,
                    where this is greatest, its value is - <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi> (<hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)∕(<hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>),—a quantity always greater than <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi>, however thick the cylinder is.</p>
                <p>In the construction of guns various devices have been used to equalize the
                    circumferential tension. With cast guns a chilled core has been employed to make
                    the inner layers solidify and cool first, so that they are afterwards compressed
                    by the later contraction of the outer layers. In guns built up of wrought-iron
                    or steel hoops the hoops are bored small by a regulated amount and are shrunk on
                    over the barrel or over the inner hoops. In Mr Longridge’s system, now under
                    trial, the gun is made by winding steel wire or ribbon, with suitable initial
                    tension, on a central barrel.</p>
                <p>76. The circumferential stress at any point of a thick hollow sphere exposed to
                    internal fluid pressure is found, by a process like that of the last paragraph,
                    to be - <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> (1 + <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>
                    ∕2 <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)∕(<hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>- <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>),
                    which gives, for the greatest tension, the value</p>
                <p>- <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> + 2 <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi>)∕2(<hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>- r <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"
                    > 3</hi>). (J. A. E. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
