<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0188-0173-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMITH, James (9th edition, volume 22, page 173)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039784">Novelle</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09w92">Addresses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n188/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMITH, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label> (1775-1839)
                    and <hi rend="smallcaps">Horace</hi> (1779-1849), sons of an eminent and
                    prosperous London solicitor, were born, the former on 10th February 1775 and the
                    latter on 31st December 1779, both in London. They were joint authors of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Rejected Addresses,</hi> described by Horace as “one of the
                    luckiest hits in literature.” The occasion of this happy <hi rend="italic">jeu
                        d'esprit</hi> was the rebuilding of Drury Lane theatre in 1812, after a fire
                    in which it had been burnt down. The managers had offered a prize of £50 for an
                    address to be recited at the reopening in October. Six weeks before that date
                    the happy thought occurred to the brothers Smith of feigning that the most
                    popular poets of the time had been among the competitors and issuing a volume of
                    unsuccessful addresses in parody of their various styles. They divided the task
                    between them, James taking Wordsworth, Southey, Coleridge, and Crabbe, while
                    Byron, Moore, Scott, and Bowles were assigned to Horace.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The particulars of the authorship are
                            given in the 18th edition (1820), and in the memoir of his brother by
                            Horace prefixed to a collection of fugitive pieces (1840). James
                            contributed the first stanza to the imitation of Byron, but otherwise
                            they worked independently.</p></note> The parodists were ready with
                    their small volume by October, but they had some difficulty in getting a
                    publisher, although the success of their clever imitations once published was
                    such that seven editions were called for within three months. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Rejected Addresses</hi> are the most widely popular parodies
                    ever published in England, and have taken quite a classical rank in that kind of
                    literature. The brothers fairly divided the honours: the elder brother’s
                    Wordsworth is evenly balanced by the younger’s Scott, and both had a hand in
                    Byron. A striking feature in the parodies is the absence of malice; none of the
                    caricatured bards took offence, while the imitation is so clever that both Byron
                    and Scott are recorded to have said in effect that they could hardly believe
                    they had not written the addresses ascribed to them.</p>
                <p>After this brilliant success James, the elder brother, determined, as he said,
                    “to leave off a winner’’and follow Warburton’s advice to Anstey: “Young man, you
                    have written a highly successful work; never put pen to paper again.” He was
                    tempted occasionally to transgress this self-denying ordinance, and made another
                    hit in writing <hi rend="italic">Country Cousins, A Trip to Paris, A Trip to
                        America,</hi> and other lively skits for Charles Mathews, earning from the
                    comedian the praise of being “the only man who can write clever nonsense.” His
                    social reputation as a wit stood high. He was reputed one of the best of
                    conversers in an age when the art was studied, and it was remarked that he held
                    his own without falling into the great error of wits,—sarcasm. But for all his
                    good-nature he did not wholly escape the Charybdis of great talkers,—the charge
                    of being something of a bore. In his old age the irreverent <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fraser's</hi> put him in its gallery of living portraits as a gouty and
                    elderly but painstaking joker. He died in London on 26th December 1839.</p>
                <p>Horace Smith was less timorously careful of his poetical reputation than his
                    elder brother, whom he survived, and, after making a fortune as a stockbroker,
                    followed in the wake of Scott and wrote about a score of historical novels, <hi
                        rend="italic">—Βrambletye House, Tor Hill, Reuben Apsley, Zillah, The New)
                        Forest, Walter Colyton,</hi> &amp;c. His sketches of eccentric character are
                    brilliant and amusing; but he was more of an essayist than a story-teller. He
                    began in 1826, when Scott, still retaining his hold on the public, had made
                    success impossible for imitators with less wealth of historical substance and
                    inferior command of stirring incident. As he went on he encountered such
                    competitors as Bulwer Lytton, Disraeli, Marryat, and Dickens. Still Horace Smith
                    established a fair reputation, and some of his novels may still be found in the
                    smoking-rooms of country houses. He was also a frequent contributor to the <hi
                        rend="italic">New Monthly Magazine</hi> under the editorship of Campbell.
                    Three volumes of <hi rend="italic">Gaieties and Gravities,</hi> published in
                    1826, contain many witty essays both in prose and in verse, but the only single
                    piece that has taken a permanent place is the “Address to the Mummy in Belzoni’s
                    Exhibition.” There is more of earnest in this than is generally found in his
                    jesting. In private life Horace Smith was not less popular than his brother,
                    though less ambitious of renown as a talker. It was of him that Shelley said:
                    “Is it not odd that the only truly generous person I ever knew who had money
                    enough to be generous with should be a stockbroker? He writes poetry and
                    pastoral dramas and yet knows how to make money, and does make it, and is still
                    generous.” Horace Smith died at Tunbridge Wells on 12th July 1849.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
