<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0603-0580-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STRABO (9th edition, volume 22, page 580)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205830">Ethiopia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205534">Libya</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n603/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STRABO</label>, the famous geographer and historian, was born
                    at Amasea in Pontus, a city which had been Hellenized to a great extent. Of his
                    father’s family we know nothing; but several of his mother’s relations, who were
                    probably Greeks, had held important posts under Mithradates Euergetes and his
                    famous son Mithradates Eupator. Dorylaus, a distinguished general of Mithradates
                    Euergetes, was the great-grandfather of Strabo’s mother. After the murder of
                    that king, Dorylaus, who at that time was collecting mercenaries in Crete, where
                    he had obtained the command<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n604/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0604-0581"/> in a successful war of the Cnossians against
                    Gortyn, settled at Cnossus. By Sterope, a Macedonian, he had a daughter and two
                    sons,—Lagetas and Stratarchus. Dorylaus had a brother Philetaerus, whose son
                    Dorylaus was brought up with Mithradates Eupator. This king, at the instance of
                    his friend invited back to Pontus the family of Dorylaus, who was himself now
                    dead, as was also his son Lagetas. Strabo saw Stratarchus in extreme old age.
                    The daughter of Lagetas was the mother of Strabo’s mother. Moaphernes, an uncle
                    of Strabo’s mother, probably on the father’s side, was governor of Colchis under
                    Mithradates Eupator. His mother’s father must have held an important position,
                    for, seeing the impending downfall of the king, and also in anger against him
                    for having put to death his kinsmen Tibius and Theophilus, he handed over
                    fifteen forts to Lucullus. In spite of this, with the ruin of the king the
                    fortunes of the family fell, since Pompey refused to ratify the rewards promised
                    by Lucullus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Life.—</hi> Though the exact date of Strabo’s birth is unknown,
                    a close approximation is possible. Clinton places it not later than 54 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The most probable date lies between 64 and 62,
                    since he speaks of certain events occurring at the former as “a little before my
                    time,” whilst he describes an occurrence in the latter year as “in my own time,”
                    phrases which he uses elsewhere with great exactness in speaking of persons and
                    events. He received a good education in the Greek poets, especially Homer; he
                    studied at Nysa under the grammarian Aristodemus, under Tyrannio the grammarian
                    at Rome, under the philosopher Xenarchus either at Rome or Alexandria, and he
                    had studied Aristotle along with Boethus (possibly at Rome under Tyrannio, who
                    had access to the Aristotelian writings in Sulla’s library). It is to be noted
                    that from none of those teachers was he likely to learn mathematics or
                    astronomy. He was at Corinth in 29 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> where he saw
                    Octavian on his return from Egypt to celebrate his triumph for Actium. He was in
                    Egypt in 24 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and took the opportunity of
                    ascending the Nile in company with the prefect Aelius Gallus. He was at Rome
                    after 14</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.,</hi> for he describes (v. 236) as an eyewitness the
                    place where the body of Augustus was burnt in the Campus. He was still writing
                    in 21 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> The date of his death is unknown. Strabo’s
                    statement that he saw P. Servilius Isauricus has caused some difficulty. This
                    Servilius died at Rome in 44 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> at an advanced age.
                    Some suppose that Strabo confused him with P. Servilius Casca, also called
                    Isauricus, or some other distinguished Roman whom he had seen in Asia, but by
                    his words he clearly means the conqueror of the Isaurians. This difficulty only
                    arises from an entirely unwarranted assumption that Strabo was on his way to
                    Rome for the first time in 29</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> We have seen that he studied under Tyrannio in
                    that city; if he did so after 29 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Tyrannio must
                    have been very old, which Strabo would probably have mentioned, as he does in
                    the case of Aristodemus. Although he had seen a comparatively small portion of
                    the regions which he describes, he had travelled much, as he states himself:
                    “Westward I have journeyed to the parts of Etruria opposite Sardinia; towards
                    the south from the Euxine to the borders of Ethiopia; and perhaps not one of
                    those who have written geographies has visited more places than I have between
                    those limits. For those who have gone farther west have not gone so far
                    eastward, and the case is the same with the regions between the northern and
                    southern limits.” The fulness of his description in certain places, contrasted
                    with the meagreness and inaccuracy in others, seems to indicate that in the
                    former cases he had actually visited the places, but that he is dependent on
                    second-hand information for the latter. He tells us that he had seen Egypt as
                    far south as Syene and Philae, Comana in Cappadocia, Ephesus, Mylasa, Nysa and
                    Hierapolis in Phrygia, Gyarus, and Populonia. Of Greece proper he saw but
                    little; he visited Corinth, Athens, Megara, and places in their vicinity, and
                    perhaps Argos, although he was not aware that the ruins of Mycenae still
                    existed; he had seen Cyrene from the sea, probably on his voyage from Puteoli to
                    Alexandria. He remained at the latter place a long time, probably amassing
                    materials, and studying astronomy and mathematics. For nowhere could he have had
                    a better means of consulting the works of historians, geographers, and
                    astronomers, such as Eratosthenes, Posidonius, Hipparchus, and Apollodorus. When
                    and where he went from Egypt we know not. It has been commonly assumed that he
                    returned home to Amasea. For this there are no grounds. Probabilities are in
                    favour of his having returned to Rome, where he undoubtedly resided in his old
                    age. The place of his death is unknown; but, since we find him at Rome in what
                    must in the course of nature have been the closing years of his life, it is not
                    unreasonable to suppose that there he died. Various passages in his work
                    indicate that he held by the Stoic rule.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Works.—</hi> His earliest writings were two (not one, as
                    commonly stated) historical works now lost, which he himself describes (xi. 515)
                    as his <hi rend="italic">Historical Memoirs</hi> and his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Continuation of Polybius.</hi> There can be no doubt but that these were
                    two distinct works; for he speaks (ii. 70) of having treated of the exploits of
                    Alexander in his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> a topic which could not have
                    found a place in a work which began where that of Polybius ended (146 B.c.).
                    According to Suidas, the continuation of Polybius was in forty-three books.
                    Plutarch, who calls him “the Philosopher,” quotes Strabo’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Memoirs (Luc.,</hi> 28), and cites him as an historian <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Sulla,</hi> 26). Josephus, who constantly calls him “the Cappadocian,”
                    often quotes from him, but does not mention the title of the work.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Geography</hi> is the most important work on that science
                    which antiquity has left us. It was, as far as we know, the first attempt to
                    collect all the geographical knowledge at the time attainable, and to compose a
                    general treatise on geography. It must not be regarded as nothing more than a
                    new edition of Eratosthenes. In general outline it follows necessarily the work
                    of the last-named geographer, who had first laid down a scientific basis for
                    geography on which his successors could not help building. Strabo made
                    considerable alterations, but not always for the better. The three books of the
                    older work formed a strictly technical geographical treatise. Its small size
                    prevented it from containing any such general description of separate countries
                    as Strabo rightly conceived to fall within the scope of the geographer. “Strabo
                    indeed appears to be the first who conceived a complete geographical treatise as
                    comprising the four divisions of mathematical, physical, political, and
                    historical geography, and he endeavoured, however imperfectly, to keep all these
                    objects in view.” Moreover, the incidental historical notices, which are often
                    of great value and interest, are all his own. These digressions at times
                    interrupt the symmetry of his plan; but Strabo had all the Greek love of
                    legendary lore, and he discusses questions relating to the journeyings of
                    Heracles as earnestly as if they were events within recent history. He regarded
                    Homer as the source of all wisdom and knowledge, and consequently accepted the
                    Homeric geography in its entirety, as needing only proper explanation for the
                    removal of all difficulties. On the other hand, he treats the work of Herodotus
                    with undeserved contempt, and classes him with Ctesias and other
                    “marvel-mongers”; and yet in some respects Herodotus had better information—for
                    instance, in regard to the Caspian—than that possessed by Strabo himself.<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n605/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0605-0582"/> Again, Strabo may be censured for discarding
                    the statements of Pytheas respecting the west and north of Europe, accepted as
                    they had been by Eratosthenes. But in this he relied on Polybius, whom he might
                    justly consider as having from his position at Rome far better means of gaining
                    accurate information about those regions. A critical sagacity far stronger than
                    that of Strabo might well have erred at a time when the data for forming
                    accurate judgments on such questions were so meagre and chaotic. It must be
                    admitted that the statements of Pytheas did not accord with the theory of Strabo
                    just in those very points where he was at variance with Eratosthenes. He showed
                    likewise an unwarranted scepticism in reference to the island of Cerne on the
                    west coast of Africa, which without doubt the Carthaginians had long used as an
                    emporium. Strabo has been censured for not making a greater use of Roman
                    authorities. Although the Roman arms had opened up much of the north and west,
                    he follows the Greek writers almost exclusively in his description of Spain,
                    Gaul, Britain, Germany, and even Italy. For, although he refers to Caesar’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Commentaries</hi> once by name, and has evidently made use of
                    them in other passages, he but imperfectly availed himself of that work. He
                    designed his geography as a sequel to his historical writings, and it had as it
                    were grown out of his historical materials. Such materials were chiefly Greek.
                    We cannot wonder if a man who at an advanced age has commenced a new work
                    utilizes his old material, and has not the energy to undertake fresh researches.
                    Again, if Strabo amassed his material in the library of Alexandria, Greek
                    authorities would naturally furnish the great bulk of his collections. This
                    involves the questions—When and where did he compose the work? He began it
                    probably later than 9 B.c. For he says that, just as Alexander had opened up
                    knowledge of the East, so the Roman arms had now opened up the geography of the
                    West as far as the Elbe. This Drusus accomplished in 9 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.c.</hi> Strabo was still engaged on the work, or certain parts of it, in
                    19 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> for he mentions in the fourth book the
                    conquest of the Taurisci as having taken place thirty-three years before; he
                    also speaks, in the sixth book, of Germanicus, who died in 20 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> as still alive, and in the seventeenth book he
                    speaks of the death of Juba II. (21 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> as a recent
                    event. As it is not probable that he wrote for the first time all of his work
                    except the first three books between 19 and 21 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi>
                    we must not make use of these passages as data for determining the date of
                    composition of the whole work, or even of particular books, but rather ought we
                    to regard them as insertions. Strabo, as already pointed out, was at Rome after
                    the death of Augustus (14 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi>; in book vii. 290 and
                    in book xiii. 609 he uses the terms “here” and “hither” in reference to Rome. It
                    may be inferred from these passages that Strabo certainly revised, if he did not
                    write, the entire work at Rome. If he returned to Rome after a long sojourn in
                    Alexandria, this explains the defectiveness of his information about the
                    countries to the east of his native land, and renders it possible for him to
                    have made use of the chorography of Agrippa, and to have obtained the few
                    incidents from Roman sources which here and there appear in his work.</p>
                <p>He designed the work for the statesman rather than for the student. He therefore
                    endeavours to give a general sketch of the character, physical peculiarities,
                    and natural productions of each country, and consequently gives us much valuable
                    information respecting ethnology, trade, and metallurgy. It was almost necessary
                    that in such an attempt he should select what he thought most important for
                    description, and at times omit what we deem of more importance. With respect to
                    physical geography, his work is a great advance on all preceding ones. Judged by
                    modern standards, his description of the direction of rivers and mountain-chains
                    seems defective, but allowance must be made for difficulties in procuring
                    information, and for want of accurate instruments. In respect of mathematical
                    geography, his want of high scientific training was of no great hindrance. He
                    had before him the results of Eratosthenes, Hipparchus, and Posidonius. The
                    chief conclusions of astronomers concerning the spherical figure and dimensions
                    of the earth, its relation to the heavenly bodies, and the great circles of the
                    globe—the equator, the ecliptic, and the tropics—were considered as well
                    established. He accepted also the division into five zones; he quotes
                    approvingly the assertion of Hipparchus that it was impossible to make real
                    advances in geography without astronomical observations for determining
                    latitudes and longitudes.</p>
                <p>The work consists of seventeen books, of which the seventh is imperfect. The
                    first two books form a general introduction; the next ten deal with Europe, the
                    four following with Asia, and the last with Africa. The first two hooks are
                    meant to comprise a general survey of the progress of geography from the
                    earliest times down to his own day. Unmethodical though they are, we owe to
                    these books almost all we know of the geographical systems of his predecessors,
                    especially that of Eratosthenes. Unfortunately he contents himself with
                    disjointed criticism of detail instead of giving us an orderly statement of the
                    previous systems. The first book begins with his claim to have geography
                    regarded as a branch of philosophy, and he supports this claim by enumerating
                    the philosophers who have studied it, beginning from Homer, as proofs of whose
                    knowledge he adduces his acquaintance with the Ocean, the Ethiopians, aud the
                    Scythians. This discussion of Homer’s geography takes up more than half the
                    book. Passing over the early geographers, not even mentioning Herodotus, he
                    censures Eratosthenes for using unreliable authorities, and for casting doubts
                    on the voyages of Jason and other early navigators. He next criticizes the
                    physical views of Eratosthenes concerning the changes in the earth’s surface,
                    and especially the hypothesis, adopted from Strato, that by sudden disruptions
                    of land the Euxine and Mediterranean had become united to the ocean, and had
                    sunk to their present level, which theory they supported by pointing to sea
                    shells at places high above the sea. This doctrine Strabo rightly rejected, and
                    referred such phenomena to those changes which with constant operation produce
                    subsidences and elevations of the land; and he quotes many instances of places
                    engulfed by earthquakes, the disappearance of some islands, and the appearing of
                    others. Hence he thinks it possible that even Sicily has been thrown up by the
                    fires of Etna. Sir C. Lyell eulogizes Strabo’s geological speculations for a
                    soundness of view very unusual on such subjects amongst the ancients. Examining
                    the second book of Eratosthenes, he discusses the length and breadth of the
                    inhabited world, and its division into three continents. He blames Eratosthenes
                    for believing Pytheas, and denies the existence of Thule, consequently rejecting
                    the latitude assigned to it by Eratosthenes, who had taken it as the
                    northernmost limit of the inhabited world. Strabo holds lerne (Ireland), which
                    lies north of Britain, to be the farthest land in that direction, and brings the
                    northern limit much farther south. As he adopts Eratosthenes’s southern
                    limit,—that through the Cinnamon Region and Taprobane (Ceylon),—it follows that
                    in his view Eratosthenes had made the inhabited world too broad. As the Greeks
                    assumed that the world was twice as long as it was broad, Eratosthenes
                    accordingly had made it too long likewise; but, though Strabo shortens it on the
                    west, there is no material difference between him and Eratosthenes. In this
                    connexion he gives his remarkable speculation that, as the inhabited world was
                    only one-third of the globe’s circumference, there might be two or more
                    inhabited worlds besides. In the second book he discusses the changes introduced
                    by Eratosthenes, and rightly defends him from the attacks of Hipparchus. He
                    adopts for Asia the map of Eratosthenes as a whole, for little additional
                    knowledge had been gained in the interval. He even still regards the Caspian as
                    opening into the Northern Ocean, as stated by Patrocles. In the general outline
                    of Africa he makes no change, but he rejects the statement of Eratosthenes about
                    Cerne. It is with respect to western and northern Europe that Strabo had
                    knowledge denied to Eratosthenes. Roman conquest had opened up many places and
                    peoples, yet his general map of Europe is inferior to that of his predecessor.
                    After discussing the “seals” of Eratosthenes, he considers the views of
                    Posidonius and Polybius, and recounts the voyages of Eudoxus of Cyzicus. Then
                    having dealt with the division into zones, due to Parmenides, he states his own
                    views, discussing briefly the mathematical geography: the earth is spherical and
                    placed in the centre of the universe; he assumes five zones, and the circles on
                    the sphere—the equator, the ecliptic or<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n606/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0606-0583"/> zodiac, the tropics, and the arctic circles;
                    he assumes the earth’s circumference as given by Eratosthenes, 252,000 stades (
                    = 25,200 geographical miles), and his division of the great circle into sixtieth
                    parts; the habitable world, the geographer’s proper province, shaped ike a
                    chlamys, occupies a quadrilateral space in the northern hemisphere, filling
                    little more than one-third of the north temperate zone; its maximum length is
                    70,000 stades, its breadth less than 30,000 stades. Whilst correcting the error
                    by which his predecessors placed Massilia and Byzantium in the same latitude, he
                    falls into an equal mistake by placing the former city two degrees south,
                    instead of two degrees north of Byzantium. As Massilia is his cardinal point for
                    measurements, this error distorts his whole map of the Mediterranean and western
                    Europe, the mouths of the Rhine and Danube being in the same latitude. He next
                    gives directions for making a plane map of the world, as a globe of sufficient
                    size, like that of Crates, is too cumbrous. All lines that are circles on a
                    globe must be straight lines on the map. Before describing each country in
                    detail, he gives a general sketch of the habitable world with reference to seas,
                    continents, and peoples, and explains the doctrine of climate and of the shadows
                    projected by objects in consequence of the sun’s varying position with respect
                    to them. In the third book, starting from the Straits, he begins his description
                    with Iberia, which he likens in shape to a bull’s hide. His chief authorities
                    were Artemidorus, whom he uses for the coasts of the Mediterranean and ocean
                    generally, Eratosthenes, Posidonius, Polybius, Pherecydes, Timosthenes,
                    Asclepiades, Myrleanus, and Dicaearchus. He gives a valuable account of the
                    Roman administrative system, probably gained from his own inquiries, also of the
                    native tribes, of the mines and methods of mining, and of the remains of the
                    Greek and Phoenician settlements; he describes the Balearic Isles, following
                    Artemidorus, and at the end of the book mentions the Cassiterides, which he
                    seems to have identified with the Scilly Isles, probably erroneously, and
                    describes their inhabitants as wearing long black garments, and walking about
                    with long wands in their hands, looking like the Furies of tragedy. It is
                    remarkable that he has no notion of the proximity of the Tin Islands to Britain,
                    but treats them in connexion with Spain. The fourth book deals with Gaul in its
                    fourfold division under Augustus, gives a meagre account of Britain, its trade
                    and relations with Rome, and mentions Ireland, the natives of which were said to
                    be cannibals and to hold their women in common, and finally treats of the Alps.
                    His authorities were Posidonius, who had travelled in Gaul and Britain,
                    Artemidorus, Ephorus, Timagenes, Aristotle, Polybius, Asinius Pollio, and
                    Caesar. For Britain Pytheas, as quoted by others, furnished some important
                    details. His description of Gallia Narbonensis is fuller than that of the rest
                    of Gaul. He mentions the four great Roman roads converging at Lyons, probably
                    following the chorography of Agrippa. He conceives the Pyrenees as running north
                    and south, and parallel to the Rhine, and Britain as lying north of Gaul,
                    extending from the Pyrenees to the Rhine’s mouths. Of the Alpine region he gives
                    an excellent description. He undoubtedly must have gathered much information for
                    this book at Rome. The fifth and sixth books contain an accurate description of
                    Italy and the adjacent islands. Besides his own observation he used
                    Eratosthenes, Polybius, Artemidorus, Ephorus, Fabius Pictor, Coelius, Antiochus
                    of Syracuse for southern Italy, and the “chorographer,” who was certainly a
                    Roman, as he gave his distances in miles, and who probably was Agrippa, the
                    chief objection to such an authorship being the wrong assumption that Strabo was
                    not in Italy after 24 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> whilst Agrippa’s work was
                    not published until after his death 12 B.c. The sixth book ends with a short but
                    valuable sketch of the extent and condition of the Roman empire. The seventh
                    comprises northern and eastern Europe, both north and south of the Danube,
                    Illyricum, Pannonia, Dalmatia, the coast of Thrace and the Euxine, and Epirus.
                    The part which dealt with Macedonia and Thrace is only known to us from the
                    epitomes. We do not know his authorities for the German tribes, but he probably
                    used Roman materials. For the other northern tribes he had Posidonius, whilst
                    for the region south of the Danube he had Aristotle’s lost work on <hi
                        rend="italic">Polities,</hi> Polybius, Posidonius, Theopompus, and Ephorus.
                    The eighth, ninth, and tenth books contain his description of the mainland of
                    Greece and the islands, which he treats rather as an antiquarian than a
                    geographer, using chiefly, besides Homer, Apollodorus. Demetrius of Scepsis,
                    Ephorus, and Eudoxus. Personally he had but little knowledge. With the eleventh
                    begins Asia. Divided from Europe by the Don, it is split up into two large
                    masses by the Taurus. Beginning with the region bounded by the Taurus, Caspian,
                    and Euxine, he next describes the part east of the Caspian, then those south of
                    the Caucasus, Media, and Armenia. His authorities are Artemidorus, Eratosthenes,
                    Theophanes, Herodotus, Apollodorus of Artemita, Patrocles, Metrodorus of
                    Scepsis, Hypsicrates of Amisus, Posidonius, and Aristobulus. In the twelfth he
                    describes Asia Minor, basing his description on oral information, personal
                    observation, and the Greek writers. In the thirteenth he continues with Asia
                    Minor, devoting much space to the Troad, his sources being Demetrius,
                    Menecrates, and the Greek mythographers. With the fourteenth he ends Asia Minor
                    and the islands lying off it, using, in addition to the authorities for the
                    last, Pherecydes, Thucydides, Anaximenes of Lampsacus, Herodotus, Ephorus,
                    Artemidorus, Eratosthenes, and Posidonius. The fifteenth deals with India and
                    Persia, giving much valuable information from Patrocles, Aristobulus, Nearchus,
                    the historians of the campaigns of Alexander and Seleucus, and with reserve from
                    Megasthenes, Onesicritus, Deimachus, and Clitarchus. In the sixteenth he treats
                    of Assyria, under which he includes Babylonia and Mesopotamia, Syria, Phoenicia,
                    Palestine, the Persian Gulf, the Red Sea and the coast of Ethiopia, and Arabia.
                    For Asia he used the historians of Alexander, Eratosthenes and Herodotus; for
                    Judaea and Syria probably Posidonius, himself a native of Apamea; for Arabia and
                    the coast of Libya Eratosthenes and Artemidorus, the latter of whom followed
                    Agatharchides of Cnidus. Strabo must have got many details about Arabia from
                    Aelius Gallus and the Stoic Athenodorus. The last book comprises Egypt,
                    Ethiopia, and the north coast of Libya. He describes Egypt from his own
                    observation, having gained much information at Alexandria in addition to that of
                    Eudoxus, Aristo, Eratosthenes, Polybius, and Posidonius, using the last three
                    with the addition of Iphicrates for Libya, and for Ethiopia Petronius,
                    Herodotus, and Agatharchides. Though probably acquainted with the work of Juba,
                    he did not make much use of it. The book concludes with a summary of the
                    provinces of the Roman empire, as organized by Augustus into senatorial and
                    imperial.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Editions.</hi> —Aldus, Venice, 1516; Hopper and Heresbach,
                    Basel, 1549; Xylander, Basel, 1571; Casaubon, Geneva, 1587, Paris, 1620
                    (Casaubon revised the text); Almeloveen, Amsterdam, 1707, reprinted Casaubon’s
                    text; Falconer, Oxford, 1807, reprinted Almeloveen’s text; Siebenkees and
                    Tzschucke, Leipsic, 1811; Koray, Paris, 1815-18, the first really critical
                    edition; Kramer, Berlin, 1844-52; C. Müller, Paris, 1853; Meineke, Leipsic,
                    1877. <hi rend="smallcaps">Translations.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Latin</hi>:
                    Guarini and Gregorio, 1471; Xylander, 1571. <hi rend="italic">French</hi>: Koray
                    and Letronne, 1805-19. <hi rend="italic">German</hi>: Groskurd, 1833 (with
                    dissertations). <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi>: Ambrosoli, 1828. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Dissertations,</hi> &amp;c.—Bunbury, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ancient Geography,</hi> Heeren; Hasenmüller; Niese, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hermes,</hi> 1878. (W. BI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
