<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0294-0277-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SOUDAN, or Súdán (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    277)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90g4n">Fur</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g34m">Fulahs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xp3b">Mayos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1939238">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936387">Fur</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129153">Speech</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242088">Sahara</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208478">Chad</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205592">Morocco</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n294/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SOUDAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Súdán</hi></label> (Bilád
                    es-Súdán, “Country of the Blacks ”), a term applied by mediaeval Arab
                    geographers to the region of Africa south of the Sahara mainly inhabited by
                    peoples of Negro blood, hence corresponding to the expressions Nigritia,
                    Negroland, at one time current amongst European writers. It lies mainly between
                    5° and 18° N. lat., consequently entirely within the tropics, and in its widest
                    sense stretches right across the continent from Cape Verd on the Atlantic to
                    Massowah on the Red Sea. But the term is more usually restricted to the region
                    bounded N. by the Sahara, S. by Upper Guinea and the lands draining to the Congo
                    basin, W. and E. by Senegambia and the Abyssinian highlands respectively (see
                    vol. i. plate II. ). Within these limits it has an extreme length of about 3000
                    miles between the Senegal river and Abyssinia, extending southwards at some
                    points 660 miles, with a total area of perhaps 2,000,000 square miles, and a
                    population approximately estimated at from 80 to 90 millions. From the arid and
                    sandy northern wastes to the well-watered and arable Soudanese lands the
                    transition is effected by an intermediate zone of level grassy steppes, partly
                    overgrown with mimosas and acacias, with a mean breadth of about 60 miles,
                    between 17° and 18° N. lat., but towards the centre reaching as far south as 15°
                    N. Excluding this somewhat uniform transitional zone, the Soudan, properly so
                    called, may be described as a moderately elevated region, diversified with
                    extensive open or rolling plains, level plateaus, and even true highlands,
                    especially in the south-west. It constitutes three distinct hydrographic
                    systems, corresponding to the three main physical divisions of Western Soudan,
                    draining through the Niger southwards to the Atlantic; Central Soudan, draining
                    to the great central depression and landlocked basin of Lake Tchad; and Eastern
                    (Egyptian) Soudan, draining through the Nile northwards to the Mediterranean.
                    Between these systems the chief water-partings are—(1) the Marrah Mountains of
                    Dar-Fur, whence flow the Bahr es-Salámát west to the Shari, and numerous
                    intermittent wadies east to the Nile; (2) the Monbuttu uplands (Mount Baginze),
                    separating the western headstreams of the White Nile from the Welle (Bahr Kuta),
                    which, according to the latest information, flows, not to the Shari as
                    Schweinfurth supposed, but to the Congo through the Mbangi; (3) the so-called
                    “Kong” Mountains, dividing the Niger basin from the Volta and other streams
                    flowing in independent channels south to the Gulf of Guinea. The Adamawa
                    highlands, culminating in Mount Alantika (9000 to 10,000 feet), do not form a
                    divide, as was supposed, between the Binue (the main eastern tributary of the
                    Niger) and the Logon and other streams flowing east to the Shari (the great
                    southern affluent of Lake Tchad). Flegel, who has recently explored the upper
                    course of the Binue, found that it sweeps right round the east foot of Mount
                    Alantika, and is even navigable round this bend and some way southwards. On the
                    other hand, the central hydrographic system of Lake Tchad has been greatly
                    reduced in size since Lupton, Grenfell, and other recent explorers have made it
                    evident that the Bahr-Kuta (Welle) flows not to the Shari but to the Congo
                    basin. The Shari basin, which is now known not to reach farther south than about
                    6° N. lat., may even be almost considered, physically as well as politically, as
                    subsidiary to the Niger hydrographic system, for there are indications that the
                    Logon once flowed into the Binue by the Mayo-Kebbi. The Mayo-Kebbi is a long
                    flat trough or valley in 9° 30' N. lat., with a level swamp at the bottom
                    receiving as a backwater the overflow of the Logon, and also draining through
                    the Binue to the Niger. By canalizing the Mayo-Kebbi the Binue and Shari basins
                    might be permanently connected, in which case the Niger system would afford a
                    navigable waterway from the Gulf of Guinea to the southernmost limits of
                    Baghirmi.</p>
                <p>From the Kong highlands, some of whose peaks appear to attain elevations of 6000
                    to 7000 feet, Western Soudan falls gradually towards the north and north-east
                    down to the Great Desert, where the city of Timbuktu still maintains an altitude
                    of 770 feet above sea-level (Lenz). Southeast of the Niger the land rises in
                    terraces of 1000 and even 3000 feet, above which isolated crests range from 5000
                    to 9000 feet. This little-known western highland region, comprised between the
                    Binue and the lower Niger,<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n295/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0295-0278"/> and extending from Adamawa to the Cameroons
                    on the Bight of Biafra, corresponds with the eastern highland region of
                    Abyssinia, lying between the Blue Nile and the Tagazze and dominating the Red
                    Sea. North of Adamawa the land falls rapidly down to the vast depression of
                    Central Soudan, whose lowest part is flooded with the waters of Lake Tchad (Chad
                    or Tsad), the largest area of inland drainage, next to the Aral-Caspian basin,
                    in the eastern hemisphere. This freshwater lacustrine depression, usually 10,000
                    square miles in extent, expands to 40,000 and even 50,000 square miles when
                    swollen by the flood-waters of its great feeders,—the Logon-Shari from the south
                    and the Komadugu from the west. From the Tchad depression, which is still 1150
                    feet above the sea, the ground rises again eastwards in the direction of Wadai
                    and Dar-Fur, to heights of 3000 feet and upwards, culminating in the volcanic
                    Jebel Marrah (6000 feet), which forms the natural eastern limit of Central
                    Soudan, and the great divide between the Tchad and Nile basins. But politically
                    the line between Central and Eastern Soudan is usually drawn more to the west
                    along the conventional frontiers of Wadai and Dar-Fur, the latter province,
                    although never completely reduced, being claimed as part of Egyptian Soudan.
                    This region constitutes two distinct physical divisions,—the first comprising
                    the provinces of Dar-Fur and Kordofan, bounded E. by the White Nile and S. by
                    the Bahr el-Arab, a tableland in which the steppe formation predominates, while
                    the second is skirted east by the Bahr el-Jebel and stretches from the Bahr
                    el-Arab southwards to the Monbuttu uplands, a vast plain watered by the numerous
                    south-western headstreams of the White Nile. This plain rises gradually towards
                    the south and south-west to the highlands, which appear to culminate in Mount
                    Baginze, and which form the water-parting between the Nile and Congo basins.
                    Included in Eastern Soudan is also the extensive plain of Senaar, stretching
                    from the Nile eastwards to the Abyssinian uplands, and rising southwards to the
                    Fazokl and Berta highlands.</p>
                <p>The prevailing geological formations are the crystalline rocks, such as granites,
                    diorites, slates, gneiss, underlying the old and new alluvia of the plains, and
                    found associated with sandstones in the highlands. In the Kong Mountains the
                    granites underlie the sandstones, but in the Tagalé group (South Kordofan) they
                    pass over to porphyries and syenites, interspersed with extensive diorites and
                    auriferous quartz veins. Volcanic rocks (basalts, lavas, tufas) appear to be
                    restricted to the isolated Defafaung and Alantika Mountains (Adamawa), although
                    solfataras occur in the Tagalé district, where sulphur abounds. Mineral waters
                    are also found in Dar-Fur and Adamawa. The most widely diffused minerals are
                    iron and copper, the oxides of iron occurring almost everywhere from the White
                    Nile to the Niger, while pure copper is met especially in Dar-Fur and Fertit.
                    Gold is chiefly restricted to the Tagalé and Kong Mountains, Bambarra, and
                    Adamawa; and lead, antimony, and tin are confined to a few isolated districts.
                    Characteristic is the apparently total absence of limestones, coal, salt, and
                    natron, the supplies of salt being imported mainly from the Sahara. Report,
                    however, speaks of a large lake in the Jebel Marrah, from which salt is
                    obtained.</p>
                <p>The climate of Soudan is distinctly tropical, with two well-defined seasons, hot
                    and rainy from April or May to October, warm and dry for the rest of the year.
                    The former is accompanied by tremendous thunderstorms and continuous downpours
                    flushing all the khors, wadies, and other watercourses, flooding large tracts
                    along the lower courses of the Shari, Logon, Komadugu, and Niger, and
                    interrupting the communications for weeks together in Baghirmi and Bornu. Before
                    the rains set in the glass seldom falls below 98° or 100° F., rising at noon to
                    104°, while the mean annual temperature at Kuka (Bornu) is about 82° F. But in
                    the dry season it is often lowered to 58° or 60°, and under the influence of the
                    cool north-east winds water often freezes on the uplands, snow falls in Dar-Fur,
                    and fires are kept up in the houses in the central districts of Kano. The chief
                    ailments are ague and other marsh fevers in the low-lying tracts subject to
                    inundations, the Guinea-worm, cutaneous diseases, and leprosy. The fevers are
                    dangerous alike to Europeans and natives.</p>
                <p>An exuberant forest vegetation is favoured by the rich alluvial soil and tropical
                    heat wherever moisture abounds. Of large growths the most characteristic and
                    widespread are—the baobab <hi rend="italic">{Adansonia),</hi> reaching north to
                    the 13th parallel and attaining a girth of 80 feet; the superb deleb palm,
                    covering extensive tracts especially in the east, where it grows to a height of
                    over 120 feet; the shea or butter tree (<hi rend="italic">Bassia
                        butyracea),</hi> in the Niger basin and Kong uplands; the cotton-tree, dum
                    palm, tamarind, several varieties of euphorbias, acacias, and mimosas, the
                    heglyg (<hi rend="italic">Balanites aegyptiaca),</hi> and jerjak of Wadai, which
                    yields a kind of vegetable honey. Owing to the absence of salt the date-palm is
                    very rare. The chief cultivated plants are cotton, maize, several kinds of
                    durrah <hi rend="italic">{Sorghum vulgare, S. cernuum,</hi> &amp;c.), hemp,
                    tobacco, gourds, water-melons, indigo (of excellent quality and growing
                    everywhere, wild and cultivated), and lastly the guru or kola nut (<hi
                        rend="italic">Sterculia acuminata</hi> and <hi rend="italic">S.
                        macrocarpa),</hi> which in Soudan takes the place of the coffee berry.
                    Cotton of the finest quality has been raised on the rich alluvial plain of Taka
                    and Senaar.</p>
                <p>The beasts of prey, nowhere very numerous, are chiefly represented by the lion,
                    panther, hyaena, aud jackal. Elephants in herds of 400 or 500 frequent the
                    swampy districts about Lake Tchad, but are not found farther north than the 12th
                    or 13th parallel. The ordinary African rhinoceros is common, and the rare
                    one-liorned species appears to have been met with in Wadai. The wild ass, zebra,
                    giraffe, and antelopes in considerable variety abound on the eastern steppe
                    lands, and endless species of monkeys in the forest districts. Crocodiles, some
                    of great size, from 16 to 18 feet long, infest all the large rivers, the
                    sangwai, —a web-footed variety, occurring in the Niger. The hippopotamus also
                    abounds in these waters, which teem with fish, mostly of unknown species. These
                    attract numerous flocks of waterfowl,—pelicans, spoonbills, cranes, ducks, and
                    many unknown species. In the Tchad, Fittri, and other districts the fish are
                    captured, dried, and exported in large quantities to Fezzan and the countries
                    beyond the Niger. Flies and mosquitoes swarm in the marshy, and locusts in the
                    dry districts; and in the woodlands insect life is represented by myriads of
                    termites and some very large species of bees, wasps, and ants, besides beetles
                    and butterflies in considerable variety.</p>
                <p>The term Bílad es-Súdán is fully justified by the ethnical conditions of this
                    region, which may be regarded as the true home of the Negro variety of mankind.
                    Here this still everywhere forms the substratum of the population, constituting
                    the distinct aboriginal element, in many places exclusively, in others
                    intermingled with foreign intruders from the north and east. As far as can now
                    be determined, these intruders belong to two separate branches of the Caucasic
                    stock—the Hamitic and the Semitic. The Hamitic is represented by three
                        divisions—Fulahs,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                ><p><hi rend="italic">Most ethnologists, adopting Fr. Müller’s
                                general classification, group the Fulahs with the Nubians in a
                                separate division (“Nuba-Fulah family”), and class the Tibus ns
                                Negroes. But more recent research has shown—(1) that the Fulahs and
                                Nubians differ fundamentally in speech and physique, the former
                                being of Caucasie and the latter of Negro type (Krause, Rüppel), and
                                (2) that the true Tibus, the Tedas of Tibesti as distinguished from
                                the Dasas or southern group, are not Negroes but Hamites, akin to
                                the Tuaregs of the Western Sahara, although the two languages are
                                totally distinct (Nachtigal). The Tibu language has been described
                                as a Negro form of speech; but this is also a mistake. It forms an
                                independent linguistic group, the oldest and purest branch of which
                                is that of the Northern Tedas. From Tibesti it appears to have
                                spread southwards to Kanem and Bornu, where the Dasa, Kanuri, and
                                other dialects have been exposed to Negro influences. Had Tibu been
                                originally a Negro language, its most primitive form would be found,
                                not in Tibesti, but in Soudan, and its progress would have been
                                thence northwards, not from the Sahara southwards.</hi></p></note>
                    Tibus, and Berbers—all of whom arrived in remote prehistoric times; the Semitic
                    by one division—the Arabs, who arrived at various periods since the spread of
                    Islam in North Africa. The bulk of the Arab tribes appear to have penetrated
                    from the Nile basin through Kordofan to Dar-Fur and Wadai, or from the
                    Mediterranean seaboard through Fezzan and across the Sahara to the Tchad basin,
                    and hence are still mostly restricted to the central and eastern districts.
                    Owing to their later appearance and stronger racial sentiment they have kept
                    more aloof from the surrounding populations than the Hamites, who have
                    everywhere intermingled with the aboriginal Negro element. The result is that
                    the present inhabitants of Soudan are of a very mixed character,—more or less
                    pure Negro peoples predominating in the Niger basin, in Adamawa, Baghirmi,
                    Wadai, parts of DarFur and Kordofan, and in the Nile basin south of 10° north
                    latitude; half-caste Negroes and Fulahs especially in Western Soudan; half-caste
                    Negroes and Berbers in the northern districts of Western and Central Soudan;
                    half-caste Negroes and Tibus (Dasas) mainly in Kanem and Bornu; true Fulahs
                    scattered in isolated groups between the Niger and Tchad basins; true Berbers
                    (Tuaregs) in the Timbuktu and Moassina districts; true Arabs chiefly in
                    Baghirmi, Wadai, Dar-Fur, and Kordofan.</p>
                <p>In the subjoined table of the chief Soudanese races the Negro divisions have
                    little more than a linguistic value.</p>
                <p>Negro and Negroid Peoples.</p>
                <p>Mandingoes <hi rend="italic">: Madinka, Malinka, and in the east Vangarawa, the
                        dominant race between the Joliba (Upper Niger) and Kong Mountains, where
                        their simple and harmonious speech is everywhere current as the chief medium
                        of intercourse; tine Negro type, tall, very dark complexion from
                        coffee-brown to black, long frizzly and woolly hair; agriculturists and
                        traders; mostly Mohammedans outwardly; population six to eight millions.
                        Chief subdivision the Bambarras, whose capital is Sego on the Joliba;
                        population 2,000,000.</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n296/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0922-0296-0279"/> Sonrhai <hi rend="italic">or</hi> Songhai <hi
                        rend="italic">: An historical race whose empire stretched in the 16th
                        century from the northern bend of the Niger to the Atlantic and Morocco;
                        speech of a monosyllabic type, still current in the Timbuktu district and
                        oases of Western Sahara; population 2,000,000.</hi></p>
                <p>Tombo, Mosso, Gurma <hi rend="italic">: Three little known Negro peoples west of
                        the Niger, within the great bend; affinities uncertain; form
                        semi-independent petty states, apparently tributary to Moassina and
                        Gando.</hi></p>
                <p>Nupe <hi rend="italic">or</hi> Nufe: <hi rend="italic">Large Negro nation along
                        both sides of the Niger from Rabba to the Binue confluence, subject to
                        Gando.</hi></p>
                <p>Yoruba <hi rend="italic">; Powerful Negro people between lower Niger and Dahomey;
                        capital Ilosin; Mohammedans, pagans, and Christians (Protestant).</hi></p>
                <p>Batta·. <hi rend="italic">The chief Negro people in Adamawa, now subject to the
                        Fulahs; pagans and Mohammedans.</hi></p>
                <p>Haussa <hi rend="italic">: Largest, most widespread, and intelligent of all the
                        Sudanese Negro peoples, mainly between the Niger and Bornu; speech very
                        musical, the chief commercial medium in Western and Central Soudan, and
                        current in parts of Tripolitana; shows distinct traces of Hamitic influences
                        (Krause); mostly Mohammedans.</hi></p>
                <p>Mosgu <hi rend="italic">or</hi> Masa <hi rend="italic">; widespread Negro family
                        between Lake Tchad and Adamawa and stretching east to the Shari; chief
                        subdivisions—Mandara, Margi, Logon, Gamergu, Margomi, Keribina; mostly
                        pagans and uncultured.</hi></p>
                <p>Yedina (Buduma) <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Kuri <hi rend="italic">: Predatory
                        Negro tribes in the islands of Lake Tchad; appear to be related to the
                        Kolokos or Mekari of Logon and Bornu; nominal Mohammedans; population
                        30,000.</hi></p>
                <p>Baghirmi·. <hi rend="italic">The dominant people in Baghirmi; cultured
                        Mohammedans; very industrious and skilled weavers and dyers; population over
                        a million.</hi></p>
                <p>Maha; <hi rend="italic">The chief Negro nation in Wadai, mainly in the Wara and
                        Abeshr districts, about the headstreams of the Batha.</hi></p>
                <p>Fur <hi rend="italic">or</hi> For <hi rend="italic">; The dominant race in
                        Dar-Fur, which takes its name from them; akin to the Nubas; chief
                        subdivision Kunjara.</hi></p>
                <p>Nubas <hi rend="italic">; Large Negro nation; Jebel Nuba, and other parts of
                        Kordofan, the original stock of the Nile Nubians; chief subdivisions—Kargo,
                        Kulfan, Kolaji, Tumali.</hi></p>
                <p>Nilotic Negroes ·. <hi rend="italic">Shilluks, Dinkas, Bongos, Baris, A-Madi
                        (Mittu), and many others about the Bahr el-Jebel and south-western
                        tributaries of the white Nile.</hi></p>
                <p>Funj <hi rend="italic">: A very mixed Negroid race, Senaar.</hi></p>
                <p>Hamites—Pure and Mixed.</p>
                <p>Tuaregs <hi rend="italic">: A main branch of the Berber race, dominant throughout
                        the Western Sahara and southern steppes; powerful, especially in the
                        Timbuktu district and on the north frontier of Bornu.</hi></p>
                <p>Sorinka <hi rend="italic">or</hi> Assuanek <hi rend="italic">: Called also
                        Serekuli or Serrakolet,</hi> i.e., <hi rend="italic">“white people ”;
                        half-caste Tuareg and Negro nation scattered in small communities front the
                        Niger to the Atlantic, and numerous especially in Senegambia and Moassina;
                        cuitured Mohammedans, and active traders.</hi></p>
                <p>Fulahs <hi rend="italic">: The most powerful, intelligent, and widespread of all
                        the Soudanese peoples; from their original home in Senegambia (Futa-Toro,
                        Futa-Jallo) have spread since the 18th century throughout Western and
                        Central Soudan, and as far east as Dar-Fur, everywhere propagating Islam,
                        overthrowing the native Haussa and other states, and founding new kingdoms
                        in the Niger basin, in Adamawa, and Central Soudan; are called Fellani by
                        the Haussas, Fulda by the Arabs, Felláta by the Kanuri, the term meaning
                        “fair” or “light coloured "; pure type, distinctly Caucasic, regular
                        features, long black hair, brown or ruddy complexion, slim well-proportioned
                        figures; but the language, which presents several remarkable features, shows
                        only faint traces of Berber influence, and appears on the whole to be
                        essentially a Negro form of speech, adopted probably during residence from
                        the remotest times in Negroland; population seven to eight
                    millions.</hi></p>
                <p>Dasas: <hi rend="italic">The southern branch of the Tibus, chiefly in Kanem and
                        northern Bornu; type and speech show distinct Negro influences.</hi></p>
                <p>Kanembu: <hi rend="italic">The people of Kanem, with settlements in eastern
                        Bornu; also originally Tibus, but betraying still more decided Negro
                        influence.</hi></p>
                <p>Kanuri <hi rend="italic">: The ruling race in Bornu; speech a development of the
                        Dasa and Kanem; type half-caste Tibu and Negro.</hi></p>
                <p>Zogháwa, Baele, Ennedi <hi rend="italic">; Mixed Tibu and Negro tribes; northern
                        Dar-Fur, originally from Borku and Wanganya, Eastern Sahara; speech akin to
                        Dasa.</hi></p>
                <p>Semites.</p>
                <p>Aulád Soleimán Arabs <hi rend="italic">: In Kanem.</hi></p>
                <p>Aulád Rashid, Mahámid: <hi rend="italic">South-east of Borku, and in
                        Dar-Fur.</hi></p>
                <p>Salámát, Aulád Hamed <hi rend="italic">: Between the lower Shari and Bahr
                        el-Ghazál.</hi></p>
                <p>Hamr, Hamrán <hi rend="italic">: Kordofan.</hi></p>
                <p>Kababish: <hi rend="italic">“Goatherds ;” widespread along west side Nile, from
                        Kordofan to Dongola.</hi></p>
                <p>Bakkára <hi rend="italic">: “Cowherds;” south of the Kababish to left bank of
                        Bahr el-Arab.</hi></p>
                <p>Politically Western and Central Soudan are divided into eight independent and
                    semi-independent states, which in their order from west to east are as under:
                    —</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bambarra,</hi> divided into two nearly equal sections by the
                    Joliba, which traverses it from south-west to north-east, is ruled by the Negro
                    Bambarras of Mandingo stock. It has recently been brought under the influence of
                    the French penetrating eastwards from their possessions on the Senegal. The
                    capital is Sego, on the right bank of the Joliba.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Moassina, Gando, Sokoto, Adamawa,</hi> the four so-called
                    “Fulah States,” occupy the Niger basin between Bambarra and the Binue
                    confluence, the whole of the Binue basin, and the region lying between the Niger
                    and Bornu. <hi rend="italic">Moassina</hi> (Massina) lies on both banks of the
                    Niger from Bambarra to Kabara, the port of Timbuktu, and is peopled by Fulahs,
                    Bambarras, and Sonrhais; capital Hamda-Alahi, on the right bank of the Niger,
                    below Jenne, which is its chief trading place. Timbuktu, with surrounding
                    district constitutes a separate territory governed by a kadia, or hereditary
                    mayor, who lately sent an envoy to Paris for the purpose of seeking French
                    protection against the rival Tuareg and Fulah tribes. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gando,</hi> so called from its capital on an eastern tributary of the
                    Niger, stretches along the main stream southwards to the Binue confluence,
                    including the Nufe territory and part of Yoruba. The lower part is extremely
                    fertile, abounding in cotton, indigo, rice, and all varieties of African grains.
                    It comes within the limits of the region over which the British protectorate has
                    recently been extended. Besides the capital, there are several large towns, such
                    as Bida (30,000 to 50,000 inhabitants) in the north; Rabba (40,000 to 50,000),
                    head of the steam navigation on the Niger, and a chief station on the great
                    trade route running from Lagos on the</p>
                <p>Guinea Coast northwards to Gando and Sokoto; Egga (8000), on the left bank of the
                    Niger, centre of the British trade; Lokoja, facing the Binue confluence, an
                    English factory, headquarters of an Anglican mission and seat of a Negro bishop.
                        <hi rend="italic">Sokoto,</hi> sometimes spoken of as the “empire of
                    Sokoto,” is the largest and most powerful of all the Soudanese states,
                    stretching from Gando to Bornu, and from the Binue northwards to the Sahara (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sokoto).</hi> In it are absorbed all the former “Haussa
                    States,” and to it Adamawa is also tributary. The inhabitants are chiefly Fulahs
                    and Haussas, intermixed with many aboriginal Negro peoples, especially in the
                    south and south-east. The land is generally fertile, yielding rich crops of
                    cereals, cotton, tobacco, indigo, sugar, yams, black pepper, ginger, melons. The
                    capital and residence of the sultan is Sokoto, in the extreme north-west. Other
                    large towns are—Katsena, before the Fulah invasion a place of 100,000
                    inhabitants, now reduced to 7000; Kano, in Barth’s time the “London of Soudan,”
                    and still with 50,000 souls (Matteucci); Wurnu (15,000); Gombe, in the province
                    of Calam (20,000); Yakoba, or Garu n-Bauchi (150,000); Keffi Abd es-Senga
                    (30,000), in Zegzeg, a great centre of the ivory trade, and converging point of
                    the two great caravan routes from the north (Kano) and the west (Egga). <hi
                        rend="italic">Adamawa,</hi> so named from its Fulah conqueror Adama, and
                    formerly known as Fumbina, or “Southland,” is ruled by a Fulah vassal of Sokoto,
                    who keeps in subjection the Battas and innumerable other Negro peoples; it lies
                    between Sokoto, Bornu, and Baghirmi, merging southwards in the unexplored
                    equatorial region back of the Cameroons. The capital is Yola, at the northern
                    foot of Mount Alantika. Adamawa appears to be one of the finest and healthiest
                    regions in Africa, splendidly diversified with lofty highlands, fertile valleys,
                    and grassy plains, overgrown in some places with forests of bananas, baobabs,
                    and plantains, in others yielding abundant harvests of cereals, cotton, and
                    indigo. The horses and cattle introduced by the Fulahs thrive well on the rich
                    pastures, and elephants abound in the woodlands.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bornu,</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Kanem,</hi> in the north,
                    now reduced, and the tributary state of <hi rend="italic">Logon</hi> in the
                    south, completely encircles Lake Tchad, except at the south-east corner, where
                    Baghirmi is wedged in between Logon and Wadai; it is mostly a flat low-lying
                    region with fertile plains yielding durrah, maize, cotton, and indigo, watered
                    by the Komadugu, Logon, and Shari, all of which flood their banks for miles
                    during the rainy season. The ruling race are the Kanuri, cultured but fanatical
                    Mohammedans of mixed Tibu and Negro stock. The capital of Bornu is Kuka (50,000
                    to 60,000 inhabitants), near the west coast of Lake Tchad, a great centre of the
                    Soudanese trade with the Sahara and Tripolitana, and terminus of the main
                    caravan route from Murzuk (Fezzan) across the desert to the Tchad basin; the
                    capital of Logon is Logon-birni, residence of a vassal prince. Population of
                    Bornu estimated at 5,000,000.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Baghirmi,</hi> a Negro state, since 1871 tributary to Wadai,
                    comprises the rich and well-watered plains of the lower Shari, with undefined
                    southern limits. Capital Masena; population about 1,500,000, of whom
                    three-fourths Baghirmi, the rest Kotokos, Fulahs, and Arabs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wadai,</hi> a powerful Mohammedan state occupying the whole
                    region between Baghirmi and Kanem in the west and Dar-Fur in the east, and
                    claiming exclusive ivory and slave-hunting rights in the southern (upper) Shari
                    basin. The capital is Abeshr, on a head-stream of the Batha. The country is
                    mainly a hilly plateau rising to 3000 feet above the sea, and yielding good
                    crops of maize, dukhn, durrah, cotton, indigo. Population four to six millions,
                    chiefly Mabas and other Negroes, and numerous Arab tribes, with some scattered
                    Baghirmi, Fulah, and Kanuri settlements.</p>
                <p>Eastern Soudan, comprising Dar-Fur, Kordofan, Senaar, Taka, and the Negro
                    countries on the White Nile and its south-western tributaries, respectively
                    called the Equatorial and Bahr-Gazal Provinces, belonged politically to Egypt
                    till the rebellion of the late Mahdi. Since his death in 1885 most of these
                    provinces appear to have lapsed into a state of anarchy and barbarism, in which
                    few vestiges remain of the peace and order introduced by the European officers
                    of the khedive. The Equatorial Province, however, and the Suakin district have
                    been exempt from these troubles,—the former being still held till 1886 by the
                    governor, Emin Bey, for the khedive, while in the latter the natives themselves
                    succeeded in the same year in putting down the “rebels” or party of Osman Digma.
                    For details of Eastern Soudan, see articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Nile,
                        Nubia,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Senaar.</hi> (A. H. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
