<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0922-0435-0412-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPOLETO (9th edition, volume 22, page 412)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n435/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPOLETO</label> (Lat. <hi rend="italic">Spoletium),</hi> a
                    city of Italy, in Umbria, placed in a commanding position near the Via Flaminia,
                    between Rome and Perugia, is said to have been colonized in 240 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> (Liv., <hi rend="italic">Epit., xx.;</hi> Vell.
                    Pat., i. 14), and is called by Cicero <hi rend="italic">(Pro Balb.,</hi> 21)
                    “colonia Latina in primis firma et illustris.” After the battle of Trasimenus
                    (217 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> Spoletium was attacked by Hannibal, who was
                    repulsed by the inhabitants (Liv., xxii. 9). During the Second Punic War the
                    city was a useful ally to Rome. It suffered greatly during the civil wars of
                    Marius and Sulla. The latter, after his victory over Crassus, confiscated the
                    territory of Spoletium and reduced it to the rank of a military colony. Under
                    the empire it again became a flourishing town (Strabo, v. p. 227; Plin., <hi
                        rend="italic">H.N.,</hi> iii. 14; Ptol., iii.</p>
                <p>1, 54). Owing to its elevated position it was an important stronghold during the
                    Vandal and Gothic wars; its walls were dismantled by Totila (Procop., <hi
                        rend="italic">Bell. Get.,</hi> iii. 12). Under the Lombards Spoleto became
                    the capital of an independent duchy (from <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 570), and
                    its dukes ruled a considerable part of central Italy. Together with other fiefs,
                    it was bequeathed to Pope Gregory VII. by the empress Matilda, but for some time
                    struggled to maintain its independence. In 1881 it had a population of 7969
                    (commune, 21,507), many of whom are occupied in the weaving of woollen stuffs.
                    It is the seat of an archbishopric for the three dioceses of Spoleto, Bevagna,
                    and Trevi.</p>
                <p>The city contains many interesting ancient remains,—traces of an early polygonal
                    wall, a Roman theatre, and parts of three temples, built into the churches of S.
                    Agostino, S. Andrea, and S. Giuliano. Remains of a fine Roman bridge were found
                    a few years ago buried in the former bed of a torrent, which now runs along a
                    different line. These remains have recently been buried again under a newly made
                    road. On the citadel, which commands the town, still stands an ancient castle,
                    originally built by Theodoric. This castle was mostly destroyed by the Goths,
                    but was afterwards rebuilt and enlarged at many different times, especially by
                    Pope Nicholas V. The existing building contains work of many different dates.
                    The cathedral of S. Maria Assunta dates partly from the time of the Lombard
                    duchy, but was much modernized in 1644. Over the main entrance is a very
                    interesting and large mosaic of Christ in Majesty signed “Salsernus,” 1207; at
                    the sides are figures of the Virgin and St John. In the choir and on the half
                    cupola of the apse are some of the finest frescos of Lippo Lippi, representing
                    scenes from the life of the Virgin. Lippo died in 1469, leaving part of the work
                    to be completed by his assistant Fra Diamante. The fine stalls and panelling in
                    the choir are attributed to Bramante. The church of S. Pietro is a fine early
                    example of Lombard architecture, though much modernized. The façade is
                    remarkable for its rich sculptured decorations of grotesque figures, dragons,
                    and foliage. S. Domenico is a fine example of later Italian Gothic with bands of
                    different coloured stones. The three-apsed crypt of the church of S. Gregorio is
                    of great interest; it probably dates from the founding of the church in the 9th
                    century. S. Niccolo is a beautiful example of Pointed Gothic.</p>
                <p>The city is still supplied with water by a grand aqueduct (see vol. ii. pl. IV.)
                    across the adjacent gorge; it has stone piers and brick arches, and is about 268
                    feet high and 676 feet long. It is said to have been built in 604 by
                    Theodelapius, the third Lombard duke, and the stone piers belong probably to
                    that time. The brick arches are later restorations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
