<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0169-0154-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SLEEP</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 154</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="83" ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15r77">Sleep</term>
                    <term n="31" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cb2k">Brain</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg38">Dreams</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="83" ref="fasttopic:1120819">Sleep</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term n="31" ref="fasttopic:837570">Brain</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1198490">Dreams</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n169/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SLEEP</label> is a normal condition of the body, occurring
                    periodically, in which there is a greater or less degree of unconsciousness due
                    to inactivity of the nervous system and more especially of the brain and spinal
                    cord. It may be regarded as the condition of rest of the nervous system during
                    which there is a renewal of the energy that has been expended in the hours of
                    wakefulness. For in the nervous system the general law holds good that periods
                    of physiological rest must alternate with periods of physiological activity,
                    and, as the nervous system is the dominating mechanism in the body, when it
                    reposes, all the other systems enjoy the same condition to a greater or less
                    extent. Rest alternates with work in all vital phenomena. After a muscle has
                    contracted frequently at short intervals, a period of relaxation is necessary
                    for the removal of waste products and the restitution of energy; the pulsating
                    heart, apparently working without intermission, is in reality not doing so, as
                    there are short intervals of relaxation between individual beats in which there
                    is no expenditure of energy; the cells in a secreting gland do not always
                    elaborate, but have periods when the protoplasm is comparatively at rest.
                    Nervous action also involves physico-chemical changes of matter and the
                    expenditure of energy. This is true even of the activity of the brain associated
                    with sensation, perception, emotion, volition, and other psychical phenomena,
                    and therefore the higher nervous centres require rest, during which they are
                    protected from the stream of impressions flowing in from the sense-organs, and
                    in which waste matters are removed and the cerebral material is recuperated for
                    another time of wakeful activity.</p>
                <p>The coincidence of the time of sleep with the occurrence of the great terrestrial
                    phenomena that cause night is more apparent than real. The oscillations of vital
                    activity are not correlated to the terrestrial revolutions as effect and cause,
                    but the occurrence of sleep, in the majority of cases, on the advent of night is
                    largely the result of habit. Whilst the darkness and stillness of night are
                    favourable to sleep, the state of physiological repose is determined more by the
                    condition of the body itself. Fatigue will normally cause sleep at any time of
                    the twenty-four hours. Thus many of the lower animals habitually sleep during<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0170-0155"/> the day and prowl in search of food in the night;
                    some hibernate during the winter season, passing into long periods of sleep
                    during both day and night; and men whose avocations require them to work during
                    the night find that they can maintain health and activity by sleeping the
                    requisite time during the day.</p>
                <p>The approach of sleep is usually marked by a desire for sleep, or sleepiness,
                    embracing an obscure and complicated group of sensations, resembling such bodily
                    states of feeling as hunger, thirst, the necessity of breathing, Ac. All of
                    these bodily states, although on the whole ill defined, are referred with some
                    precision to special organs. Thus hunger, although due to a general bodily want,
                    is referred to the stomach, thirst to the fauces, and breathing to the chest;
                    and in like manner the desire for sleep is referred chiefly to the region of the
                    head and neck. There is a sensation of weight in the upper eyelids, intermittent
                    spasm of the sub-hyoid muscles causing yawning, and drooping of the head. Along
                    with these signs there is obscuration of the intelligence, depression both of
                    general sensibility and of the special senses, and relaxation of the muscular
                    system. The half-closed eyelids tend more and more to close; the inspirations
                    become slower and deeper; the muscles supporting the lower jaw become relaxed,
                    so that the mouth opens; the muscles of the back of the neck that tend to
                    support the head also relax and the chin droops on the breast; and the limbs
                    relax and tend to fall into a line with the body. At the same time the
                    hesitating utterances of the sleepy man indicate vagueness of thought, and
                    external objects gradually cease to make an impression on the senses. These are
                    the chief phenomena of the advent of sleep. After it has supervened there are
                    many gradations in its depth and character. In some cases the sleep may be so
                    light that the individual is partially conscious of external impressions and of
                    the disordered trains of thought and feeling that pass through his mind,
                    constituting dreams, and these may be more or less vivid according to the degree
                    of consciousness remaining. On the other hand, the sleep may be so profound as
                    to abolish all psychical phenomena: there are no dreams, and when the sleeper
                    awakes the time passed in this unconscious state is a blank. The first period of
                    sleep is the most profound. After a variable period, usually from five to six
                    hours of deep sleep, the faculties awaken, not simultaneously but often
                    fitfully, so that there are transient periods of consciousness. This is the time
                    of dreaming. As the period of waking approaches the sensibility becomes more
                    acute, so that external impressions are faintly perceived. These impressions may
                    influence and mould the flow of images in the mind of the sleeper, frequently
                    altering the nature of his dreams or making them more vivid. The moment of
                    waking is usually not instantaneous, but is preceded by an intermediate state of
                    partial consciousness, in which there are feelings of a pleasant lassitude, a
                    sense of repose, a luxurious abandonment of the body to any position in which it
                    may happen to be, and a strange play of the mental faculties that has more of
                    the character of an “intellectual mirage” than of consecutive thought.</p>
                <p>The intensity of sleep has been measured by Kohlschütter by the intensity of the
                    sound necessary to awaken the sleeper. This intensity increases rapidly during
                    the first hour, then decreases, sometimes rapidly, sometimes slowly, during the
                    next two or three hours, and then very slowly until the time of waking. This
                    statement agrees generally with experience. As a rule the deeper the sleep the
                    longer it lasts.</p>
                <p>Various physiological changes have been observed during sleep, but much remains
                    to be done in this direction. The pulse becomes less frequent; the respiratory
                    movements are fewer in number and are almost wholly thoracic, not abdominal; all
                    the secretions are reduced in quantity; the gastric and intestinal peristaltic
                    movements are less rapid; the pupils of the eye are contracted and during
                    profound sleep are not affected by light; and the eyeballs are rotated upwards.
                    The pupils dilate slightly when strong sensory or auditory stimuli are applied,
                    and they dilate the more the lighter the sleep; at the moment of waking they
                    become widely dilated. Whilst muscular relaxation is general, there seems to be
                    increased contraction of certain sphincter muscles, as the circular fibres of
                    the iris and the fibres concerned in closing the eyelids. The state of the
                    circulation of the brain has been frequently investigated. The older view was
                    that there was a degree of plethora or congestion of the vessels of the brain,
                    as is the state of matters in coma, to which the state of sleep has a
                    superficial resemblance. Coma, however, is not sleep, but a condition of
                    inactivity of the cerebral matter owing to the accumulation of dark venous blood
                    in its vessels. This has been actually observed in cases where it was possible
                    to see the brain. During sleep the surface of the exposed brain has been
                    observed to become pale and to shrink somewhat from the sides of the opening
                    (Blumenbach). A careful experimental research was conducted by Arthur E. Durham
                    in 1860, in which he trephined a portion of bone as large as a shilling from the
                    parietal region of a dog, and, to obviate the effects of atmospheric pressure,
                    inserted a watch glass into the aperture so that the surface of the brain could
                    be seen. His results are summarized thus :—</p>
                <p>“ (1) Pressure of distended veins on the brain is not the cause of sleep, for
                    during sleep the veins are not distended; and, when they are, symptoms and
                    appearances arise which differ from those which characterize sleep. (2) During
                    sleep the brain is in a comparatively bloodless condition, and the blood in the
                    encephalic vessels is not only diminished in quantity, but moves with diminished
                    rapidity. (3) The condition of the cerebral circulation during sleep is, from
                    physical causes, that which is most favourable to the nutrition of the brain
                    tissue; and, on the other hand, the condition which prevails during waking is
                    associated with mental activity, because it is that which is most favourable to
                    oxidation of the brain substance, and to various changes in its chemical
                    constitution. (4) The blood which is derived from the brain during sleep is
                    distributed to the alimentary and excretory organs. (5) Whatever increases the
                    activity of the cerebral circulation tends to preserve wakefulness; and whatever
                    decreases the activity of the cerebral circulation, and, at the same time, is
                    not inconsistent with the general health of the body, tends to induce and favour
                    sleep. Such circumstances may act primarily through the nervous or through the
                    vascular system. Among those which act through the nervous system may be
                    instanced the presence or absence of impressions upon the senses, and the
                    presence or absence of exciting ideas. Among those which act through the
                    vascular system may be mentioned unnaturally or naturally increased or decreased
                    force or frequency of the heart’s action.”</p>
                <p>Dr William A. Hammond and Dr Weir Mitchell have repeated and extended Durham’s
                    observations, with the same general results (1866), and more recently Ehrmann,
                    Salathé (1877), François Franck (1877), and Mosso (1881), by more refined
                    methods of observation, have arrived at the same general conclusions. Mosso in
                    particular has applied with great success the graphic method of registration to
                    the study of the movements of the brain and of the circulation during sleep. He
                    made observations on three persons who had lost a portion of the cranial vault
                    and in whom there was a soft pulsating cicatrix. They were a woman of
                    thirty-seven years of age, a man of thirty-seven years, and a child of about
                    twelve years. By special arrangements, Mosso took simultaneous tracings of the
                    pulse at the wrist, of the beat of the heart, of the movements of the wall of
                    the chest in respiration, and of the movements of the denuded brain. Further, by
                    means of the plethysmograph,—an instrument of Mosso’s own invention,—he obtained
                    tracings showing changes in the volume of the hand and forearm; and he succeeded
                    in showing that during sleep there is a diminished amount<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0171-0156"/> of blood in the brain, and at the same time an
                    increased amount in the extremities. He showed further that there are frequent
                    adjustments in the distribution of the blood, even during sleep. Thus a strong
                    stimulus to the skin or to a sense organ—but not strong enough to awaken the
                    sleeper—caused a contraction of the vessels of the forearm, an increase of blood
                    pressure, and a determination of blood towards the brain; and, on the other
                    hand, on suddenly awakening the sleeper, there was a contraction of the vessels
                    of the brain, a general rise of pressure, and an accelerated flow of blood
                    through the hemispheres of the brain. So sensitive is the whole organism in this
                    respect, even during sleep, that a loudly spoken word, a sound, a touch, the
                    action of light, or any moderate sensory impression modified the rhythm of
                    respiration, determined a contraction of the vessels of the forearm, increased
                    the general pressure of the blood, caused an increased flow to the brain, and
                    quickened the frequency of the beats of the heart. These observations show how a
                    physiological explanation can be suggested of the influence of external
                    impressions in modifying the dreams of a sleeper. Further, Mosso found that
                    during very profound sleep these oscillations disappear: the pulsatory movements
                    are uniform and are not affected by sensory impressions, and probably this
                    condition exists when there is the absolute unconsciousness of a “dead” sleep.
                    By such methods as have been employed by Mosso, three movements of the brain
                    have been observed,—(1) <hi rend="italic">pulsations</hi>, corresponding to the
                    beats of the heart; (2) <hi rend="italic">oscillations,</hi> or longer waves,
                    sometimes coinciding with the heart beats, or more generally consisting of
                    longer festoons, carrying each a number of smaller waves, and believed to
                    correspond generally to the respiratory movements; and (3) <hi rend="italic"
                    >undulations,</hi> still longer and less marked elevations and depressions,
                    first clearly observed by Mosso, and believed by him to indicate rhythmic
                    contractions of the vessels of the pia mater and of the brain. This view is in
                    keeping with the observations of Donders, Kussmaul, Tenner, and others on
                    changes of calibre observed in the cerebral vessels, and with the experiments of
                    many physiologists, showing that the vessels of the pia mater, like other
                    vessels, are controlled by the vaso-motor system of nerves (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi> “Nervous System”). It may therefore be
                    considered certain that during sleep there is an anaemia, or partially bloodless
                    condition, of the brain, and that the blood is drawn off to other organs, whilst
                    at the same time this anaemic condition may be modified by changes in the
                    circulation or in the respiratory mechanism caused by position, by sensory
                    impressions, or by sudden changes in the state of repose of the muscles. The
                    examination of the retina (which may be regarded as a cerebral outwork) by the
                    ophthalmoscope during sleep also shows a comparatively bloodless condition. Such
                    are the facts; the deficiency in the way of a theoretical explanation is that
                    physiologists cannot satisfactorily account for the anaemic condition causing
                    unconsciousness. Sudden haemorrhage from the brain and nerve-centres, or a
                    sudden cessation of the supply of blood to the brain, as occurs in syncope
                    (failure of the heart’s action,—a faint), no doubt causes unconsciousness, but
                    in these circumstances there is a tendency to convulsive spasm. Such spasm is
                    usually absent in sleep, but sudden jerks of the limbs may sometimes be observed
                    during the time when there is the confusion of ideas preceding the passage into
                    sleep.</p>
                <p>During sleep the amount of carbonic acid eliminated is very much reduced,
                    indicating that molecular changes in the tissues do not occur to the same extent
                    as in the waking state. This is also shown by the fact that less heat is
                    produced. Helmholtz states that the amount of heat produced by a man weighing 67
                    kilogrammes (147∙4 lb) is about 40 calories per hour during sleep, as against
                    112 calories per hour while awake. This diminished production of heat may be
                    largely accounted for by the quiet condition of the muscles of locomotion, but
                    it also indicates diminished tissue changes throughout the body. In profound
                    sleep the bodily temperature may fall from ∙6° to 2° Fahr. In consequence of
                    diminished oxidation changes during sleep, it is not improbable that excess of
                    nutrient matter may then be stored up in the form of fat, and that thus the
                    proverb “He who sleeps dines” is based on a correct appreciation of the fact
                    that sleep tends to produce plethora or obesity.</p>
                <p>Whilst it is easy to state that sleep is caused by fatigue of the nervous system,
                    it is a more difficult matter to explain what the precise changes are that
                    produce the state of unconsciousness. Various hypotheses have been advanced, but
                    it cannot be said that any one is wholly satisfactory. Aware that the fatigue of
                    muscle is associated with the accumulation of sarcolactic acid, Preyer surmised
                    that the activity of nervous matter might be interfered with by the accumulation
                    in the nerve-centres of some such acid, or of its soda salt (lactate of soda),
                    but this view has not been supported by the results of experiment, as the
                    injection into the blood of a dose of lactate of soda has not produced sleep.
                    Pflüger has observed that frogs deprived for a considerable time of oxygen
                    passed gradually into a state resembling profound sleep, and he has advanced the
                    theory that there is no organ of the body so quickly affected by deprivation of
                    oxygen as the brain. According to Pflüger, the phenomena of life depend on a
                    dissociation of living matter, and in particular the activity of the cerebral
                    substance connected with psychical states depends on dissociation changes in the
                    grey matter. To excite the dissociation, however, oxygen is necessary. The
                    oxygen unites with certain of the compounds set free by the dissociation,
                    forming, amongst other substances, carbonic acid. If such matters as these that
                    unite with oxygen are in sufficient amount to use up all the oxygen, the grey
                    matter of the brain suffers from a deficiency of oxygen (or from its absence),
                    and also from the accumulation of carbonic acid. According to such a theory,
                    cerebral activity depends on cerebral respiration, and sleep is a kind of
                    cerebral asphyxia. Some such condition is not improbable, but it must be stated
                    that the evidence at present in support of it is meagre. Possibly, in attempting
                    to account for the phenomenon of sleep, too much importance has been attributed
                    to the changes occurring in the brain, forgetting that not merely brain matter
                    but every tissue of the body becomes exhausted by work, and that sleep may be
                    partly due to phenomena occurring throughout the body and not in the brain
                    alone. Some more comprehensive hypothesis than any yet advanced may be possible
                    when the condition of all the functions during sleep has been more thoroughly
                    investigated.</p>
                <p>All the phenomena of sleep point to a diminished excitability of the cerebral
                    nerve-centres and of the spinal cord. Contrary to what is often stated, there
                    can be no doubt that reflex action is in partial abeyance and that the spinal
                    cord is in a state of partial inactivity as well as the brain. The only
                    nerve-centres that do not sleep are those absolutely essential to life, such as
                    those connected with the heart, with respiratory movements, and with the
                    distribution of blood by the vaso-motor arrangements; and Mosso’s experiments
                    indicate that even these have a certain amount of repose in profound sleep.</p>
                <p>There is little doubt that all living beings require periods of repose
                    alternating with periods of activity. Many plants close their flowers and bend
                    their petioles at certain times of the day. These phenomena, called “the sleep
                    of plants,” depend apparently on changes in solar radiation,<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n172/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0172-0157"/> and there is no reason to believe that during the
                    time of quiescence any reparative processes go on, as during the sleeping period
                    of animals. Naturalists have observed many of the lower animals apparently in a
                    state of sleep. Insects, crustaceans, fishes, reptiles, may all be observed
                    occasionally to be almost motionless for considerable periods of time. The
                    sleeping of birds is familiar to all, and in these there are anatomical
                    arrangements by which the bird may, like the crane, sleep perched on one leg, or
                    grasping a branch with both feet, like perching birds generally, without any
                    muscular effort and consequently without fatigue.</p>
                <p>The amount of sleep required by man varies according to age, sex, and habit. The
                    popular notion that a child sleeps half its time, an adult one-third, whilst an
                    old person may do little except eat and sleep is not far wrong. In early life
                    the cerebral faculties appear to be easily exhausted and during the frequent and
                    prolonged sleeps of infancy the brain rests and the vegetative changes connected
                    with nutrition and growth go on actively. As life advances, less sleep is
                    required, until in adult life a period of seven or eight hours is sufficient. As
                    a rule, women require more sleep than men; but much depends on habit. Thus most
                    women bear the loss of sleep in the first instance better than men, because they
                    have been accustomed more to loss or irregularity of sleep. The effect of habit
                    is well seen in nurses, both male and female, who will often be able to work for
                    weeks continuously with snatches of sleep, not amounting to more than two or
                    three hours daily. Sooner or later, however, even in these cases nature asserts
                    her demands, and prolonged sleep is necessary to maintain health and vigour.</p>
                <p>Wakefulness during the time when one ought to be asleep is frequently a
                    distressing condition, undermining the strength and incapacitating for active
                    and efficient work. Insomnia or sleeplessness often afflicts those of active
                    mental habits and lays the foundation of premature decay. From what has been
                    stated as to the cause of sleep it is evident that whatever tends to augment
                    unduly the circulation through the brain may cause wakefulness. Thus
                    long-continued or excessive intellectual action, or any powerful emotion, may be
                    injurious. Moderate intellectual work is favourable to sleep. The remedy in such
                    cases is to avoid as far as possible the exciting causes or to counteract them
                    by bodily exercise and attention to the general health. When sleeplessness
                    overtakes a brain-worker it is a sure indication that less intellectual work
                    must be done, and that he ought to betake himself, if possible, to outof-door
                    exercise in the pure air of the country. It is dangerous to persist, and still
                    more to induce sleep artificially by drugs, as the overworked organ may become
                    the seat of permanent disease or pernicious habits may be formed. The posture of
                    the body in bed may influence sleep. Thus such positions as impede the flow of
                    blood from the brain without affecting the supply of blood to it by the arteries
                    may cause sleeplessness. Sometimes in cases of insomnia from excessive mental
                    work there is the distressing condition that sleep disappears when the person
                    lies down in bed, although before lying down he felt drowsy. In such a case
                    resting with the head high may produce the desired result. Insomnia may also be
                    caused by various functional diseases, whereby the amount of blood in the brain
                    is increased. Thus in young females derangement of the menstrual functions may
                    cause a hyperaesthesia or increased sensibility to such an extent that the
                    sufferer cannot sleep, or, if sleep be obtained, it is so light as to be
                    dispelled by weak sensory impressions that would fail to arouse a healthy
                    person. Again, an irregular or deficient action of the heart may cause
                    wakefulness, especially if associated with coldness of the extremities. In such
                    cases the application of heat to the feet and attention to the digestive organs
                    may produce refreshing sleep. Lastly, the excessive use of various drugs, such
                    as alcohol, opium, belladonna, Indian hemp, tea, and coffee, may cause
                    sleeplessness. In these cases a moderate dose usually acts as a hypnotic, whilst
                    frequently repeated doses have the reverse effect. Thus sleeplessness is one of
                    the most distressing symptoms of delirium tremens, and it occurs also in those
                    in the habit of indulging in opium, morphia, chloral, or Indian hemp. The
                    general correctives of sleeplessness are active work, a moderate amount of
                    bodily exercise, freedom from worry and anxiety, the use of the warm bath in
                    some cases to allay irritability before going to bed, and such a posture in bed
                    as the individual has found in his own case to be favourable. Sometimes a light
                    but nutritious meal about an hour before retiring may con duce to sleep, but as
                    a rule late suppers are unfavourable. The use of drugs should be indulged in
                    only with medical advice. It is not too much to say that the injudicious use of
                    bromide of potassium, chloral, opium, morphia, and stimulants by literary
                    persons to procure sleep has often been productive of sad results, such as
                    shattered health, an incurable habit of self-indulgence, and even accidental
                    death (see Hammond, <hi rend="italic">On Wakefulness).</hi></p>
                <p>It is a matter of common observation not only that certain persons require more
                    sleep than others but that they have less power of resisting its onset and of
                    awaking. This condition may become morbid, constituting a veritable nervous
                    disease, to which the name “maladie du sommeil” or <hi rend="italic"
                    >hypnosia</hi> may be given. It may be described as invincible sleep, and it may
                    continue for weeks and for months, terminating in convulsive seizures, and even
                    death. A persistent drooping of the upper eyelid has been observed even during
                    waking hours. Dr W. Ogle has observed in such cases an engorgement of the
                    cervical ganglia of the sympathetic; but this may have nothing to do with the
                    condition. Cases of very prolonged sleep are not uncommon, especially amongst
                    hysterical females, lasting four, seven, or ten days. On awaking the patient is
                    exhausted and pale, with cold extremities, and not unfrequently, after a brief
                    interval of waking, passes off into another lethargic sleep. Something similar
                    to this may be seen in very aged persons towards the close of life.</p>
                <p>Dreams (cf. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dream,</hi> vol. vii. p. 452 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.)</hi> only occur when sleep is light, and they indicate that consciousness
                    is still continued. The characteristic feature of dreaming is that the mind has
                    no control over the groups of images that crowd upon it. These images are either
                    revivals of old sensory impressions that have been stored up in the brain or
                    they are the result of an untrammelled imagination. The will has lost the power
                    of direction and control; ideas, often grotesque, always confused, rise
                    apparently spontaneously, are vivid for an instant, and then disappear. Dreaming
                    may be described as a kind of physiological delirium. A consideration of the
                    state indicates that the cerebral hemispheres are partially active and that it
                    is the inhibitory power that is deficient (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Physiology,</hi> “Nervous System”). A further explanation cannot be given in
                    the present state of our knowledge of cerebral physiology, but some of the more
                    evident conditions or laws of the dreaming state may be indicated. (1) The
                    character of dreams is often determined by a predominant thought or train of
                    ideas that has occupied the mind before going to sleep. Thus the events of the
                    preceding day may produce a particular kind of dream, and not unfrequently when
                    a person attempts on waking to unravel his dream he may find the connecting
                    thread in an occurrence or in a conversation or in the thoughts suggested by a
                    book on the previous day. It would thus seem that the memory of recent things
                    (and physiologically there must be an organic basis for memory) may revivify old
                    and apparently forgotten impressions. (2) In dreaming, the train of thought may
                    be influenced by impressions made on the senses of the sleeper, sufficiently
                    intense to produce this result, but not intense enough to awake him. Thus a
                    sudden sensory impression, such as a loud sound, a current of cold air, a
                    restrained position of one of the limbs, a word or sentence uttered by a
                    familiar voice, may arouse a dream or turn the disordered throng of fancies in a
                    new direction. In some instances, the dreamer is peculiarly susceptible to such
                    external impressions, so that the same stimulus will always give rise to the
                    same kind of dream. (3) It has frequently been observed that in dreaming there
                    may be memories of old impressions, scenes, faces, words, that have long since
                    faded from the recollection during waking hours, showing that many impressions
                    that are supposed to be lost are only forgotten and require but the appropriate
                    stimulus to cause them to start vividly into mental life. (4) In rare instances
                    there may be consecutive thought in dreams, so that the dreamer may write verse,
                    frame speeches, or even work out mathematical problems. Most persons have had
                    experience of this strange kind of power and have regretted, in the partially
                    conscious state before awaking, that they could not preserve some of the
                    results, feeling assured that the sober reality of waking life would dispel the
                    vision. (5) Dreams make only a feeble impression on the memory, so that on
                    awaking what is at first vivid and distinct fades insensibly and rapidly away.
                    This may be accounted for by the evanescent character of the mental “stuff” of
                    dreams. In the waking state an act of attention is required to fix anything in
                    the memory, and, as this is absent in dreaming, the impressions do not leave a
                    permanent effect. For this reason also in dreams we have no memory of former
                    dreams. (6) All have observed that there is no feeling of time or of space in
                    dreams. We live in an ideal world. This probably arises from the absence of
                    fixity of thought, so that there is no apparent connexion between the successive
                    pictures of the imagination. (7) In some dreams the activity of the cerebrum is
                    such that the train of thoughts prompts to movement, and the sleeper may be
                    heard muttering in his sleep or tossing the arms or making gestures. There are
                    gradations between this condition of a “troubled” dream and that of true
                    somnambulism.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Somnambulism.—</hi> Some persons rise during sleep, walk about,
                    apparently unconscious of all external impressions, after a time<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n173/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0173-0158"/> return to bed, and when they are awake they have
                    no recollection of any of these occurrences. Sometimes the actions performed are
                    of a complicated character and bear some relation to the daily life of the
                    sleeper. Thus a cook has been known to rise out of bed, carry a pitcher to a
                    well in the garden, fill it, go back to the house, fill various vessels
                    carefully and without spilling a drop of water, then return to bed, and have no
                    recollection of what had transpired. Again, somnambulists have been observed to
                    write letters or reports, execute drawings, and play upon musical instruments.
                    Frequently they have gone along dangerous paths, executing delicate movements
                    with precision. Four types of somnambulist may be noticed,—(1) those who speak
                    without acting, a common variety often observed in children and not usually
                    considered somnambulistic; (2) those who act without speaking, also well known
                    and the most common type; (3) those who both act and speak, more exceptional;
                    and (4) those who both act and speak and who have not merely the sense of touch
                    active but also the senses of sight and hearing. The fourth class is the most
                    extreme type and merges into the physiological condition of mesmerism or
                    hypnotism. This peculiar condition has already been fully described under animal
                    magnetism (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Magnetism, Animal),</hi> and it is necessary
                    here only to notice it in connexion with the subject of sleep. Many observations
                    indicate that, at all events in some cases, the somnambulist, engaged, for
                    example, in writing, has a mental picture of the page before him and of the
                    words he has written. He does not see what he really writes. This has been
                    proved by causing persons to write on a sheet of paper lying on the top of other
                    sheets. After he has been allowed to write a few sentences, the sheet was
                    carefully withdrawn and he continued his writing on the next sheet, beginning on
                    the new sheet at the corresponding point where he left off on the first one.
                    Moreover, the somnambulist, by force of habit, stroked t’s and dotted i’s at the
                    exact places where the t’s and i’s would have been had he written continuously
                    on one sheet, showing that what he was conscious of was not what was before him
                    but the mental picture of what he had done.</p>
                <p>The following table, modified from two such tables given by Ball and Chambard in
                    their exhaustive article “Somnambulisme” in the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire
                    Encylopédique des Sciences Médicales,</hi> shows the relation of the various
                    intermediate conditions of sleeping and awaking and of the dreaming and
                    somnambulistic states. The horizontal stroke indicates the presence of the
                    condition the name of which heads the column :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Organic</p><p>Life.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Conscious ness.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Imagin
                            ative</p><p>Faculties.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Co-ordi
                            nating</p><p>Faculties.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Power of Movement and
                            Sensibility.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Normal waking state .. Sleep, 1st
                            degree</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, 2d degree</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">,, 3d degree</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Deep sleep</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Waking, 1st degree .... ,, 2d degree
                            (specially dreaming state)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>,, 3d degree</p><p>Complete
                            waking</p><p>Dreaming state</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p><p>—</p><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p><p>—</p><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p><p>—</p><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>—</p><p>—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Ordinary somnambulism —(2) above</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Profound somnambulism (perfect
                            unconsciousness)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Somnambulistic dream (movements in a
                            dream)</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">—</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The somnambulist acts his dream. His condition is that of a vivid dream in which
                    the cerebrum is so active as to influence centres usually concerned in voluntary
                    movements. Under the dominant idea he executes the movements that this idea
                    would naturally excite in the waking state. Many of his movements are in a sense
                    purposive; his eyes may be shut so that the movements are executed in the dark,
                    or the eyes may be open so that there is a picture on the retina that may awaken
                    no consciousness, and yet may, by reflex mechanisms, be the starting-point of
                    definite and deliberate movements. In many cases he does not hear, the auditory
                    centres not responding; but in others suggestive words may alter the current of
                    his dream and lead him to perform other actions than what he intended to do. On
                    awaking there is either no memory of what has taken place or the dim
                    recollection of a fading dream.</p>
                <p>It is important to notice that there is scarcely any action of which a
                    somnambulist may not be capable, and immoral acts from which the individual
                    would shrink in waking hours may be performed with indifference. Considering the
                    abrogation of self-control peculiar to the physiological condition, it is
                    evident that no moral responsibility can be attached to such actions. In cases
                    where somnambulistic propensities place a person in danger, an endeavour should
                    be made to induce him to return to bed without awaking him; as a rude awakening
                    may produce a serious shock to the nervous system. Inquiry should then be made
                    into the exciting cause of the somnambulistic dream, such as a particular train
                    of thought, over-excitement, the reading of special books, the recollection of
                    an accident or of a crisis in the person’s history, with the view of removing
                    the cause if possible. It should never be forgotten that somnambulism, like
                    chorea, hysteria, and epilepsy, is the expression of a general morbid
                    predisposition, an indication of a nervous diathesis, requiring careful
                    treatment so as to avoid more dangerous maladies.</p>
                <p>See article "Sommeil "in the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Encyclopédique des
                    Sciences Médicales,</hi> where a full bibliography is given and where also there
                    is an account of the medico-legal questions connected with sleep and
                    somnambulism; Macnish, <hi rend="italic">Physiology of Sleep</hi>; Durham, “On
                    the Physiology of Sleep,” in Gay’s <hi rend="italic">Hospital Reports,</hi>
                    1860; Kohlschütter, “Die Mekanik des Schlafes,” in <hi rend="italic">Z. f.
                    ration. Med.,</hi> vol. xxxiii., 1869; Pflüger, “Theorie des Schlafes,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Pflüger's Archiv,</hi> vol. x., 1875; Mosso, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Heber den Kreislauf des Blutes im menschlichen Gehirn,</hi> Leipsic, 1881. As
                    to somnambulism, see the article on the subject in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionnaire</hi> both for füll details and a copious bibliography. (J. G.
                    M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
