<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0192-0177-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">SMITH, Sydney</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 22, page 177</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n192/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SMITH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sydney</hi></label> (1771-1845),
                    one of the founders of the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review,</hi> and one of
                    the wittiest talkers and political writers of his generation, was the son of an
                    English country gentleman, and was born at Woodford in Essex on 3d June 1771.
                    His father, a man of restless ingenuity and activity, “very clever, odd by
                    nature, but still more odd by design,” who bought, altered, spoiled, and sold
                    about nineteen different estates in England, had talent and eccentricity enough
                    to be the father of such a wit as Sydney Smith on the strictest principles of
                    heredity; but Sydney was wont himself to attribute not a little of his
                    constitutional gaiety to an infusion of French blood, his maternal grandfather
                    being a French Protestant refugee of the name of Ollier, who could not speak a
                    word of English. Sydney was the second of a family of four brothers and one
                    sister, all remarkable for their talents. While two of the brothers, “Bobus” and
                    Cecil, were sent to Eton, Sydney was sent with the youngest to Winchester, where
                    he rose to be captain of the school, and with his brother so distinguished
                    himself that their schoolfellows signed a round-robin “refusing to try for the
                    college prizes if the Smiths were allowed to contend for them any more, as they
                    always gained them,” From Winchester Sydney went to New College, Oxford, and in
                    due course became a fellow of his college. It was his wish then to read for the
                    bar, but his father would add nothing to his fellowship, and he was reluctantly
                    compelled to enter the church, and became a curate in a small village in the
                    midst of Salisbury Plain. From this dreary incumbency he was relieved after two
                    years, and conducted to the scene of the foundation of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Edinburgh Review</hi> by a combination of accidents. The squire of the parish
                    invited the new curate to dine, was astonished and charmed to find such a man in
                    such a place, and engaged him after a time as tutor to his eldest son. “It was
                    arranged,” he afterwards said, “that I and his son should proceed to the
                    university of Weimar. We set out, but before reaching our destination Germany
                    was disturbed by war, and in stress of politics we put into Edinburgh.” This was
                    in 1797. In Edinburgh, as everywhere else, Smith made numerous friends, whose
                    cordiality was in no way abated by his constant quizzing of the national foibles
                    and peculiarities; and among those friends were the future Edinburgh Reviewers.
                    It was towards the end of his five years’ residence in Edinburgh, in the
                    elevated residence of the then Mr Jeffrey, “in the eighth or ninth story or flat
                    in a house in Buccleuch Place,” that Sydney Smith proposed the setting up of a
                    review as an organ for the opinions and a vehicle for the ambition of the young
                    malcontents with things as they were. “I was appointed editor,” he says in the
                    preface to the collection of his contributions, “and remained long enough in
                    Edinburgh to edit the first number [October 1802] of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Edinburgh Review.</hi> The motto I proposed for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Review</hi> was ‘Tenui musam meditamur avena’—‘We cultivate literature on a
                    little oatmeal.’ But this was too near the truth to be admitted, and so we took
                    our present grave motto from Publius Syrus, of whom none of us had, I am sure,
                    ever read a single line.” He continued to write for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Review</hi> for the next quarter of a century, and his brilliant articles were
                    a main element in its success. They represent the very perfection of journalism.
                    They were not merely the most readable, the most entertaining: the solidity of
                    substance and the seriousness of purpose were quite as indisputable as the
                    brilliancy of the execution.</p>
                <p>The writer seemed to tackle the gravest of political and social questions in the
                    highest of spirits, yet he never lost sight of his aim in purposeless
                    buffoonery; and, however heartily the reader might be made to laugh, the
                    laughter was always directed at what seemed to the writer absurd and
                    unreasonable opinion. It was remarked of his wit in conversation that the butts
                    of it were often seen to laugh as heartily as the audience; there was nothing
                    base and personal in Sydney Smith’s raillery. The same with his writing when it
                    was anonymous. His wonderful powers of humorous exaggeration were such as to
                    detach a ridiculous opinion as far as possible from its human incarnation and
                    present it in the bare essence of its absurdity. This was his habit as a
                    controversialist; and, when his purpose was simply to convey information, to
                    give the gist of a book of travels, or a system of education, or a body of
                    statistics, he was unequalled in the art of amusing the reader with ludicrous
                    images in the most unexpected places without departing from the main lines of a
                    most clear, orderly, and instructive exposition. The fact is that the serious
                    didactic purpose in all Sydney Smith’s writing and the closeness of his
                    adherence to the matter in hand are the main obstacles to the living permanence
                    of his fame as the writer of the best colloquial prose of his generation; for
                    though his range of topics was wide—political, ecclesiastical, educational,
                    geographical, and otherwise miscellaneous—they were all of immediate, practical,
                    and passing interest, and his remarks were pushed home to the life of the time
                    so closely as to have comparatively little independent interest for
                    posterity.</p>
                <p>Most of Sydney Smith’s contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Review</hi> were sent from the country parish of Foston-le-Clay in Yorkshire,
                    where he spent the best part of his life. He left Edinburgh for good in 1803,
                    when the education of his pupils was completed; and, yielding to his wife’s
                    confidence in his powers—he had married Miss Pybus, an English lady of good
                    family, while still unsettled in life— adventured on London, where he rapidly
                    became known as a preacher, a lecturer, and a social lion. His success as a
                    preacher, although so marked that there was often not standing room in the
                    church in Berkeley Square, where he conducted the morning service, was not
                    gained by any sacrifice of dignity: there was no eccentricity, nothing
                    sensational in his preaching; it was a pure triumph of good sense, right
                    feeling, earnestness, and freshness of pulpit oratory. He lectured on moral
                    philosophy at the Royal Institution for three seasons, from 1804 to 1808; and
                    here also, handling the ordinary topics of a philosophy chair in a Scotch
                    university, he treated them with such vigour, freshness, and liveliness of
                    illustration that the London world crowded to Albemarle Street to hear him. He
                    made no pretence to originality, and in the main followed Dugald Stewart, whose
                    lectures he had attended in Edinburgh; but there is more originality as well as
                    good sense in his lectures, especially on such topics as imagination and wit and
                    humour, than in many more pretentious systems of philosophy. With the brilliant
                    reputation that Sydney Smith had acquired in the course of a few seasons in
                    London, he would probably have obtained some good preferment had he been on the
                    powerful side in politics. His Whig friends came into office for a short time in
                    1806, and presented him with the living of Foston-le-Clay in Yorkshire. He
                    shrank from this banishment for a time, and discharged his parish duties through
                    a curate; but Mr Percival’s Residence Act was passed in 1808, and, after trying
                    in vain to negotiate an exchange, he quitted London in 1809 and moved his
                    household to Yorkshire. His most famous single production, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Peter Plymley's Letters</hi> on the subject of Catholic emancipation,
                    ridiculing the opposition of the country clergy, appeared<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n193/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0193-0178"/> before this migration. From being the idol of
                    London society to being the pastor of a country parish with no educated
                    neighbour within 7 miles was a violent change; but Sydney Smith accommodated
                    himself cheerfully to his new circumstances, and won the hearts of his
                    parishioners as quickly as he had conquered a wider world. Not the least
                    entertaining chapter in his daughter’s biography of him is the account of his
                    Yorkshire life. An interesting contrast might be drawn between it and Carlyle’s
                    life in somewhat similar circumstances at Craigenputtock. Sydney Smith’s life at
                    Foston, with its cheerful energy and ingenuity, its vigorous jesting at
                    difficulties and eccentric ways of conquering them, is of much better example,
                    and moralists might do worse than put the story into form for general
                    edification.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Lady
                    Holland’s <hi rend="italic">Memoir,</hi> chaps. v., vi. Lady Holland, Sydney
                    Smith’s eldest daughter, was the wife of Sir Henry Holland, the famous
                    physician,—not of Lord Holland, as is sometimes absurdly stated.</p></note></p>
                <p>Sydney Smith, after twenty years’ service in Yorkshire, obtained preferment at
                    last from a Tory minister, Lord Lyndhurst, who presented him with a canonry in
                    Bristol cathedral in 1828, and afterwards enabled him to exchange Foston for the
                    living of Combe Florey near Taunton. From this time he discontinued writing for
                    the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> on the ground that it was more
                    becoming in a dignitary of the church to put his name to what he wrote. It was
                    expected that when the Whigs came into power Sydney Smith would be made a
                    bishop. There was nothing in his writings, as in the case of Swift, to stand in
                    the way, for with all his humour and high spirits he had always, as he said
                    himself, fashioned his manners and conversation so as not to bring discredit on
                    his reverend profession. He had been most sedulous as a parochial clergyman.
                    Still, though he was not without warm friends at headquarters, the opposition
                    was too strong for them. One of the first things that Lord Grey said on entering
                    Downing Street was, “Now I shall be able to do something for Sydney Smith”; but
                    he was not able to do more than appoint him to a prebendal stall at St Paul’s in
                    exchange for the one of inferior value he held at Bristol. Lord Melbourne is
                    reported to have said that there was nothing he more regretted than the not
                    having made Sydney Smith a bishop. Some surprise must be felt now that Sydney
                    Smith’s reputation as a humourist and wit should have caused any hesitation
                    about elevating him to the episcopal dignity, and perhaps he was right in
                    thinking that the real obstacle lay in his being known as “a high-spirited,
                    honest, uncompromising man, whom all the bench of bishops could not turn upon
                    vital questions.” With characteristic philosophy, when he saw that the promotion
                    was doubtful, he made his position certain by resolving not to be a bishop and
                    definitely forbidding his friends to intercede for him. This loss and the much
                    more painful loss of his eldest son did not destroy the cheerfulness of his
                    later life. He retained his high spirits, his wit, practical energy, and powers
                    of argumentative ridicule to the last. His <hi rend="italic">Letters to
                    Archdeacon Singleton</hi> on the Ecclesiastical Commission (1837), and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Petition</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> on the
                    repudiation of debts by the State of Pennsylvania (1843), are as bright and
                    trenchant as his best contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Review.</hi> Smith died in London on 22d February 1845.</p>
                <p>Lady Holland’s <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi> of her father, containing such
                    specimens of his table talk as give one some idea of his charm and worth as a
                    mirthful companion and philosopher, is one of the most interesting of
                    biographies. A cheap edition of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> was published
                    in 1869. (W. M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
