<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-2869-0042-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLAUTUS (7th edition, volume 18, page 42)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4000029t">Curculio</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085673">Queros</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193532869?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLAUTUS</label>, Μ. <hi rend="smallcaps">Attius,</hi> the
                    father of Roman comedy, was born of humble parents, in the Umbrian village of
                    Sar-sina. He flourished during the second Punic war; and his death happened <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. 184, when Terence had reached his ninth year. Of his
                    private circumstances we are entirely ignorant; but fortune, which had blessed
                    him with extraordinary talents, does not appear to have been very bountiful in
                    worldly goods. To gain a livelihood, he was compelled to have recourse to the
                    most laborious employments; yet still he contrived to write comedies, by the
                    sale of which he added something to his enjoyments. The number of comedies
                    composed by Plautus, or at least known under his name, was, according to Aulus
                    Gellius, about one hundred and thirty, of which L. AElius considered only
                    twenty-five as genuine productions. Gellius imagines that the others, if they
                    were not composed by Plautus, belong at least to the poets of that period, and
                    had been read and amended by him; so that in this manner they had acquired his
                    style and character. Varro considered as genuine only twenty-one, which were
                    hence called <hi rend="italic">Varronianae</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> and
                    perhaps a few others, from their similarity of style. Changes in the text and in
                    the arrangement, which were brought about at the will of the aediles, to whom he
                    sold the plays, and even of the actors who were employed in performing them,
                    became still more frequent after the death of the poet. The substitution, too,
                    of the plays of another unknown poet, Plautius, for those of Plautus, has
                    increased <pb break="no" facs="nls:193532882?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-2882-0043"/> the difficulty of distinguishing the genuine
                    productions of the poet from those erroneously ascribed to him. Thus we find
                    grammarians and critics, such as AElins, Volcatius, Se-digitius, Claudius, and
                    Aurelius, writing treatises respecting the genuine pieces of Plautus. The number
                    of comedies which have been preserved, though by no means quite perfect,
                    amounts, according to Varro, to twenty. The <hi rend="italic">Quero-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">lus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Aulularia,</hi> written in prose,
                    though found in the manuscripts of Plautus, and even cited by Servius as
                    belonging to him, is considered by some as of a later date, probably of the time
                    of the younger Theodosius. Vossius and Tirlemont considered Claudius Rutilius
                    Nnmatianus as the author, whilst Vincent was rather inclined to suppose it the
                    production of Phaedrus, the cclcbratcd writer of fables. All the manuscripts of
                    Plautus which have yet been discovered, with the exception of the Palimpsest of
                    the Ambrosian Library, seem to be of a recent date, and must have flowed from a
                    common source, as the same passages arc corrupt in all.</p>
                <p>It is usually supposed that we are indebted to the grammarian Priscian for the
                    order in which we find these twenty plays arranged; and he, too, is the author
                    of the short arguments prefixed to each comedy in some of the old manuscripts.
                    The purity of the language proves their remote antiquity, even though we bc
                    inclined to think that Plautus is not the author. The plays are found generally
                    in the following arrangement. <hi rend="italic">Amphitrus,</hi> called by
                    Plautus himself in the prologue a tragi-comedy, because gods and princes are the
                    principal characters, and tragic events arc brought upon the comic stage; it has
                    been imitated by Boccacio, Molière, and Dryden. <hi rend="italic">Asinaria,</hi>
                    in imitation of the Greek play <hi rend="italic">'Oναγgος</hi> of Demophilus,
                    exhibiting in strongly-marked characters the corruption of Greek manners. <hi
                    rend="italic">Aulularia,</hi> one of the best, distinguished by its Roman
                    colouring; but its end is wanting: it is the foundation of Molière’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Avare.</hi><hi rend="italic">Captivi,</hi> according to the
                    opinion of the poet himself, one of his most successful efforts, which is
                    recommended particularly by the moral feeling that pervades it. The subject is
                    more grave, and the coarse licentiousness and extravagance which disgust us in
                    his other plays are here thrown into the back-ground, whilst a purely moral
                    character steps forward, without any diminution in the comic vigour and genius
                    of the poet, who must have written it in the latter years of his life. <hi
                    rend="italic">Curculio,</hi> from the name of the parasite who acts the chief
                    part. <hi rend="italic">Casina,</hi> in imitation of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kλη-gουμενοι of</hi> Diphilus. <hi rend="italic">Cistellaria. Epidicus,</hi> a
                    play highly thought of by the author. <hi rend="italic">Chrysalus</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Bacchidcs,</hi> in which the prologue and beginning are wanting:
                    the copy which Lascaris pretended to have found in Sicily is not considered as
                    genuine, being probably the work of Petrarch. <hi rend="italic">Phasma,</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">Mostellaria,</hi> in modern times imitated by Reynard and
                    Addison. <hi rend="italic">Menaechmus,</hi> also imitated by Reynard, and even
                    by Shakspeare in some parts. <hi rend="italic">Miles</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gloriosus,</hi> one of his most successful pieces, which reminds us of
                    Holbein’s Bramarbas. <hi rend="italic">Mercator,</hi> in imitation of the <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> E <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> απosoς of Philemon.
                    <hi rend="italic">Pseudolus,</hi> one of the favourites of the poet, as appears
                    from Cicero. <hi rend="italic">Paenulus,</hi> represented probably about 191,
                    and therefore to be numbered amongst the latest plays of Plautus. This is proved
                    by the labour he has bestowed upon it, the superior manner in which it
                    delineates character, and the skilful arrangement of the whole. It is remarkable
                    for the introduction of Carthaginian words, the only monument of the language
                    which remains, with the exception of coins and inscriptions; and it has
                    therefore been frequently referred to by the learned of ancient and modern
                    times. <hi rend="italic">Persa,</hi> from which Pliny quotes some verses that
                    are not found in the play which has come down to us. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pudens,</hi> a beautiful play, in imitation of the Greek of Diphilus. <hi
                    rend="italic">Stichus. Trinummus,</hi> in imitation of the of Phile mon: after
                    the <hi rend="italic">Captivi,</hi> it is the most remarkable play, both in
                    regard to the design of the whole, and the delineation of character, as well as
                    in the skilful arrangement of individual parts. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Truculentus,</hi> also a favourite of the poet. Besides these, we have likewise
                    the names and fragments of many other comedies.</p>
                <p>These comedies belong to the class of <hi rend="italic">Comoediae Palìiatae,</hi>
                    and are so far to bc considered as free imitations of the works of die Greek
                    comedians of the new school; yet it would bc doing injustice to the talents of
                    Plautus to suppose that he imitated slavishly the Greek originals, and copied
                    their works without asserting his own intellectual powers, or making changes
                    both in relation to the form and design of the whole, as well as of its
                    individual parts. The bold manner in which he made use of the Greek materials,
                    by which the poet was able to bring into play his natural genius and vein of
                    comic humour, and the frequent introduction of Roman characters and customs,
                    even into the midst of Greek plays, distinguished Plautus from the polished
                    Terence, who adhered much more closely to the Greek originals. It marks him as
                    the genuine poet of the people, who knew how to create a popular drama, and
                    thereby to furnish amusement for the lower ranks of life. He sold his plays to
                    the aediles, and therefore must have written them expressly for the diversion of
                    the people. We need scarcely doubt that the poet would have taken a still wider
                    range, and have exhibited still more of the true national character of the
                    Romans, if he had not had before his eyes the fate of Naevius, to warn him from
                    the dangerous path on which he was entering. The entire loss of the Greek
                    originals prevents us from being able to decide how much of his materials the
                    poet borrowed, and how far he imitated them in the design and conduct of his
                    plays. Plautus must have made more use of the productions of the Attic comic
                    writers than of those of the Sicilian poets. Yet Epicharmus and some others he
                    had evidently read with much care, and may also have imitated them, as he
                    certainly did in respect to Theocritus. The prologue, which is generally thought
                    to have been wanting to the Greek comedy, was peculiar to him and his imitators.
                    The poet was chiefly distinguished by the raciness of his wit, and the original
                    and spirited manner in which he treated his subjects. But as it was' not the
                    higher and more polished classes of society for whom he wrote, but rather for
                    those in humble life, from which he himself had sprung, we may expect to find in
                    his' comedies much low buffoonery, as well as many words and expressions bearing
                    a double meaning; and here and there he oversteps the bounds of modesty and
                    decency, which may however be forgiven, in return for the rich vein of humour
                    which will always stamp Plautus as one of the most original of the comic poets
                    of Rome. For this reason, however, much caution ought to be*used in introducing
                    the young to an acquaintance with the writings of Plautus.</p>
                <p>The language of Plautus is natural and forcible, though not always harmonious and
                    musical. Neither is it free from a certain harshness and ruggedness, apparent in
                    the use of old forms of words and expressions, which became obsolete in later
                    times, though we may ascribe this to the still uncultivated state of the
                    language. The form of the ’ verse is not regular; indeed the prosody and metre
                    are both treated with so much carelessness, that wc are almost inclined to
                    believe that the poet either refused to submit to the trammels of a regular
                    metre, or was unacquainted with the laws and rules of prosody. Yet of late a
                    more minute examination of his writings, and a more profound study of the
                    principles of Latin prosody and metrical laws, have led writers to take a
                    different view of the subject. Many of the ancients bestowed unmeasured praise
                    on the language of Plautus; yet we need not be surprised at the less favour- ∙
                    able opinion pronounced by Horace, whose taste was formed upon a purer Greek
                    model.</p>
                <p>The earliest edition of Plautus is that of Venice, 1472; and the best is that
                    published by Brunck, Bipont, 1788, in three vols. 8vo.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193532895?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-2895-0044"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
