<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-8966-0507-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRECESSION OF THE EQUINOXES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 507</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046145">Opera</term>
                    <term n="65" ref="fasttopic:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term n="65" ref="fasttopic:1119629">Sins</term>
                    <term n="32" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term n="25" ref="fasttopic:918891">Expressionism</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:1068347">Poles</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="31" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term n="65" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term n="41" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term n="32" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="27" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193538966" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRECESSION OF THE EQUINOXES</label>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">In</hi> the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy</hi>
                    (vol. vi. p. 767), the phenomenon of the annual precession of the equinoxes has
                    been described, and its physical cause stated to be the attraction of the sun
                    and moon upon the protuberant mass of matter accumulated about the earth’s
                    equator, combined with the diurnal rotation. We shall here discuss the subject
                    more particularly, and shew in what manner the different forces which tend to
                    displace the plane of the earth’s equator give rise to the phenomenon in
                    question, and how their effects are computed from the fundamental principles of
                    dynamics. The general problem, which is that of determining the perturbations of
                    the earth’s axis of rotation, embraces the <hi rend="italic">Nutation</hi> of
                    the axis, as well as the processional motion of the equinoctial points, and is
                    one of the most important and interesting in physical astronomy.</p>
                <p>If the earth were a perfect sphere, the attraction of the sun or moon would have
                    no tendency to communicate to it any motion about its centre of gravity. In this
                    case, all the particles being symmetrically disposed with reference to every
                    plane passing through its centre, the forces acting on opposite sides of any
                    plane passing through its centre and the centre of the attracting body, would
                    exactly balance each other, and consequently would have no tendency to produce a
                    rotatory motion. But by reason of the spheroidal form of the earth, and of the
                    intensity of the force of attraction varying with the distance, the action of a
                    distant body which is not situated either in the plane of the equator, or in the
                    prolongation of the axis of rotation, produces an unequal effect on the opposite
                    sides of every plane passing through the earth’s centre, (excepting the meridian
                    in which the body is situated), and tends to produce a rotatory motion about
                    that diameter of the equator which is perpendicular to the line which joins the
                    centre of the earth with the centre of the attracting body. Hence the sun exerts
                    a force, which at every instant has a tendency to bring the plane of the earth’s
                    equator towards the plane of the ecl iptic; and if the earth had no motion of
                    rotation about its axis, the two planes would at length be brought to coincide.
                    In consequence, however, of the rotatory motion, the inclination of the two
                    planes, as we shall shew, undergoes no permanent alteration; but a motion is
                    given to the earth’s axis, such that the pole of the equator constantly revolves
                    about the pole of the ecliptic in the direction opposite to that of the diurnal
                    rotation, and the intersection of the equator and ecliptic, following the motion
                    of the pole, is carried backwards along the ecliptic. The moon produces a
                    similar effect in reference to the plane of the lunar orbit; and the motion
                    produced by the combined action of the sun and moon, which is the phenomenon
                    observed, is the <hi rend="italic">luni solar</hi> precession of the
                    equinoxes.</p>
                <p>As the efficacy of the disturbing force to turn the earth about an axis varies
                    with the distance of the attracting body from the ,plane of the equator, the
                    precessional motion of the equinoxes is not uniform. The efficacy of the sun’s
                    force continues to increase, while the sun passes from either equinox to the
                    solstice, and to diminish while it passes from the solstice to the equinox. The
                    period of the inequality is consequently half a-year. The period in <hi
                    rend="subscript"> ¾</hi> which the action of the moon passes through all its
                    degrees of intensity is about nine years, being that in which the nodes of the
                    lunar orbit accomplish half a revolution on the ecliptic. The apparent effect of
                    this irregular action, is an alternate increase and diminution of the
                    declinations of the fixed stars, most sensible for those nearest the pole, which
                    is characteristically called the <hi rend="italic">nutation</hi> of the earth’s
                    axis. The solar nutation, however, is so small as to be insensible to
                    observation; the lunar nutation is sufficiently sensible, amounting to about 18
                    <hi rend="superscript"> z,</hi> between the extreme positions of the pole.</p>
                <p>Before proceeding with the investigation of the problem, it will be convenient to
                    premise the two following elementary theorems respecting the composition of
                    rotatory motion, referring the reader for their demonstration to the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Rotation.</hi><hi rend="italic">Theorem</hi> 1. If a rigid body
                    revolving about an axis A¢z, which passes through its centre of gravity O, with
                    an angular velocity =v, receive an impulse which alone would cause it to revolve
                    about an axis Bó, also passing through its centre of gravity, with a velocity
                    =ψ, the body will now revolve about a third axis <hi rend="italic">Cc,</hi>
                    passing through its centre of gravity, and lying in the plane of the two axes
                    <hi rend="italic">Aa</hi> and B⅞, and so situated that the sine of its
                    inclination to the axis Aα will be to the sine of its inclination to the axis
                    BZ&gt;, as the velocity about BZ&gt; to the velocity about Aα; that is, the new
                    axis will divide the angle AOB, so that sin AOC: sin BOC:: <hi rend="italic"
                    >φ</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">v.</hi></p>
                <p>In order to determine whether the pole C of the new axis lies between A and B, or
                    between A and <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> it is only necessary to consider that
                    the new axis must evidently be that line in the body in which every point is at
                    rest in respect of both motions. If, therefore, we suppose the original motion
                    about Aα, to be in the direction which would raise the point B above the plane
                    of the paper, and to depress <hi rend="italic">b</hi> below it, and the new
                    impulse to be given in the direction which would depress the point A below the
                    plane of the paper, and raise <hi rend="italic">a</hi> above it, then C will lie
                    between A and B; but if the new impulse tends to raise A above the plane of the
                    paper, then C will lie between A and <hi rend="italic">b.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Corollary</hi> 1. If the two axes <hi rend="italic">Aa</hi> and B6 are at right
                    sin <hi rend="smallcaps">jAO(√</hi> angles, then sin BOC=cos AOC, and we have
                    rτ=vz, <hi rend="italic">% φ</hi> cosAOC</p>
                <p>= —, that is, tan AOC= —.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">v v</hi><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 2. If the impulse is
                    renewed at every instant of time, the axis about which the body actually
                    revolves must have a uniform motion in space from OA towards OB.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Theorem</hi> 2. If the force which tends to give the body a
                    motion of rotation about an axis which is always perpendicular to the axis about
                    which it is already revolving, and situated in the plane AOB, be uniform, the
                    angular velocity of rotation remains unaltered, or <hi rend="italic">v</hi> is a
                    constant quantity.</p>
                <p>These theorems, which are true of bodies in general, whatever be their figure,
                    were first demonstrated byFrisi.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Proposition</hi> 1. To determine the efficacy of the sun’s
                    attraction to turn the spheroid about its centre, the earth being supposed
                    homogeneous.</p>
                <p>Let P∕&gt; be the axis of rotation, <hi rend="italic">Ctq</hi> the projection of
                    the equator, S the sun, C the centre of the spheroid, and D <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193538979" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8979-0508"/>the projection of a point in
                    the interior of the spheroid on the ])lane <hi rend="italic">YQpq.</hi> Join SC,
                    SD, DC; and draw CG perpendicular to SC, and DE, DF respectively perpendicular
                    to SC, CG.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">f</hi> represent the force of the sun’s attraction on a
                    particle at the centre C, and <hi rend="italic">f'</hi> the force of its
                    attraction on a particle at D, then the attraction being inversely as the</p>
                <p>SC <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> square of the distance, we have <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">=f.</hi> g^^∙ Now the force <hi
                    rend="italic">f',</hi> which acts on D in the direction SD, may be resolved into
                    two; one in the direction CD, which has no tendency to turn the spheroid about
                    its centre, and the other in the direction FD parallel to SC, which tends to
                    turn the spheroid in the direction PQ about an axis passing through C, and
                    perpendicular to the plane <hi rend="italic">VQpq.</hi> The resolved part of the
                    force <hi rend="italic">f</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> in the direction FD is
                    so <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> SC</p>
                <p>/∙ gjj2 ∙ gß’ <hi rend="superscript"> since</hi> SD is the diagonal of a
                    parallelogram of which SC and CD are the sides. Now, if the resolved force in
                    the direction FD parallel to SC were the same on every particle, and equal <hi
                    rend="italic">to f,</hi> it would have no tendency to produce rotation in the
                    spheroid; we may therefore conceive the force on any particle which tends to
                    produce rotation to be the difference between the part of the force acting on
                    that particle in the direction parallel to SC, and the force <hi rend="italic"
                    >f</hi> acting on the particle at C. Hence the force on D tending to impress a
                    rotatory motion on the spheroid is <hi rend="italic">p</hi> ∕SC2 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> φ</hi> SC <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">p</hi>
                    SC3—SD3 ∕ (SC—SD) (SC <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +∙SC ∙ SD-∣-SD2) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> j</hi> ' ∖SD2 ' SD <hi rend="superscript"> - 1</hi> ∕~ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> l,</hi> ’ SD3 <hi rend="italic">~d '</hi> ~ SD3</p>
                <p>Nowbyreasonof the great distance of thesun in comparisonof the radius of the
                    earth, SD is very nearly parallel to SC, and equal to SC—CE. Substituting
                    therefore SC—CE for SD, and neglecting terms divided by SC <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> which are so small</p>
                <p>, , <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. ... . <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>, <hi
                    rend="subscript"> t</hi> SC <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + SC∙SD + SD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> as to be altogether insensible, the factor ≈—srvr^
                    <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi></p>
                <p>SD <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi></p>
                <p>3</p>
                <p>becomes - -∙, and consequently the above expression is</p>
                <p>CE CE</p>
                <p>reduced to 3f., or to 3 A ~ <hi rend="subscript"> z</hi> √-, since the difference
                    <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> SD <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> SC</p>
                <p>between l÷SD and l-÷-SC is a quantity divided by SC <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>, and therefore insensible. This is the part of the force on D which tends
                    to turn the spheroid about the diameter of the equator which is perpendicular to
                    Qç; and by the principles of mechanics, its efficacy in communicating a rotatory
                    motion to the spheroid is proportional to the distance of its line of direction
                    from the axis, that is, proportional to CF; whence the moment of the force at
                    the point D becomes</p>
                <p>CE&lt;F</p>
                <p>∙ ʹ ∙ SC ∙</p>
                <p>'Assume r=SC, and let S denote the absolute force of the sun, then ∕=S÷r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; and if <hi rend="italic">k—</hi> the density at D,
                    then <hi rend="italic">hdm</hi> is the quantity of matter in the particle <hi
                    rend="italic">dm</hi> at D, and the moment of the force on that particle tending
                    to produce in the spheroid a motion about its centre in the direction QP (which
                    is the general direction of the motion produced by</p>
                <p>3S</p>
                <p>the forces on all the particles) is -— ∙ CE.CF. <hi rend="italic">k.dm</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> the integral of which must be taken for the
                    whole spheroid.</p>
                <p>Draw DM parallel to P∕&gt;, and MN perpendicular to DF, meeting SC in 0, and
                    make</p>
                <p>CM=X, DM=y, SCP=0,</p>
                <p>(¢ being the complement of the sun’s declination) then CE=DN + NF='τ∕ cos i+^ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> sin 0, and CF=MN—MO =ysintf—A7cos0, whence the moment
                    of the force impressed on D becomes <hi rend="italic">kdm</hi> (x <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —# <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) sin ♯ cos <hi
                    rend="italic">⅛∙</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">∙xy</hi> (cos <hi
                    rend="superscript"> e</hi> 0—∙sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0) j-.</p>
                <p>In order to find the integrals <hi rend="italic">fkx</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dm,fky</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dm,J'kxydm</hi> for every particle in the
                    spheroid, let <hi rend="italic">z</hi> be the co-ordinate perpendicular to the
                    plane of the figure, and conceive the whole spheroid to be divided into an
                    infinite number of thin slices parallel to the plane ofτ∕z, the thickness of
                    each slice being <hi rend="italic">dχ</hi>; suppose, again, each slice to be
                    divided into an infinity of parallelepipeds, parallel to the axis <hi
                    rend="italic">z,</hi> and terminated by the surface of the spheroid, the breadth
                    of each being <hi rend="italic">dy</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> and, lastly, let
                    each parallelepiped be divided into an infinite number oflengths, each <hi
                    rend="italic">—dz.</hi> The element of the volume, <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>
                    then becomes <hi rend="italic">dxdydz</hi>; and consequently the sum of <hi
                    rend="italic">kχ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >din</hi> in respect of every particle is expressed by the triple integral <hi
                    rend="italic">fffkx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dxdydz.</hi></p>
                <p>Assuming x <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, <hi rend="italic">dx</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">dy</hi> to be constant, and integrating with respect to <hi
                    rend="italic">z,</hi> we obtain <hi rend="italic">kχ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dxdyz A-const.</hi> Let ¢z= the
                    semi-diameter of the equator, <hi rend="italic">b~</hi> the polar semi-axis, and
                    the equation of the spheroid i≡~ + y^4 2^~B fr° <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi>
                    which the limits of <hi rend="italic">z</hi> must be found. This equation gives
                    for a point at the surface, <hi rend="italic">z~z±za J</hi> ; '∑1 ^i,andbe-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> tween those values of <hi
                    rend="italic">z</hi> the definite integral becomes</p>
                <p>τ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 77≡</p>
                <p>1— ⅜-,</p>
                <p>α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Z&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>This expresses the sum of <hi rend="italic">kχ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic">dm</hi> for the parallelepiped corresponding to a given
                    value of <hi rend="italic">x.</hi></p>
                <p>If we next suppose <hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">dx</hi> to be constant, and integrate this expression with
                    respect to <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> we shall have the sum of <hi rend="italic"
                    >kχ-din</hi> for the slice, the distance of which from the plane <hi
                    rend="italic">,, , . xU</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">‘2 /2 ^ ~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> X ÌÌ</hi> 1 1</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">yz</hi> is <hi rend="italic">χ.</hi> Make 1 , or <hi
                    rend="italic">u—b</hi> —, and the <hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">α</hi> “<hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">' a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> υ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="subscript"> z</hi> ——</p>
                <p>expression becomes ——— <hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >J</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> u</hi><hi rend="italic">v y2. dy.</hi> In
                    integrat-</p>
                <p>ing this expression, the limits of <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> in respect, of any
                    given value of a∙, are obtained from the equation of the section of <hi
                    rend="italic">•</hi><hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">ι∕</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> the
                    ellipsoid in the plane <hi rend="italic">χy,</hi> namely ^y+ — 1∙ This</p>
                <p>Z» <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> equation gives# <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">-b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> —; whence, at
                    thelimitsy <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =w <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and
                    therefore #= <hi rend="italic">z±zu.</hi> Now, by a known formula, the intcgrai
                    y^∕u <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — <hi rend="italic">y-∙dy</hi> from <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi> to <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">= + u</hi> is
                    ½ τr <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> (π being the
                    ratio of the circumference to the diameter); therefore the integral of <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dm</hi> for the slice corresponding to a <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1 c</hi><hi rend="italic">. Tikau</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">dX , . ,</hi>... A</p>
                <p>given value of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is; winch, on substituting for <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >-</hi> u <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, its value 7&gt; <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 2</hi> — —- <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript
                    smallcaps"> q</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ,</hi> becomes <hi rend="italic"
                    >a-</hi><hi rend="italic">πk- (a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">)dx. α</hi></p>
                <p>We have lastly to integrate this expression from <hi rend="italic">x=</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. m <hi rend="subscript"> 1 1 1</hi>
                    i ,. . <hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> c</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">2.∙nkb</hi> to <hi rend="italic">x— + a∙</hi> The integral between
                    those limits is <hi rend="italic">(d</hi><hi rend="italic">ei'*</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi> y — —}; whence we have ultimately, in respect of the whole
                    spheroid, <hi rend="italic">fff kx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dxdydz=f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >τrka</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">b.</hi></p>
                <p>On going through the same process <hi rend="italic">fory</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dm,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dxdydz,</hi> and observing
                    that the integral <hi rend="italic">J'y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">Ju</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">y-∙dy</hi> from <hi rend="italic">y=</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">uloy—A-u</hi> is ½ mi <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 4</hi>, there results for the whole spheroid <hi
                    rend="italic">fffky</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dxdydz≈A</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">τrka</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p>With respect to the remaining integral <hi rend="italic">fxydm,</hi> it is easy
                    to see that its value in respect of the whole spheroid must <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193538992" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8992-0509"/>be 0, for on integrating <hi
                    rend="italic">kxydxdydx</hi> with respect to <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> there
                    results <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">kx</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">ydydz,</hi> which vanishes on giving <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi> all values between — <hi rend="italic">t</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">-t, t</hi> being
                    any definite quantity.</p>
                <p>From these values of <hi rend="italic">'Jx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">dm,fy</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dm,fxydm,∙we,</hi> obtain the following expression for the moment
                    of all the forces impressed on the spheroid,</p>
                <p>—. Zζ <hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >-b(a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">-b</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">}</hi> sin <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ô</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ð. r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> lo
                    <hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 2. To determine the efficacy of the sun’s
                    attraction to turn the spheroid about its centre, the earth being supposed
                    heterogeneous.</p>
                <p>Conceive the spheroid to be composed of infinitely thin concentric layers,
                    bounded by spheroidal surfaces, and suppose the ellipticity and density to be
                    different for each layer, but both to be functions of the distance from the
                    centre of the spheroid. Let <hi rend="italic">α</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >β</hi> be respectively the equatorial and polar semi-diameters of the layer
                    which contains a particle <hi rend="italic">dm, e==</hi> its ellipticity, and
                    <hi rend="italic">k</hi> its density. In order to find the moment of all the
                    forces impressed on the spheroid, we must first find an expression in terms of
                    <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> for their moment on the elementary layer containing
                    <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi> and then integrate this expression from /3=0 to <hi
                    rend="italic">β≈b.</hi> Now, suppose all the matter of the spheroid exterior to
                    the layer in question to be removed, and suppose also for a moment the matter in
                    the interior of the spheroidal surface passing through <hi rend="italic">dm</hi>
                    to be all of the same density, <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> then the moment of the
                    impressed forces on the spheroid whose surface passes through <hi rend="italic"
                    >dm,</hi> is by the last proposition</p>
                <p>3S <hi rend="italic">4ττ , ,</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> n</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ka</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">β(a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> z</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> ∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) sm <hi rend="italic"
                    >ô</hi> eos <hi rend="italic">ô. r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi>
                    15</p>
                <p>The variable part of this expression isΛα <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕3(α <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>). Now, since
                    &lt;ι=∕3(1 +β), we have, on neglecting terms multiplied by t <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, which, by reason of the smallness of the earth’s
                    ellipticity are altogether insensible, <hi rend="smallcaps">λ</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">=∕3</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">+</hi> 2∕3 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> e and α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — <hi
                    rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=z2β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">e,</hi> whence
                    Aα <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕3(α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —∕3 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)=2Λ∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> e. Suppose now
                    the semi-axis <hi rend="italic">β</hi> to receive an infinitely small increment,
                    and to become <hi rend="italic">β-</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >-dβ</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> then since <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> are both functions of <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> the
                    expression <hi rend="italic">Tkβ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> c,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> will become <hi rend="italic">2kβ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 5</hi><hi rend="italic">e +</hi> ∙jqq <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>
                    ; <hi rend="subscript"> s t</hi> ; <hi rend="subscript"> le va</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">dβ</hi> riable part of the
                    moment of the forces on the spheroid whose semiaxis is <hi rend="italic"
                    >βA∙dβ</hi>; consequently, in respect of the spheroidal layer which remains on
                    subtracting the spheroid i ∙ ∙ „ ∙ i <hi rend="italic">2d(kβ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">e) .</hi> whose semiaxis is
                    <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> it becomes ——-—⅛∕3. Let the mte- <hi rend="italic"
                    >dβ</hi> gral of this expression between the limits /3=0 and ∕3=δbe denoted by 2
                    F (∕3); then the moment of all the forces impressed on the spheroid supposed
                    heterogeneous is</p>
                <p>3S 8π</p>
                <p>—. — F <hi rend="italic">(β)</hi> sm <hi rend="italic">ð</hi> eos <hi
                    rend="italic">ð. r∙</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> y</hi> 15′ <hi
                    rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 3. To determine the angular velocity &lt;p generated by
                    the sun’s force, and the position of the equator after the infinitely small time
                    <hi rend="italic">dt.</hi></p>
                <p>By dynamics, the angular velocity of rotation is equal to the moment of the
                    impressed forces divided by the moment of inertia of the mass to be moved. Now,
                    the moment of inertia of a body, with respect to a given axis of rotation, is
                    the sum of the products obtained by multiplying each particle of the body into
                    the square of its distance from the axis; that is, in respect of the axis <hi
                    rend="italic">z,</hi> about which the impressed forces tend to turn the
                    spheroid, the moment of inertia <hi rend="italic">is f(x</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">-j-y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">)dm,</hi> supposing the spheroid homogeneous, and the
                    density Z, <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> =1. But it has been shewn that in
                    thiseasej⅛ <hi rend="italic">dmz=yÇ¶ra</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    4</hi><hi rend="italic">b,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jy</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dm=f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    s</hi><hi rend="italic">πa</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi>; therefore the moment
                    of inertia of the spheroid is <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅛τiz <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0(n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +^ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>). And by prop. 1, the moment of the impressed forces
                    is <hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">. f</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">ττa</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">b^a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> 6 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) sin <hi rend="italic"
                    >ō</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ô,</hi> therefore</p>
                <p>__3S <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">~b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >-</hi><hi rend="superscript"> φ</hi> ~^∙^+T≡ <hi rend="superscript"> sin</hi> ^
                    <hi rend="superscript"> cosa</hi></p>
                <p>In the ease of the heterogeneous spheroid the moment of inertia is thus found. As
                    before, let <hi rend="subscript"> α</hi> and <hi rend="italic">β</hi> be the
                    equatorial and polar semiaxes of the spheroidal surface passing through the
                    particle <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi> then if the matter within this surface be
                    supposed of uniform density <hi rend="italic">=k,</hi> the moment of inertia of
                    this spheroid, by what is already shewn, is <hi rend="italic">‰kα</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">β(α</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> + ∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>). But α <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =2 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> y</hi> δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2∕3e, and <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >β=β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">+</hi> 2∕3∙¼
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">β(</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> a</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> +∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)=2∕3 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi> + 6∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> e; and since <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> is a • very small quantity, the second term of this
                    expression is very small, and may be neglected in comparison of the first;
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">ka</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> ∕3(<hi
                    rend="subscript"> α</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +∕3 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)=2λ∙∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi>. For the
                    spheroid whose sermaxis is <hi rend="italic">β-}-dβ,</hi> this quantity becomes
                    2A∙∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> + <hi rend="italic">^dβ, dβ</hi> and
                    therefore in respect of the elementary spheroidal layer the semiaxes of whose
                    interior and exterior surfaces are <hi rend="italic">β 2d(kβ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 5y</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >β + dβ,</hi> it is ——— <hi rend="italic">dβ.</hi> Let 2F ʹ (∕3) denote the
                    integral of this quantity from /3=0 to <hi rend="italic">β=b,</hi> that is, let
                    <hi rend="italic">Γ^^-dβ</hi><hi rend="italic">J</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dβ</hi></p>
                <p>=2F ʹ (β), and the moment of inertia of the heterogeneous Sττ</p>
                <p>spheroid becomes — F ʹ (∕3). But the moment of the im-io <hi rend="subscript"> 1
                    c</hi>. . „ 3S 8τr pressed forces is by prop. 2, =-. — F(<hi rend="subscript">
                    i</hi> β) sin <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">θ,</hi> therefore
                    in the case of the heterogeneous spheroid, <hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi> 3S F(∕3)
                    . <hi rend="subscript"> λ λ</hi><hi rend="italic">φ=z</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">)
                    &lt;</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> eos <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 3</hi> F
                    ʹ (∕3) α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi> Let us assume K= ——— in
                    the case of the homo&lt;re- <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">A-b~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    o</hi></p>
                <p>F(∕3)</p>
                <p>neous spheroid, and K= =τ~( in the ease of the heterose- <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >F</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> z</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(∕3)</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> ö</hi> neous spheroid, and we have for both cases,
                    3S.K .</p>
                <p>&lt;⅛= —— sin <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> eos <hi rend="italic">ß.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">'i</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >5</hi></p>
                <p>Now to find the place of the pole, and the position of the equator after the
                    small interval of time <hi rend="italic">dt,</hi> we must apply the first of the
                    two theorems above premised. If the earth had no diurnal rotation, the sun’s
                    force would cause it to revolve about an axis passing through C perpendicular to
                    the meridian PQpy, or perpendicular to the plane of the paper, so as to bring
                    the point Q nearer to the line SC, with a velocity =&lt;∕&gt;. But the earth is
                    already revolving about the axis <hi rend="italic">Ρp,</hi> with a velocity <hi
                    rend="italic">=v,</hi> and in the direction which raises the point <hi
                    rend="italic">q</hi> above the plane of the paper. Hence, by theorem 1, the new
                    axis of rotation will be in the plane passing through <hi rend="italic">Pp,</hi>
                    perpendicular to the plane of the paper, and after the time <hi rend="italic"
                    >dt</hi> will make with <hi rend="italic">Pp</hi> an angle whose tangent = —,
                    the pole P rising above the plane of the paper; and the new equator will
                    intersect the former in the line <hi rend="italic">Q,q,</hi> and make with it an
                    angle whose tangent is also —. The <hi rend="italic">v</hi> cffcet of the
                    compound motion is thus to twist as it were the equator about the line <hi
                    rend="italic">Q,q</hi> as an axis, or about that diameter of the equator which
                    lies in the same meridian with the sun, instead of twisting it about the
                    diameter perpendicular to that meridian, as would be the case if the earth had
                    no diurnal motion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop. 4. To</hi> find the amount of the solar precession after
                    any given time.</p>
                <p>Let AB be the intersection of the plane of the ecliptic, with the surface of
                    sphere whose centre is at the centre of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193539005"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-9005-0510"/>the earth; let ACB be the equator, and S the
                    projection of the sun’s place in the ecliptic. Now, the plane of the equator
                    being always perpendicular to the axis of rotation, when the axis changes its
                    position the equator will also change its position, and the new equator will
                    intersect the former in an angle equal to the deviation of the axis. Let A ʹ CB
                    ʹ be the new position of the equator, after the infinitely small time <hi
                    rend="italic">dt,</hi> intersecting the former in C, then the angle ACA ʹ is the
                    measure of the momentary deviation of the axis, and AA ʹ, which is the amount of
                    variation in the place of the node, is the precession in the time <hi
                    rend="italic">dt.</hi></p>
                <p>From the properties of spherical triangles we have sin SAC: sin ACA ʹ:: sin A ʹ
                    C: sin AA ʹ. But because ACA ʹ is a very small angle, and AA ʹ a very small arc,
                    the arcs may be taken instead of the sines; whence, since ci <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">tì</hi> A C <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></p>
                <p>A ʹ C = AC, the proportion gives AA ʹ = ACA ʹ.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> r b</hi> sin SAC</p>
                <p>ó 3S K</p>
                <p>But by the lastproposition tan AC A ʹ = — = —'~ sin ¢ cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >i,</hi> therefore, as the small arc may be substituted for its tangent, 3S.K
                    sin AC . .</p>
                <p>AA = — ;———- sin <hi rend="italic">ō</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ô.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vr</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 5</hi> sin SAC</p>
                <p>It will now be convenient to express this value of AA ʹ in terms of the sun’s
                    longitude and the obliquity of the ecliptic. Since the equator, as was shewn in
                    the last proposition, is twisted about the diameter which is in the same
                    meridian with the sun, it follows that the line joining S and C is a part of the
                    meridian; whence ACS is a right angle, and SC (the sun’s declination)≈90° — <hi
                    rend="italic">ê.</hi> Let Z=AS, (the sun’s longitude), and I=SAC, (the obliquity
                    of the ecliptic), then, in the right angled spherical triangle SAC, we have cos
                    SC . cos AC=cos AS, or sin <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> cos AC==cos <hi
                    rend="italic">l</hi>; and sin SC= sin SAC sin AS, or cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >ê—</hi> sin I sin <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> therefore <hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> •</hi><hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> λ</hi> ≡i <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> I sin <hi
                    rend="superscript"> cos</hi> sm <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >θ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> cos</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">ac</hi> ’ Again, i <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> the same
                    triangle we have tan AC=cos SAC tan AS, whence sin AC=cos AC cos I tan Z, and
                    (dividing by sin SAC= sin I) <hi rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    underline"> n</hi><hi rend="underline">A</hi> 9- — <hi rend="superscript">
                    j</hi> sin SAC ~ cos AC cos I sin <hi rend="italic">l .</hi></p>
                <p>- . . Substituting these values of sin <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> cos <hi
                    rend="italic">ô</hi> olll X LUS <hi rend="italic">V</hi></p>
                <p>, sin AC , and <hi rend="strikethrough">~s^Xc</hi><hi rend="superscript"> ιn the
                    above</hi> value of AA ʹ, we get</p>
                <p>3S K</p>
                <p>AA ʹ = —— cos I sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Z.</p>
                <p>This is the solar precession in the element of time <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> consequently for a given time T we have solar precession =
                    <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi><hi rend="italic">pg</hi> the integral being
                    taken from i=0 to i=T.</p>
                <p>To prepare this expression for integration, <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> ≡ and
                    <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> must be expressed in terms of <hi rend="italic">l</hi>
                    and known quantities Let α=semiaxis major of the earth’s orbit, ε=its
                    eccentricity T≈a sidereal year, then <hi rend="italic">r</hi> being the radius
                    vector and <hi rend="italic">dl</hi> the angle described in the time <hi
                    rend="italic">dt, l</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >*dl</hi> is the space passed over by the radius vector in the element of the
                    time, and by Kepler’s law of the equable description of areas we’have <hi
                    rend="italic">dt</hi>: T :: ½r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> cZZ: area of
                    orbit.</p>
                <p>Now the area of the orbit is πα <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> x</hi> ∕l- <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>, therefore this pro-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tr</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dl</hi> portion gives <hi rend="italic">dt=z -</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> But
                    it is shewn in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy,</hi> part iii. art.
                    10, that T=2π√α÷ <hi rend="subscript"> χ</hi> ∕p∖ where F is the attracting
                    force at the mean distance <hi rend="italic">a.</hi></p>
                <p>But we have assumed S to denote the sun’s force at the unit of distance;
                    therefore, the forces being inversely as the squares of the distances, F=S÷α <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, whence T= <hi rend="underline">-</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript underline"> π</hi><hi rend="underline">~</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript underline"> a</hi> _</p>
                <p>√S '</p>
                <p>From this formula we get S= - <hi rend="strikethrough">7-</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript strikethrough"> α</hi>, and therefore ~ <hi rend="superscript"
                    > di</hi></p>
                <p>1 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> 5</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2nadl</hi></p>
                <p>— —- <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∙ Again, assuming λ= longitude of sun’s
                    perigee, the polar equation of the ellipse gives <hi rend="italic">r =</hi></p>
                <p>α(1—ε <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) , <hi rend="italic">Sxlt</hi>
                    2τrjΙ+εcos(Z—λ)i&lt;ZZ</p>
                <p>1+ecos(Z-λ) <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> ~ T(1-ε
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)2 ’ <hi rend="superscript"> d</hi> the above
                    expression becomes</p>
                <p>. 6τrK cos I r∙</p>
                <p>solar precession = ∕ <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> ; <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi>
                    2Zn + ecos(λ-Z] <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> Z∕.</p>
                <p>Tr(1- <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> 2)V <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi></p>
                <p>The expression under the sign of integration consists of two parts, of which the
                    first <hi rend="italic">f</hi> sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ZrfZ=½(C + Z—
                    cos Z sin Z). (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fluxions,</hi> art. 153.) The second
                    part, namely <hi rend="italic">fe</hi> sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Z
                    cos(Z—λ)cZZ, when integrated becomes e sin(Z—λ)</p>
                <p>sin(Z+λ)— — sin(3Z—λ), but by reason of the smallness <hi rend="italic">Zi</hi>
                    0</p>
                <p>of ε these terms are insensible, and are therefore neglected. Rejecting also the
                    terms in the divisor of the coefficient which are multiplied by ε <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and observing that cos Z sin <hi rend="italic">l—
                    ½</hi> sin 2Z, we obtain, finally, <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. 3χK <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">cos</hi> I . <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>, , , .</p>
                <p>solar precession= — (C+Z—½ sin 2Z).</p>
                <p>The first term of this expression, which depends on C + Z, or on the sun’s
                    longitude, is the constant or uniform precession. Its amount in one year is
                    found by supposing , <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>, . 1 1 r&gt; J ∙ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 67r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> K cos I</p>
                <p>Z to be increased by 2π∙, and is consequently y .</p>
                <p>The second is periodic, and being proportional to twice the sine of the sun’s
                    longitude, it runs through its changes in half a-year. It is usually regarded as
                    a part of solar nutation, and called <hi rend="italic">the solar equation of the
                    equinoxes in longitude.</hi><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 5. To find the
                    diminution of the obliquity of the ecliptic produced by the sun’s
                    attraction.</p>
                <p>Referring to the last diagram, make AE=EB=90°, and let ED be perpendicular to AB
                    the ecliptic, and meet A ʹ CB ʹ in E ʹ, then EE ʹ is the small change in the
                    inclination in the time <hi rend="italic">dt.</hi> In the triangle ECE ʹ, we
                    have sin EE ʹ = sin CE sin ECE ʹ. But EE ʹ being very small, the arc may be
                    taken for the sine, and therefore EE ʹ == sin CE sin ECE'.</p>
                <p>cos Z</p>
                <p>Now sin CE= cos AC= —7; and it has been already sin ∂ <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">φ</hi> 3S.K</p>
                <p>seen that sin ECE ʹ = AC A ʹ =- = — sinocos£; therefore <hi rend="italic">v
                    r</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >υ</hi></p>
                <p>3S.K</p>
                <p>EE ʹ = —-— cos <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> cos Z, or since cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >ô</hi> = sin I sin Z, EE ʹ = <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">ν</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi></p>
                <p>3S K</p>
                <p>--~- sin I sin Z cos Z. Multiplying by <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> i</hi> and making the same substitutions as in the last proposition,
                    we have</p>
                <p>_ 6πK ∕ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> *</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">∕eE</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> z</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">&lt;Z∕ =</hi> ——- sin I /sinZcos Zp +ε&gt;cos(Z-λ)WZ, <hi
                    rend="italic">J</hi> Tf(l-e≡p <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> ≠</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193539018" xml:id="kp-eb0718-9018-0511"/>
                <p>whence neglecting as before terms multiplied by <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and
                    integrating, there results <hi rend="italic">íVM/dt—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> sin I cos 2Z, <hi rend="italic">J 2 lv</hi> for the solar nutation in
                    obliquity. This expression, depending on twice the cosine of the sun’s
                    longitude, runs through all its changes in half a year; but its greatest value
                    amounts to scarcely half a second, and is consequently altogether insensible to
                    observation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 6. To investigate the precessional motion of the
                    equinoxes produced by the moon. Let</p>
                <p>Μ — moon’s mass,</p>
                <p>E — earth’s mass,</p>
                <p>I' = inclination of moon’s orbit to the equator, <hi rend="italic">l</hi> ’ =
                    moon’s distance from the intersection of her orbit with the equator, <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> ’ = radius vector of the moon’s orbit, <hi rend="italic"
                    >a'</hi> = semitransverse axis of moon’s orbit, <hi rend="italic">d</hi> =
                    eccentricity of the lunar orbit, T'= sidereal time of revolution, then, by
                    following exactly the same reasoning as was pursued in <hi rend="italic">prop.
                    4,</hi> there results for the retrograde motion of the points in which the plane
                    of the lunar orbit intersects the plane of the equator (corresponding to the
                    solar precession in <hi rend="italic">prop.</hi> 4.), the expression</p>
                <p>3M.K cos I ʹ /sin <hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">l</hi> ’
                    <hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="italic">∕</hi><hi rend="italic">——</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dt.</hi><hi rend="italic">v ,; τ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">Tr</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    r</hi><hi rend="italic">*dl'</hi>, α ʹ (1-√ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)</p>
                <p>Now, we have αZ= . <hi rend="underline">·</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r ~</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi></p>
                <p>2 <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> rα' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> √1-√^ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> + e'cos(λ'-Z ʹ)</p>
                <p>of T ’ fl +e ’ cos(λ ʹ-Z ʹ)7 <hi rend="italic">dl</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> n</hi><hi rend="italic">. ,</hi> therefore — = -—- <hi rend="italic"
                    >-A</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> But in the pre-</p>
                <p>√3 3 <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">2πa</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> r3</hi> 1 —√ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)⅛</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2τra</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi> sent case T ’ =
                    - <hi rend="subscript"> 77τ</hi>,—√,χ (for the mass of the moon cannot √(E + M)
                    <hi rend="superscript"> v</hi> be neglected in comparison of that of the earth,
                    as the mass of the earth is neglected in comparison of that of the sun),</p>
                <p>1 4√-</p>
                <p>hence ~- = _. _ , .,r∙ The above expression therefore α <hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi> I <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (E+M)</p>
                <p>becomes</p>
                <p>6πM.KeosI' <hi rend="italic">F</hi><hi rend="italic">. .,</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">, ,</hi></p>
                <p>∕ sm <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Z{1 + ∈ cos (a·—Z ʹ)dZ ʹ, ], TT∙(E+M)(1- <hi
                    rend="subscript"> e</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)⅜' <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 7</hi> the integral of which (rejecting, as before, terms
                    multiplied by e ʹ) gives</p>
                <p>3a∙M.K cos I ʹ.. . .</p>
                <p><hi rend="strikethrough"/><hi rend="strikethrough">7</hi><hi rend="subscript
                    strikethrough"> l</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">.</hi> 7- <hi rend="subscript">
                    z</hi>-√,—r7τ- (C + Z ʹ —½ sin <hi rend="italic">2f).</hi></p>
                <p>1′ v(E+M) <hi rend="superscript"> v 2 7</hi> for the regression of the equator on
                    the plane of the lunar orbit. Suppose Z ’ to be increased by <hi rend="italic"
                    >2π,</hi> or a whole circumference, the regression caused by the moon’s action
                    in a</p>
                <p>. <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, , . . 6π <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> M .K cos
                    I ʹ sidereal revolution becomes , <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>,,∙ &gt; , <hi
                    rend="subscript"> λ</hi> — <hi rend="subscript"> ττ</hi>-—.</p>
                <p>T ʹ r(E + M)</p>
                <p>It is now necessary to reduce this retrograde motion to the plane of the
                    ecliptic.</p>
                <p>Let AB be the ecliptic, ACB the equator, A'CB ʹ the new position of the equator,
                    and FH the plane of the lunar orbit intersecting the new equator in F ʹ and H ʹ,
                    and the ecliptic in N. The mean effect of the moon’s action in the course of a
                    month, if the earth had no motion of rotation, would be to bring the equator
                    nearer the plane of the hinar orbit, causing it to revolve about the line of its
                    intersection with the lunar orbit; therefore by <hi rend="italic">Theorem</hi>
                    I., the momentary axis of rotation lies in the plane passing through that line
                    and the pole of the equator, and the equator is consequently twisted about the
                    equatorial diameter which is perpendicular to the intersection of the equator
                    and lunar orbit. Hence,FC=CHandF ʹ C= CH'; and since FC + CH==180°, therefore FC
                    and F ʹ C are quadrantal arcs, and the two triangles CFF and CHH ʹ are in all
                    respects equal. Now sin FC: CF ʹ F:: sin FF':: ACA ʹ, that is, 1: sin I':: FF'::
                    ACA ʹ, and sin CA ʹ A: sin AC:: sin ACA':: sin AA ʹ, that is, sin I: cos AF::
                    ACA ’:: AA ʹ, therefor e, sin I: sin I' cos AF:: FF ʹ: A A', and
                    consequently,</p>
                <p>. F'F sin I ʹ cos AF AA ʹ = <hi rend="subscript">:</hi> — .</p>
                <p>sin I</p>
                <p>But AA' represents the velocity along the ecliptic, and FF ʹ the velocity along
                    the plane of the moon’s orbit, and we have seen that the motion along this plane
                    is 6π <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> K.M cos I ʹ. <hi rend="subscript"> v</hi>.
                    <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> v</hi>. <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 1 1</hi><hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> ⅛</hi><hi rend="strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> ∣</hi><hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> ∕</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough                     smallcaps"> /t?</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> . ⅝&lt;</hi><hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps">
                    ∖</hi> &gt; <hi rend="superscript"> ιn the</hi> time 1 , or a sidereal
                    revolution. Di- 1′ t∙(L+M)</p>
                <p>viding this by T ʹ, we get the mean velocity in the plane of the orbit in the
                    unit of time; whence FF'= <hi rend="strikethrough">θΣ,...^^</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript strikethrough"> c</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">θ</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript strikethrough"> s</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough">
                    r</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">&lt;.</hi></p>
                <p>T ʹ ⅛(E + M)</p>
                <p>+ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> K Μ</p>
                <p>For the sake of brevity let Q= — <hi rend="italic">f</hi> ——-,thenFF'=Q 1′ W(E +
                    M)</p>
                <p>cos I', and we have</p>
                <p>... Q cos I ʹ sin I ’ cos AF AA ʹ ≈= :— .</p>
                <p>sin 1</p>
                <p>We must now express cos I ʹ sin I ʹ cos AF, in terms of the obliquity and
                    inclination of the lunar orbit to the ecliptic. Let Z=ANF= inclination of moon’s
                    orbit to the ecliptic, ri-NA, the longitude of the node; then in the triangle
                    ANF, we have by spherical trigonometry, cos ANF= cos NAF cos NFA+ sin NAF sin
                    NFAcos AF, that is, since NAF=I, NFA=I ʹ, cos i=cos I cos I'+sin I sin I' cos
                    AF,</p>
                <p>In like manner, in the same triangle, cos I ʹ = cos I cos z'+ sin I sin <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">n.</hi></p>
                <p>From these two equations we obtain this other, cos I ʹ sin I ʹ cos AF=cos I sin I
                    cos <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi></p>
                <p>—(cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 1—sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 1) cos
                    ∙ sin <hi rend="italic">i</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">n</hi> —cos I sin I sin <hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi> cos <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">n,</hi> which, on substituting in it cos
                    21 for cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> I—sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    1, ½ sin <hi rend="italic">2i</hi> for cos <hi rend="italic">i</hi> sin <hi
                    rend="italic">i,</hi> and ½+½ cos <hi rend="italic">2n</hi> for cos <hi
                    rend="italic                         superscript"> 9</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >n,</hi> becomes cos l’ sin I ʹ cos AF =cos I sin I (cos <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi> —½ sin <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> Z)</p>
                <p>—½ cos 21 sin <hi rend="italic">2i</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">η</hi></p>
                <p>—⅛ cos I sin I sin <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi>
                    cos <hi rend="italic">2n.</hi></p>
                <p>Assuming z(the inclination of the moon’s orbit) to be constant, which may be done
                    in the present case without sensible error, the only variable in this expression
                    is w, (the longitude of the node), which, on the supposition of <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> constant, is proportional to the time. Let τ denote the
                    time of a revolution of the node, then for any time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>
                    Ave have <hi rend="italic">2ττt</hi><hi rend="italic">n—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> On making this substitution in the last
                    equation, Ave obtain by means of it</p>
                <p>A A'=Q cos I (cos <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >i</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> I sin <hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ι)</hi></p>
                <p>½ cos 21 . . 2⅛r&lt;</p>
                <p>— —;—sm <hi rend="smallcaps">2í</hi> cos — sin I τ</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> T ∙ o∙ 4îT&lt; 1 —⅛ cos 1 sm <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> ι cos &gt;</p>
                <p>Now, if we assume y=the regression of the equinoctial points on the ecliptic
                    caused by the lunar action, and suppose<pb break="no" facs="nls:193539031"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-9031-0512"/><hi rend="italic">y</hi> a function of <hi
                    rend="italic">t,</hi> then AA'= ~. and the amount of <hi rend="italic">dt</hi>
                    this regression in a given time = <hi rend="italic">f -'L dt.</hi> Multiplying
                    therefore the right hand side of the last equation by <hi rend="italic">dt,</hi>
                    and integrating, ^observing that <hi rend="italic">J</hi> cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >dt—</hi> sin —ζ</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">, P</hi> 4π&lt; _ τ . 4τri∖ <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi>, „</p>
                <p>and <hi rend="italic">J</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">dt ~</hi> — sin ì, we obtain,
                    finally, for the regression of the equinoctial points, or the processional
                    motion of the equinoxes, produced by the moon in the time <hi rend="italic"
                    >t,</hi></p>
                <p>Q cos I (cos <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> ½ sin <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ι)t</hi><hi rend="italic">τ</hi> cos 21 sin 2? . <hi rend="italic"
                    >2τrt</hi></p>
                <p>— -7 :—ψ sin</p>
                <p>4w sin I τ</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">r . . . 4πt )</hi></p>
                <p>— — cos 1 sin <hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi> sin —
                    &gt; + const.</p>
                <p>C7Γ T J</p>
                <p>The first term of this expression increases uniformly with the time, and is
                    called the <hi rend="italic">lunar precession.</hi> The second</p>
                <p>2τri term, being multiplied by sin —, is periodic, and depends on the mean
                    longitude of the moon’s ascending node. It is called the <hi rend="italic">lunar
                    equation of the equinoxes in longitude.</hi> The third term is also periodic,
                    but its numerical value is so small as to be insensible, and it is therefore
                    omitted in the calculation. The lunar precession in a sidereal year is found by
                    substituting T for <hi rend="italic">t</hi> in the first term, and we have,
                    therefore, lunar annual precession =Q, cos I (cos <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> ½ sin <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z)T.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 7∙ To find the diminution in the inclination of the
                    equator to the ecliptic produced by the moon’s action.</p>
                <p>Let AB be bisected in D, and let DE be an arc perpendicular to AB, and meeting
                    A'B' in E ’; then the alteration of obliquity produced by the moon in the time
                    <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> is represented by EE'. Now in the triangle CFF' we
                    have sin CF': sin CFF':: sin FF': sin FCF', that is, 1: sin I':: FF': FCF'; and
                    in the triangle CEE',</p>
                <p>Sin CE'E: sin CE:: sin ECE': sin EE'</p>
                <p>that is, by reason ofCE=AF (since FC=AE=90°) and ECE'=FCF'</p>
                <p>1: sin AF:: FCF': EE'; whence EE'=FF' sin I' sin AF. Now it was shewn in the last
                    proposition that FF'≈QeosI', therefore</p>
                <p>EE'= Q. cos I' sin I' sin AF.</p>
                <p>To refer this to the ecliptic we have in the triangle NAF, sin NF A: sin ANF::
                    sin AN: sin A F</p>
                <p>which gives the equation sin I' sin AF=sin <hi rend="italic">i</hi> sin <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and, as before we have cos I'= cos
                    I cos z'+sin I sin <hi rend="italic">i</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">η</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> whence multiplying the two equations together, and
                    substituting ½ sin <hi rend="italic">2i</hi> for cos <hi rend="italic">i</hi>
                    sin <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> and ½ sin <hi rend="italic">2n</hi> for cos <hi
                    rend="italic">η</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> we get cos l’ sin I' sin AF=½
                    cos I sin <hi rend="italic">2i</hi> sin τz + ½ sin I sin <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">2n,</hi> 1
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∙ ∙ p ∙ 1 2/TÍ</p>
                <p>and, consequently, writing for <hi rend="italic">n</hi> its value —,</p>
                <p>EE'=Q -∣ ½ cos I sin 2z sin —-+½ sin I sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z* sin
                    —— j- .</p>
                <p>Multiplying this by t⅛and integrating, we obtain for the diminution of the
                    inclination, or <hi rend="italic">lunar nutation in obliquity</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">„</hi><hi rend="italic">∕ τ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    τ</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> o</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">. 2ττt τ .</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> τ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">∙
                    4πt</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi></p>
                <p>—.Q, I — cos I sin <hi rend="italic">2ι</hi> cos 1- — sm I sin z cos ).</p>
                <p>∖4w τ 8τr τ ∕</p>
                <p>Both terms of this expression are periodic; but the second is omitted in the
                    calculation, as being too small to be sensible. Hence we have</p>
                <p>τ . <hi rend="italic">2πt</hi> lunar nutation in obliquity =—Q. . — cos I sin <hi
                    rend="italic">2i</hi> cos —-.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 8. To compute the numerical value of the annual
                    precession.</p>
                <p>, . . 6τr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> KeosI</p>
                <p>By prop. 4. the solar precession in one year = — ∙</p>
                <p>Now Tv is the angle which any point of the earth describes about its axis of
                    rotation in a sidereal year, or 366 ’ 26 days, and consequently = 2τr × 36G ’
                    26. The solar precession <hi rend="subscript"> 1 ρ</hi>, 3τrK cos (23° 28′)
                    therelore becomes ππ7⅛77 ' expressed in parts 0.</p>
                <p>3ob∙2b <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> the radius. To reduce it to seconds, we
                    have, assuming radius = 1, %∙=180° = 180 × GO ×60=G48000 seconds. Substituting
                    this for τr, and computing the above expression by the logarithmic tables we get
                    solar annual precession = K×4869".</p>
                <p>By prop. 6, the lunar precession in a sidereal year (on sub- . . _ ^ . <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1 λ</hi>. 6τr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> K. Μ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> τ z</hi>,.</p>
                <p>stitting for Q its value) is <hi rend="superscript"> c0s</hi> * (<hi
                    rend="superscript"> cos</hi> ‘ —</p>
                <p>½sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z)T. But T'v is the angle described by the
                    diurnal rotation of the earth in one sidereal revolution of the moon, or 27∙32
                    days <hi rend="smallcaps">(Astronomy,</hi> vol. iii. p. 792), and therefore
                    =2;r×27*32. We have also (p. 791), z=5° 8' 47 ’ 9", and, as before, T=366∙26
                    days. Now assuming the moon’s mass = 1-70th of the earth’s mass, M÷(E-j-M)= <hi
                    rend="subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> l</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi>. By the substitution of these numbers, the lunar annual precession
                    becomes</p>
                <p>3π. K × 366∙26 × cos (23° 28') × {1—g sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (5° 8'
                    50") ; 27∙32×27∙32×71</p>
                <p>the calculation of which, reduced to seconds as before, gives lunar annual
                    precession = K× 12176".</p>
                <p>Adding this to the solar annual precession, we obtain the effect produced by the
                    joint action of the sun and moon, or luni-solar annual precession =K ×
                    17045".</p>
                <p>It is now necessary to assign a value to the quantity K which depends on the law
                    of the density of the earth. Supposing</p>
                <p>, , 1 <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> τr <hi rend="superscript"> ft2</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> e</hi>, .</p>
                <p>the earth homogeneous, we have K= <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi> —τ⅛=⅛ ,eeing <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >A∙b</hi> 1— <hi rend="italic">e</hi> the elipticity =—ιp <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(Figure of the Earth,</hi> vol. ix. p.</p>
                <p>563), whence K=^ð. This value of K gives</p>
                <p>17045" luni-solar annual precession =—- <hi rend="strikethrough">θ^-</hi>
                    =5β"∙82.</p>
                <p>The observed quantity is only 50"·4; the difference being occasioned chiefly by
                    the erroneous assumption of the homogeneity of the earth. If the earth be denser
                    towards the centre, (and it is known to be so from other phenomena), the
                    momentum of the protuberant parts will not be so great as if it were equally
                    dense with the interior parts, and the precession will be less. From Cavendish’s
                    experiment, and experiments on the attraction of mountains, it has been
                    ascertained that the mean density of the whole earth is about five times greater
                    than that of water, and twice as great as that of the solid substances composing
                    its exterior crust. But we are entirely ignorant of the law according to which
                    the density varies from the surface towards the centre, and an infinity of
                    hypotheses may be made which would give the observed precession, and at the same
                    time satisfy the condition of a superficial density equal to half the mean
                    density.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 9∙ To compute the numerical value of the solar and
                    lunar nutation.</p>
                <p>The solar nutation consists of two parts. The first is the solar equation of the
                    equinoxes in longitude, or the second term of the expression for the solar
                    precession in prop. 4, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193539044"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-9044-0513"/>its value is 4w~ cos I × ½ sin 2Z. Substituting
                    2τr × 366*26 1 <hi rend="italic">v</hi> r oe ι <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∙ ι
                    ∙ ι 180×60×60 <hi rend="subscript"> ÷ 1 ÷</hi> _</p>
                <p>for 1 <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> and multiplying by — to reduce to se-</p>
                <p>7Γ</p>
                <p>con ds, the computation gives</p>
                <p>1st part of solar nutation ==K × 387 <hi rend="superscript"> zz,</hi> 5 × sin
                    2Z.</p>
                <p>The second part is the nutation in obliquity, found by prop.</p>
                <p>3∙τriv</p>
                <p>5, the value of which is ——sin I×½cos2Z. This being 1 <hi rend="italic">v</hi>
                    computed in the same manner as the last gives</p>
                <p>2d part of solar nutation =K × 168 ″ ∙3 × cos 2Z. Assuming the earth to be
                    homogeneous, and consequently</p>
                <p>K = —we have for the sum of the two parts solar nutation =1 ″ ∙29 sin 2Z+0 ″ ∙56
                    cos 2Z, both terms being so small as to be insensible to observation.</p>
                <p>The lunar nutation is also composed of two parts; the first being the lunar
                    equation of the equinoxes in longitude, or the second term of the expression in
                    prop. 6; and the second the nutation in obliquity found in prop. 7. By prop. 6,
                    the first of these parts is</p>
                <p>3πK . Μ . τ cos 21 sin <hi rend="italic">2i . 2πt</hi> ——— — <hi rend="subscript"
                    > β</hi> ’ ⅞1Γ) -∙</p>
                <p>2T ʹ ⅛(E + M) sin I . τ</p>
                <p>which, since τ=18∙6 × 366∙26 days, becomes, on substituting for the different
                    quantities their numerical values, and reducing to seconds, <hi rend="subscript"
                    > κ</hi> 3x64800×18∙6×366∙26×cos(46°56) sin (10° 17'36) . <hi rend="italic"
                    >2τi</hi> 2(r×(27∙32) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ×2×71 sin (23° 28) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> Sm</hi> V’</p>
                <p>whence there is found from computation, lunar nutation in longitude = K× 6093" ×
                    sin —.</p>
                <p>By prop. 7. the lunar nutation in obliquity becomes, on substituting for Q. its
                    value, and neglecting the sign,</p>
                <p>3%K. M. <hi rend="italic">τ</hi>. . 2%√</p>
                <p><hi rend="strikethrough">2T'⅛(E+M)</hi><hi rend="superscript"> cos 1</hi> × <hi
                    rend="superscript"> sm 2</hi> ' × <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi> V</p>
                <p>Comparing the coefficient of cos ^→n this expression with <hi rend="italic"
                    >2ττt</hi> that of sin — in the above, it is obvious that the latter r</p>
                <p>. z. , , <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. . . <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> „ , cos I
                    sin I sin 21</p>
                <p>is found by multiplying the former by — —</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> cos 21 2 cos 21</p>
                <p>=½ tan 2l=½tan (46°56′). The multiplication gives</p>
                <p>2π∕</p>
                <p>lunar nutation in obliquity =K× 3260" cos .</p>
                <p>Assuming that the earth is homogeneous, and consequently K= <hi rend="italic
                    strikethrough smallcaps"> 3^</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> q∙&gt;</hi> these
                    two parts added together give lunar nutation =20 ″ ∙31 sin —— + 10 ″ ∙88 cos</p>
                <p>The observed values of the coefficients are 18 ″ ∙36 and 9 ″ ∙239, the
                    differences between the observed and computed values, as in the case of the
                    precession, arising from the assumption of the uniform density of the earth.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 10. To determine the motion of the pole of the
                    earth’s axis of rotation.</p>
                <p>As the inclination of the equator to the ecliptic undergoes no permanent
                    alteration in consequence of the action of the sun and moon, and as the
                    precessional motion of the equinoxes is proportional to the time, it follows
                    that, abstracting the effects of lunar and solar nutation, the pole of the
                    equator must describe a circle about the pole of the ecliptic, the plane of
                    which is parallel to the ecliptic, and of which the radius is equal to the sine
                    of the obliquity, or ≡ sin</p>
                <p>(23° 2 8′). The mean velocity corresponding to the regression of the equinoctial
                    points, is 50 ″.4 in a year, and consequently the period of a revolution is
                    about 25900 years. Now in order to take account of the lunar nutation (the
                    solar, as has already been remarked, is scarcely sensible), it is only necessary
                    to remark that the absolute velocity of the pole in its small circle, is to the
                    velocity with which the equinoctial points regress in the ecliptic, as the
                    radius of the small circle to the radius of the ecliptic, or as sin 1:1. Hence
                    the motion of the pole in the plane of the small circle, is obtained by
                    multiplying the expression in prop. 6, by sin I; and therefore the correction to
                    be applied to the uniform motion of the pole, is the second term of that
                    expression, multiplied by sin I, or sin I × lunar equation of the equinoxes in
                    longitude. But by prop. 9, this term = K × 6093 ″ sin therefore the
                    corresponding motion of the pole =</p>
                <p>K × 6093 ″ sin (23° 28′)!sin — = K × 2427′ ' sin —.</p>
                <p>With respect to the second part of the nutation, it is obvious that any change of
                    obliquity produces an equal change in the place of the pole on the meridian, and
                    therefore, by the last proposition, the motion of the pole in this <hi
                    rend="italic">2πt</hi> direction is K× 3260" cos —. Now let K × 2427 ″ =α, and
                    K×326θ ″ =δ, and let the motion of the pole in the two directions be
                    respectively denoted by <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>
                    we have <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. 2π∕, <hi rend="italic">2πt</hi> then a≈αsm
                    -— <hi rend="italic">,y=b cos</hi>; and consequently the equa tion</p>
                <p>— -+-—=1; <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2÷</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">b*</hi> ’ which is the equation to an ellipse, and shews that the
                    pole describes a small ellipse about its mean place in the course of a
                    revolution of the nodes, as was discovered by Bradley from observation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prop.</hi> 11. From the observed values of the precession and
                    nutation, to determine the ratio of the moon’s mass to the mass of the
                    earth.</p>
                <p>The quantities most accurately determined from observation, from which the moon’s
                    mass can be found, are the whole annual precession <hi rend="italic">p</hi> (=50
                    ″ ∙4), and the coefficient of the lunar nutation in obliquity <hi rend="italic"
                    >q</hi> (=9 ″ ∙239)∙ Let s = the solar annual precession, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >m</hi> = the lunar annual precession, then <hi rend="italic">s=p</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">in.</hi> Now, by prop. 7, <hi
                    rend="italic">q~Q½-</hi> cos I sin <hi rend="italic">2i,</hi> 4χ</p>
                <p>and, by prop. 6, wι=Qeos I (cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z—½sin <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z)T, whence by eliminating Q, cos I, we get <hi
                    rend="italic">__</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> q. 4π .</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">T(cos</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">?</hi><hi rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline"
                    >½sin</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> *i)</hi><hi rend="italic">τ</hi> sin <hi
                    rend="italic">2i</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> and on computing <hi rend="italic"
                    >m</hi> from the values of T, <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >i</hi> above given, we find ∞ = y×3 ″ ∙735 = 34 ″ ∙51; therefore, also, <hi
                    rend="italic">s=p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">m—</hi> 15 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> zz,</hi> 89∙</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">•</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">a ∙</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                    4L 6w <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∙ K <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi> I <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> r</p>
                <p>Again, from prop. 4, we have &lt;?=— , and from</p>
                <p>T⅛</p>
                <p>prop. 6, (on substituting for Qits value), <hi rend="italic">m—</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough">J~</hi> (cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z—½ sin <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∕)T; whence</p>
                <p>_£ __ ___ 1+A <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">m</hi> T <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z—½ sin <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> z) * Μ</p>
                <p>By computing the coefficient of (E+M)-÷-M, and by means of the values &lt;y and
                    <hi rend="italic">m</hi> now found, this equation gives</p>
                <p>E + M</p>
                <p>~⅛- = 81∙755, whence it follows that the mass of the moon is to the mass of the
                    earth in the ratio of 1 to 80 ’ 755.</p>
                <p>The phenomena of the precession and nutation, and those <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193539057" xml:id="kp-eb0718-9057-0514"/>of the tides, are the only
                    astronomical facts which enable us to determine the moon’s mass. From a long
                    series of observations on the tides at the harbour of Brest, Laplace found the
                    ratio of the masses of the moon and earth to be 1: 75∙77.</p>
                <p>The regression of the equinoctial points amongst the fixed stars, and consequent
                    precession of the equinoxes, being a motion which, though extremely slow
                    amounting only to a degree in about seventy-two years, increases constantly with
                    the time, was detected at an early period in the history of astronomy, and its
                    rate was determined with considerable accuracy by Hipparchus. Its physical cause
                    was of course not suspected until after the discovery of gravitation; but Newton
                    himself, by a process of reasoning, which, although not quite accurate, affords
                    one of the most remarkable instances of his extraordinary sagacity, <hi
                    rend="italic">(Principia,</hi> lib. iii. prop. 39), shewed it to be a necessary
                    consequence of the flattened form of the earth. D’Alembert was the first who
                    gave a general and accurate solution of the problem, in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Re-cherches</hi><hi rend="italic">sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la Precession des
                    Equinoxes</hi> (1749); and Euler also treated the subject in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Berlin Memoirs</hi> for the same year. Various solutions of the
                    problem have since been given, amongst which may be mentioned those of
                    Sylvabella and Walmesley in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Transactions</hi> (vols. xlviii andxlix); thatofSimson <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Miscellaneous Tracts,</hi> 1757); thatof Frisiin his <hi rend="italic">Theoria
                    Geometrica Diurni Motus</hi><hi rend="italic">(Opera,</hi> tom. iii.); that of
                    Lagrange in his <hi rend="italic">Memoir on the Libration of the Moon,</hi>
                    which obtained the prize of the Academy of Sciences of Paris for 1769; that of
                    Landen <hi rend="italic">(Mathematical Memoirs,</hi> 1780); and that of Vince
                    <hi rend="italic">(Philosophical Transactions,</hi> 1787∙) Of these solutions,
                    that of Frisi deserves to be noticed as perhaps the most perspicuous and
                    elegant. An excellent elementary demonstration is given by Mr. Airy, the present
                    astronomer royal, in his <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Tracts,</hi> (1826 and
                    1831) of which we have freely availed ourselves in the present article; but for
                    a complete investigation of the question in all its generality, we must refer
                    the reader to the <hi rend="italic">Mécanique</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Celeste,</hi> and still more particularly to a Memoir of Poisson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Sur le Mouvement de la Terre autour de son Centre de Gravite,</hi>
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Academie Royale des Sciences,</hi> tome vii. 1829·</p>
                <p>The nutation, as has already been remarked, (see also <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Astronomy,</hi> vol. iii. p. 768), was detected by Bradley, from a comparison
                    of observations which were undertaken with a view to determine the parallax of
                    the fixed stars. Bradley assigned to the coefficient or constant of nutation the
                    value 9", which till a late period was adopted by most astronomers. Laplace
                    computed its value from theory to be 9"∙63; but as this result could only be
                    obtained by having recourse to hypotheses respecting the ellipticity and density
                    of the earth, and also the mass of the moon, which may possibly differ
                    considerably from the truth, it cannot be regarded as of much weight. There are,
                    however, three other determinations of the constant (besides that of Bradley),
                    from observation, which may be supposed to give its value with all the precision
                    that is capable of being attained. The first is that of Von Lindenau, from about
                    800 observations of Polaris made between the years 1750 and 1815, and
                    consequently including three revolutions of the moon’s node; as well as from
                    those made by Bradley, Maskelyne, Bessel, Carlini, Piazzi, and Von Lindenau
                    himself. From these observations he found the value of theconstantof nutation to
                    be 8"∙97718. The second determination is that of Dr. Brinkley <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Philosophical Transactions,</hi> 1821) deduced from his own observations with
                    the Dublin Mural Circle; andthevalue which he found was 9" <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 25. The third determination, and that which has the
                    greatest probability in its favour, is a very recent one by Dr. Robinson of
                    Armagh, undertaken at the instance of the British Association. It is deduced
                    from 11,000 observations made at Greenwich with the mural circle, between the
                    years 1812 and 1834, and embraces more than a complete revolution of the node.
                    The result gives the constant of nutation =9"∙23913. (See the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Monthly Notices oíÜ\e</hi> Royal Astronomical Society for May 1838). s.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
