<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-6580-0716-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DENBIGHSHIRE (7th edition, volume 7, page 716)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208401">Angola</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935118">Friars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095688">Respect</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154ds5t">Friars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194756580?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DENBIGHSHIRE</label>, a county of North Wales. This district,
                    which in Welsh is called <hi rend="italic">Sir l)inbech,</hi> was in the time of
                    the Romans included in that part of Cambria occupied by the Ordovices, and
                    formed a portion of Vene-dotia, one of the minor partitions of Britannia
                    Secunda.</p>
                <p>The figure of Denbighshire is very irregular, continually varying in length and
                    breadth. Its length from northwest to south-east is about forty-eight miles, and
                    its greatest breadth twenty miles, but in some parts it is not more than eight
                    miles. It is 170 miles in circumference, and is computed to contain 731 square
                    miles. On the north it is bounded by the Irish Sea, on the north-east it is
                    separated from Flintshire by the river Dee, on the south-east by Shropshire, on
                    the south by Montgomeryshire and Merionethshire, and on the west it is separated
                    from Caernarvonshire by the river Conway.</p>
                <p>This county is divided into six hundreds, Isdulas, Isaled, Ruthin, Yale,
                    Bromfield, and Chirk. It includes one borough, six market-towns, viz. Denbigh,
                    Ruthin, Wrexham, Holt, Llangollen, and Llanruost, and consists of fifty-seven
                    parishes. It is included in the Chester circuit; and, with respect to
                    ecclesiastical jurisdiction, it is under the Archbishop of Canterbury, partly in
                    the diocese of Bangor, and partly in that of St Asaph, the deanery of Duffryn
                    Chvyd being in the former see. By the reform act it returns one member to
                    parliament for the county, and one is chosen by the four burghs of Denbigh,
                    Ruthin, Holt, and the town of Wrexham. The borough of Denbigh affords the title
                    of earl to the noble family of Fielding, and that of Yelver-toιι derives the
                    title of baron from the town of Ruthin.</p>
                <p>The surface <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the country is much diversified, affording
                    a very great variety of scenery. The western parts are rather mountainous,
                    abounding with hills, upon which are <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194756593?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6593-0717"/> small lakes.
                    The northern parts have the same character, excepting that tract which stretches
                    from Abergeley along the sea-coast, which gradually slopes into the extensive
                    plain of Morva Rhyddlan. The celebrated Vale of Clwyd is a fine scene. The land
                    spreads on each side of a river of the same name from its source to the sea, a
                    distance of more than twenty miles, and from about five to seven in breadth. The
                    mountains, which rise on each side, with their brown and barren summits, form a
                    fine contrast with the verdant meads and luxuriant fields, which gratify the
                    sight as far as the eye can reach! Towns, villages, and seats, thickly studded
                    over its surface, tend still more to enliven the scene, and to beautify this
                    charming vale. The land included between the Alun and the Dee is fertile,
                    pleasant, and highly productive. The central parts of the hundred of Isaled
                    consist of bleak and barren hills, and the southern comprise a large tract of
                    land, devoid of wood, and productive of peat only, which principally affords the
                    fuel of tlιe inhabitants. Yale is a mountainous region, chiefly covered with
                    heath, forming an excellent cover for grouse. Bromfield, the most important part
                    of this county in population and wealth, though sharing in the mountainous
                    character of the rest, furnishes a great proportion of rich land.</p>
                <p>The irregularities of the surface, and the variety of the soils, produce a
                    considerable difference in the climate of Denbighshire. On the hills the air is
                    sharp, being deprived of its softness in its passage over Snowden and the
                    neighbouring hills. Still it is reckoned salubrious. The atmosphere in the vales
                    is milder. Duffryn Clwyd, being open towards the sea,and defended by its
                    mountain barriers, is proverbially celebrated for its salubrity. The inhabitants
                    of this district are remarkable for their bright complexion, cheerful
                    countenances, and sound constitutions; a display of vivacity in youth, and a
                    vigour in age, not possessed in less favoured situations; longevity, therefore,
                    ceases to be remarkable, because it is here a common occurrence.</p>
                <p>The principal rivers of this county are the Clwyd, the Conway, and the Dee,
                    neither of which are navigable in those portions which pass through
                    Denbighshire. The lesser are Ceriog, rising on the western side, and forming a
                    junction with the Dee near Chirk Castle; the Alun, commencing from Llandegla,
                    and, after a most circuitous route, tailing into the Dee a little below the town
                    of Holt. The Ellesmere Canal passes through the southern part of the county; but
                    there is great difficulty in obtaining a sufficient supply of water to keep it
                    navigable.</p>
                <p>Rich veins of iron and lead ore and coal have been found in various places; and
                    mines of these substances have been opened in several districts. Slate of a
                    durable quality is worked in the southern parts, and meets with a great demand.
                    Limestone is abundant; and freestone and other siliceous substances are obtained
                    in various parts.</p>
                <p>In agricultural improvements few counties surpass Denbighshire. The encouragement
                    given for the amelioration of the soil, by the establishment of two agricultural
                    societies, one in the Vale of Clwyd, and another in the neighbourhood of
                    Wrexham, together with the co-operating effects produced by Sir Watkin Williams
                    Wynne’s show of cattlc and sheep, annually held at his seat, Wynnstay, with a
                    distribution of prizes on the occasion, is very visible in the county. It is
                    stated to contain 410,000 acres, of which 150,000 is arable land and 250,000 is
                    pasturage. The roads also, which used to be very bad, have been much improved
                    during the last few years.</p>
                <p>The native horses are of a small size, but exceedingly hardy. The cows are
                    generally of the black kind, low-in stature, and yield milk of an excellent
                    quality. The sheep are the light horned sort, producing wool well adapted for
                    the manufactures of the country. The goat, superior in size, and in the length
                    and fineness of its hair, to that of most other countries, is found here in its
                    ferine and domesticated state. In an agricultural point of view, the chief
                    products are cattle, corn, and cheese. The latter is in some parts not inferior
                    to the best Cheshire.</p>
                <p>Its manufactures chiefly consist of coarse cloth made in the parish of Glynn, of
                    flannels wrought from the country wool, of cotton twist and Angola hose in the
                    town of Denbigh, of a small quantity of iron, and of a few harps at
                    Llanrwst.</p>
                <p>Among the customs peculiar to this-county, in common with other parts of Wales,
                    are those pertaining to marriages and burials. Their weddings are thus
                    conducted: When the marriage is agreed to be celebrated, a <hi rend="italic"
                    >bidder,</hi> that is, one whose charge is to <hi rend="italic">bid</hi> or
                    invite the guests, is appointed. He must be a person of respectable character,
                    and as well gifted with eloquence and address as can be procured, as on his
                    abilities the number of guests chiefly depends. He is to be sufficiently skilled
                    in pedigrees and family anecdotes, in order to be able to introduce compliments
                    derived from these sources. The purport of his bidding is to request the
                    attendance of the friends of the young couple, and their benevolent presents, in
                    order to enable the new-married pair to begin life with comfort and prosperity.
                    These contributions are some article of furniture or money, and are regularly
                    repaid, by gifts of a similar kind, on a like occasion. By this custom, a
                    deserving young couple of the lower class are sometimes set up in a state of
                    comparative wealth.</p>
                <p>Previously to a funeral, it is customary, when the corpse is brought out of the
                    house and laid upon a bier, for the next of kin to distribute bread, cheese, and
                    beer over the coffin, to some poor persons of the same sex, and nearly of the
                    same age, as the deceased. This being done, all kneel down, and the minister
                    repeats the Lord’s prayer. At every cross way they stop, and the same ceremony
                    is repeated, till they arrive at the place of interment. The funerals are
                    generally attended by immense crowds of people of both sexes. All the graves are
                    planted with the choicest evergreens and flowers; so that a church-yard has all
                    the appearance of a beautiful well-managed flower-garden.</p>
                <p>The peasantry of this county are firm believers in <hi rend="italic"
                    >fairies,</hi> a diminutive race, clad in green, who hold their merry dances
                    invisibly by moonlight, footing it to lyric measures on the verdant turf of
                    their mountains, and leaving their marks, in darkened circles, to the admiration
                    of the beholders. Allied to this race are the <hi rend="italic">hnochers,</hi> a
                    species of aerial beings, who, the miners say, are heard under ground, and by
                    their noises pointing out to the workman the place where a rich vein of ore lies
                    hid. The corpse candle is a light proceeding from the dwelling of a person who
                    is shortly to die, to the churchyard where he is to be buried. Witchcraft and
                    the second-sight are also articles of firm belief among the lower class.</p>
                <p>Denbighshire contains several remains of ancient castles; that near the county
                    town has been compared, with respect to its situation, to Stirling. It is placed
                    on the summit of a lofty hill, and assumes at a distance a most imposing
                    appearance. From its present remains it appears to have been a superb structure,
                    and, from the strength of its position, invulnerable except by heavy artillery,
                    and irreducible, except in cases of treachery or famine. It is supposed to be of
                    British foundation. The castle of Ruthin was built of red stone, and erected in
                    the time <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Edward I. It stood on the side of a hill
                    fronting the vale to the west. The remains of this once proud pile consist of a
                    few fragments of towers and fallen walls, reduced nearly to the foundations; and
                    the area at present comprises a meadow, fives-court, and bowling-green. There
                    are also the remains of a castle at Chirk, on the line of Offa’s Dike; <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194756606?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6606-0718"/> and
                    another at Holt, built by Earl Warren in the reign of Edward I. whose remains
                    are now little attractive.</p>
                <p>Its ecclesiastical antiquities consist of the remains of St Hiliary’s Chapel,
                    founded in 1579, by Dudley, earl of Leicester, and a priory of Carmelites, or
                    White Friars, in the town of Denbigh. Llan Eqwert Abbey, a fine picturesque
                    object, was a house of Cistertians founded in 1200, and generally known by the
                    name of Valle Crucis. Wrexham Church, formerly collegiate, and not only the
                    glory of the county, but ranked among the wonders of Wales, was erected about
                    the year 1472; but the tower doe3 not appear to have been finished till 1506. It
                    exhibits a specimen of the chaste proportions and moderate decorations of Henry
                    VlI.’s time.</p>
                <p>Among the modern buildings, Wynnstay Hall, the hospitable mansion of Sir W. W.
                    Wynne, and Chirk Castle, the seat of the Honourable Mr West, deserve particular
                    notice.</p>
                <p>The amount of population, from returns not of very certain accuracy, in 1700
                    appears to have been 39,700, and 46,900 in 1750; but by the more correct returns
                    of late years it has been as follows, viz. 60,352 in 1801, 64,240 in 1811,
                    76,311 in 1821, and 82,800 in 1831. The annual value of the real property, as
                    assessed for the property-tax of 1815, appears to have been L.22l,763.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
