<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-3103-0060-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLOTINUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 60</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:828168">Basil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193533103" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLOTINUS</label>, a Platonic philosopher of the third
                    century. He was born at Lycopolis, a city of Egypt, in 204; and began very early
                    to show a great singularity both in his taste and in his manners. At eight years
                    of age, when he went to school, he used to run to his nurse, and uncover her
                    breast to suck; and would have continued that practice longer if he had not been
                    discouraged by her. At the age of twenty-eight he had a strong desire to study
                    philosophy, on which occasion he was recommended to the most famous professors
                    of Alexandria. He was not satisfied with their lectures; but upon hearing those
                    of Ammonius, he confessed that this was the man he wanted. He studied for eleven
                    years under that excellent master, and then went to hear the Persian and Indian
                    philosophers. In 243, when the Emperor Gordianus intended to wage war against
                    the Persians, he followed the Roman army, but probably repented of it; for it
                    was with difficulty he could save his life by flight after the emperor had been
                    slain. He was then thirty-nine. The year following he went to Rome, and read
                    philosophical lectures in that city; but avoided following the example of
                    Erennius and Origen, his fellowpupils, who, having like him promised not to
                    reveal some hidden and excellent doctrines which they had received from
                    Anunonius, had nevertheless broken their pledge. Plotinus continued ten years in
                    Rome without writing anything; but in his fiftieth year he obtained as his
                    scholar Porphyry, who, being of an exquisitely fine genius, was not satisfied
                    with superficial answers, but required to have all difficulties thoroughly
                    explained; and therefore Plotinus, to treat things with greater accuracy, was
                    obliged to write more books. He had previously written twenty-one books, and
                    during the six years of Porphyry’s sojourn with him he wrote twenty-four, and
                    nine after Porphyry left Rome, making in all fifty-four. The Romans had a high
                    veneration for him; and he passed for a man of such judgment and virtue, that
                    many persons of both sexes, when they found themselves dying, intrusted him, as
                    a kind of guardian angel, with the care of their estates and children. He was
                    the arbiter of numberless lawsuits ∙, and constantly behaved with such humanity
                    and rectitude, that he did not create a single enemy during the twenty-six years
                    he resided in Rome. He did not meet with the same justice, however, from all of
                    his own profession; for Olympias, a philosopher of Alexandria, being envious of
                    his glory, used his utmost endeavours, though in vain, to ruin him. The Emperor
                    Gallienus and the Empress Salonina had a very high regard for him; and if it had
                    not been for the opposition of some jealous courtiers, they would have caused
                    the city of Campania to be rebuilt, and given it to him, with the territory
                    belonging to it, to establish a colony of philosophers, and to govern it
                    according to the ideal laws of Plato’s commonwealth. He laboured under various
                    disorders during the last year of his life, which obliged him to leave Rome,
                    when he was carried to Campania, to the heirs of one of his friends, who
                    furnished him with everything necessary; and he died there in the year 270, at
                    the age of sixty-six, in the noblest manner that an heathen philosopher could
                    expire. “I am labouring with all my might,” said he, “to return the divine part
                    of me to the Divine Whole which fills the universe.”</p>
                <p>We have already remarked that the ideas of Plotinus were singular and
                    extraordinary; and we shall now show that they were so. He was ashamed of being
                    lodged in a body, for which reason he did not care to tell the place of his
                    birth or family. The contempt he had for all earthly things was the reason why
                    he would not permit his picture to be drawn; and when his disciple Amelius urged
                    him to do so, “Is it not enough,” said he, “to drag after us, whithersoever we
                    go, that image in which nature has shut us up? Do you think that we should
                    likewise transmit to future ages an image of that image, as a sight worthy of
                    their attention ?” On the same principle, he refused to attend to his health;
                    for he never made use of preservatives or baths, and did not even eat the flesh
                    of tame animals. He ate but <pb break="no" facs="nls:193533116"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-3116-0061"/>little, and often abstained from bread; which,
                    joined to his intense meditation, prevented him from sleeping. In short, he
                    thought the body altogether below his notice, and had so little respect for it,
                    that he considered it as a prison, from which it would be his supreme happiness
                    to be freed. When Amelins, after his death, inquired of the oracle of Apollo
                    about the state of his soul, he was told that it was gone to the assembly of the
                    blessed, where charity, joy, and a love of the union with God, prevail. And the
                    reason given for this, as related by Porphyry, is, “that Plotinus had been
                    peaceable, gracious, and vigilant; that he had perpetually elevated his spotless
                    soul to God; that he had loved God with his whole heart; that he had disengaged
                    himself, to the utmost of his abilities, from this wretched life; that,
                    elevating himself with all the powers of his soul, and by the several gradations
                    taught by Plato, towards that Supreme Being which fills the universe, he had
                    been enlightened by him, had enjoyed the vision of him without the help or
                    interposition of ideas, and, in short, had often been united to him.” This is
                    the account of Porphyry, who also tells us that he himself had once been
                    favoured with the vision. We need scarcely add, however, that little credit is
                    due to such a story, which agrees pretty much with modern enthusiasm and the
                    reveries of Behmenists. Plotinus had his familiar spirit, as well as Socrates;
                    but, according to Porphyry, it was not one of those called <hi rend="italic"
                    >demons,</hi> but of the order of those who are called <hi rend="italic"
                    >gods;</hi> so that he was under the protection of a spirit superior to that of
                    other men. The superiority of his genins puffed him up not a little;</p>
                <p>)i∙ when Amelins desired him to share in the sacrifices which he used to offer up
                    on solemn festivals, “It is their business,” replied Plotinus, “to come to me;
                    not mine to go to them.”</p>
                <p>Porphyry put the fifty-four books of Plotinus in order, and divided them into six
                    nonades. The greater part of them turn on the most high-flown ideas in
                    metaphysics; and this philosopher seems, in certain points, to differ but little
                    from Spinoza. He wrote two books to prove that all being is one and the same;
                    which is, in fact, the very doctrine of Baruc Spinoza. He inquires, in another
                    book, whether there are many souls, or only one. His manner of composing partook
                    of the singularity of his nature. He never read over his compositions after he
                    had written them; he wrote a bad hand, and was not exact in his orthography; he
                    stood in need, therefore, of a faithful friend to revise and correct his
                    writings; and he chose Porphyry for this purpose in preference to Amelius, who
                    had been his disciple twenty-four years, and was very much esteemed by him. Some
                    have accused Plotinus of plagiarism with regard to Numcnius; a slander which
                    Amelius refuted. Longinus was once much prejudiced against this philosopher, and
                    wrote against his Treatise of Ideas, and against Porphyry’s answer in defence of
                    that treatise. He afterwards conceived a high esteem for Plotinus; sought
                    industriously for all his books; and, in order to have them correct, desired
                    Porphyry to lend him his copy. At the same time he wrote to the latter in the
                    following manner. “I always observed to you, when we were together, when we were
                    at a distance from one another, as well as when you lived at Tyre, that I did
                    not comprehend many of the subjects treated of by Plotinus; but I was extremely
                    fond of his manner of writing, the variety of his knowledge, and the order and
                    disposition of his questions, which are altogether philosophical.” This single
                    passage, says Baylc, shows the exalted genius, the exquisite discernment, and
                    judicious penetration of Longinus. It cannot be denied that most subjects which
                    this philosopher examines are incomprehensible; nevertheless, we discover in his
                    works a very elevated, fruitful, and capacious genius, and a close way of
                    reasoning. Had Longinus been an injudicious critic, had he not possessed an
                    exalted and beautiful genius, he would not have been so sensible of Plotinus’s
                    obscurity; for no persons complain less of the obscurity of a book, than those
                    whose thoughts are confused, and whose understanding is shallow. Marsilius
                    Ficinus, at the request of Cosmo de’ Medici, executed a Latin version of the
                    works of Plotinus, with a summary and analysis of each book; which was printed
                    at Basil, first by itself in 1559, and afterwards with the Greek in 1580, folio.
                    His life was written by Porphyry, the most illustrious of his disciples.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
