<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-8108-0441-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PORISM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 441</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="24" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx29">Porisms</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1181567">Wrens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046145">Opera</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="24" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1071831">Porisms</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193538108" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PORISM</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> is a name
                    given by the ancient geometers to two classes of mathematical propositions.
                    Euclid applies this name to propositions, which are involved in others which he
                    is professedly investigating, and which, although they do not form his principal
                    object, are obtained along with it, as is expressed by their name <hi
                    rend="italic">porismata,</hi> or acquisitions. Such propositions are now called
                    <hi rend="italic">corollaries.</hi> But he gives the same name, by way of
                    eminence, to a particular class of propositions which be collected in the course
                    of his researches, and selected from amongst many others, on account of their
                    great subserviency to the business of geometrical investigation in general.
                    These propositions were so named by him, either from the way in which he
                    discovered them, that is to say, whilsthe was investigating something else, so
                    that theymight be considered as <hi rend="italic">gains</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">acquisitions,</hi> or from their utility as steps in the
                    investigation. In this sense they are <hi rend="italic">pοτis-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">mata;</hi> for <hi rend="italic">πορίζω</hi> (from which,
                    according to Proclus, the term is derived) signifies both to investigate and to
                    acquire by investigation. These propositions formed a collection in three books,
                    which was familiarly known to the ancient geometers by the name of Euclid’s <hi
                    rend="italic">porisms;</hi> and Pappus of Alexandria says, that it was a most
                    ingenious collection of many things conducive to the analysis or solution of the
                    most difficult problems, and which afforded great delight to those who were able
                    to understand and investigate them.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately for mathematical science, this valuable collection is now lost, and
                    it still remains a doubtful question in what manner the ancients conducted their
                    researches upon this curious subject. We have, however, reason to believe that
                    their method was both comprehensive and excellent; for their analysis led them
                    to many profound discoveries, and was restricted by the severest logic. The only
                    account we have of this class of geometrical propositions, is in a fragment of
                    Pappus, in which he attempts a general description of them, as a set of
                    mathematical propositions distinguishable in kind from all others; but of this
                    description nothing remains, except a criticism on a definition of the term
                    given by some geometers, namely, “A Porism is that which is deficient in
                    hypothesis from a local theorem,” and which he finds fault with, as defining the
                    porisms only by an accidental circumstance. Pappus also gives an account of
                    Euclid’s porisms; but the enunciations are so extremely defective, at the same
                    time that they refer to a figure now lost, that Dr. Halley confesses the
                    fragment in question to be beyond his comprehension.</p>
                <p>The high encomiums pronounced by Pappus on these pro positions have excited the
                    curiosity of the greatest geometers of modern times, who have attempted to
                    discover their nature and the manner of investigating them. Fermat gave a few
                    propositions, which have been published in his <hi rend="italic">Opera</hi>
                    (Tolosae, 1679), and Bulh'aldus, in a tract entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Exercitationes</hi><hi rend="italic">Geometricae Tres</hi> (Paris, 1657),
                    attempted the same thing, but with less success. Albert Girard, at a still
                    earlier period, announced that he had restored the whole of the three books of
                    Euclid, but it does not appear that this part of his works was ever
                    published.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In his <hi
                    rend="italic">Τri&lt;jοηοιnetry,</hi> published at the Hague in 1S29, after
                    enumerating the forms of certain rectilinear figures, Girard adds, “Le tout,
                    quand il n’y a que deux lignes qui passent par un point, comme jadis estoyent
                    les Porismes d’Euclid, qui sont perdus, lesquelles J’espère de mettre bientôt en
                    lumière, les ayant restituez, il y a quelques années en ça." <hi rend="italic"
                    >Α</hi> similar announcement is also made by him in his edition of the works of
                    Steviuus (Lugduni. Batav. 1634. p. 459 ) Having mentioned that Euclid rarely
                    employs a compound ratio, he adds, “Mais il est à estimer qu’il en a plus escrit
                    en ses trois livres de Porismes qui sont perdus, lesquelles, Dieu aidant,
                    J'espère de mettre en lumière, les ayant inventez de nouveau.” (See the preface
                    to Simson⅛ <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Porismalibus,</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Opera</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Reliqua.}</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>1 At length Dr. Simson, Professor of Mathematics in the University of Glasgow,
                    was so fortunate as to succeed in <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538121"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-8121-0442"/>restoring the porisms of Euclid. In the preface to
                    his treatise <hi rend="italic">De Porismatibus,</hi> he gives the following
                    account of his progress and of the obstacles he encountered: “Postquam vero apud
                    Pappum legeram Porismata Euclidis Collectionem fuisse artificiosissimam multarum
                    rerum, qnae spectant ad analysin difficiliorum ct generalium problematum, magno
                    desiderio tenebar, aliquid de iis cognoscendi; quare saepius et multis variisque
                    viis tum Pappi propositionem generalem, mancam et imperfectum, tum primum lib.
                    1. Porisma, quod, ut dictum fuit, solum ex omnibus in tribus libris integrum
                    adhuc manet, intelligere et restituere conabar; frustra tamen, nihil enim
                    proficiebam. Cumque cogitationes de hac re multum mihi temporis consumpserint,
                    atque tandem mo-lestae admodum evaserint, firmiter animum induxi haec nunquam in
                    posterum investigare; praesertim cum optimus Geometra Halleius spem omnem de iis
                    intelligendis abjecisset. Unde quoties menti occurrebant, toties eas arcebam.
                    Postea tamen accidit ut improvidum et propositi immemorem invaserint, meque
                    detinuerint donce tandem lux quaedam effulserit quae spem mihi faciebat
                    inveniendi saltem Pappi propositionem generalem, quam quidem multa
                    investigatione tandem restitui.”</p>
                <p>Dr. Simson’s <hi rend="italic">Restoration</hi> has every appearance of being
                    just. All the lemmas which Pappus has given for the better understanding of
                    Euclid’s propositions are equally applicable to those of Dr. Simson, which are
                    found to differ from local theorems precisely as Pappus affirms those of Euclid
                    to have done. They require a particular mode of analysis, and are of immense
                    service in geometrical investiga tion.</p>
                <p>Whilst Dr. Simson was employed in this inquiry, he carried on a correspondence
                    upon the subject with the late Dr. Matthew Stewart, Professor of Mathematics in
                    the University of Edinburgh; who, besides entering into Dr. Simson’s views, and
                    communicating to him many curious porisms, pursued the same subject in a new and
                    very different direction. He published the result of his inquiries in 1746,
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">General Theorems,</hi> not wishing to give
                    them any other name, lest he might appear to anticipate the labours of his
                    friend and former preceptor. The greater part of the propositions contained in
                    that work are porisms, but without demonstration; and those who wish to
                    investigate one of the most curious subjects in geometry, will there find
                    abundance of materials, and an ample field for discussion.</p>
                <p>Dr. Simson defines a porism to be “a proposition, in which it is proposed to
                    demonstrate, that one or more things are given, between which, and every one of
                    innumerable other things not given, but assumed according to a given law, a
                    certain relation, described in the proposition, is to be shewn to take
                    place.”</p>
                <p>This definition is somewhat obscure, but will be plainer if expressed thus: “A
                    porism is a proposition affirming the possibility of finding such conditions as
                    will render a certain problem indeterminate, or capable of innumerable
                    solutions.” This definition agrees with Pappus’s idea of these propositions, as
                    far at least as they can be understood from the fragment already mentioned; for
                    the propositions here defined, like those which he describes, are, strictly
                    speaking, neither theorems nor problems, but of an intermediate nature between
                    both. They neither simply enunciate a truth to be demonstrated, nor propose a
                    question to be resolved, but are affirmations of a truth in which the
                    determination of an unknown quantity is involved. In as far, therefore, as they
                    assert that a certain problem may become indeterminate, they are of the nature
                    of theorems; and, in as far as they seek to discover the condition by which that
                    is brought about, they are of the nature of problems.</p>
                <p>In order to give our readers a clear idea of the subject of porisms, we shall
                    consider them in the way in which it is probable they occurred to the ancient
                    geometers in the course of their researches. This will at the same time shew the
                    nature of the analysis peculiar to them, and their great use in the solution of
                    problems.</p>
                <p>It appears to be certain, that it has been the solution of problems which, in all
                    states of the mathematical sciences, has led to the discovery of geometrical
                    truths. The first mathematical inquiries, in particular, must have occurred in
                    the form of question^ where something was given, and something required to be
                    done; and by the reasoning necessary to answer these questions, or to discover
                    the relation between the things given and those to be found, many truths were
                    suggested, which came afterwards to be the subject of separate demonstrations.
                    The number of these was the greater, because the ancient geometers always
                    undertook the solution of problems, with a scrupulous and minute attention,
                    insomuch that they would scarcely suffer any of the collateral truths to escape
                    their observation.</p>
                <p>Now, as this cautious manner of proceeding was not better calculated to avoid
                    error than to lay hold of every collateral truth connected with the main object
                    of inquiry, these geometers soon perceived, that there were many problems which
                    in certain cases would admit of no solution whatever, in consequence of a
                    particular relation existing amongst the quantities which were given. Such
                    problems were said to become impossible; and it was soon perceived, that this
                    always happened when one of the conditions of the problem was inconsistent with
                    the rest. Thus, when it was required to divide a line, so that the rectangle
                    contained by its segments might be equal to a given space, it was found that
                    this was possible only when the given space was less than the square of half the
                    line; for when it was otherwise, the two conditions defining, the one the
                    magnitude of the line, and the other the rectangle of its segments, were
                    inconsistent with each other. Such cases would occur in the solution of the most
                    simple problems; but if they were more complicated, it must have been remarked,
                    that the constructions would sometimes fail, for a reason directly contrary to
                    that just now assigned. Cases would occur, where the lines, which by their
                    intersection were to determine the thing sought, instead of intersecting each
                    other as they did commonly, or of not meeting at all, as in the above mentioned
                    case of impossibility, would coincide with one another entirely, and of course
                    leave the problem unresolved. It would appear to geometers upon a little
                    reflection, that since, in the case of determinate problems, the thing required
                    was determined by the intersection of the two lines already mentioned, that is,
                    by the points common to both; so in the case of their coincidence, as all their
                    parts were in common, every one of these points must give a solution, or, in
                    other words, the solutions must be indefinite in number.</p>
                <p>Upon inquiry, it would be found that this proceeded from some condition of the
                    problem having been involved in another, so that, in fact, the two formed but
                    one, and thus there was not a sufficient number of independent conditions to
                    limit the problem to a single or to any determinate number of solutions. It
                    would soon be perceived, that these cases formed very curious propositions of an
                    intermediate nature between problems and theorems; and that they admitted of
                    being enunciated in a manner peculiarly elegant and concise. It was to such
                    propositions that the ancients gave the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >porisms.</hi></p>
                <p>This deduction requires to be illustrated by an example. Suppose, therefore, that
                    it were required to resolve the following problem. A circle ABC, (fig. 1), a
                    straight line DE, and a point F, being given in position, to find a point G in
                    the straight line DE such, that GF, the line drawn from it to the given point,
                    shall be equal to GB, the line drawn from it touching the given circle.</p>
                <p>Suppose G to be found, and GB to be drawn touching the given circle ABC in B, let
                    H be its centre, join HB, and let HD be perpendicular to DE. From D draw’ DL&gt;
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538134" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8134-0443"/>touching the
                    circle ABC in L, and join IIL; also from the centre G, with the distance GB or
                    GF, describe the circle BKF, meeting HD in the points K and K'. It is evident
                    that HD and DL are given in position and magnitude: also because GB touches the
                    circle ABC, HBG is a right angle; and since G is the centre of the circle BKF,
                    IIB touches that circle, and consequently HB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> or
                    III. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = KH×HK'; but because KK' is bisected in D,
                    KH×HK' + DK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = DIP, therefore III. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + DK-=DH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. But III. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = DH <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, therefore DK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =DL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> and DK=DL. But DL is given in magnitude, and
                    consequently K is a given point. For the same reason <hi rend="italic">K'</hi>
                    is a given point, therefore the point F being given in position, the circle KFK'
                    is given in position. The point G, which is its centre, is therefore given in
                    position, which was to be found. Hence this construction:</p>
                <p>Having drawn HD perpendicular to DE, and DL touching the circle ABC, make DK and
                    DK ’ each equal to DL, and find G the centre of the circle described through the
                    points K'FK; that is, let FK ’ be joined and bisected at right angles by MN,
                    which meets DE in G, G will be the point required; or it will be such a point,
                    that if GB be drawn touching the circle ABC, and GF to the given point, GB is
                    equal to GF.</p>
                <p>The synthetical demonstration is easily derived from the preceding analysis; but
                    it must be remarked, that in some cases this construction fails. For, first, if
                    F fall anywhere in DH, as at F ’, the line MN becomes parallel to DE, and the
                    point G is nowhere to be found; or, in other words, it is at an infinite
                    distance from D. This is true in general; but if the given point F coincide with
                    K, then MN evidently coincides with DE; so that, agreeable to a remark already
                    made, every point of the line DE may be taken for G, and will satisfy the
                    conditions of the problem; that is to say, GB will be equal to GK, wherever the
                    point G is taken in the line DE: the same is true if F coincide with K'. Thus we
                    have an instance of a problem, and that too a very simple one, which, in
                    general, admits but of one solution; but which, in one particular case, when a
                    certain relation takes place among the things given, becomes indefinite, and
                    admits of innumerable solutions. The proposition which results from this case of
                    the problem is a porism, and may be thus enunciated:</p>
                <p>“A circle ABC being given by position, and also a straight line DE, which does
                    not cut the circle, a point K may be found, such, that if G be any point
                    whatever in DE, the straight line drawn from G to the point K shall be equal to
                    the straight line drawn from G touching the given circle ABC.”</p>
                <p>The problem which follows, appears to have led to the discovery of many
                    porisms.</p>
                <p>A circle ABC (fig. 2), and two points D, E, in a diameter of it being given, to
                    find a point F in the circumference of the given circle, from which, if straight
                    lines be drawn to the given points E, D, these straight lines shall have to one
                    another the given ratio of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi rend="italic">β,</hi>
                    which is supposed to be that of a greater to a less. Suppose the problem
                    resolved, and that F is found, so that FE has to FD the given ratio of <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi rend="italic">β</hi>; produce EF towards G, bisect
                    the angle EFD by FL, and DFG by FM: therefore EL: LD:: EF: FD, that is in a
                    given ratio, and since ED is given, each of the segments EL, LD, is given, and
                    the point L is also given; again, because DFG is bisected by FM, EM: MD:: EF:
                    FD, that is, in a given ratio, and therefore Μ is given. Since DFL is half of
                    DFE, and DFM half of DFG, therefore LFM is half of (DFE + DFB), that is, the
                    half of two right angles, therefore LFM is a right angle; and since the points
                    L, Μ, are given, the point F is in the circumference of a circle described upon
                    LM as a diameter, and therefore given in position. Now the point F is also in
                    the circumference of the given circle ABC, therefore it is in the intersection
                    of the two given circumferences, and therefore is found. Hence this
                    construction: Divide ED in L, so that EL may be to LD in the given ratio of <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> and produce ED also to Μ, so
                    that EM may be to MD in the same given ratio of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi
                    rend="italic">β</hi>; bisect LM in N, and from the centre N with the distance
                    NL, describe the semicircle LFM; and the point F, in which it intersects the
                    circle ABC, is the point required.</p>
                <p>The synthetical demonstration is easily derived from the preceding analysis. It
                    must, however, be remarked, that the construction fails when the circle LFM
                    falls either wholly within or wholly without the circle ABC, so that the
                    circumferences do not intersect; and in these cases the problem cannot be
                    solved. It is also obvious that the construction will fail in another case, viz.
                    when the two circumferences LFM, ABC, entirely coincide. In this case, it is
                    farther evident, that every point in the circumference ABC will answer the
                    conditions of the problem, which is therefore capable of numberless solutions,
                    and may, as in the former instance, be converted into a porism. We are now to
                    inquire, therefore, in what circumstances the point L will coincide with A, and
                    also the point Μ with C, and of consequence the circumference LFM with ABC. If
                    we suppose that they coincide, EA: AD:: <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">β</hi>:: EC: CD, and EA: EC:: AD ∙ CD, or
                    by conversion, E A: AC:: AD: CD—AD:: AD: 2DO, 0 being the centre of the circle
                    ABC; therefore, also, EA: AO:: AD: DO, and by com-positition, EO: AO:: AO: DO,
                    therefore EO × OD= AO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Hence, if the given points
                    E and D (fig. 3), be so situated that EO × OD=AO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,
                    and at the same time <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic">::</hi> EA: AD:: EC: CD, the problem
                    admits of numberless solutions; and if either of the points D or E be given, the
                    other point, and also the ratio which will render the problem indeterminate, may
                    be found. Hence we have this porism:</p>
                <p>“A circle ABC, and also a point D being given, another point E may be found, such
                    that the two lines inflected from these points to any point in the circumference
                    ABC, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538147" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8147-0444"/>shall
                    have to each other a given ratio, which ratio is also to be found.” Hence also
                    we have an example of the derivation of porisms from one another, for the circle
                    ABC, and the points D and E remaining as before, if, through D <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">wp</hi> draw any line whatever HDB, meeting the circle in B and
                    H; and if the lines EB, EH, he also drawn, these lines will cut off equal
                    circumferences BF, HG. Let FC be drawn, and it is plain from the foregoing
                    analysis, that the angles DFC, CFB, are equal; therefore if OG, OB, be drawn,
                    the angles BOC, COG, are also eqifal; and consequently the angles DOB, DOG. In
                    the same manner, by joining AB, the angle DBE being bisected by BA, it is
                    evident that the angle AOF is equal to AOH, and therefore the angle FOB to HOG;
                    hence the arch FB is equal to the arch HG. It is evident that if the circle ABC,
                    and either of the points DE were given, the other point might be found.
                    Therefore we have this porism, which appears to have been the last but one of
                    the third book of Euclid’s <hi rend="italic">Porisms.</hi> “A point being given,
                    either within or without a circle given by position, if there be drawn, anyhow
                    through that point, a line cutting the circle in two points; another point may
                    be found, such, that if two lines be drawn from it to the points in which the
                    line already drawn cuts the circle, these two lines will cut oft'from the circle
                    equal circumferences.”</p>
                <p>The proposition from which we have deduced these two porisms, also affords an
                    illustration of the remark, that the conditions of a problem are involved in one
                    another in the porismatic or indefinite case; for here several independent
                    conditions are laid down, by the help of which the problem is to be resolved.
                    Two points D and E are given, from which two lines are to be inflected, and a
                    circumference ABC, in which these lines are to meet, as also a ratio which these
                    lines are to have to each other. Now these conditions are all independent of one
                    another, so that any one may be changed without any change whatever in the rest.
                    This is true in general; but yet in one case, viz. when the points are so
                    related to another, that the rectangle under their distances from the centre is
                    equal to the square of the radius of the circle, it follows, from the preceding
                    analysis, that the ratio of the inflected lines is no longer a matter of choice,
                    but a necessary consequence of this disposition of the points.</p>
                <p>From what has been already said, we may trace the imperfect definition of a
                    porism which Pappus ascribes to the later geometers, viz. that it differs from a
                    local theorem, by wanting the hypothesis assumed in that theorem. Now, to
                    understand this, it must be observed, that if we take one of the propositions
                    called <hi rend="italic">loci,</hi> and make the construction of the figure a
                    part of the hypothesis, we get what was called by the ancient geometers, a <hi
                    rend="italic">local theorem.</hi> If, again, in the enunciation of the theorem,
                    that part of the hypothesis which contains the construction be suppressed, the
                    proposition thence arising will be a porism, for it will enunciate a truth, and
                    will require to the full understanding and investigation of that truth, that
                    something should be found, viz. the circumstances in the construction supposed
                    to be omitted.</p>
                <p>Thus, when we say, if from two given points, E, D, two straight lines EF, FD, are
                    inflected to a third point F, so as to be to one another in a given ratio, the
                    point F is in the circumference of a given circle, we have a locus. But when
                    conversely, it is said, if a circle ABC, of which the centre is 0, be given by
                    position, as also a point E; and if D be taken in the line EO, so that EO ×
                    OD⊂AO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and if from E and D the lines EF, DF be
                    inflected to any point of the circumference ABC, the ratio of EF to DF will be
                    given, viz. the same with that of EA to AD, we have a local theorem.</p>
                <p>Lastly, when it is said, if a circle ABC be given by position, and also a point
                    E, a point D may be found, such that if EF, FD be inflected from E and D to any
                    point F in the circumference ABC, these lines shall have a given ratio to one
                    another, the proposition becomes a porism, and is the same that has just now
                    been investigated.</p>
                <p>Hence it is evident, that the local theorem is changed into a porism, by leaving
                    out what relates to the determination of D, and of the given ratio. But though
                    all propositions formed in this way from the conversion of loci, are porisms,
                    yet all porisms are not formed from the conversion of loci; the first, for
                    instance, of the preceding, cannot, by conversion, be changed into a locus;
                    therefore Fermat’s idea of porisms, founded upon this circumstance, could not
                    fail to be imperfect.</p>
                <p>If the idea which we have given of these propositions be just, it follows, that
                    they are to be discovered by considering those cases in which the construction
                    of a problem fails, in consequence of the lines which by their intersection, or
                    the points which by their position, were to determine the problem required,
                    happening to coincide with one another. A porism may therefore be deduced from
                    the problem to which it belongs, just as propositions concerning the <hi
                    rend="italic">maxima</hi> and <hi rend="italic">minima</hi> of quantities are
                    deduced from the problems of which they form limitations; and such is the most
                    natural and obvious analysis of which this class of propositions admits.</p>
                <p>Another general remark which may be made on the analysis of porisms is, that it
                    often happens that the magnitudes required may all, or a part of them, be found
                    by considering the extreme cases; but for the discovery of the relation between
                    them, and the indefinite magnitudes, we must have recourse to the hypothesis of
                    the porism in its most general or indefinite form; and must endeavour so to
                    conduct the reasoning, that the indefinite magnitudes may at length totally
                    disappear, and leave a proposition asserting the relation between determinate
                    magnitudes only.</p>
                <p>Forthis purpose accordingly Dr. Simson frequentlyemploys two statements of the
                    general hypothesis, which he compares together. This double statement, however,
                    cannot be made without rendering the investigation long and complicated; nor is
                    it even necessary, for it may be avoided by <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi>
                    having recourse to simpler <hi rend="italic">porisms,</hi> or to <hi
                    rend="italic">loci,</hi> or to propositions of the <hi rend="italic">data.</hi>
                    The porism which follows, is given as an example where this is done with some
                    difficulty, but with considerable advantage, both with regard to the simplicity
                    and shortness of the demonstration. It will be proper to premise the following
                    lemma.</p>
                <p>Let AB (fig. 4.) be a straight line, and D, L any two points in it, one of which
                    D is between A and B; also let CI. be any straight line. Then shall</p>
                <p>~∙AD≡÷ ÈÉ* <hi rend="superscript"> BD</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">-Èl'</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> AL</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">‘</hi> + ⅛E‘ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> BLS</hi> ÷ <hi rend="smallcaps">⅜T</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    smallcaps"> d1a</hi></p>
                <p>For place CI. perpendicular to AB, and through the point·</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538160" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8160-0445"/>
                <p>A, C, B describe a circle, and let CI. meet the circle again in E, and join AE,
                    BE. Also draw DG parallel to CE, meeting AE and BE in H and G, and draw EK
                    parallel to AB. Then, from the elements of geometry,</p>
                <p>CI.: LB :: (LA: LE :: ) LA <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: LA ×LE, and hence LA ×
                    LE=-í(?-‘LA <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Also CI.: LA :: (LB: LE ::) LB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: LB × LE, ī A</p>
                <p>and hence LB × LE=-^--∙LB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Now CI.: LB :: LA: LE :: EK or LD: KH, and CI.: LA :: LA: LE :: EK or LD: KG,
                    therefore, CI.: AB :: (LD: GH ::) LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: EK× GH,</p>
                <p>AB and hence EK× GH=—∙LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>From the three equations now deduced, there results --.LA*+ξ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> 4∙LB <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> + ~∙LD≡ =
                    AB×LE+EK×GH. LC LC CI.</p>
                <p>Again, because</p>
                <p>CI.: LA :: (LB: LE :: DB: DG ::) DB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: DB ×DG, LA
                    therefore DB × DG=-" -∙DB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. And because</p>
                <p>LL·.</p>
                <p>CI.: LB :: (LA: LE :: DA: DH ::) DA <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: DA × DH,
                    therefore DA ×DH=-^pDA <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. From the result of these
                    two last propositions we have <hi rend="smallcaps">⅛γ'</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    smallcaps"> da2</hi> +'ēE <hi rend="superscript"> DB2=DA</hi> X <hi
                    rend="superscript"> dh</hi> + <hi rend="superscript"> db</hi> × <hi
                    rend="superscript"> dg</hi>;</p>
                <p>But DA X DH=ta'ce <hi rend="italic">trian.</hi> ADH, and DB × DG=ftc⅛e <hi
                    rend="italic">lrian.</hi> BDG, and therefore DA× DH + DB × DG=2 <hi
                    rend="italic">(trian.</hi> ADH + irz'αw. BDG)=2 <hi rend="italic">(frian.
                    AΕM-±trian.</hi> HEG)=AB × LE + EK× HG∙ Nowithas been proved, that DA × DH+DB
                    ×DG=⅛A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi>-⅛Δ-.BD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and that AB×LE + EK×HG=⅛-∙LA <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> +-^-∙LB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +</p>
                <p>-^5-∙LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, therefore-^-·AD <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> + <hi rend="smallcaps">^</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> l</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">BD</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =-t^-∙AL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + <hi rend="smallcaps">v√L; wJL√</hi> VI. w-Li</p>
                <p>-^-∙BL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + <hi rend="italic">^5-∙DL</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> as was to be
                    demonstrated.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Porism.</hi> Let there be three straight lines AB, AC, CB
                    given in position; (fig. 5) and from any point whatever in one of them, as D,
                    let perpendiculars be drawn to the other two, as DF, DE, a point G may be found,
                    such, that if GD be drawn from it to the point D, the square of that line shall
                    have a given ratio to the sumofthesquares of the perpendiculars DF and DE, which
                    ratio is to be found.</p>
                <p>Draw AH, BK perpendicular to BC and AC; and in</p>
                <p>AB take L, so that AL: LB :: AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: BK <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:: AC <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: CB <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. The point L is therefore given; and if a line N be
                    taken, so as to have to AL the same ratio that AB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    has to AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, N will be given in magnitude. Also,
                    since AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: BK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:: AL:
                    LB, and AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>::
                    AL: N, <hi rend="italic">ex equo,</hi> BK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AB∙ ::
                    LB: N. Draw LO, LM perpendicular to AC, CB LO, LM are therefore given in
                    magnitude. Now, because AB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: BK <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:: AD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: DF <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, N: LB :: AD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: DF <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and DF ’ =—∙AD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. For
                    the same reason DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =-^^-∙BD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>LO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =⅛∙AL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and LM
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> ^∙BL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. N N</p>
                <p>But, by the preceding lemma, -^^-∙AD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +-^^-∙BD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =</p>
                <p>IBAT AR</p>
                <p>-^r-∙AL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + -^v-∙BL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +
                    ~~-∙DL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; that is, DE <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> +DF <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi></p>
                <p>AB</p>
                <p>= LO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + LM <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> q——∙DL
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Join LG, then by hypothesis LO <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + LM <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> has to LG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, the same ratio as DF <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    + DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> has to DG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>;
                    let it be that of R to N, then LO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + LM <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =^.LG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; and therefore
                    DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + DF <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =-^.LG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 4?.DL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; but DE <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + DF <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =⅛G <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; therefore,-⅛.LG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> N N
                    N</p>
                <p>+ ^∙DL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =⅛ and <hi rend="smallcaps">4γ∙DL</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">=</hi>-⅛DG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-LG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>); <hi
                    rend="superscript"> l</hi> N N N N <hi rend="superscript"> v j</hi> therefore DG
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —LG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> has to DL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> a constant ratio, viz. that of AB to R. The angle DLG
                    is therefore a right angle, and the ratio of AB to R that of equality, otherwise
                    LD would be given in magnitude, contrary to the supposition. LG is therefore
                    given in position: and since R: N :: AB: N :: LO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    + LM <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: LG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>;
                    therefore the square of LG, and consequently LG, is given in magnitude. The
                    point G is therefore given, and also the ratio of DE <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> =DF <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to DG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,
                    which is the same with that of AB to N.</p>
                <p>The construction easily follows from the analysis, but it may be rendered more
                    simple; for since AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AB <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>:: AL: N, and BK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AB <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 2</hi>:: BL: N; therefore AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + BK <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:: AB: N. Likewise,
                    if AG, BG, be joined, AB: N :: AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and AB: N :: BK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: BG
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; wherefore, AB: N :: AH <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> + BK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +
                    BG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, but it was proved that AB: N :: AH <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + BK <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: AB <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, therefore AG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + BG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =AB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; therefore the
                    angle AGB is a right angle, and AL: LG :: LG: LB. If therefore AB be divided in
                    L, so that AL: LB :: AH <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: BK <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; and if LG, a mean proportional between AL and LB, be
                    placed perpendicular to AB, G will be the point required.</p>
                <p>The step in the analysis, by which a second introduction of the general
                    hypothesis is avoided, is that in which the angle GLD is concluded to be a right
                    angle; which follows from DG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —GL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> having a given ratio to LD <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>, at the same time that LD is of no determinate magnitude. For, if
                    possible, let GLD be obtuse, (fig. 6,) and let the perpendicular from G to AB
                    meet in V, therefore V is given: and since GD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —LG
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × 2DL X LV;
                    therefore, by the supposition, LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2 DL X LV
                    must have a given ratio to LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; therefore the
                    ratio of LD <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to DL × VI., that is, of LD to VI.,
                    is given, so that VI. being given in magnitude, LD is also given. But this is
                    contrary to the supposition; for LD is indefinite by hypothesis, and therefore
                    GLD cannot be obtuse, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538173"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-8173-0446"/>nor any other than a right angle. The conclusion
                    that is here drawn immediately from the indetermination of LD would be deduced,
                    according to Dr. Simson’s method, by assuming another point D ʹ any how, and
                    from the supposition that GD' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-GL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: LD' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:: GD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-GL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: LD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, it would easily appear that GLD must be a right
                    angle, and the ratio that of equality.</p>
                <p>These porisms facilitate the solution of the general problems from which they are
                    derived. For example, let three straight lines AB, AC, BC, (fig. 5), be given in
                    position, and also a point R, to find a point D in one of the given lines, so
                    that DE and DF being drawn perpendicular to BC, AC, and DR, joined; DE <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +DF <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> may have to DR <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> a given ratio. It is plain, that having found G, the
                    problem would be nothing more than to find D, such that the ratio of GD <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to DR <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and therefore
                    that of GD to DR, might be given, from which it would follow, that the point D
                    is in the circumference of a given circle, as is well known to geometers.</p>
                <p>The same porism also assists in the solution of another problem. For if it were
                    required to find D such that DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + DF <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> might be a given space; having found G, DG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> would have to DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + DF
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> a given ratio, and DG would therefore be given;
                    whence the solution is obvious.</p>
                <p>The connection of this porism with the impossible case of the problem is evident;
                    the point L being that from which, if perpendiculars be drawn to AC and CB, the
                    sum of their squares is the least possible. For since DF <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> + DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: DG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>::
                    LO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + LM <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: LG <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; and since LG is less than DG, LO <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +LM <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> must be less than
                    DF <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + DE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>It is evident from what has now appeared, that in some instances at least there
                    is a close connection between these propositions and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >maxima</hi> or <hi rend="italic">minima,</hi> and of consequence the impossible
                    cases of problems. The nature of this connection requires to be farther
                    investigated, and is the more interesting because the transition from the
                    indefinite to the impossible case seems to be made with wonderful rapidity. Thus
                    in the first proposition, though there be not properly speaking an impossible
                    case, but only one where the point to be found goes off <hi rend="italic">in
                    infinitum,</hi> it may be remarked, that if the given point F (fig.1), be
                    anywhere out of the line HD, the problem of drawing GB equal to GF is always
                    possible, and admits of just one solution; but if F be in DH, the problem admits
                    of no solution at all, the point being then at an infinite distance, and
                    therefore impossible to be assigned. There is, however, this exception, that if
                    the given point be at K in this same line, DH is determined by making DK equal
                    to DL. Then every point in the line DE gives a solution, and may be taken for
                    the point G. Here therefore the case of numberless solutions, and of no solution
                    at all, are as it were <hi rend="italic">conterminal,</hi> and so close to one
                    another, that if the given point be at K the problem is indefinite; but if it
                    remove ever so little from K, remaining at the same time in the line DH, the
                    problem cannot be resolved. This affinity might have been determined <hi
                    rend="italic">a priori</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> for, as we have seen, it is
                    a general principle, that a problem is converted into a porism when one or when
                    two of the conditions of it necessarily involve in them some one of the rest.
                    Suppose, then, that two of the conditions are exactly in that state which
                    determines the third; then whilst they remain fixed or given, should that third
                    one vary or differ ever so little from the state required by the other two, a
                    contradiction will ensue. Therefore if, in the hypothesis of a problem, the
                    conditions be so related to one another as to render it indeterminate, a porism
                    is produced; but if, of the conditions thus related to one another, some one be
                    supposed to vary, whilst the others continue the same, an absurdity follows, and
                    the problem becomes impossible. <hi rend="italic">Wherever, therefore, any
                    problem admits both of an indeterminate and an impossible ease, it is certain,
                    that these cases are nearly related to one another,</hi><hi rend="italic">and
                    that some of the conditions by which they are produced are common to
                    both.</hi></p>
                <p>It is supposed above, that <hi rend="italic">two</hi> of the conditions of a
                    problem involve in them a third; and wherever that happens, the conclusion which
                    has been deduced will invariably take place. But a porism may in some cases be
                    so simple as to arise from the mere coincidence of <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
                    condition with another, though in no case whatever can any inconsistency take
                    place between them. There are, however, comparatively few porisms so simple in
                    their origin, or that arise from problems where the conditions are but little
                    complicated; for it usually happens that a problem which can become indefinite
                    may also become impossible; and if so, the connection already explained never
                    fails to take place.</p>
                <p>Another species of impossibility may frequently arise from the porismatic case of
                    a problem which will aifect in some measure the application of geometry to
                    astronomy, or any of the sciences depending upon experiment or observation. For
                    when a problem is to be resolved by means of data furnished by experiment or
                    observation, the first thing to be considered is, whether the data so obtained
                    be sufficient for determining the thing sought; and in this a very erroneous
                    judgment may be formed, if we rest satisfied with a general view of the subject.
                    For though the problem may in general be resolved from the data with which we
                    are provided, yet these data may be so related to one another in the case under
                    consideration, that the problem will become indeterminate, and instead of one
                    solution will admit of an indefinite number. This we have already found to be
                    the case in the foregoing propositions. Such cases may not indeed occur in any
                    of the practical applications of geometry; but there is one of the same kind
                    which has actually occurred in astronomy. Sir Isaac Newton, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Principia,</hi> has considered a small part of the orbit of a
                    comet as a straight line described with an uniform motion. From this hypothesis,
                    by means of four observations made at proper intervals of time, the
                    determination of the path of the comet is reduced to this geometrical problem.
                    Four straight lines being in position, it is required to draw a fifth line
                    across them, so as to be cut by them into three parts, having given ratios to
                    one another. Now this problem had been constructed by Dr. Wallis and Sir
                    Cristopher Wren, and also in three different ways by Sir Isaac himself in
                    different parts of his works; yet none of these geometers observed that there
                    was a particular situation of the lines in which the problem admitted of
                    innumerable solutions; and this happens to be the very case in which the problem
                    is applicable to the determination of the comet’s path, as was first discovered
                    by Boscovich, who was led to it by finding, that in this way he could never
                    determine the path of a comet with any degree of certainty.</p>
                <p>The preceding account of this interesting branch of the ancient geometry, is
                    taken from a very elegant and elaborate paper, <hi rend="italic">On the Origin
                    and Investigation of Porisms,</hi> by the late Professor Playfair, published in
                    the third volume of the Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, and also
                    in his collected <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> (vol. iii. p. 178.) For further
                    particulars on the subject, the reader may consult the original paper of
                    Professor Playfair; Dr. Simson’s treatise, <hi rend="italic">De
                    Porismatibus,</hi> contained in his <hi rend="italic">Opera Feliqua</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> a paper in the fourth volume of the Edinburgh Transactions,
                    by Professor Wallace, entitled, <hi rend="italic">Some Geometrical Porisms, with
                    examples of their application to the Solution of Problems</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> Dr. Traill’s <hi rend="italic">Account of the Life and Writings of
                    Fobert Simson, M.D</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and Professor Leslie’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Geometrical Analysis.</hi> At the end of Dr. Stewart’s <hi
                    rend="italic">General Theorems,</hi> above mentioned, five very remarkable
                    porisms are enunciated, the demonstration of the first of which is given in
                    Leybourn’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Repository,</hi> (vol.i.) and of the
                    remaining four in the fifth volume of the same work published <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193538186" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8186-0447"/>in 1830. The algebraic
                    analysis may frequently be applied with great advantage in the investigation of
                    porisms, but this manner of treating the subject does not come within the scope
                    of the present article.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
