<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-3077-0058-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLINIUS Secundus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 58</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1035984">Nephews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193533077" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLINIUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Secundus</hi></label>, C., a
                    celebrated Roman writer, but who is to be distinguished from his nephew, Pliny
                    the younger. He was born <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 23, in the tenth year
                    of Tiberius, and died on the 2d of November, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 80,
                    the first year of the Emperor Titus, and the day after the eruption of Mount λ
                    <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> esuvius. Two cities contend for the honour of
                    giving birth to him; but the inhabitants of Novum Comum, now <hi rend="italic"
                    >Como,</hi> seem to have a better claim to him as their fellow-citizen than
                    those of Verona. His earlier years were spent under the profligate reign of
                    Caligula and Claudius, but he does not appear to have mingled in the dissolute
                    scenes of those times. Though he devoted himself to the study of literature, he
                    did not withdraw himself from the active business of life. It appears that he
                    served his first military campaign in Africa, probably about his twenty-third
                    year, and that he afterwards spent some time in Germany, under his friend and
                    commander L. Pomponius Secundus, whom we find in Tacitus to have triumphed over
                    the Catti. It was about this time, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 48, that he
                    published his work entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Jaculatione Equestri</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and as Pomponius died shortly
                    after his triumph, Pliny performed the mournful though pleasing duty of
                    transmitting to posterity the transactions of his friend, in a work entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Pomponii</hi><hi rend="italic">Vita.</hi> He next devoted himself
                    to forensic duties, and displayed the same activity and zeal in defending the
                    causes of his fellow-citizens, as he had before done in maintaining the honour
                    of his country by arms. It seems probable that at this time he published his
                    work <hi rend="italic">Studiorum Tres Libri,</hi> divided into six volumes,
                    which was a manual for the formation of an orator, a subject which was
                    subsequently treated by Quintilian. He also published another work, <hi
                    rend="italic">Germanica</hi><hi rend="italic">Della,</hi> in which he gave a
                    detailed account of the wars of Drusus and Germanicus. In the reign of Nero,
                    Pliny was employed in Spain as Procurator Caesaris; an equestrian dignity, but
                    with the duties of which we are by no means well acquainted. He employed his
                    leisure hours in making a selection of passages from various authors, called <hi
                    rend="italic">Electorum Commentarii,</hi> which on his death he left, to the
                    number of one hundred and sixty, to his nephew. He also published, about <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 67, a grammatical work, <hi rend="italic">Dubii
                    Sermonis Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">Octo</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and
                    thirty-one books of History, which was a continuation of that of Aufidius
                    Bassus, who seems to have written an account of the civil wars. Pliny became the
                    intimate friend of Vespasian and his son Titus; and it was in the reign of the
                    former, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 77, that he published his celebrated
                    work, <hi rend="italic">Historia Naturalis,</hi> in thirty-seven books. Two
                    years afterwards, Pliny was stationed at Misenum, in Campania, in command of the
                    fleet; and when the eruption of Vesuvius broke out, he hurried towards it, to
                    assist bis friends, and to examine more minutely this wonderful phenomenon of
                    nature. But he fell a victim to his thirst for knowledge; being suffocated by
                    the sulphureous exhalations, as he was approaching the mountain from the side of
                    Stabiae, now <hi rend="italic">Castellarnare.</hi></p>
                <p>The work for which he is most distinguished is his Natural History, the materials
                    for which he has drawn from upwards of two thousand authors, which have
                    generally disappeared. It was divided into thirty-six books, with a dedication
                    to Titus, and a kind of index of the whole; but these are now considered as the
                    first book. The second book contains introductory remarks on astronomy and
                    meteorology; and from the third to the sixth inclusive we have a description of
                    the earth, the lands and their inhabitants, being a sort of universal geography,
                    though it is frequently nothing more than a simple enumeration of names. Then
                    follows the Natural History, beginning with the animal kingdom, which occupies
                    from the seventh to the eleventh books; then botany from the twelfth to the
                    nineteenth. With the twentieth begins his account of the medicinal qualities of
                    various herbs, which extends to the twenty-seventh; and then of the medicines
                    which may be prepared from animals, to the thirty-second. The remaining books
                    are occupied with the mineral kingdom, in which he takes occasion to introduce
                    much curious information respecting the fine arts, sculpture, painting, &amp;c.;
                    and concludes with an account of the most celebrated artists and their works.
                    Cuvier, who was so well able to judge of the value of such a work, thus
                    expresses himself. “Ce grand ouvrage est le scule de Pline qui soit arrivé
                    jusqu’à nous. Il est en même temps l’un des monumens les plus précieux que
                    l’antiquité nous ait laissés, et la preuve d’une érudition bien étonnante dans
                    un homme de guerre et un homme d’état. Pour apprécier avec justice cette vaste
                    et célèbre composition, il est nécessaire d’y distinguer le plan, les faits, et
                    le style. Le plan en est immense. Pline ne se propose point d’écrire sculement
                    one Histoire Naturelle dans le sens restreint où nous prenons aujourd’hui cette
                    science, c’est-à-dire, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193533090"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-3090-0059"/>un traité, plus ou moins détaillé, des animaux,
                    des plantes, et des minéraux; il embrasse l’astronomie, la physique, la
                    géographie, l’agriculture, le commerce, la médecine, et les arts, aussi bien que
                    l’Histoire Naturelle proprement dite; et il mêle sans cesse à ce qu’il en dit
                    des traits relatif, à la connaissance morale de Thomme, et à Thistoire des
                    peuples, en sorte qu’à beaucoup d’égards on a pu dire de cet ouvrage qu’il était
                    l’Encyclopédie de son temps Pline n’a point été un observateur tel qu’Aristote;
                    encore moins un homme de génie, capable, comme ce grand philosophe, de saisir
                    les lois et les rapports d’après lesquels la nature a co-ordonné ses
                    productions. Il n’est en général qu’un compilateur, et même le plus souvent un
                    compilateur qui, n’ayant point par lui-même d’idée des choses sur lesquelles il
                    rassemble les témoignages des autres, n’a pu apprécier la vérité de ces
                    témoignages, ni même toujours comprendre ce qu’ils avaient voulu dire Si Pline a
                    pour nous au jourd’hui peu de mérite comme critique et comme naturaliste, il
                    n’en est pas de même de son talent comme écrivain, ni du trésor immense de
                    termes et de locutions Latines dont l’abondance des matières l’a obligé de se
                    servir, et qui ont fait de son ouvrage l’un des plus riches dépôts de la langue
                    des Romains. Malgré les défauts que nous sommes obligés de lui reconnaitre quand
                    nous le considérons comme naturaliste, nous ne le regardons pas moins comme l’un
                    des auteurs les plus recommandables et les plus dignes d’être placés au nombre
                    des classiques parmi ceux qui ont écrit après le règne d’Auguste.”</p>
                <p>The best edition of Pliny is that edited by Cuvier, assisted by other learned men
                    in France, and published by Lemaire, Paris, 1827-1832, ten vols.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
