<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-4130-0139-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">POESTUM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 139</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1765196">Space</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:896967">Dorians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pz6r">Pillars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m29x">Dorians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193534130" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POESTUM</label>, of <hi rend="smallcaps">PaesTum,</hi> a
                    celebrated city of Italy, now in ruins, but anciently a place of great opulence
                    and magnitude. Its remains stand on a fertile plain, considerably to the south
                    of the city of Salerno, being bounded on the west by the Tyrrhenian Sea, and
                    about a mile distant by five hills, amongst which the town of Acropoli is
                    embosomed; on the north by the Bay of Salerno; and on the east by two hills,
                    which still retain their ancient names of Callimara and Cantena. The walls of
                    the city remain. In some places they are five, and in others twelve feet in
                    height. They are formed of solid blocks of stone, and appear to have been
                    furnished with towers at intervals; but the archway of only one gate stands
                    entire. This rampart encloses a space of about four miles in circumference; but
                    of the splendid cluster of buildings which it once enclosed, only three temples
                    rise, like the mausoleums of the ruined city, dark, silent, and majestic, to
                    attest the ancient magnificence of the place. They are the admiration of all who
                    visit them, and are considered as the purest and most perfect specimen in
                    existence of the foreign Doric order of architecture. The first temple which
                    presents itself to the view of the traveller is the smallest. It consists of six
                    pillars at each end, and thirteen at each side, counting the angular pillars in
                    both directions; and it is one hundred and seven feet in length, by forty-seven
                    feet in breadth. The architrave is pretty entire, as is the pediment at the west
                    end, with the exception of the corner stones and triglyphs, which are fallen,
                    and the first cornice, which is worn away. At the east end, part of the pediment
                    remains, and also much of the frize and cornice. The cella occupied more than
                    one third of the length, and had a porticoof two rows of columns, the ruins of
                    which, now overgrown with vegetation, encumber the area of the temple.</p>
                <p>The second edifice has six columns at each end, and fourteen on each side,
                    including those of the angles. The entablature and the pediments are entire. A
                    double row of columns adorned the interior of the cella, and supported each
                    another row of small pillars; the upper being separated from the lower by an
                    architrave only, without frize or cornice. A number of these pillars on each
                    side remain standing. The cella had two entrances, one at each end, with a
                    porticoformed of two pillars and two antae. The foundation and part of the wall
                    of this cella still remain: underneath it there was a vault. The third edifice
                    is the largest, being one hundred and ninety-five feet four inches in length, by
                    seventy-eight feet ten inches in breadth. It has nine pillars at each end, and
                    eighteen on each side, including the angular columns as before. Nor is its size
                    its only claim to distinction. A row of pillars, extending from the middle
                    pillar at one end to the middle pillar at the other, divides it into two equal
                    parts, and is considered as a proof that it was not a temple. What it was
                    intended for is yet a disputed point amongst the learned. In the centre there
                    appears to have been an aperture in the pavement, and at some distance another,
                    both leading, it is said, to subterranean vaults.</p>
                <p>Such appear to be the peculiar features of each of these edifices. They are all
                    raised upon substructions forming three gradations (for they are too high to be
                    called steps), intended solely to give due elevation and relief to the building;
                    the columns of all rise without bases from the uppermost of these degrees. They
                    are all fluted, between four and five diameters in height, and taper as they
                    ascend about one fourth; the capitals of the whole are very flat and prominent;
                    the intercolumniation is a little more than one diameter; the order and the
                    ornaments in all are the same; the pediment is almost invariably low; and,
                    finally, they are all built of a porous stone, of a light or rather yellow-grey
                    colour, and in many places perforated and worn away. In the open space between
                    the first and second temple there were two other large edifices, built of the
                    same stone, and of nearly the same size; but they are totally overthrowrf. All
                    these temples stand in a line, and border a street which ran from gate to gate,
                    and divided the town into two nearly equal parts. A hollow space, scooped out in
                    a semicircular form, seems to be the traces of a theatre; and as it lies in
                    front of the temples, gives reason to suppose that other public buildings might
                    have ornamented the same side, and made it correspond in grandeur with that
                    opposite; in which case few cities could have surpassed Poestum in the splendour
                    of its appearance.</p>
                <p>Although the city has left such magnificent monuments of its existence,
                    considerable obscurity hangs over its origin and general history. According to
                    the learned Mazzochi, Poestum was founded by a colony of Dorians, from Dora, a
                    city of Phoenicia. It was first called Posetan or Postan, which in Phoenician
                    signifies Neptune, to whom it was dedicated; but it was afterwards invaded, and
                    its primitive inhabitants expelled, by the Sybarites. This event is supposed to
                    have taken place about five centuries before the Christian era. Under its new
                    possessors the city assumed the Greek appellation Posidonia, of the same import
                    as its Phoenician, because it was a city of great opulence and magnitude, and is
                    supposed to have extended from the present ruin southward to the hill on which
                    stands the little town of Acropoli. The Lucanians afterwards expelled the
                    Sybarites, and checked the prosperity of Posidonia, which was in its turn
                    deserted and left to moulder imperceptibly away. Vestiges of it are still
                    visible all over the plain of Spinazzo or Saracino. The original city then
                    recovered its ancient name, and not long afterwards it was taken and colonized
                    by the Romans. From this period Poestum is mentioned almost solely by the poets;
                    indeed, from Virgil to Claudian, they all delight to expatiate upon the beauty
                    of its gardens, and to celebrate the bloom, the sweetness, and the fertility of
                    its roses; and to this day the roses are remarkable for their fragrance. A few
                    bushes, the remnants of <hi rend="italic">biferi rosaria</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Poesti,</hi> flourish here and there neglected, and still blossom twice a year,
                    in May and December, as if to support their ancient fame, and justify the
                    descriptions of the poets.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Virgil and Ovid just mention the Poestan roses; Propertius introduced them
                    as an emblem of mortality; Claudian employs them to grace a complimentary
                    comparison. Ausonius alone presents them in all their beauty and
                    freshness.</p><p>Vidi Poestano gaudere rosaria cultu</p><p>Exoriente novo
                    roscida Lucifero.</p></note> Poestum was subsequently plundered by the Saracens
                    and the Normans; and its remaining inhabitants were at length compelled to flee
                    for refuge to the mountains. The Dorians appear to have the fairest claim to the
                    erection of the majestic monuments which we have described. “But at what period
                    were they erected ?” says Mr Eustace. “To judge from their form, we must
                    conclude that they are the oldest specimens of Grecian architecture now in
                    existence. In beholding them and contemplating their solidity, bordering upon
                    heaviness, we are tempted to consider them as an intermediate link between the
                    Egyptian and Grecian manner, and the first attempt to pass from the immense
                    masses of the former to the graceful proportions of the latter. In fact, the
                    temples of Poestum, Agrigentum, and Athens, seem instances of the commencement,
                    the improvement, and the perfection of the Doric order.” <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(r. r. r.)</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193534143" xml:id="kp-eb0718-4143-0140"
                    /></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
