<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-8654-0483-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">POSITION, Centre of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 483</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j916">Passes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4td9n96c">Uniforms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1161356">Uniforms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1095872">Rest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1765196">Space</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193538654" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POSITION, <hi rend="smallcaps">Centre of</hi></label>. From
                    Archimedes to Doctor Wallis, w∙riters have assumed, that there belongs to every
                    <hi rend="italic">body an</hi> individual point, where, for most purposes, the
                    whole weight may be conceived to reside; and they have called it the <hi
                    rend="italic">centre of gravity.</hi> The learned Englishman, however, believed
                    himself the first to accomplish a demonstration from the nature of gravity.
                    (Scholium to Prop. xv. <hi rend="italic">De Centro</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gravitatis.)</hi></p>
                <p>But the same point is admirably connected with other properties and contingencies
                    of the body than its weight; and hence different names have been considered as
                    preferable by many writers, such as <hi rend="italic">centre of inertia·,</hi>
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>And from viewing a body as composed of physical points, it is found that the
                    relation of this centre to their positions is fertile in some of the most
                    beautiful theorems in the mathematics; whence it has properly received the
                    geometrical designation of the <hi rend="italic">centre of position.</hi></p>
                <p>We here introduce it in this geometrical character; and shall demonstrate very
                    briefly, but we trust sufficiently, a collection ofelegant and most important
                    properties,ofwhich some are virtually proved elsewhere, in a manner more suited
                    to the direct object of their introduction.</p>
                <p>If there be any multitude of distinct points in space, it is clear that a plane
                    may move, parallel to any given plane, until the collective distances of the
                    points on one side of it be equal to those on the other.</p>
                <p>Let a plane thus situated, relatively to a system of points, be called a plane of
                    equidistance.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538667" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8667-0484"/>
                <p>Suppose two planes of equidistance, A and B, perpendi cular to each other. Then,
                    first, we shall find that any plane C which passes through their common section
                    or axis, is also a plane of equidistance to the same system of points. For, let
                    any plane, perpendicular to this axis in 0, cut the planes A, B, C, in the
                    straight lines Aα, BZ&gt;, <hi rend="italic">Cc,</hi> respectively. Then <hi
                    rend="italic">Åa</hi> and B6 are at right angles. Let a perpendicular from any
                    point of the system meet the plane ABC in <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> Draw <hi
                    rend="italic">pq</hi> at right angles to <hi rend="italic">Cc,</hi> and let it
                    be positive when on the same side of the plane C as AO. Also draw <hi
                    rend="italic">ρr</hi> perpendicular to B6, and meeting Cc in s; and let <hi
                    rend="italic">pr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">rs</hi> be positive when on the same
                    sides of the planes B and C respectively as AO. The triangle <hi rend="italic"
                    >ρqs</hi> being given in species, <hi rend="italic">pq</hi> is as <hi
                    rend="italic">ps,</hi> that is, <hi rend="italic">aspr-∖-rs</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> so that the sum of the <hi rend="italic">ρq</hi> is as the
                    sum of the <hi rend="italic">pr</hi> together with that of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >rs.</hi></p>
                <p>But the <hi rend="italic">ρr</hi> are the distances of the points of the system
                    from the plane B, which is a plane of equidistance; and therefore their
                    aggregate is nothing. And again, the <hi rend="italic">rs</hi> are as the rO,
                    which are the distances from the plane A; and, having different signs on the two
                    sides, their aggregate is also nothing. Thus the sum of thejuç is nothing; and
                    the plane C is a plane of equidistance.</p>
                <p>Now let 0 move along the axis to make ABC a plane of equidistance. Then shall any
                    plane K which passes through 0 be such a plane.</p>
                <p>For let the plane K cut ABC in the line <hi rend="italic">Cc.</hi> The plane ABC,
                    and the plane C, which cuts it perpendicularly in the line <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cc,</hi> are planes of equidistance; therefore, by what we have just proved,
                    the plane K which passes through their common axis <hi rend="italic">Cc</hi> is
                    also a plane of equidistance. Thus, to every system of points, there is a point
                    through which every plane is a plane of equidistance. And there cannot be more
                    than one. For if there were two, we might have through them two parallel planes
                    of equidistance, which is manifestly absurd.</p>
                <p>This single point has been called the centre of position.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 1. The difference of the centre of position from any
                    given plane is an average of the distances of the several points of the system;
                    the distances on different sides being distinguished by contrary signs.</p>
                <p>For conceive the parallel plane of equidistance, at the distance D from the given
                    plane. Let the distance of a point of the system from the given plane be denoted
                    by D +&lt;Z. Then <hi rend="italic">d</hi> will vary its sign according as the
                    point of the system and the given plane be on different sides of the plane of
                    equidistance, or on the same side.</p>
                <p>Now if there be <hi rend="italic">p</hi> points in the system, the aggregate of
                    their distances from the given plane will be pD, together with the aggregate of
                    the <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> But the collective <hi rend="italic">d</hi> are
                    nothing; so that it will be ∕&gt;D; or D is the average distance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 2. If the average distances of the points of a sys
                    tem from three planes, perpendicular or inclined to each other, be given, the
                    centre of position is given. For, by the distances of a point from three such
                    planes, its position in space is given.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 3. If the centre of position, and the multitude of
                    points in each of two systems be given , the centre of the united systems is
                    found in the straight line joining the given centres at distances from these
                    reciprocally proportional to the multitudes.</p>
                <p>Let P and Q be the centres of position of two systems of <hi rend="italic">p</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">q</hi> points respectively. Let perpendiculars from P and
                    Q meet any plane of equidistance in <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> respectively.</p>
                <p>Then <hi rend="italic">p.~PaJ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">q Qb</hi> expresses the collective distances of the points of the
                    united systems from the plane of equidistance, consequently the two terms are of
                    opposite signs and equal magnitude.</p>
                <p>And because Pα and Q6 are perpendicular to the same plane, they are parallel: so
                    that Pα, <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi><hi rend="italic">bQ,</hi> are in one plane.
                    Let 0 be the intersection of PQ and <hi rend="italic">ab.</hi> Then PO and OQ
                    are as Pα and Q6; and since <hi rend="italic">p . l</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">a-q .</hi> Qó, we have also <hi
                    rend="italic">p .</hi> PO=g . QO, or PO: QO :: <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">p.</hi></p>
                <p>Thus every plane of equidistance passes through the same point 0, which is
                    therefore the centre of position.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scholium.</hi> Hence, if we have any points A, B, C, D,
                    &amp;c., bisecting AB in Μ, or making AM=⅛AB; again, making MN to NC as 1 to 2,
                    or MN=⅜MC; and NO to OD as 1 to 3, or NO-— ND, and so on: Then Μ is the centre
                    of position of the two points A and B; N of the three points A, B, C; 0 of the
                    four points A, B, C, D, and so on. And as we have proved that there cannot be
                    more than one centre of position to the same system of points, the ultimate
                    point must be the same in whatever order we take the given points into the
                    operation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 4. The difference of the squares of the distances of
                    the centre of position from the extremities of any straight line is an average
                    of the difference of the squares of the several points of a system from these
                    extremities.</p>
                <p>Let SO be the straight line; A a point of a system whose centre of position is G;
                    and Aα and <hi rend="italic">Gg</hi> perpendicular to the extension of SO. Then
                    AS <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —AO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =αS <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-αO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ==(αS + αO). OS;
                    making as and αO negative when measured contrary to the tendency OS.</p>
                <p>Hence Σ (AS <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —AO <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>)=∑(αS).</p>
                <p>OS-f-∑aO).OS. But, if there be <hi rend="italic">ρ</hi> points, ∑(as)
                    is7&gt;.&lt;7S, and ∑(αO) is <hi rend="italic">p∙gC).</hi> Therefore, ∑(AS <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —AO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">×^O).OS=λ(GS</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">-</hi> GO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 5. The squares of the distances of any points in
                    space from their centre of position are together less than from any point in the
                    surface of a sphere about this centre, by the square of the radius multiplied by
                    the number of points.</p>
                <p>For when G coincides with O, <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is also there; and we have
                    ∑(AS <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-AO <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)=p.OS.OS,
                    or^.OS <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 6. If A, B, C, &amp;c., express the number of points
                    . whose respective centres are in the positions A, B, C; and 0 be the centre of
                    position of all the points united in one system; then, S being any other point,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">A.SA</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> s</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">+B.SB+</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">C.sc</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">=A.OA</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">+b.OB</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">+C∙OC</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">+ (a+b+c)oS*.</hi></p>
                <p>For, by Cor. 4, A(SA <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-OA <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>)+B(SB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-OB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) +
                    C(SC <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193538680"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0718-8680-0485"/>—OC <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) expresses the
                    excess of the squares of the distances of all the points from S over the squares
                    of their distances from 0, which (by the last cor.) is equal to (A + B + C). OS
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor. 1.</hi> In any system of points, the motion of the centre
                    of position, in any given direction, is an average of their several motions in
                    that direction.</p>
                <p>For assume a plane perpendicular to the given direction behind all their motions.
                    Let there be <hi rend="italic">p</hi> points, and the sum of their distances
                    from the assumed plane, at the beginning of the motion <hi rend="italic"
                    >pd.</hi> Then the distance of the centre of position from this plane is <hi
                    rend="italic">d.</hi></p>
                <p>At any instant afterwards, let their united distances from this plane be∫&gt;D,
                    that of their centre of position being therefore D.</p>
                <p>The aggregate motion of the system in the given direction has been, pD— <hi
                    rend="italic">pd,</hi> or ^(D— <hi rend="italic">d),</hi> while that of the
                    centre of position has been D— <hi rend="italic">d.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Cor.</hi> 8. If the several points of a system be uniform as to their motion,
                    the centre of position either rests or moves uniformly.</p>
                <p>If it do not rest, whatever be its first tendency, it must persevere in the same.
                    For as it begins without any motion perpendicular to this direction, the
                    aggregate of the motions of the system in any direction perpendicular to this
                    must be nothing, and therefore will continue nothing; so that the centre will
                    never be taken out of its first direction. And as the motion of each point,
                    estimated in this direction, is the same during a given time, the average, or
                    the motion of the centre is the same; so that it traces its path uniformly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Otherwise.</hi></p>
                <p>Because the motion of any point of the system, estimated in three different
                    directions not in the same plane, is uniform in each; that of the centre of
                    position is uniform in these directions, or is nothing. Hence it can have no
                    motion other than uniform in direction and velocity.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 9∙ If a body, or system of bodies, be put in motion,
                    and subject to no other disturbance than the action of the parts or bodies upon
                    each other; the centre of position will either rest or move uniformly in a
                    straight line.</p>
                <p>For every particle is at first determined to a certain direction and velocity, or
                    put in a condition of uniform motion. And the actions of material particles or
                    bodies upon each other, (whether by impulsion, attraction, impact, or leverage,)
                    are equal and contrary; so that the aggregate motion, and consequently the
                    average motion, is not affected by it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 10. The agregate momentum of a system, in any
                    direction, is as if it were all collected into the centre of position.</p>
                <p>The momentum in any direction is the united momenta of the several particles.
                    Now, if there be <hi rend="italic">p</hi> particles, and their several
                    velocities in a given direction be denoted by <hi rend="italic">d, v", v</hi> ’
                    <hi rend="italic">",</hi> &amp;c.; these also represent their several momenta;
                    and if we put <hi rend="italic">pv=d + vl'</hi> + υ'" + <hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi> is the velocity of the centre of position. Thus
                    the aggregate momentum is as if every particle were in this centre.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scholium.</hi> When the system is connected these parallel
                    momenta compound a force in the given direction, which passes through the centre
                    of position, or centre of gravity; and is equal to the sum of the several
                    forces. So that the impact of the system is as if all were collected in the
                    centre.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 11. If a body be left to itself in a state of
                    rotation, the axis of rotation will pass through the centre of position.</p>
                <p>For when there is rotation, no point out of the axis can either rest or move in a
                    straight line. Therefore the centre of position will be in the axis.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 12. If attracting particles be left to their mutual
                    attraction, they will coalesce abcut their centre of position.</p>
                <p>For their attractions do not affect the aggregate or average motion in any
                    direction. Therefore the centre of position remains at rest while they are
                    brought together around it. (o. o. o.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
