<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0674-0641-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HELST, Bartholomaeus (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    641)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1153089">Touch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1073567">Potters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rj4928x">Potters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dz71">Watches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nt76">Touch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n674/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HELST, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartholomaeus</hi></label><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">van</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">der,</hi> was born in Holland
                    at the opening of the 17th century, and died at Amsterdam in 1670. The date and
                    place of his birth are uncertain; and it is equally difficult to confirm or to
                    deny the time-honoured statement that he was born in 1G13 at Amsterdam. It has
                    been urged indeed by competent authority that Van der Heist was not a native of
                    Amsterdam, because a family of that name lived as early as 1G07 at Haarlem, and
                    pictures are shown as works of Van der Hebt in the Haarlem Museum which might
                    tend to prove that he was in practice there before he acquired repute at
                    Amsterdam. Unhappily Bartholomew has not been traced amongst the children of
                    Severijn van der Helst, who married at Haarlem in 1G07, and there is no proof
                    that the pictures at Haarlem are really his; though if they were so they would
                    show that he learnt his art from Frans Hals and became a skilled master as early
                    as 1G31. Scheltema, a very competent judge in matters of Dutch art chronology,
                    supposes that Van der Heist was a resident at Amsterdam in 1G36. His first great
                    picture, representing a gathering of civic guards at a brewery, is variously
                    assigned to 1G39 and 1643, and still adorns the town-hall of Amsterdam. His
                    noble portraits of the burgomaster Bicker and Andreas Bicker the younger, in the
                    gallery of Amsterdam, of the same date no doubt as Bicker’s wife lately in the
                    Ruhl collection at Cologne, were completed in 1642. From that time till his
                    death there is no difficulty in tracing Van der Helst’s career at Amsterdam. He
                    acquired and kept the position of a distinguished portraiLpainter, producing
                    indeed little or nothing besides portraits at any time, but founding, in
                    conjunction with Nicolaes de Helt Stokade, the painters’ guild at Amsterdam in
                    1654. At some unknown date he married Constance Reynst, of a good patrician
                    family in the Netherlands, bought himself a house in the Doelenstrasse, and
                    ended by earning a competence. His likeness of Paul Potter at the Hague,
                    executed in 1654, and his partnership with Backhuysen, who laid in the
                    backgrounds of some of his pictures in 1668, indicate a constant companionship
                    with the best artists of the time. Waagen has said that his portrait of Admiral
                    Kortenaar, in the gallery of Amsterdam, betrays the teaching of Frans Hals, and
                    the statement need not be gainsaid; yet on the whole Van der Heist’s career as a
                    painter was mainly a protest against the systems of Hals and Rembrandt. It is
                    needless to dwell on the pictures which preceded that of 1648, called the Peace
                    of Münster, in the gallery of Amsterdam. The Peace challenges comparison at once
                    with the so-called Night Watch by Rembrandt, and the less important but not less
                    characteristic portraits of Hals and his wife in a neighbouring room. Sir Joshua
                    Reynolds waβ disappointed by Rembrandt, whilst Van der Helst surpassed his
                    expectation. But Bürger asked whether Reynolds had not already been struck with
                    blindness when he ventured on this criticism. The question is still an open one.
                    But certainly Van der Heist attracts by qualities entirely differing from those
                    of Rembrandt and Frans Hals. Nothing can be more striking than the contrast
                    between the strong concentrated light and the deep gloom of Rembrandt and the
                    contempt of chiaroscuro peculiar to his rival, except the contrast between the
                    rapid sketchy touch of Hals and the careful finish and rounding of Van der
                    Helst. The Peace is a meeting of guards to celebrate the signature of the treaty
                    of Münster. The members of the Doele of St George meet to feast and congratulate
                    each other not at a formal banquet but in a spot laid out for good cheer, where
                    De Wit, the captain of his company, can shake hands with his lieutenant Waveren,
                    yet hold in solemn state the great drinking-horn of St George. The rest of the
                    company sit, stand, or busy themselves around,—some eating, others drinking,
                    others carving or serving—an animated scene on a long canvas, with figures large
                    as life. Well has Bürger said, the heads are full of life and the hands
                    admirable. The dresses and subordinate ’ parts are finished to a nicety without
                    sacrifice of detail or loss of breadth in touch or impast. But the eye glides
                    from shape to shape, arrested here by expressive features, there by a bright
                    stretch of colours, nowhere at perfect rest because of the lack of a central
                    thought in light and shade, harmonies, or composition. Great as the qualities of
                    Van der Heist undoubtedly are, he remains below the line of demarcation which
                    separates the second from the first-rate masters of art.</p>
                <p>His pictures are very numerous, and almost uniformly good; but in his later
                    creations he wants power, and though still amazingly careful, he becomes grey
                    and woolly in touch. At Amsterdam the four regents in the Werkhuys (1650), four
                    syndics in the gallery (1656), and four syndics in the town-hall (1657) are
                    masterpieces, to which may be added a number of fine single portraits.
                    Rotterdam, notwithstanding the fire of 1864, still boasts of three of Van der
                    Heist’s works. The Hague, as we saw, owns but one. St Petersburg, on the other
                    hand, possesses ten or eleven, of various shades of excellence. The Louvre has
                    three, Munich four. Other pieces are in the galleries of Berlin, Brunswick,
                    Brussels, Carlsπιhe, Cassel, Darmstadt, Dresden, Frankfort, Gotha, Stuttgart,
                    and Vienna.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
