<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0415-0396-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HALLER, Albrecht von</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 396</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n415/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HALLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Albrecht von</hi></label>
                    (1708-1777), one of the greatest of the anatomists and physiologists of the 18th
                    century, was born of an old Swiss family at Bern, October 16, 1708. Prevented by
                    long-continued ill-health from taking part in boyish sports, he had the more
                    opportunity for the development of his precocious mind. At the age of four, it
                    is said, he used to read and expound the Bible to his father’s, servants; before
                    he was ten he had sketched a Chaldee grammar, prepared a Greek and a Hebrew
                    vocabulary, compiled a collection of two thousand biographies of famous men and
                    women on the model of the great works of Bayle and Moreri, and written in Latin
                    verse a satire on his tutor, who had warned him against a too great
                    excursiveness. When still hardly fifteen he was already the author of numerous
                    metrical translations from Ovid, Horace, and Virgil, as well as of original
                    lyrics, dramas, and an epic of four thousand lines on the origin of the Swiss
                    confederation, writings which he is said on one occasion to have rescued from a
                    fire at the risk of his life, only, however, to burn them a little later (1729)
                    with his own hand. Haller’s attention had been directed to the profession of
                    medicine while he was residing in the house of a physician at Biel after his
                    father’s death in 1721; and, following the choice then made, he while still a
                    sickly and excessively shy youth went in his sixteenth year to the university of
                    Tiibingen (December 1723), where he studied under Camerarius and Duvernoy.
                    Dissatisfied with his progress, he in 1725 exchanged Tübingen for Leyden, where
                    Boerhaave was in the zenith of his fame, and where Albinus had already begun to
                    lecture in anatomy. At that university he graduated in May 1727, undertaking
                    successfully in his thesis to prove that the so-called salivary duct, claimed as
                    a recent discovery by <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n416/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0416-0397"/> Coschwitz, was nothing more than a blood-vessel.
                    Haller then visited London, making the acquaintance of Sir Hans Sloane,
                    Cheselden, Pringle, Douglas, and other scientific men; next, after a short stay
                    in Oxford, he visited Paris, where he studied under Ledran and Winslow <hi
                    rend="italic">; and</hi> in 1728 lie proceeded to Basel, where he devoted
                    himself to the study of the higher mathematics under John Bernoulli. It was
                    during his stay there also that his first great interest in botany was awakened;
                    and, in the course of a tour through Savoy, Baden, and several of the Swiss
                    cantons, he began a collection of plants which was afterwards the basis of his
                    great work on the flora of Switzerland. In 1729 he returned to Bern and began to
                    practise as a physician; his best energies, however, were devoted to the
                    botanical and anatomical researches which rapidly gave him a European
                    •reputation, and procured for him from George II. in 1736 a call to the chair of
                    medicine, anatomy, botany, and surgery, in the newly-founded university of
                    Göttingen. The quantity of work achieved by Haller in the seventeen years during
                    which he occupied this post was immense. Apart from the ordinary work of his
                    classes, which entailed upon him the task of newly organizing a botanical
                    garden, an anatomical theatre and museum, an obstetrical school, and similar
                    institutions, he carried on without interruption those original investigations
                    in botany and physiology, the results of which are preserved in the numerous
                    works associated with his name; he continued also to persevere in his youthful
                    habit of poetical composition, while at the same time he conducted a monthly
                    scientific journal to which he is said to have contributed twelve thousand
                    articles relating to almost every branch of human knowledge. He also warmly
                    interested himself in most of the religious questions, both ephemeral and
                    permanent, of his day; and the erection of the Reformed church in Göttingen was
                    mainly due to his unwearied energy. Notwithstanding all this variety of
                    absorbing interests he never felt at home in Göttingen; his untravelled heart
                    kept ever turning towards his native Bern (where he had been elected a member of
                    the great council in 1745), and in 1753 he resolved to resign his chair and
                    return to Switzerland. The twenty-one years of his life which followed were
                    largely occupied in the discharge of his duties as “amman,” to which honourable
                    office he had been chosen by his fellow-citizens, and in the preparation of his
                    <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic">Medica,</hi> the botanical,
                    surgical, and anatomical parts of which he lived to complete; but he also found
                    time to write the three philosophical romances, <hi rend="italic">—Usong</hi>
                    (1771), <hi rend="italic">Alfred</hi> (1773), and <hi rend="italic">Fabius and
                    Cato</hi> (1774),—in which his views as to the respective merits of despotism,
                    of limited monarchy, and of aristocratic republican government are fully set
                    forth. About 1773 the state of his health rendered necessary his entire
                    withdrawal from public business; for some time he supported his failing strength
                    by means of opium, on the use of which he communicated a paper to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> of the Göttingen Royal Society in 1776; the
                    excessive use of the drug is believed, however, to havehastened his death,
                    whichoccurred on the 17th of December 1777. Haller, who had been three times
                    married, left eight children, the eldest of whom, Gottlieb Emanuel, attained to
                    some distinction as a botanist and as a writer on Swiss history.</p>
                <p>For some account of Haller’s contributions to the sciences of which he was
                    especially an ornament, see the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy</hi> (vol.
                    i. p. 814) and <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology.</hi> Subjoined is a classified
                    but by no means an exhaustive list of his very numerous works in various
                    branches of science and. literature :—(1) Anatomical :— <hi rend="italic">leones
                    αnα-tomfκ</hi> (1743-54); <hi rend="italic">Disputationes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >anatomicae</hi><hi rend="italic">seleetiores</hi> (1746-52); and <hi
                    rend="italic">Opera, aead. minora</hi><hi rend="italic">anatomici argumenti</hi>
                    (1762-68). (2)</p>
                <p>Physiologic al: — <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">respiratione
                    experimenta anatomica</hi> (1747); <hi rend="italic">Primae lmeae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">physiologia</hi> (1747); and <hi rend="italic">Elementa
                    physiologia corporis humani</hi> (1757-6θ). (3) Pathological and surgical :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Opusculapatho</hi><hi rend="italic">logica</hi> (1755); <hi
                    rend="italic">Disputationum</hi><hi rend="italic">Chirurg,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >collectio</hi> (1777); also careful editions of Boerhaave’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Praelectiones academicoe in proprias</hi><hi rend="italic">insti</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">tutiones rei medicae</hi> (1739), and of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Artis</hi><hi rend="italic">medicae principia</hi> of the same author
                    (1769-74). (4) Botanical :— <hi rend="italic">Enumeratio stirpium Hel</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">veticarum</hi> (1742); <hi rend="italic">Opuscula botanica</hi>
                    (1749); <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca botanica</hi> (1771). (5) Theological :—
                    <hi rend="italic">Briefe über die wichtigsten Wahrheiten</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >der Offenbarung</hi> (1772); and <hi rend="italic">Briefe zur Vertheidigung der
                    Offenbarung</hi><hi rend="italic">jmo-∏j</hi> (6) Poetical <hi rend="italic"
                    >-.—Gedichte</hi> (1732, 12th ed. 1777). His three romances have been already
                    mentioned. Several volumes of lectures and “Tagebücher” or journals were
                    published posthumously.</p>
                <p>See J. G. Zimmermann, <hi rend="italic">Das Leben des Herrn von</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Haller</hi> (1755), and the articles by Forster and Seiler in
                    Erseh and Gruber's <hi rend="italic">Encyklopädie.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
