<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0828-0791-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HIERAPOLIS (9th edition, volume 11, page 791)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1054016">Parthians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866649">Coins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1118724">Silk</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994503">Lays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rg4g">Coins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39453">Silk</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n828/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HIERAPOLIS</label>. Of the many cities in the Greek world
                    bearing this name the following are the most important.</p>
                <p>1. A city of Syria Cyrrhestica, situated on some hills about 16 miles south-west
                    from the junction of the Euphrates and the Sajur. Besides the natural strength
                    of its position, it was important as lying on the line of intercourse between
                    Northern Syria and Mesopotamia, and was always a great trading city. Its early
                    history is quite unknown. It is not mentioned during the Assyrian wars in this
                    part of Syria (see Sayce, <hi rend="italic">Academy,</hi> October 1876). Abul
                    Farâz asserts that Josiah was defeated there by Pharaoh Necho (611 B.c.) on his
                    march towards Carchemish; but according to 2 Chron. xxxv. 20 the battle took
                    place at Carchemish, which lay on the Euphrates a little further north on the
                    site of the modern Jerablûs, or Jerabis; and probably Abul Farâz confounded the
                    two cities. The same confusion perhaps has caused the statement of Ammianus that
                    Hierapolis was identical with Ninus Vetus on the Euphrates. Jerablûs is clearly
                    a corruption of Hierapolis, by which name therefore Carchemish must at some time
                    have been styled by the Greeks; but it is surprising to find two great cities of
                    the same name so near one another. No proof exists that Hierapolis was an
                    important city before the time of the Seleucidae, and Professor Say ce suggests
                    that it then succeeded to the trade and name of the older city, which had now
                    decayed. Its original name is given in Greek as <hi rend="italic">⅛αpβνκη,</hi>
                    which points back to a form Bambyg or Mambug, while the Syrian form is given by
                    Pliny as Mabog, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> Mabbog for Mambog. The romance of
                    trade by which this name has become naturalized in many European languages
                    deserves a passing notice. As the city lay on the highway to the East, cotton
                    and silk were important branches of its trade. Probably cotton plantations
                    existed there in old time; and after the cultivation of silk was introduced to
                    western Asia in the time of the Sassan ian kings, large groves of mulberry trees
                    surrounded the city. The name Mambe was afterwards confounded with the Persian
                    word pambe, silk; and the Greek form <hi rend="italic">^B&gt;apβvκη</hi> also
                    was similarly mixed up with the word <hi rend="italic">β0pβvξ,</hi><note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                                >Βόμβυξ</hi> is borrowed from the Persian word (Benfey, <hi
                                rend="italic">Wurzellex.,</hi> ii. 113), though the form it has
                            taken in Greek is influenced by the word <hi rend="italic">βομβόω,</hi>
                            to buzz. It is used by Aristotle, &amp;c., to denote a gnat found in
                            Asia Minor, which has certainly nothing to do with silk.</p></note><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> γ</hi> which originally denoted the fly supposed
                    to spin on trees the cotton or silk (for the two substances were confused by the
                    Greeks and Romans) which men then gathered off the trees (Virg., <hi
                        rend="italic">Georg.,</hi> ii. 121). Hence the “Bombycinae vestes” of the
                    Roman writers; while the city itself is called “Bombycina urbs.” In Asia cotton
                    seems to have been known as a distinct article, and was named after the city
                    which was the chief seat of its manufacture, as muslin is from Mosul. By the
                    crusaders the stuff and the name were carried to Europe, and the latter exists
                    in English in the form “bombazine.” The Syrian goddess Atargatis, called by the
                    Greeks Derceto, a personification of the nature power worshipped under different
                    names over the whole of western Asia, had one of her most famous temples in the.
                    city; and perhaps Mambe may have been a local name of the goddess. Hence in the
                    3d century <hi rend="smallcaps">b,c.,</hi> when, under the Seleucid kings,
                    Bambyce became a great Greek city and the most important station between Antioch
                    and Seleucia, it was called Hierapolis or Hieropolis. The latter form is found
                    on coins, the former is used in classical literature. The coinage of Hierapolis
                    begins under the Seleucidae. The autonomous coins, probably for commercial
                    reasons, imitate closely the coins of Antioch. The temple was plundered by
                    Crassus on his Parthian expedition (53 B.C.). Under Diocletian or Constantine,
                    Hierapolis became the capital of the new province of Euphratensis, a name which
                    soon gave place to the older name Commagene. As paganism decayed, Hierapolis
                    ceased to be the sacred city, and recovered its ancient name; at the same time
                    its importance and population declined. In the time of Julian, who concentrated
                    there the Roman troops for the fatal Parthian campaign, it was still one of the
                    greatest cities of Syria; but under Justinian, who made some attempt to restore
                    it, great part of its area was a desert, and the once strong fortifications were
                    so decayed that the place was not defensible against the Parthian king Chosroes.
                    At the Arab conquest it passed into the hands of the caliphs. Haroun-al-Raschid
                    '(786-808) restored it and strengthened its walls, and it is mentioned about
                    1150 by Edrisi as a strong city. As the empire of the caliphs dwindled, Mambedj
                    became a frontier post in the struggle between Christians and Mahometans, and
                    its possession carried with it the rule in this part of Syria. The emperor
                    Romanus Diogenes captured it in his gallant struggle against the Turks (1068).
                    Recaptured by the Seljuk Turks, it soon afterwards fell into the power of the
                    crusaders, until it was stormed by Saladin (1175). It was for some time the
                    headquarters of the Mongol host under Hulagu Khan; and, as with many other
                    Syrian cities, its desolation dates from this time. The ruins which still exist
                    called Kara Bambuche or Buyuk Mambedj, have been described by Pococke and
                    others, and most carefully by Chesney <hi rend="italic">{Euphrates
                        Expedition,</hi> i. 420).</p>
                <p>Strabo (xvi. p. 748) confuses this Hierapolis with Edessa in Mesopotamia. A very
                    full account of the city to supplement the brief outline here given may be found
                    in Ritter, <hi rend="italic">Erdkunde,</hi> x. 1041-65.</p>
                <p>2. A city in Phrygia, at the junction of the Lycus and Meander, on the road from
                    Apamea to Sardis. In it there were warm springs which had and still have a
                    remarkable power of forming incrustations. Its name Hierapolis is due to the
                    sanctity conferred on it by these hot springs, and by the Plutonium, a small
                    cave under a projecting rock, from which there constantly emanated a dark vapour
                    deadly to man and beast (Strabo, xiii. 629; Vitruv., viii. 3; Apuleius, <hi
                        rend="italic">De Mundo,</hi> p. 65). In reference to this we find sometimes
                    on its coins Pluto carrying off Proserpine.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n829/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0829-0792"/>
                <p>The water was also much used for dyeing. Nothing is known of the origin of the
                    city; from the legend <hi rend="italic">αρχηγέτη·:</hi> on coins, with a radiate
                    head of the sun-god, Eckhel concludes that a Greek foundation was made under the
                    guidance of Apollo; but a native city may have already existed there. The native
                    name of the sun-god was <hi rend="italic">Baιpβηvoς,</hi> which often occurs on
                    coins; he was probably a Phrygian form of the Greek Zeus. The goddess of
                    healthful drinking, Euposia, is also seen on coins. Cybele also, who is found on
                    the coins, was one of the chief deities of the place. Little is known of the
                    history of the city. The philosopher Epictetus was born there; and there St Paul
                    founded a church (Coloss. iv. 13). The very considerable ruins which still
                    exist, called Pambuk Kalessi (“Cottoh Castle <hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi>),
                    have been described by Pococke, Leake, &lt;fcc. The ancient theatre and
                    gymnasium are in a state of remarkable preservation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
