<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0547-0516-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HASTINGS, Francis Rawdon Hastings, First Marquis of
                    (9th edition, volume 11, page 516)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n547/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HASTINGS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis Rawdon Hastings, First
                            Marquis of</hi></label> (1754-1826), ranks among those governorsgeneral
                    of India who, completing the work of Clive and Warren Hastings, achieved the
                    creation of the Indian empire of England. The services of Lord Hastings in this
                    respect were special and important. He was both governorgeneral and
                    commander-in-chief in India from 1813 till the end of 1822; during that period
                    he carried two important wars, the Nepaulese and the Mahratta, to a successful
                    issue; while adding to the territories of the East India Company, he in several
                    respects altered and improved their policy; and by the sagacity and at the same
                    time the generosity of his own administration (in which he exhibited the true
                    qualities of a Christian proconsul) he won reverence from the natives and left a
                    great name in India.</p>
                <p>Lord Hastings was in no way connected with Warren Hastings; his family name was
                    Rawdon. His father, Sir John Rawdon of Moira in the county of Down, fourth
                    baronet, was created Baron Rawdon of Moira, and afterwards Earl of Moira, in the
                    Irish peerage. His mother was the Lady Elizabeth Hastings, daughter of the ninth
                    earl of Huntingdon. Both his father and mother appear to have been persons of
                    considerable ability and high cultivation. Lord Rawdon, as he was then called,
                    having gone at an early age to the university of Oxford, joined the army in his
                    seventeenth year as ensign in the 15th foot His life henceforth was entirely
                    spent in the service of his country, and may naturally be divided into four
                    periods :— from 1773 to 1782 he was engaged with much distinction in the
                    American war; from 1783 to 1813 he held various high appointments at home, and
                    took an active part in the business of the House of Lords; from 1813 to 1823 was
                    the period of his labours in India; after retiring from which, in the last years
                    of his life (1824-1826), he was governor of Malta.</p>
                <p>In America Lord Rawdon served at the battles of Bunker’s Hill, Brooklyn, White
                    Plains, Monmouth, and Camden, at the attacks on Forts Washington and Clinton,
                    and at the siege of Charleston. In fact he was engaged in all the chief
                    operations of the war. Perhaps his most noted achievements were the raising of a
                    corps at Philadelphia, called the Irish Volunteers, who under him became famous
                    for their fighting qualities, and the victory of Hob-kirk<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n548/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0548-0517"/> Hill, which, when in command of only a small
                    force, he gained by superior military skill and determination against an
                    American <hi rend="italic">corps</hi><hi rend="italic">T armée.</hi> In 1782 he
                    was invalided. The vessel in which he returned to England wa3 captured and
                    carried into Brest. This occasioned the loss of his papers and personal records
                    of the war which would doubtless have been interesting. He was speedily
                    released, and on his arrival in England was much honoured by George III., who
                    created him an English peer (Baron Rawdon) in March 1783.</p>
                <p>In 1793 Lord Rawdon succeeded his father as earl of Moira. In 1794 he was sent
                    with 10,000 men from Southampton to Ostend to reinforce the duke of York and the
                    allies in Flanders. The march by which he effected a junction was considered
                    extraordinary. In 1803 he was appointed commander-in-chief in Scotland, and in
                    1804 he married Flora Muir Campbell, countess of Loudon in her own right. He and
                    Lady Loudon lived at Duddingston House near Edinburgh, where they were very
                    popular. The opposition coming into power in 1806, Lord Moira, who had always
                    voted with them, received the place of master general of the ordnance. He was
                    now enabled to carry a philanthropic measure, of which from his first entry into
                    the House of Lords he had been a great promoter, namely, the Debtor and Creditor
                    Bill for relief of poor debtors. Ireland was another subject to which he had
                    given particular attention: in 1797 there was published a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Speech by Lord Moira on the Dreadful and Alarming State of Ireland.</hi>
                    Lord Moira’s sound judgment on public affairs, combined with his military
                    reputation and the honourable uprightness of his character, won for him a high
                    position among the statesmen of the day, and he gained an additional <hi
                        rend="italic">prestige</hi> from his intimate relations with the prince of
                    Wales. On two occasions, in 1809 and again in 1812 after the assassination of
                    Percival, there were negotiations for placing him at the head of affairs. As a
                    further mark of the regent’s regard Lord Moira received the order of the Garter,
                    and in the same year was appointed governor-general and commander-in-chief of
                    India. He landed at Calcutta, and assumed office in succession to Lord Minto in
                    October 1813. He was now fifty-nine years of age. One of the chief questions
                    which awaited him was that of relations with the Goorkha state of Nepaul. The
                    Goorkhas, a brave and warlike little nation, failing to extend their conquests
                    in the direction of China, had begun to encroach on territories held or
                    protected by the East India Company; especially they had seized the districts of
                    Bootwul and Seoraj, in the northern part of Oudh, and when called upon to
                    relinquish these, they deliberately elected (April 1814) to go to war rather
                    than do so. Lord Moira, having travelled through the northern provinces and
                    fully studied the question, declared war against Nepaul (November 1814). The
                    enemy’s frontier was 600 miles long, and Lord Moira, who directed the plan of
                    the campaign, resolved to act offensively along the whole line. It was an
                    anxious undertaking, because the native states of India were all watching the
                    issue and waiting for any serious reverse to the English to join against them.
                    At first all seemed to go badly, as the British officers too much despised the
                    enemy, and the Sepoys were unaccustomed to mountain warfare, and thus alternate
                    extremes of rashness and despondency were exhibited. But this rectified itself
                    in time, especially through the achievements of General (afterwards Sir David)
                    Ochterlony, who before the end of 1815 had taken all the Goorkha posts to the
                    west, and early in 1816 was advancing victoriously within 50 miles of Katmandoo,
                    the capital. The Goorkhas now made peace; they abandoned the disputed districts,
                    ceded some territory to the English, and agreed to receive a British resident.
                    Ever since they have faithfully kept these terms; the northern frontier of India
                    has been securely fixed, and the Goorkhas have entirely kept aloof from the
                    machinations of disaffected native states. For his masterly conduct of these
                    affairs Lord Moira was created Marquis of Hastings in 1816.</p>
                <p>He had now to deal with internal dangers. A treacherous combination of Mahratta
                    powers was constantly threatening the continuance of British rule, under the
                    guise of plausible assurances severally given by the peshwah, Sindia, Holkar,
                    and other princes. At the same time the existence of the Pindhâree state was not
                    only dangerous to the English, a3 being a warlike power always ready to turn
                    against them, but it was a scourge to India itself. In 1816, however, the
                    Pindhârees entered British territory in the Northern Circars, where they
                    destroyed 339 villages. On this, permission was obtained to act for their
                    suppression. Before the end of 1817 the preparations of Lord Hastings were
                    completed, when the peshwah suddenly broke into war, and the British were
                    opposed at once to the Mahratta and Pindhâree powers, estimated at 200,000 men
                    and 500 guns. “The whole was utterly shattered in a brief campaign<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For the interesting
                            details of this campaign, as well as of the war in Nepaul, see Prinsep’s
                                <hi rend="italic">History of the Political and Military Transactions
                                in India, during the administration of the Marquis of
                            Hastings.</hi></p></note> of four months (1817- 1818). The peshwah’s
                    dominion had been annexed, and those of Sindia, Holkar, and the rajah of Berar
                    lay at the mercy of the governor-general, and were saved only by his exceeding
                    and honourable moderation. There was at last, after sixty years from the battle
                    of Plassy, no question of the supremacy of British power in India, now more
                    perfectly established and more effectively dominant than that of
                        Aurungzebe.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Meadows
                            Taylor’s <hi rend="italic">Studentis</hi><hi rend="italic">Manual of the
                                History of India,</hi> p. 595.</p></note> The Pindhârees had ceased
                    to exist, and peace and security had been substituted for misery and terror.</p>
                <p>“It is a proud phrase to use,” said Lord Hastings,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Reply to Address of Inhabitants of
                            Calcutta; see <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Journal,</hi> February
                        1819.</p></note> “but it is a true one, that we have bestowed blessings upon
                    millions. Nothing can be more delightful than the reports I receive of the
                    sensibility manifested by the inhabitants to this change in their circumstances.
                    The smallest detachment of our troops cannot pass through that district without
                    meeting everywhere eager and exulting gratulations, the tone of which proves
                    them to come from glowing hearts. Multitudes of people have, even in this short
                    interval, come from the hills and fastnesses in which they had sought refuge for
                    years, and have reoccupied their ancient deserted villages. The ploughshare is
                    again in every quarter turning up a soil which had for many seasons never been
                    stirred, except by the hoofs of predatory cavalry.”</p>
                <p>While the natives of India appreciated the resulta of Lord Hastings’s
                    achievements, the court of directors grumbled at his having extended the British
                    territory. They also disliked and opposed his measures for introducing education
                    among the natives and his encouraging the freedom of the press. Posterity has,
                    however, vindicated the policy of Lord Hastings in all respects. In 1819 he
                    obtained the cession by purchase of the island of Singapore. In finance his
                    administration was very successful, as notwithstanding the expenses of his wars
                    he showed an annual surplus of two millions sterling. He laboured much at law
                    reform, and he succeeded in greatly raising t <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> e
                    status and character of the civil service of India. Lord and Lady Hastings by
                    their stately and yet genial manners, and by their warm encouragement of
                    literature and science, gave a high tone to the society of Calcutta. And he was
                    the first governor-general to exhibit a personal interest in the exertions of
                    the missionaries. Brilliant and beneficent as his career had been, Lord Hastings
                    did not escape, any more than Clive, Warren Hastings, or Lord Wellesley, the
                    assaults of unjust detraction. His last years of office were embittered by the
                    discussions on a matter very notorious <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n549/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0549-0518"/> at the time, namely, the affairs of the
                    banking-house of W. Palmer and Company. The whole affair was mixed up with
                    insinuations against Lord Hastings, especially charging him with having been
                    actuated by favouritism towards one of the partners in the firm. From
                    imputations which were inconsistent with his whole character he has subsequently
                    been exonerated. But while smarting under them he tendered his resignation in
                    1821, though he did not leave India till January 1823. He was much exhausted by
                    the arduous and almost incredible labours which for more than nine years he had
                    sustained. Among his characteristics it is mentioned that “his ample fortune
                    absolutely sank under the benevolence of his nature;” and, so far from having
                    enriched himself in the appointment of governorgeneral, he returned to England
                    in circumstances which obliged him still to seek public employment. In 1824 he
                    received the comparatively small post of governor of Malta, in which island he
                    introduced many reforms and endeared himself to the inhabitants. He died in
                    1826, leaving a request that his right hand should be cut off and preserved till
                    the death of the marchioness of Hastings, and then interred in her coffin.</p>
                <p>No “Life” of the marquis of Hastings has appeared, hut a diary of his first tours
                    in India, written for his children, has been published, and affords interesting
                    indications of his character. For further particulars of his career see the <hi
                        rend="italic">Asiatic Journal</hi> for November 1823, and the √innuαZ <hi
                        rend="italic">Biography and Obituary</hi> for 1828; and for details of his
                    Indian administration see Prinsep ’ s work cited above, Wilson’s continuation of
                    Mill’s <hi rend="italic">History of India,</hi> and other Indian histories. (A..
                    GR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
