<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0640-0607-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEBRIDES, The, or Western Isles of Scotland</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 607</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90227c">Rent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n640/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HEBRIDES, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi>, or <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Western Isles of Scotland</hi></label>, is a name sometimes
                    applied collectively to all the islands on the west ceast of Scotland, but
                    seldom including Bute, Arran, and the other islands situated in the Firth of
                    Clyde. The group is usually divided into the Outer Hebrides, or Long Island, and
                    the Inner Hebrides. The former division embraces the Lewis, Harris, North and
                    South Uist, Benbecula, Barra, and a number of small islands, the whole length of
                    this group from Barra-Head to the Butt of Lewis being about 130 miles. The Inner
                    Hebrides include Islay, Skye, Mull, Jura, Coll, Colonsay, Rum, Eigg, Tiree,
                    Lismore, and Ulva. The number of inhabited islands is over 100, and the
                    population is nearly 100,000. The principal islands are noticed under separate
                    headings. The outer range consists almost exclusively of gneiss rocks, with poor
                    soil and large proportions of peat and moor. The inner range is composed chiefly
                    of trap and slate. The scenery of the islands may be generally described as
                    partaking of the wild and sublime. Large masses of mountains of all forms tower
                    up in the interior; and the coasts, indented by arms of the sea, are rugged and
                    varied in outline. Spots of great beauty—green pastoral glens, sheltered bays
                    and lake3—are interspersed with the wildest scenes. The climate, though mild, is
                    humid and unsuitable for corn crops. Only a very small portion of the surface is
                    arable, the greater part being mountains, and the valleys intersecting them
                    narrow and frequently covered with peat moss. Much of the land has, however,
                    been converted into sheep walks, and the moors and desolate tracts are often let
                    at high rents to sportsmen. The development of the prosperity of the islands has
                    been greatly aided by the construction of excellent roads, and by the
                    establishment of various lines of steamers in connexion with Glasgow, thus
                    rendering the fine and in some respects unique scenery fully and easily
                    accessible to tourists. One of the principal sources of wealth is that of the
                    fisheries, Stornoway in the island of Lewis being the headquarters of that
                    industry on the western coast.</p>
                <p>The Hebrides are mentioned by Ptolemy under the name of <hi rend="superscript">
                    μ</hi> E∕3ouδαι and by Pliny under that of <hi rend="italic">Hebudes,</hi> the
                    modern spelling having, it is said, originated in an accidental misprint. By the
                    Norwegians they were called <hi rend="italic">Sudreyjar op</hi> Southern
                    Islands. The Latinized form was Sodorenses, preserved to modem times in the
                    title of the bishop of Sodor and Mam The original inhabitants of the Hebrides
                    seem to have been of the same Celtic race as those settled on the mainland—the
                    Scoto-Irish whom Columba about the middle of the 6th century converted to
                    Christianity. Scandinavian hordes then poured in with their northern idolatry
                    and lust of plunder, but in time they adopted the language and faith of the
                    islanders. Mention is made of incursions of the vikings on their shores as early
                    as 793, but the principal emigration took place towards the end of the 9th
                    century in the early part of the reign of Harold Haarfager, and consisted of
                    persons driven thither, as well as to Orkney and Shetland, to escape from his
                    tyrannous rule. Soon afterwards they began to make incursions against their
                    mother-country, and on this account King Harold fitted out an expedition against
                    them, and placed Orkney, Shetland, the Hebrides, and the Isle of Man under
                    Norwegian government. The chief seat of the Norwegian sovereignty was Colonsay.
                    About the year 1095 Godred Crovan, king of Dublin, of Man, and of the Hebrides,
                    died in Islay. His third son, Olaus or Olave, succeeded to the government about
                    1103, and the daughter of Olaus was married to Somerled or Sorlet of Argyle, who
                    became the founder of the dynasty known as Lords of the Isles. Many efforts were
                    made by the Scottish monarchs to displace the Norwegians. Alexander II. led a
                    fleet and army to the shores of Argyllshire in 1249, but he died in the island
                    of Kerrera. On the other hand King Haco, at once to restrain the independence of
                    his jarls and to keep in check the ambition of the Scottish kings, set sail in
                    1263 on a great expedition, which, however, ended disastrously. Magnus, son of
                    Haco, concluded in 1266 a peace with the Scots, renouncing all claim to the
                    Hebrides and other islands except Orkney and Shetland, and King Alexander agreed
                    to give him a sum of 4000 merks in four yearly payments. It was also stipulated
                    that Margaret, daughter of Alexander, should be betrothed to Eric, the son of
                    Magnus, a connexion long remembered and lamented in Scottish song and story.</p>
                <p>The race of Somerled continued to rule the islands, and from a younger son of the
                    same potentate sprang the lords of Lorn, who took the patronymic of Macdougall.
                    John Macdonald of Isle of Islay, who died about 1386, was the first to adopt the
                    title of “Lord of the Isles.” He was one of the most potent of the island
                    princes, and was married to a daughter of the Earl of Strathern, steward of
                    Scotland. His son, Donald of the Isles, was memorable for his rebellion in
                    support of his claim to the earldom of Ross, in which, however, he was
                    unsuccessful. Alexander, son of Donald, resumed the hereditary warfare against
                    the Scottish crown; and in 1462 a treaty was concluded between Alexander’s son
                    and successor John and King Edward IV. of England, by which John, his son Donald
                    Balloch, and his grandson John, became bound to assist King Edward and James,
                    earl of Douglas, in subduing the kingdom of Scotland. The alliance seems to have
                    led to no active operations, and the island king was adjudged to be a traitor to
                    his liege sovereign of Scotland. In the reign of James V. another John of Islay
                    resumed the title of “Lord of the Isles,” but was compelled to surrender the
                    dignity. The glory of the lordship of the isles— the insular sovereignty—had
                    departed. From the time of Brace the Campbells had been gaining the ascendency
                    in Argyll. The Macleans, Macnaughtons, Maclaehlans, Lamonts, and other ancient
                    races had sunk before this favourite family. The lordship of Lorn was wrested
                    from the Macdougalls by Brace, and their extensive possessions, with
                    Dunstaffnage Castle, bestowed on the king’s relative,- Stewart, and his
                    descendants, afterwards lords of Lorn. The Macdonalds of Sleat, the direct
                    representatives of Somerled, though driven from Islay and deprived of supreme
                    power by <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n641/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0641-0608"/> James V., still kept a sort of insular state in
                    Skye. There were also the Macdonalds of CTanranald and Glengarry (descendants of
                    Somerled), with the powerful houses of Macleod of Dunvegan and Macleod of
                    Harris, M ’ Neill of Barra and Maclean of Mull. Fierce sanguinary feuds
                    continued throughout the 16th and 17th centuries among these rival clans and
                    their dependent tribes, and the turbulent spirit was not subdued till a
                    comparatively recent period. James VI. made an abortive endeavour to colonize
                    Lewis. William III. and Queen Anne attempted to subsidize the chiefs in order to
                    preserve tranquillity, but the wars of Montrose and Dundee, and the Jacobite
                    insurrections of 1715 and 1745, showed how futile were all such efforts. It was
                    not till 1748, when a decisive blow was struck at the power of the chiefs by the
                    abolition of heritable jurisdictions, and the appointment of sheriffs in the
                    different districts, that the arts of peace and social improvement made way in
                    these remote regions.</p>
                <p>The change was great, and at first not unmixed with evil. A new system of
                    management and high rents were imposed, in consequence of which numbers of the
                    tacksmen, or large tenants, emigrated to America. The exodus continued for many
                    years. Sheep-farming on a large scale was next introduced, and the crofters were
                    thrust into villages or barιcn corners of the land. The consequence was that,
                    despite the numbers who entered the army or emigrated to Canada, the standard of
                    civilization sank lower, and the population multiplied in the islands. The
                    people came to subsist almost entirely on potatoes and herrings; and in 1846,
                    when the potato blight commenced its ravages, a scene of nearly universal
                    destitution ensued,—embracing, over the islands generally, 70 per cent, of the
                    population. Temporary relief was administered in the shape of employment on
                    roads and other works; and an emigration fund being raised, from 4000 to 5000 of
                    the people in the most crowded districts were removed to Australia.</p>
                <p>The principal books on the Hebrides are Martin’s <hi rend="italic">Description of
                    the Western Islands of Scotland,</hi> 1703; Pennant’s <hi rend="italic">Tour in
                    Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides,</hi> 1774; Sir Joseph Bank’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Contributions to Pennant's Tour·,</hi> Boswell’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tour to the Hebrides with Samuel Johnson, LL.D.·,</hi> Maccullocli’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Geological Account of the Hebrides,</hi> 1819; Hugh Miller’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Cruise of the Betsy</hi>; W. A. Smith’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lcwisiana, or Life in the Outer Hebrides,</hi> 1874. Their history under
                    Norwegian rule is given in the <hi rend="italic">Chronica Regum Mannion</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et Insularum,</hi> edited, with learned notes, from the MS. in the
                    British Museum by Professor P. A. Munch of Christiania, 1860.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
