<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0466-0445-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HANNIBAL (9th edition, volume 11, page 445)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204724">Missouri</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204323">Kansas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202705">Gambia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432109">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vk4z">Orientation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n466/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HANNIBAL</label>, a city of the United States, in Marion
                    county, Missouri, is situated on the west bank of the Mississippi river, 150
                    miles above St Louis. Owing to its position on the river and its extensive
                    railroad connexions, it has become a busy commercial town; and evidence of the
                    prosperity of many of its inhabitants is afforded by the number of fine
                    residences on the surrounding slopes. It possesses a city hall, a Roman Catholic
                    seminary, and a high school. The river is crossed by a splendid iron bridge,
                    which has provision both for ordinary and for railway traffic. The principal
                    shipping trade is in lumber with other parts of the State, as well as with
                    Kansas and Texas; but tobacco, pork, and flour are also extensively shipped. The
                    manufactories include foundries, car-works, machineshops, tobacco-works,
                    beef-curing establishments, and flourmills. In the neighbourhood there are
                    lime-works and coal-pits. The population, which in 18G0 was 6505, and in 1870
                    was 10,125, of whom 1616 were coloured and 1632 foreigners, is now (1880)
                    estimated at 15,000.</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> v</hi> HANNO (a very common Carthaginian name, Greek
                    Aιτωv), according to the title of the <hi rend="italic">Peripl·us</hi> that
                    passes under the name, was a king (basileus) of the Carthaginians who undertook
                    an exploring and colonizing expedition along the north-western coasts of Africa
                    beyond the Pillars of Hercules, and on his return inscribed a narrative of his
                    voyage in the temple of Saturn. There are no data to fix with any precision the
                    time at which he flourished, the most definite statement about the matter being
                    Pliny’s “Punicis rebus florentissimis.” Bougainville and Vivien de Saint Martin
                    are disposed to assign him to <hi rend="italic">circa</hi> 570 B.C.; Heeren,
                    Kluge, and others make him contemporary with a Hanno, father of Hamilcar (c. 510
                    B.c.); and Müller thinks he may be possibly identified with Hanno the son of
                    Hamilcar (c. 470 B.C.). According to the <hi rend="italic">Periplus,</hi> which
                    is the only detailed notice of the expedition that has come down to us, he
                    sailed with sixty galleys <hi rend="italic">(ρentecontoroi')</hi> and 30,000 (?)
                    men and women, and in the course of his voyage south founded the city of
                    Thymiaterium and settled colonies at Gytte, Aera, Melitta, Arambys, and in the
                    island of Cerne or Kerne. The terminus of the voyage was an island beyond a gulf
                    called the Noti Cornu, in which they found a number of “hairy women” whom the
                    interpreters named <hi rend="italic">gorillas.</hi></p>
                <p>The identification of the various points mentioned in the narrative has given
                    scope to abundant dissertation and conjecture, and the question as to the site
                    of the gorilla island, or southmost limit of the exploration, has been
                    discussed, with special interest. Bougainville and Dureau de la Malle maintain
                    that Hanno reached the Bight of Benin; Müller and Vivien de Saint Martin find
                    his <hi rend="italic">ultima Thule</hi> in the Gulf of Sherboro; Mannert decides
                    in favour of Bissagos, Heeren for the mouth of the Gambia, Malte Brun for the
                    Bay of Cintra, and Quatremère for the neighbourhood of the Senegal, while
                    Gosselin would go no further south than Cape Nun. But while authorities differ
                    so much in the matter of identification, almost all agree that the narrative is
                    one of the most remarkable records of early exploration that have been
                    preserved. “In its original form,” says Vivien de Saint Martin, “it was only a
                    commemorative inscription of barely a hundred lines, and yet in spite of this
                    extreme conciseness there is not one of its details, whether of localities or
                    distances, which is not rigorously conformable to the very accurate acquaintance
                    which we now have of these coasts.” In the 18th century Dodwell called tire
                    authenticity of the <hi rend="italic">Periplus</hi><hi rend="italic">va.</hi>
                    question, but it was considered that his arguments had been disposed of by
                    Falconer and others. Recently, however, Μ. Tauxier has renewed the attack,
                    maintaining that in reality we have nothing before us but “a compilation due to
                    an ignorant Greek of the 1st century B.c., brought to its present form by some
                    Christian of the time of Theodosius, probably a student to whom the task was
                    assigned of adapting the old <hi rend="italic">Periplus</hi> to the geographical
                    ideas of the day.”</p>
                <p>The editio princeps of the <hi rend="italic">Peι∙iρlus</hi> of Hanno issued from
                    the press of Frohenius at Basel in 1533 <hi rend="italic">(Άρριανοΰ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">τreρι∙7rXου^,κ.τ.X.', Avυωvοv 7repi∙πX0υ9</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Λιβύην,</hi> κ.τ.λ.). Of more recent editions it is enough to
                    mention that in Hudson’s <hi rend="italic">Geographice veteris
                        scriptores</hi><hi rend="italic">Graci nιinories,</hi> vol.i., Oxford, 1698,
                    with Dodwe∏ ’ s dissertations prefixed; Arnold Schmidt, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Arrians indische Merkwürdigkeiten und</hi><hi rend="italic">Hannons</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Seereise,</hi> Brunswick and Wolfenbüttel, 1764; Thomas
                    Falconer, <hi rend="italic">The Voyage of</hi><hi rend="italic">Hanno</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">translated . . . and defended against the objections of Mr
                        Dodwell,</hi> London, 1797: Kluge, <hi rend="italic">Hannonis
                        Navigatio,</hi> Leipsic, 1829; and Carl Müller, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geographi,Grad</hi><hi rend="italic">Minores,</hi> Paris, 1855. For further
                    details see Muller’s <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena;</hi> Bougainville in <hi
                        rend="italic">Acad, des Inscr. el Belles</hi><hi rend="italic">Lettres,</hi>
                    tome xxvi.; Vivien de Saint Martin, <hi rend="italic">Le Nord de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="italic">Afrique dans</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >V</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquité,</hi> Paris, 1863; Dr Judas in <hi
                        rend="italic">La Revue d'orient;</hi> and Μ. Tauxier in <hi rend="italic">La
                        Globe,</hi> Geneva, 1867, and <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de ΓAcad. des Jnscr.,</hi> Paris, 1875.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
