<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0390-0371-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAGUE, The (9th edition, volume 11, page 371)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n390/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAGUE, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label> (in Dutch, ’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Gravenhage</hi> or <hi rend="italic">den Haag;</hi> in
                    French, <hi rend="italic">La Haye</hi>; and in Modern Latin, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Haga</hi><hi rend="italic">Comitis),</hi> a town of the Netherlands, in the
                    province of South Holland, 13 miles N.W. of Rotterdam, 10 miles S.W. of Leyden,
                    and 2 miles inland from the German Ocean. It is connected<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n391/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0391-0372"/> with both Rotterdam and Leyden by the
                    “Holland Railway,” and with Utrecht by the railway of the Rhine. Besides being
                    the chief town of the province, the Hague is the usual residence of the court,
                    and the seat of the Government, the states-general, the high council of the
                    Netherlands, the council of state, the chamber of accounts, and various other
                    administrative bodies. The characteristics of the town are quite in keeping with
                    its political position. It is “the handsomest, the most fashionable, and the
                    most modern-looking” town in the Netherlands. D’Amicis rightly describes it in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Olanda</hi> as half Dutch half French, Broad and regular
                    streets, extensive avenues and drives, and spacious squares well planted with
                    trees, are the main features of its general plan; large and beautiful buildings
                    are numerous; and the population consists for the most part of Government
                    officials and members of the nobility, the army, and the navy. A good idea of
                    the place is obtained by passing along the Vijverberg or Fishpond Hill, which
                    takes its name from the large basin of water which it skirts, the Voorhout, and
                    the Willemspark, next through Java Street and Sumatra Street, and then the
                    Buitenhof or Outer Court, the Binnenhof or Inner Court, the Plein, the
                    Kneuterdijk, and the Groote Markt. Willemspark was laid out by King William II.,
                    and in 1869 it was chosen as the site of the national monument in memory of the
                    recovery of independence in 1813, executed by Waaijen, Pietersen, and Koelman.
                    The Plein, a square bordered with the offices of the various ministers and the
                    high council, is adorned with a statue of William I., the “father of his
                    people,” by Louis Royer; an equestrian statue of the same prince, by the count
                    of Nieuwerkerke, is placed in front of the royal palace; and there is a statue
                    of William II. by Georges in the Buitenhof.</p>
                <p>The centre of the Hague, both historically and topographically, is the buildings
                    of the court. The oldest portion was founded by Count William II., “king of the
                    Romans,” in 1249. A handsome Gothic building, with towers at each corner of the
                    façade, contains the great or knights’ hall, a noble chamber 130 feet in length,
                    62 feet in breadth, and 69 in height, in which the states of the Netherlands
                    abjured their allegiance to Philip II. of Spain, and in front of which the
                    greyheaded Olden-Barneveldt lost his life in 1619. To the south-east of the hall
                    is the troonzaal, or throne room, in which the second chamber of the
                    states-general holds its sittings; and to the west is the meeting-place of the
                    first chamber. The archives of the kingdom and several Government offices are in
                    the same range of buildings. The royal palace proper was purchased by the states
                    of the Netherlands in 1595, rebuilt by Prince William III., and extended by King
                    William I. The palace of the prince of Orange was founded about 1720 by Count
                    Unico William of Wassenaar Twiekels; the palace of Prince Frederick of the
                    Netherlands dates from 1825 to 1828; the palace of Prince Henry was erected in
                    1743 for the deputies of Rotterdam; and the palace of Prince Alexander was in
                    the 17th century the house of John de Witt, pensionary of the council. Among the
                    public institutions of the Hague, the following are the most important :—the
                    royal library, with upwards of 100,000 volumes, and a collection of manuscripts,
                    coins, and gems, erected between 1734 and 1738; the Museum
                    Meermanno-Westreenianum, comprising books, manuscripts, maps, plates, pictures,
                    antiquities, and curiosities; the royal picture gallery in the
                    Prins-Mauritz-Huis, which was founded in 1633 by Prince John Maurice of
                    Nassau-Siegen, governor of Brazil; the Vijverberg hôtel, with a collection of
                    curiosities; the town museum of antiquities and modern art; the zoological
                    gardens, founded in 1862; the royal school of design and music; and the new
                    buildings for the arts and sciences, erected in 1874. Of the fourteen churches
                    of the Hague five belong to the Dutch Reformed communion, six to the Roman
                    Catholics, and one to the Old Catholics; one is Episcopalian, one German
                    Evangelical, and two Apostolical. There are also two synagogues and one Greek
                    chapel. Architecturally the Groote Kerk, under the patronage of St James, is the
                    most note-λvorthy; it is 300 feet long by 154 broad, and has a lofty tower and
                    spire; in the interior are the sepulchral monuments of James Baron of Wassenaar
                    Obdam, a Dutch naval hero, of Gerrit of Assendelft, and of Philip, landgrave of
                    Hessen-Philipsthal. The Willemskerk was a present of William III. to the
                    Reformed community of the Hague.’</p>
                <p>The principal industries of the town are iron-casting, copper and lead smelting,
                    cannon-founding, the manufacture of furniture and carriages, silk-dyeing,
                    liqueur-distilling, lithographing, and printing. In 1622 the population of the
                    Hague was only 17,430; in 1732 it was estimated at 34,000; in 1796, inclusive of
                    the inhabitants of Scheveningen,—a watering-place now connected with the town by
                    a tramway line,—it was 41,266; in 1811, 42,150; in 1830, 56,105; in 1840,
                    58,521; and in 1850, 66,329. In 1860 it was 78,405, and in 1870, 91,328. At the
                    last date 52,600 belonged to the Dutch Reformed Church; 27,486 were Roman
                    Catholics, 3471 Dutch Jews, and 148 Portuguese Jews. In 1874 the total was
                    stated at 94,895.</p>
                <p>The Hague, mentioned as early as 1097 in a document by Count Floris II., seems
                    originally to have been a shooting lodge of the counts of Holland. Under William
                    II. it became a residence of the court; and in the 15th century it begins to be
                    called a town, though for long after, down even to the time of Louis Napoleon,
                    it was as frequently described as a village. In 1479 the soldiers of Maximilian
                    of Austria put the place to ransom; in 1525 it was the scene of the martyrdom of
                    Johannes Pistorius (Jan de Bakker of Woerd); in!528 it was plundered by the
                    people of Guelderland; and in 1572, 1573, and 1574 it was laid waste by the
                    Spaniards. Restored by William <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n392/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0392-0373"/> I. in 1576, it was in 1584 the seat of the
                    sessions of the States of Holland. Fosses were constructed round the town in
                    1620. In 1672 it was the scene of the famous assassination of the brothers De
                    Witt. It was at the Hague that the convention was arranged in 1710 between the
                    German emperor, the king of Prussia, the emperor of Russia, and the maritime
                    powers, for the maintenance of the neutrality of North Germany; it was at the
                    Hague that the Triple Alliance of 1717 was concluded, and that the peace of the
                    same year was signed between Spain, Savoy, and Austria. From 1782 to 1787 the
                    town had its full share in the civil disturbances of the country. In 1808 it was
                    made the seat of the Government administrative offices.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi><hi rend="italic">ou Nouvelle</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Description de la Haye,</hi> The Hague, 1785; <hi
                        rend="italic">Description</hi><hi rend="italic">succincte de la
                        ville</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Haye,</hi> The Hague, 1823; <hi
                        rend="italic">Aforgen-wandelingen door</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">in den omtrek van</hi><hi rend="italic">’s</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Gravenhage,</hi> The Hague, 1832; <hi rend="italic">Gezigten
                        van</hi><hi rend="italic">’s</hi><hi rend="italic">Gravenhagen,</hi>
                    Amsterdam, 1845; <hi rend="italic">Petit Guide de la Haye,</hi> The Hague, 1860;
                        <hi rend="italic">La Haye et</hi><hi rend="italic">Scheveningue
                        photographiis,</hi> The Hague, 1860.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
