<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0853-0816-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HILDESHEIM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 816</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4222r92r">Templars</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1152439">Tombs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1066737">Plate</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:976135">Interest</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n853/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HILDESHEIM</label>, the chief town of a district in the
                    province of Hanover, Prussia, is beautifully situated on the right bank of the
                    Innerste, 18 miles south-east of Hanover by railway. It has a very antique and
                    quaint appearance, and is surrounded by old ramparts which have been converted
                    into shady alleys and promenades. The streets are for the most part narrow and
                    irregular, and contain many old houses with overhanging upper stories and richly
                    and curiously adorned wooden façades. The town is the seat of a district
                    governorship, a high court of justice, two justice courts, a general
                    superintendency of the Evangelical Church, and a Roman Catholic chapter. The
                    Catholic cathedral, which occupies the site of a building founded by Louis the
                    Pious in 818, dates from the middle of the 11th century. It is chiefly
                    remarkable for the antiquities and notable works of art connected with it,
                    including the bronze doors executed by Bishop Bernward, with reliefs from the
                    history of Adam and Christ; the so-called Trmensäule, at one time believed to
                    have been erected, before it was transferred to its present site, in honour of
                    the Saxon idol Irmin, but now regarded as belonging to an old Roman aqueduct;
                    the Christ column by Bishop Bernward, adorned with reliefs from the history of
                    the Saviour; a brazen font of the 13th century, two candelabra of the 12th
                    century, the sarcophagus of St Godehard, the tomb of St Epiphanius, and an
                    immense number of minor articles of ecclesiastical furniture. The rose-bush on
                    the wall of the crypt is alleged to be a thousand years old. Among the other
                    churches those of special interest are St Godehard’s church, completed in 1172
                    and restored in 1863, a remarkably fine specimen of the Romanesque style, with
                    three massive pyramidal towers; the church of St Michael, an almost equally fine
                    specimen of Romanesque, founded by Bishop Bernward, and restored in 1186 after
                    injury by fire, containing a beautiful painted ceiling of the 12th century, and
                    the tomb and monument of Bishop Bernward; St Magdalene’s church, which possesses
                    various works in metal by Bishop Bernward; St Martin’s church, now used as a
                    museum and library; the Lutheran church of St Andrew, with very lofty towers;
                    and the fine columnar basilica of the abbey church of Moritzburg, a suburb half
                    a mile south-west of the town. The other principal buildings are the townhouse,
                    dating from the 15 th century, and containing the archives of the town; the
                    house in the late Gothic style said, but erroneously, to have been built by the
                    Knights Templars; the Michaelis monastery, now used as a lunatic asylum; and the
                    old Carthusian monastery. The educational establishments include a Catholic and
                    a Lutheran gymnasium, a Catholic normal school, a weaving school, and an
                    agricultural school. The other principal public institutions are the Georgstift
                    for daughters of state servants, the maternity hospital, two orphanages, and
                    several other hospitals and infirmaries. The town has iron foundries,
                    manufactures of cloth, damasks, linen fabrics, thread, sail-cloth, wadding,
                    leather, machines, carriages, stoves, glass, tobacco, alcohol, perfumeries,
                    chocolate, and starch. The population in 1875 was 22,581.</p>
                <p>Hildesheim, though previously in existence, owes its rise and prosperity to the
                    transference to it in 822 of the bishopric instituted by Charlemagne at Elze in
                    812. In the 10th century its importance was largely increased under Bishop
                    Bernward, who, if he did not introduce, greatly stimulated by his example and
                    patronage the art of working in metals, for which the town retained a high
                    reputation until the close of the Middle Ages. It also obtained considerable
                    fame by its cathedral school, at which several sons of the emperors received
                    their education. In 1241 it joined the Hanseatic League, and in 1249 received
                    town rights. It was frequently at feud with its bishops, and in the 14th century
                    placed itself more than once under the protection of the house of
                    Brunswick-Lüneburg. The bishops in the course of time had acquired considerable
                    territory, but their feuds with the neighbouring princes resulted in 1523 in the
                    annexation of a great part of their possessions to Brunswick. A restoration,
                    however, took place in 1643, and in the beginning of the present century the
                    principality amounted to 682 square miles. The last bishop of Hildesheim
                    possessed also the bishopric of Paderborn, acquired by his predecessor. Both
                    bishoprics were secularized and ceded to Prussia in 1803. In 1807 they were
                    incorporated with the kingdom of "Westphalia, but in 1813 they were restored to
                    Prussia, which ceded Hildesheim to Hanover, retaining only Paderborn. In 1866
                    the principality was united, along with Hanover, to Prussia.</p>
                <p>On October 9,1868, a unique collection of ancient plate was discovered on the
                    Galgenberg near Hildesheim, about 10 feet below the surface. This <hi
                    rend="italic">Hildesheimer Silberfund,</hi> as it is usually called, has excited
                    great interest among classical archaeologists, comprising, as it does, no less
                    than 60 pieces, or a complete service for three persons—plates, dishes,
                    mixing-bowls, &amp;c. The workmanship evidently "belongs to the Augustan age,
                    and by some authorities it is conjectured that we have nothing less than the
                    plate that belonged to Drusus, himself. The most noteworthy of the pieces are a
                    <hi rend="italic">crater</hi> richly ornamented with arabesques and figures of
                    children, a platter with a representation of Minerva, and others with a boy
                    Hercules, a Cybele, and a Deus Lunus. The whole collection is preserved in the
                    Berlin Museum. For details see Wieseler, <hi rend="italic">Der Hildesheimer
                    Silberfund,</hi> Bonn, 1868.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n854/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0854-0817"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
