<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0814-0777-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HESIOD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 777</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22m9r">Giants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03xx31">Shields</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:954573">Helicon</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1115918">Shields</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151519">Titanates</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n814/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HESIOD</label>, the father of didactic poetry in Greece, is
                    placed by Herodotus after Homer, but not more than 400 years before his own
                    epoch; and, though the settlement of the. question must depend on the internal
                    evidence of the Hesiodic poems, this testimony is corroborated by the Parian
                    marble and the historian Ephorus. He probably flourished about nine centuries
                    before Christ. His father had migrated from Cyme in Aeolia to Boeotia,
                    exchanging there a seafaring life for agriculture; and Hesiod and his brother, a
                    scapegrace named Perses, were born at Ascra, near the base of Helicon and under
                    the mountains which encircle Boeotia. Of this locality—whose claim to be his
                    birthplace was disputed by the city Orchomenus on the score of possession of his
                    relics—Hesiod’s description differs from that of modern topographers in
                    pronouncing the climate ungen ial, with alternations of excessive heat and cold;
                    but the poet’s prejudice may have been influenced by the injustice of Boeotian
                    law-courts, and it was at any rate here, as he fed his father’s flocks beside
                    Helicon, that he received his commission from the Muses to be their prophet and
                    poet—a commission which he recognized by dedicating to them an eared tripod won
                    by him in a contest of song at funeral games in Eubcea, and extant at Helicon in
                    the age of Pausanias <hi rend="italic">{Theog.,</hi> 20-34; Pausan., ix. 31, §
                    3). But to this call were linked, no doubt, literary antecedents in Aeolia, as
                    well as local associations of music and poetry in Hellas. His earliest poem, the
                    famous <hi rend="italic">Works and Days,</hi> embodies the experiences of his
                    life afield, and, interwoven with episodes of fable, allegory, and personal
                    history, forms a sort of Boeotian shepherd’s calendar. The first portion is an
                    ethical enforcement of honest labour and dissuasive of strife and idleness
                    (1-383); the second consists of hints and rules as to husbandry (384-764); and
                    the third is a religious calendar of the months, with remarks on the days most
                    lucky or the contrary for rural or nautical employments. The connecting link of
                    the whole poem is the author’s advice to his brother, who appears tb have bribed
                    the corrupt judges to deprive Hesiod of his already scantier inheritance, and to
                    whom, as he wasted his substance lounging in the agora, the poet more than once
                    returned good for evil, though he tells him there will be a limit to this
                    unmerited kindness. In the <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi> the episodes
                    which rise above an even didactic level are the “Creation and Equipment of
                    Pandora,” the “Five Ages of the World,” and the much-admired “Description of
                    Winter” (by some critics judged post-Hesiodic). It is in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Works and Days</hi> especially that we glean indications of Hesiod’s rank and
                    condition in life, that of a stay-athome farmer of the lower class, whose sole
                    experience of the sea was a single voyage of 40 yards across the Euripus, and an
                    old-fashioned bachelor whose misogynie views and prejudice against matrimony
                    have been conjecturally traced to his brother Perses having a wife as
                    extravagant as himself.</p>
                <p>The other poem attributed to Hesiod or his school which has come down in great
                    part to modern times is <hi rend="italic">The Theogony,</hi> a work of grander
                    scope, inspired alike by older traditions and abundant local associations. It
                    seems that no more congenial task could have suggested itself to the Ascraean
                    shepherd than to work into system, as none had essayed to do before, the
                    floating legends of the gods and goddesses and their offspring. This task
                    Herodotus attributes to him, and he is quoted by Plato in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Symposium</hi> (p. 178 B) as the author of the <hi rend="italic">Theogony.</hi>
                    The first to question his claim to this distinction was Pausanias, the
                    geographer (200 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.).</hi> The Alexandrian grammarians had
                    no doubt on the subject; and indications of the hand that wrote the <hi
                    rend="italic">Works and Days</hi> may be found in the severe strictures on
                    women, in the high esteem for the wealth-giveι Plutus, and in coincidences of
                    verbal expression. If, too, as commentators assert, the proper beginning of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi> is at verse 11—</p>
                <p>Oυκ &amp;ρα μoυvov èhv 'Ερίδων yévos, άλλ.’ ènl γαΐαν Είσι δύω, it is hard to
                    avoid the conclusion that the poet there corrects a statement made in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Theogony</hi> (225), where he had described Eris, the daughter of
                    Night, as one and indivisible. One thing is clear, that, as Mr Grote puts it, it
                    was the aim of Hesiod, or the member of his school who composed the <hi
                    rend="italic">Theogony,</hi> “to cast the divine functions into a systematic
                    sequence,”—so welding into intelligible coherence the generations and
                    genealogies of the deities of Hellas, whom Homer had dealt with in passing and
                    scattered notices only. The <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi> consists of three
                    divisions—(1) a cosmogony, or creation; (2) a theogony proper, recounting the
                    history of the dynasties of Zeus and Cronus; and (3) a brief and abruptly
                    terminated heroogony, or generation of heroes by immortal sires from mortd
                    mothers; the starting-point not improbably of the Hesiodic poem, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Eoiai,</hi> or “Catalogues of Women,” of which all but a few
                    fragments are lost. Prefaced by an account of the Muses’ visit to their bard,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n815/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0815-0778"/> proceeds, from the spontaneous generation of
                    Erebus and Night from Chaos, to detail a cosmogonic order at first corresponding
                    with the Mosaic. The first ruler of creation, Uranus, is disabled and dethroned
                    by Cronus, and Cronus in turn by his sixth son by Rhea, Zeus; but the
                    chronicling of Titans and Cyclopes, of Nereids and Oceanids, divine rivers and
                    water-nymphs, defies even the briefest enumeration. The poet has interwoven
                    several episodes of rare merit, such as the contest of Zeus and the Olympian
                    gods with the Titans, or the description of the prison-house in which the
                    vanquished Titans are confined, with the Giants for keepers and Day and Night
                    for janitors (735 <hi rend="italic">seqf).</hi> Notable also is the version of
                    the legend of Pandora given in the <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi> as compared
                    with that in the <hi rend="italic">Worlcs and Days.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theogony</hi> omits the part played in the earlier poem by Epimetheus in
                    accepting Pandora at Jove’s hands in spite of the counsel of Prometheus, as well
                    as the mention of the casket of evils from which in the <hi rend="italic">Worlcs
                    and Days</hi> Pandora lifts the lid with such woeful results.</p>
                <p>The only other approach to a poem of Hesiod is the so-called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shield of Hercules,</hi> a piece of patchwork with which interpolators have
                    done their worst. The opening verses are attributed by a nameless grammarian to
                    the fourth book of <hi rend="italic">Eoiai.</hi> The theme of the piece is the
                    expedition of Hercules and Iolaus against the robber Cycnus; but its main object
                    apparently is to describe the shield of Hercules (141-317). C. O. Müller deems
                    this description worthy of a place beside Homer’s shield of Achilles in <hi
                    rend="italic">II.</hi> xiii,, and recognizes in it the genuine spirit of the
                    Hesiodic school. Titles and fragments of other lost poems of Hesiod have come
                    down to us: didactic, as the <hi rend="italic">Maxims of Chiron</hi>;
                    généalogie, as the <hi rend="italic">Aegirnius</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and
                    mythic, as the <hi rend="italic">Marriage of Ceyx</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Descent of Theseus to Hades.</hi></p>
                <p>A strong characteristic of Hesiod’s style is his sententious and proverbial
                    philosophy (as in <hi rend="italic">Works and Days,</hi> 24-5, 40, 218, 345,
                    371). There is naturally less of this in the <hi rend="italic">Theogony,</hi>
                    yet there too not a few sentiments take the form of the saw or adage. With the
                    poet’s history, apart from the evidence of his poems, we have little
                    acquaintance. There is reason to suppose that in later life he removed from
                    Ascra to Orchomenus, where, according to Pausanias, were his sepulchre and
                    epitaph. Tradition has assigned a tragical ending to a life seemingly placid and
                    unemotional; but the story that he met a violent death near the Locrian Oeneon
                    in the territory of Naupactus, by reason of an intrigue with a sister of his
                    host, or a guilty knowledge of such intrigue, is probably valueless except as
                    evidence of the hero-worship of Hesiod in Locris and Boeotia <hi rend="italic"
                    >(cf.</hi> Friedel, <hi rend="italic">Die Sage vom</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Tode</hi><hi rend="italic">Hesiods,</hi> Leipsic, 1879). The poet will be
                    remembered as the first of didactic poets, the accredited systematizer of Greek
                    mythology, and the rough but not unpoetical sketcher of the lines on which
                    Virgil wrought out his exquisitely finished <hi rend="italic">Georgies.</hi></p>
                <p>Among the older editions of the Hesiodie poems may be mentioned those published
                    at Venice in 1495 and 1537, and those of Heinsius (Leyd. 1622), Schrevelius
                    (Leyd. 1650), Graevius (Amst. 1701), Robinson (Oxf. 1737); and among those of
                    modern date, Paley (Lond. 1861), Lehrs (Leips.. 1840, new ed. 1868), Schümann
                    (Berl. 1869), Kochly and Kinkel (Leip. 1870), Flach (Berl. 1874). The <hi
                    rend="italic">Works mid Days</hi> has been edited apart by Spohn (Leip. 1819),
                    Vollbehr (Kiel, 1844), Lennep (Amst. 1847); and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theogony</hi> by F. A. Wolf (Halle, 1783), Lennep (Amst. 1843), Schümann (Berl.
                    1869), and Flach (Berl. 1873). The <hi rend="italic">Fragments</hi> were
                    collected by Markscheffel (Leip. 1840). The many disputed questions associated
                    with the name of Hesiod have given rise to a vast critical and polemic
                    literature. In regard to the language of the poems the student may consult W.
                    Clemm, “Krit. Beiträge zur Lehre vom Digamma” in Curtius, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Studien,</hi> ix.; Dr H. Flach, <hi rend="italic">Das dialektische Digamma des
                    Hesiodos</hi> (Berl. 1876); Alois Rzach, <hi rend="italic">Der Dialekt
                    des</hi><hi rend="italic">Hesiodus</hi> (Leip. 1876). The composition and system
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi> have been investigated by Kock (Breslau,
                    1842), Gerhard (Berl. 1856), Wolcker (Elberf. 1865), Leitschuh (Wurzburg, 1867),
                    Schomann (Berl. 1868), Flach (Leip. 1874), Fritz Ehlung (Clausthal, 1875); and
                    special studies on the <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi> have been
                    contributed by Twesten (Kiel, 1815), Ranke (Gotting. 1838), Steitz (Leip. 1869),
                    Betke ^Münster, 1872), and Canna (Tur. 1874). Works of more general criticism
                    are Creuzer and Hermann, <hi rend="italic">Briefe</hi><hi rend="italic">uber
                    Homer</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">Hesiod</hi> (Heidelb.
                    1817); Thiersch, <hi rend="italic">Ucber die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gedichte</hi><hi rend="italic">des Hesiods</hi> (Munich, 1813); J. P. Mahaffy,
                    “Studies in Greek Literature” in <hi rend="italic">Hermathena,</hi> iv. The MSS.
                    are discussed by Flach, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">beiden
                    ältesten Handschriften des Hesiod</hi> (Leip. 1877); Kinkel, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ddcodic.</hi><hi rend="italic">Hesiodeis nonnullis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglia</hi><hi rend="italic">asservatis</hi> (Heidelb.
                    1866); Wrobel, “Uber eine neue Hesiodhand-schrift” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sitzungsber.</hi> of Vienna Academy, 1879. There are English translations of
                    the Hesiodie poems by Cooke (Lond. 1728), Elton (Lond. 1815), and Banks (Lond.
                    1856); German translations by J. H. Voss (Heidelb. 1806) and Uschner (Berl.
                    1865); French translations by Leconte de Lisle (Par. 1869) and Patin (Par.
                    1872-3); and Italian by Chiodi (Cosenza, 1867) and Pozzuolo (Milan, 1873). (J.
                    DA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
