<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0687-0654-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENNA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 654</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:955157">Henna</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:950358">Hair</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:994342">Lawsonia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:955321">Herbals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tq07">Hair</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vm0g">Beard</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w950r2g">Dyeing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n687/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENNA</label> is the Persian name for a small shrub found in
                    the East Indies, Persia, the Levant, and along the African coasts of the
                    Mediterranean, where it is frequently cultivated. It is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lawsonia alba</hi> of botanists, and from the fact that young trees are
                    spineless, while older ones have the branchlets hardened into spines, it has
                    also received the names of <hi rend="italic">Lawsonia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >inermis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">L.</hi><hi rend="italic">spinosa.</hi> It
                    forms a slender shrubby plant of from 8 to 10 feet high, furnished with opposite
                    oval-lanceshaped smooth leaves, which are entire at the margins, and bears small
                    white four-petalled sweet-scented flowers disposed in panicles. The four
                    spreading petals are obovate, and furnished with claws; and alternating with
                    them are eight stamens approximating by pairs. Its Egyptian name is <hi
                    rend="italic">Khenna,</hi> its Arabic name <hi rend="italic">Al Khanna,</hi> its
                    Indian name <hi rend="italic">Mendee,</hi> while in England it is called <hi
                    rend="italic">Egyptian privet,</hi> and in the West Indies, where it is
                    naturalized, <hi rend="italic">Jamaica mignonette.</hi></p>
                <p>Henna or Henné is of ancient repute as a cosmetic. This consists of the leaves of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Lawsonia</hi> powdered and made up into a paste; this is
                    employed by the Egyptian women, and also by the Mahometan women in India, to dye
                    their finger nails and other parts of their hands and feet of an orange-red
                    colour, which is considered to add to their beauty. The colour lasts for three
                    or four weeks, when it requires to be renewed. It is moreover used for dyeing
                    the hair and beard, and even the manes of horses; and the same material is
                    employed for dyeing skins and moroccoleather a reddish-yellow, but it contains
                    no tannin. The practice of dyeing the nails was common amongst the Egyptians,
                    and not to conform to it would have been considered indecent. It has descended
                    from very remote ages, as Ï3 proved by the evidence afforded by Egyptian
                    mummies, the nails of which are most commouly stained of a reddish hue. Henna is
                    also said to have been held in repute amongst the Hebrews, being considered to
                    be the plant referred to as camphire in the Bible (Song of Solomon i. 14; iv,
                    13). “The custom of dyeing the nails and palms of the hands and soles of the
                    feet of an iron-rust colour with henna,” observes Dr Royle, “exists throughout
                    the East from the Mediterranean to the Ganges, as well as in Northern Africa. In
                    some parts the practice is not confined to women and children, but is also
                    followed by men, especially in Persia. In dyeing the beard, the hair is turned
                    to red by this application, which is then changed to black by a preparation of
                    indigo. In dyeing the hair of children, and the tails and manes of horses and
                    asses, the process is allowed to stop at the red colour which the henna
                    produces.” Mahomet, it is said, used henna as a dye for his beard, and the
                    fashion was adopted by the caliphs. “The use of henna,” remarks Lady Callcott in
                    her <hi rend="italic">Scripture Herbal,</hi> “is scarcely to be called a caprice
                    in the East. There is a quality in the drug which gently restrains perspiration
                    in the hands and feet, and produces an agreeable coolness equally conducive to
                    health and comfort.” She further suggests that if the Jewish women were not in
                    the habit of using this dye before the time of Solomon, it might probably have
                    been introduced amongst them by his wife, the daughter of Pharaoh, and traces to
                    this probability the allusion to “camphire” in the passages in Canticles above
                    referred to.</p>
                <p>The preparation of henna consists in reducing the leaves and young twigs to a
                    fine powder, catechu or lucerne leaves in a pulverized state being sometimes
                    mixed with them. When required for use, the.powder is made into a pasty mass
                    with hot water, and is then spread upon the part to be dyed, where it is
                    generally allowed to remain for one night.</p>
                <p>It has been already noted that the flowers of the <hi rend="italic">Lawsonia</hi>
                    are very fragrant, whence they derive in the West Indies the name of Jamaica
                    mignonette. According to Lady Callcott, they are often used by the eastern women
                    to adorn their hair; and Mr Simmonds states that the distilled water from the
                    flowers is used as a perfume. The plant is further credited with the possession
                    of vulnerary and astringent properties.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
