<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0538-0507-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARZ MOUNTAINS, The (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    507)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0721x">Archives</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150508">Thuringians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814030">Archives</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n538/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARZ MOUNTAINS, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label> (also
                    spelt <hi rend="smallcaps">Hartz,</hi> the German <hi rend="italic"
                        >Harzgebirge,</hi> and the ancient <hi rend="italic">Silva Hercynia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">∖</hi> the most northerly mountain-system of Germany, situated
                    between the rivers Weser and Elbe, occupy an area of about 786 square miles, of
                    which 457 belong to Prussia, 286 to Brunswick, and 43 to Anhalt. Their greatest
                    length extends in a S.E. and N.W. direction for about 56 miles, and their
                    maximum breadth is about 20 miles. The group is made up of an irregular series
                    of terraced plateaus, rising here and there into rounded summits, and
                    intersected in various directions by narrow, deep valleys. The N.W. and higher
                    part of the mass is called the Ober or Upper Harz; the S.E. and more extensive
                    part, the Unter or Lower Harz; while the N.W. and S.W. slopes of the Upper Harz
                    form the Vorharz. The Brocken group, which divides the Upper and Lower Harz, is
                    generally regarded as a part of the former. The prevalent upper geological
                    formation of the whole disttict is greywacke and clay-slate, through which the
                    granite here and there protrudes, as in the case of the Brocken. The highest
                    summits of the Upper Harz are the Brocken (3743 feet), the Heinrichshöhe (3402
                    feet), the Greater and Less Königsberg (3376 feet and 3369 feet), and the
                    Wormberg (3182 feet); the Lower Harz, the Auersberg (1870 feet), and the
                    Victorshöhe (1762 feet). The towns in the district, though not large, are
                    tolerably numerous. The principal are—in the Upper Harz, Goslar, Klausthal,
                    Zellerfeld, Andreasberg, Altenau, Lautenthal, Wildemann, Grund, Harzburg,
                    Ilsenburg, and Wernigerode; and in the Lower Harz, Harzgerode, Elbingerode,
                    Rübeland, Quedlinburg, Ballenstedt, Gernrode, Suderode, Blankenburg, Thaïe, and
                    Stolberg.</p>
                <p>The chief industry is mining, which has been carried on since the middle of the
                    10th century. The Harz is second only to the Erzgebirge among the mountains of
                    Germany in mineral wealth. The most important mineral is a peculiarly rich
                    argentiferous lead, but gold in small quantities, copper, iron, sulphur, alum,
                    and arsenic are also found. Marble, granite, and gypsum are worked; and large
                    quantities of vitriol are manufactured. The vast forests that cover the mountain
                    slopes supply the materials for a very considerable trade in timber. Much wood
                    is exported for building and other purposes, while in the Harz itself no other
                    fuel is used, whether for smelting the ores, which is done at the mines, or for
                    domestic use. Employment is thus given to a large number of charcoal burners.
                    The saw-dust of the numerous wood-factories is collected for use in the
                    manufacture of paper. Turf-cutting, coarse lace-making, and the breeding of
                    canaries and native song-birds also occupy many of the people. Agriculture is
                    carried on chiefly on the plateaus of the Lower Harz; but there is excellent
                    pasturage both in the north and in the south. In the Lower Harz, as in
                    Switzerland, the cows, which carry bells harmoniously tuned, are driven up into
                    the heights in early summer, returning to the sheltered regions in late
                    autumn.</p>
                <p>The Harz being the first obstacle to oppose the moist, cold winds from the North
                    Sea, the northern summits are destitute of trees, but the lower slopes of the
                    Upper Harz are heavily wooded with pines and firs. Between the forests of these
                    stretch numerous peat-mosses, which contain in their spongy reservoirs the
                    sources of many small streams. On the Brocken are found one or two arctic and
                    several alpine plants. In the Lower Harz the forests contain a great variety of
                    timber. The oak, elm, and birch are common, while the beech especially attains
                    an unusual size and beauty. The walnut-tree grows in the eastern districts.</p>
                <p>The last bear was killed in the Harz in 1705, and the last lynx in 1817, and
                    since that time the wolf too has become extinct; but deer, foxes, wild cats, and
                    badgers are still to be found in the forests.</p>
                <p>The streams are very numerous, but are all small. While they are rendered
                    extensively useful, by various skilful artifices, in working the mines
                    underground, at other parts of their course they present the most picturesque
                    scenery in all the picturesque Harz. Perhaps the finest valley is the rocky
                    Bodethal, with the Ross-Trappe, the Hexentanz-platz, the Baumannshöhle, and the
                    Bielshöhle.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants, about 70,000 in number, are descended from various stocks. The
                    Upper and Lower Saxon, the Thuringian, and the Frankish races have all
                    contributed to form the present people, and their respective influences are
                    still to be traced in the varieties of dialect. The boundary line between High
                    and Low German passes through the Harz.</p>
                <p>The Harz is now one of the most frequented tourist resorts of Germany. It is
                    traversed by excellent roads in all directions, and is completely girt by
                    railways from the principal towns of the empire. The chief point of interest is
                    undoubtedly the Brocken or Blocksberg, famous as the scene of the
                    “Walpurgisnacht” in Goethe’s <hi rend="italic">Faust,</hi> as well as for the
                    atmospherical phenomena of which the “spectre of the Brocken” (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Halo)</hi> is the best known. The Harz was the last
                    stronghold of paganism in Germany, and to that fact are due the weird legends,
                    in which no district is <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n539/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0539-0508"/> richer, ani the wild and fanciful names that
                    are given by the people to the peculiar objects and appearances of nature.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> A very full list of works on the Harz,
                    especially on the Blöcken, will be found appended to the pamphlet <hi
                        rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der Brockenreisen,</hi> 4th ed., Aschersleben
                    and Leipsic, 1375. See also Holzmann, <hi rend="italic">Hercynischcs</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Archiv,</hi> Halle, 1803; Honemann, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Alterthümer des Harzes,</hi> Klausthal, 1827;
                    Zimmerman, <hi rend="italic">Harzgebirge,</hi> Darmstadt, 1834; Hoffmann, <hi
                        rend="italic">Burgen und Burgfesten des Harzes,</hi> Quedlinburg, 1836;
                    Hausmann, <hi rend="italic">Ueber die</hi><hi rend="italic">Bildung des
                        Harzgebirges,</hi> Gottingen, 1842; <hi rend="italic">Brockenstammbuch,</hi>
                    1850; Brederlow, <hi rend="italic">Der Harz, zur Belehrung sind
                        Unterhaltung</hi><hi rend="italic">fur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Harzreisende,</hi> Brunswick, 1851; Lachmann, <hi rend="italic">Nivellement
                        des Harzgebirges,</hi> Brunswick, 1851; Spieker, <hi rend="italic">Der Harz,
                        seine Ruinen und Sagen,</hi> Berlin, 1852 and 1856; Ey, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Harzbuch,</hi> Goslar, 1855: Pröhle, <hi rend="italic">Harzsagen,</hi>
                    1854; <hi rend="italic">Harzbilder,</hi> 1856; <hi rend="italic">Harz und
                        Kyffhäusf in Gedichten, Schilderimgen,</hi> &amp;c., 1870, and <hi
                        rend="italic">Der Harz,</hi> 1878; <hi rend="italic">Wegweiser im Harz und
                        dessen Umgegend,</hi> Berlin, 1857; Nauenburg, <hi rend="italic">Der
                        Lustwanderer im Harz,</hi> Eisleben, 1857; Mrs Burton, <hi rend="italic">Our
                        Summer in</hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic">Harz Forest,</hi>
                    Edinburgh, 1865; Groddeck, <hi rend="italic">Abriss der Geognosie des
                        Harzes,</hi> Klausthal, 1871; Hampe, <hi rend="italic">Flora</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Hercynia,</hi> Halle, 1873; Blackburn, <hi rend="italic"
                        >The</hi><hi rend="italic">Harz Mountains,</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Tour,</hi> London, 1873; Buch <hi rend="italic">{Gesammelte
                        Schriften),</hi> “Ueber den Harz,” 1877; Rev. J. S. Hill and J. W. Tanley,
                    in <hi rend="italic">Colliery</hi><hi rend="italic">Guardian,</hi> vol. xxx.;
                    Heine, <hi rend="italic">Harzreise.</hi> Among the Handbooks may be noted those
                    of Schweizer, Werner, Gottschalk, Meyer, Muller, Prediger, and Grieben.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
