<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0444-0425-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAMMER (9th edition, volume 11, page 425)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:950782">Hammers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064861">Pistons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:810947">Anvils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1011191">Mass</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918096">Exhibitionism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xs40">Pistons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s24s">Mass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h12b">Tools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n444/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAMMER</label>. This well-known tool stands quite without
                    rival for producing the numberless effects which are due to the remarkable force
                    of “impact.” Of all the array of hand tools in use in the industrial arts it is
                    undoubtedly the one that could least be dispensed with, and so it must have been
                    from the very earliest days of handicraft. A hammer of some rude kind must have
                    been as essential to the shaping of an arrow-head out of a flint, as is its
                    modern representative to the forging of a bayonet out of a bar of steel.</p>
                <p>Hammer3 to be used by hand are made of an endless variety of shapes, and of
                    weights varying from a small fraction of an ounce to 23 or 30 B⅛. Of the various
                    types now in use the differences are mainly due to the special requirements of
                    the particular trades for which they are intended, but partly also to individual
                    fancy. A few examples are given in fig. 1— <hi rend="italic">a</hi> being the
                    ordinary carpenter’s hammer with a cross pane, δ a claw hammer, <hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi> an engineer’s, and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> a
                    shoemaker’s hammer, which last has apparently retained its form for many
                    generations. The same may also be said of the two others in the woodcut, which
                    are good examples of the roughness of the instruments with which results of
                    almost incredible delicacy can be produced. Of these <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is
                    a favourite hammer used in the workshops of a London firm of goldbeaters, with
                    which, together with others not less rude in appearance, gold is hammered out
                    into leaves of such exceeding thinness that 250,000 are required to make up the
                    thickness of an inch. Extraordinarily ill-shaped as ∕, the file-cutter’s hammer,
                    looks, yet with this and a simple chisel the teeth of files are cut by hand with
                    a precision with which no machinery has as yet been able to compete, at least in
                    England.</p>
                <p>Hanl-hammers and sledge-hammers being rigidly limited as to weight by the
                    trifling power which one man—or at most two men—can bring to bear upon them, it
                    long ago became obviously desirable to obtain the force of impact from some more
                    powerful source than human muscles, so that the weight of hammer heads might be
                    largely increased and their blows made proportionately more effective. The first
                    step taken in this direction seems to have been the introduction of the
                    “Hercules,” a ponderous mass of. iron attached to a vertical guide rod, which
                    was lifted originally by a gang of men with ropes, but afterwards by steam
                    power, and allowed to fall by its own weight. This was. a fairly efficient tool
                    for forging large anchors and for similar purposes, the strength of the blow and
                    the point at which it was delivered being easily regulated. But as the demand
                    for wrought iron increased, the necessity for more rapid as well as more
                    powerful hammers to aid in its manu facture increased also. The lift or helve
                    hammer (fig. 2) and the tilt hammer (fig. 3) thus came into use, and under these
                    forms hammers may be said to have ranked for the first time as true machine
                    tools. Each of these consists of a heavy head attached to a beam mounted on
                    gudgeons, which is lifted at regular intervals by suitable cams or pins carried
                    by a revolving shaft driven by steam or other power, their chief points of
                    difference being the relative position of the gudgeons and the portion of the
                    beam at which the power is applied, as shown in the diagrams. Heavy blows are
                    thus obtained with the one, and lighter but much more rapid blows with the
                    other, both, however, invariable in their intensity, the lift being always to
                    one fixed height.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n445/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0445-0426"/>
                <p>In the steam hammer (fig. 4), which was first patented by Nasmyth in the year
                    1842, this objection is completely obviated. By the simple device of attaching
                    the hammer head to the lower end of the rod of a piston working in an inverted
                    steam cylinder, he produced a machine capable of being made to deliver its blows
                    with a force to which no limit has yet been found, and yet so perfectly under
                    control as to be able to crack a hazel nut without injuring the kernel. To the
                    introduction of this invaluable tool is due more than to any other single cause
                    the power which we now possess of producing the forgings in iron and steel which
                    are demanded by the arts of modern times; and in one or other of its many forms
                    it is now to be met with in every workshop in which heavy work is carried on.
                    Many modifications of the Nasmyth steam hammer have been introduced. In one of
                    these steam pressure has been applied above the piston to intensify the blow, it
                    being only used in the original form for lifting the “tup” and piston and for
                    regulating their descent. In another the piston and piston-rod have been
                    attached to the framing, and the cylinder made movable, its weight being thu3
                    added to that of the hammer.</p>
                <p>Duplex hammers differ materially from the ordinary steam hammer, inasmuch as no
                    anvil is necessary,—two hammer heads of equal weight (and for some purposes they
                    weigh only a few pounds, for others as much as 30 tons) being made to deliver
                    horizontal blows of equal force simultaneously on opposite sides of the forging,
                    which thus receive perfectly equal treatment. The importance of this may be
                    gathered from the fact that every increase in the weight of the vertical steam
                    hammer necessitates a very much larger increase in the weight and solidity of
                    the anvil which is necessary to afford the requisite inertia for resisting the
                    blow. For instance, the anvil of a 40-ton hammer now in use at Woolwich Arsenal
                    weighs upwards of 160 tons, and has nearly 500 tons of iron in its foundation,
                    whereas the anvil of an 80-ton hammer of which a full-sized model was amongst
                    the most striking objects at the Paris Exhibition of 1878, is of no less than
                    720 tons weight.</p>
                <p>The recent growth of steam hammers to the enormous size just mentioned is due
                    chiefly to the large dimensions, independently of the mere weight, of the
                    forgings which have now to be made for heavy ordnance and for other purposes. As
                    long as the thickness of a forging is moderate, the reaction of the anvil acting
                    upon, its under side has an effect not greatly inferior to that of the hammer on
                    the upper side. But with every increase in thickness some of this reaction is
                    lost and the effect of the blow is more and more confined to the outer portions
                    of the mass, which thus receive more than their share of treatment at the
                    expense of the central portions. On this account the difficulty of obtaining
                    thick forgings thoroughly sound throughout their substance is very great, and it
                    seems as if we had now reached the limit beyond which the hammer cannot be
                    advantageously applied for their production.. It has been found indeed in the
                    case of large shafts that dispensing altogether with the central portion, thus
                    making them tubular instead of solid, is accompanied by an increase in their
                    strength, owing to the possibility of thus forging the metal uniformly
                    throughout. But a much more widely applicable remedy, and one which will
                    doubtless come into general use for heavy work, is the substitution of hydraulic
                    or other pressure for the force of impact, a system which has lately been
                    employed by Sir Joseph Whitworth with wonderfully good results. The reason of
                    the superiority of its effect seems to be mainly this, that a certain amount of
                    time is essential for completing the “flow” of the metal which it is the object
                    of forging to induce. Under continuous pressure this flow can take place
                    uniformly throughout the mass, whereas the instantaneous blow of the hammer,
                    though it acts violently on the surface particles, and to a decreasing extent on
                    the adjacent ones, is entirely expended before the action has had time to reach
                    those at the centre, so that unequal density and consequent weakness is the
                    result. For massive forgings therefore the old saying can be no longer accepted
                    that “there is.no machine like a hammer.” (c. p. <hi rend="smallcaps">b.
                        s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
