<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0515-0484-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAROLD III</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 484</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1076505">Princesses</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1103513">Sailing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n86">Sails</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n515/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAROLD III</label>., surnamed Stern in Council (Harald
                    Haardraade or Hardrada), son of Jarl Sigurd, half-brother of King Olaf the Holy,
                    and descended by his father from Harold I., was one of the most distinguished
                    warriors among the old Norse kings. About his fifteenth year he made his escape
                    wounded from the battle of Stiklestad (1030), where his half-brother Olaf was
                    killed; and after staying till he was cured of his wounds with a “bonde” in a
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n516/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0516-0485"/> forest, he made his way to Sweden, whence after
                    the winter wa3 over he went to Russia, where he was kiudly received by King
                    Yaroslaf of Novgorod. He remained in Russia for several years, but, being
                    refused the hand of a Russian princess, he betook himself with several
                    companions to’ Constantinople, and became chief commander of the famous
                    Byzantine life-guards known as Varangians, and consisting almost wholly of
                    Norsemen. At the head of these warriors he gained many victories over the
                    Saracens in Sicily and Italy. It is even said that in a crusade against the
                    infidels he penetrated as far as Jerusalem, but most probably if he entered that
                    city it was in the peaceful character of a pilgrim. Returning after his exploits
                    to Constantinople, he was refused the hand of a niece of the empress Zoe,
                    because, according to the legend, the empress herself was enamoured of him; and
                    offended at the refusal he one night made his escape with two galleys, carrying
                    with him all his treasures, and also it is said the princess whose hand had been
                    denied him, whom, however, he put on shore after he had passed the Bosphorus,
                    with a message to the empress that, if lie had so willed, her power would have
                    been vain against his strategy aud skill. He now set sail for Russia, where he
                    was warmly welcomed by King Yaroslaf; and as he was now a man of great fame and
                    wealth Yaroslaf gave him in marriage his daughter Ellisof or Elizabeth, whose
                    hand he had formerly asked in vain. Soon after his marriage he resolved to
                    return home and if possible to win the crown of Norway from his nephew Magnus
                    the Good. With that purpose he about the year 1045 came to an agreement with his
                    relative Swend of Denmark, who had been driven by Magnus into exile in Sweden;
                    but Magnus, having obtained news of the intended joint expedition against him,
                    entered into communication with Harold, and agreed to share with him the
                    government of Norway, each ruling over a separate division. They now turned
                    their united forces against Swend, drove him from Denmark, and completely
                    prostrated his power; but just when he had resolved finally in despair to give
                    up the contest, Magnus about the year 1047 took suddenly ill and died,
                    bequeathing on his death-bed the whole of Norway to Harold and Denmark to Swend.
                    Such a bequest did not however coincide with the desires of Harold, and between
                    him and Swend a constant warfare raged for several years, until in 1064 they
                    agreed to a peace by which each retained his dominions according to the old
                    established boundaries. The chief motive of Harold in consenting to this
                    arrangement was probably that he might be free to embark on a purpose of wider
                    ambition, namely, to revive in his own person the old Scandinavian sovereignty
                    of England which had ended with the death of Hardicanute. The story goes that he
                    was instigated to the enterprise by a visit from Tostig, the exiled earl of
                    Northumbria; but whether that be so or not, he in 1066 set sail for England with
                    an immense fleet, which carried his wife Ellisof, his son Olaf, his treasures,
                    and more than half of all his fighting men. After touching at Orkney, where he
                    left his wife, he proceeded southwards to the Tyne, and was there joined by
                    Tostig and by a contingent of troops from Malcolm of Scotland. From the Tyne
                    they sailed southwards along the coast of Yorkshire, stopping at intervals to
                    ravage the country for provisions, and after proceeding up the Humber cast
                    anchor on the left bank of the Ouse near the village of Riccall. Leaving a
                    detachment under his son Olaf to guard the fleet, Harold along with Tostig.
                    marched with a great force towards York, and, defeating the Northumbrians with
                    heavy loss at Fulford on September 20th, received the surrender of the city on
                    September 24th. Meanwhile Harold of England, having heard of the Norse invasion,
                    was marching northwards from London day and night with an immense army; and
                    passing through York on the day after its surrender, he appeared suddenly on the
                    afternoon before the Norsemen encamped at Stamfordbridge. Taken by surprise, the
                    Norsemen fought nevertheless with stubborn courage and fierce energy, but though
                    the battle was for some time doubtful it ended at nightfall in their total
                    overthrow, with a slaughter so enormous that the great majority of them lay dead
                    upon the field. Tostig was slain and also Harold Hardrada himself, who, towering
                    head and shoulders above all his warriors, was inflicting death on all who dared
                    to meet him, till struck by an arrow in the windpipe he received the wound which
                    laid him low. According to some writers his body ultimately found burial in
                    Norway.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
