<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0798-0763-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERRICK, Robert</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 763</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1076612">Printing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1090554">Readers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:963520">Humanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:963588">Humanities</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x362">Printing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qv84">Wakefulness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tb36">Humanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d87m">Humanities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n798/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERRICK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>
                    (1591-1674), English poet, was born in Cheapside, London, and baptized on the
                    24th of August 1591. He was the seventh child of Nicholas Herrick, goldsmith, of
                    the city of London, who died in 1592, under suspicion of suicide. The children w
                    ere brought up by their uncle, Sir William Herrick, one of the richest
                    goldsmiths of the day, to whom in 1607 Robert was bound apprentice. In 1613 he
                    proceeded to Cambridge; and it was no doubt between these dates that the young
                    poet was introduced to that circle of wits which he <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n799/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0799-0764"/> was afterwards to adorn. He seems to have been
                    present at the first performance of <hi rend="italic">The Alchemist</hi> in
                    1610, and it was probably about this time that Ben Jonson adopted him as his
                    poetical “son.” He entered the university as fellow-commoner of St John’s
                    College, and he remained there until, in 1616, upon taking his degree, he
                    removed to Trinity Hall; in 1620 he became master of arts. From this date until
                    1629 we entirely lose sight of him; it has been variously conjectured that he
                    spent these nine years preparing for the ministry at Cambridge, or in much
                    looser pursuits in London. In the latter year his mother died, and, taking
                    orders, he was presented to the rural living of Dean Prior, not far from Totnes
                    in Devonshire. He entered upon this new career on October 2, 1629, being in his
                    thirtyninth year. At Dean Prior he resided quietly until 1648, when he was
                    ejected by the Puritans. The solitude there oppressed him at first; the village
                    was dull and remote, and he felt very bitterly that he was cut off from all
                    literary and social associations; but soon the quiet existence in Devonshire
                    soothed and delighted him. He was pleased with the rural and semi-pagan customs
                    that survived in the village, and in some of his most charming verses he has
                    immortalized the morris-dances, wakes, and quintains, the Christmas mummersand
                    the Twelfth Nightrevellings, that diversified the quiet of Dean Prior. Herrick
                    never married, but lived at the vicarage surrounded by a happy family of pets,
                    and tended by an excellent old servant named Prudence Baldwin. His first
                    appearance in print was in some verses lie contributed to <hi rend="italic">A
                    Description of the King and Queen of Fairies,</hi> in 1635. In 1640 a volume of
                    <hi rend="italic">Wit’s Recreations</hi> contained sixty-two small poems
                    afterwards acknowledged by Herrick in the <hi rend="italic">Hesperides,</hi> and
                    one not reprinted until our own day. These partial appearances make it probable
                    that he visited. London from time to time. We have few hints of his life as a
                    clergyman. Anthony Wood says that Herrick’s sermons were florid and witty, and
                    that he was “beloved by the neighbouring gentry.” A very aged woman, one Dorothy
                    King, stated that the poet once threw his sermon at his congregation, cursing
                    them for their inattention. The same old woman recollected his favourite pig,
                    which he taught to drink out of a tankard. In 1648 he published his celebrated
                    collection of lyrical poems, entitled <hi rend="italic">Hesp&gt;erides, or the
                    Works both Human and Divine of Robert Herrick,</hi> only a few weeks, it would
                    seem, after his ejection from his living by the Puritans. That he was reduced to
                    great poverty in London has been stated, but Dr Grosart shows this to be very
                    unlikely. In August 1662 Herrick returned to Dean Prior, supplanting his own
                    supplanter, Dr John Syms. He died in his eightyfourth year, and was buried at
                    Dean Prior, October 15, 1674. A monument was erected to his memory in the parish
                    church in 1857.</p>
                <p>As a pastoral lyrist Herrick stands first among English poets. His genius is
                    limited in scope, and comparatively unambitious, but in its own field it is
                    unrivalled. His tiny poems—and of the thirteen hundred that he has left behind
                    him not one is long—are like jewels of various value, heaped together in a
                    casket. Some are of the purest water, radiant with light and colour, some were
                    originally set in false metal that has tarnished, some were rude and repulsive
                    from the first. Out of the unarranged, heterogeneous mass the student has to
                    select what is not worth reading, but, after he has cast aside all the rubbish,
                    he is astonished at the amount of excellent and exquisite work that remains.
                    Herrick has himself summed up, very correctly, the themes of his sylvan muse
                    when he says :—</p>
                <p>I sing of brooks, of blossoms, birds and bowers, Of April, May, of June and July
                    flowers, 1 sing of May-poles, hock-carts, wassails, wakes, Of bridegrooms,
                    brides, and of their bridal-cakes.</p>
                <p>He saw the picturesqueness of English homely life as no one before him had seen
                    it, and he described it in his verse with a certain purple glow of Arcadian
                    romance over it, in tones of immortal vigour and freshness. His love poems are
                    still more beautiful; the best of them have an ardour and tender sweetness which
                    give them a place in the forefront of modern lyrical poetry, and remind us of
                    what was best in Horace and in the poets of the Greek anthology.</p>
                <p>After suffering complete extinction for more than a century, the fame of Herrick
                    was revived by Mr Nichols (Sylvanus Urban), who introduced his poems to the
                    readers of the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> of 1796 and 1797. Dr
                    Drake followed in 1798 with considerable enthusiasm. By 1810 interest had so far
                    revived in the forgotten poet that Dr Nott ventured to print a selection from
                    his poems, which attracted the favourable notice of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quarterly Review..</hi> In 1823 the <hi rend="italic">Hesperides</hi> and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Noble Numbers</hi> were for the first time edited by Mr T.
                    Maitland, afterwards Lord Dundrennan. Other editions followed in 1839, 1844,
                    1846, 1850, 1852, and 1859. A more complete collection, by Mr W. C. Hazlitt, was
                    brought out in 1869. In 1876 followed Dr Grosart’s exhaustive and authoritative
                    edition in three vols., and in 1877, under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chrysomela,</hi> a very elegant selection by Mr F. T. Palgrave, with a
                    prefatory essay. There are therefore few English poets of the 17th century whose
                    writings are now more accessible to every class of readers than those of
                    Herrick.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
