<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0431-0412-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALEXANDER HAMILTON (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    412)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n431/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALEXANDER HAMILTON</label><hi rend="italic">Copyright,</hi>
                    1880, <hi rend="italic">by George Shea.</hi><hi> ALEXANDER HAMILTON</hi>, the
                    ablest American jurist and statesman of the early constitutional era of the
                    United States, was born at the island of Nevis, one of the Antilles under the
                    dominion of England, on January 11, 1757. His father was a Scotch emigrant who
                    had settled at St Christopher, where he engaged in mercantile business. His
                    mother was the daughter of a Huguenot named Faucette, a prosperous physician of
                    Nevis. She had been the wife of a Mr Irvine, also a physician, and during a
                    brief married life dwelt at St Christopher; but, owing to faults of his, she
                    appears to have been driven to procure the judicial dissolution of the marriage,
                    after which ehe returned to her father’s home at Nevis, and there married James
                    Hamilton. She bore to him many sons, of whom none but Thomas and Alexander lived
                    to maturity. Alexander, the youngest, was called after his paternal grandfather,
                    who described himself “of Grange,” which is said to have been the family seat in
                    Ayrshire, Scotland. The master of Grange married, in 1730, Elizabeth, eldest
                    daughter of Sir Robert Pollock; and young Hamilton, when he had risen to fame
                    and station, said, “My blood is as good as that of those who plume themselves
                    upon their ancestry.” He styled his suburban residence, near New York, “the
                    Grange.”</p>
                <p>His mother died while he was still a child, but not before he was capable of
                    receiving and preserving distinct recollections of her. He derived from her an
                    independent spirit, energy, self-reliance, and a disposition for metaphysical
                    inquiries; and these qualities were conspicuous from an early age. His father’s
                    business misfortunes casting the boy upon the care of some of the mother’s
                    relatives, he was taken by them to their home at St Croix, and there at school
                    he first evinced that proficiency which marked him throughout his career. The
                    opportunities for school training were at that time very limited at St Croix,
                    and when, in his thirteenth year, he entered the counting-house of Mr Nicholas
                    Cruger, at that port, he had already received all the benefit such schools were
                    able to impart. This was in the autumn of 1769. In less than a year he was
                    capable of more than clerkly duty, and Mr Cruger, going on a foreign journey,
                    left him in sole charge of the mercantile house. His business correspondence
                    during this time, and the prosperity which attended the affairs, show that Mr
                    Cruger’s confidence was not misplaced. This practical acquaintance with
                    mercantile affairs was to be most serviceable to Hamilton. In the methodical and
                    energetic management of matters of state, and in the prudent care υf weighty
                    interests, the influence of the knowledge and experience acquired by him in the
                    counting-house at St Croix is notable. During these three years he was the same
                    close student that his after years more fully reveal. He read standard books,
                    which laid open the theories of value and of trade, thinking out to feasible
                    methods how those theories might be advantageously applied to the daily work he
                    had in hand. He read history, poetry, and philosophy. The French language became
                    familiar to him by its general use in society and in the transactions of
                    commerce, and he always wrote it with accuracy and elegance, and spoke it
                    fluently and with the accent of native speech. The Rev. Hugh Knox, D.D., an
                    Irishman, a divine of the Presbyterian Church, a scholar of distinction honoured
                    as such by the university of Glasgow, was Hamilton’s first adequate preceptor,
                    and was the first to discover the rich resources and useful tendencies of his
                    intellectual and moral character. Under his friendly and gratuitous tutorship
                    Hamilton supplied many parts in which his education was deficient. But the boy
                    had aims beyond where he was; and when an incident, trivial in itself, led to an
                    arrangement by which a more liberal education was opened to him, he left the
                    West Indies, in October 1772, and proceeded to New York. There, aided by letters
                    from his friend Dr Knox, he made the acquaintance of some of the leading men in
                    that and the adjoining province of New Jersey. A year at the grammar school at
                    Elizabethtown in the latter province proved sufficient to prepare him for the
                    collegiate course, and in the spring of 1774 he entered as a student the King’s
                    (now Columbia) College, and, by special privilege, pursued the usual studies
                    according to a plan which he laid out for himself.</p>
                <p>When, in 1774, the enforcement of the Boston “Port Bill” aroused even the most
                    moderate in the other colonies to sympathize with the province of Massachusetts
                    Bay, Hamilton studied the political questions relating to the controversy
                    between the colonies and the parliament of England with his habitual research
                    and enlightened reasoning. He was convinced that his duty as an Englishman
                    required him to take part with the colonists against the assertion of the
                    “omnipotence of parliament.” The famous tract by Lord Somers entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">The Judgment of whole Kingdoms and Nations,</hi> &lt;fcc.,
                    which repudiates this as a thing unknown to the law of England, was republished
                    in 1773 at Philadelphia, and widely circulated throughout the provinces, in aid
                    of the cause of colonial resistance. Its effect upon the mind of Hamilton is to
                    be observed in his writings of this time. With his usual ardour he now busied
                    himself in public discussion. Before his eighteenth year ended his reputation as
                    an orator and writer was established. His chief opponent at this period was the
                    distinguished divine Samuel Seabury, who a few years later (1783) was
                    consecrated in Scotland the first bishop of the United States of America. The
                    fame of their debates spread over the whole country, and Hamilton was the
                    acknowledged “oracle” of the party of moderation, with which he acted.</p>
                <p>While still a collegian he joined the military of the province of New York, and
                    began as the captain of its first company of artillery employed in the
                    continental service. To qualify himself for such a position he had, under the
                    immediate instruction of an experienced soldier and officer, not only studied
                    the theoretic art of war but engaged with others in receiving daily for several
                    months practical lessons in the field-drill. He was active with his company of
                    artillerists at the battle on Long Island, at Harlem Plains, at Chatterton’s
                    Hill, New Brunswick, Trenton, and Princeton. At Harlem Heights he first
                    attracted the attention of Washington, and again at New Brunswick excited the
                    commander’s admiration by the courage and skill with which he held in check the
                    advance of the British forces, while the American army was retreating toward the
                    Delaware. When the army went, in January 1777, into winter quarters at
                    Morristown, Hamilton, now grown in the friendship and confidence of Washington,
                    resigned his command, became Washington’s private secretary, and was raised to
                    the rank of lieutenant-colonel. Hamilton remained on the staff until April 1781,
                    when an unusual and hasty warmth of temper on both sides led to the severance of
                    this particular connexion, but their mutual friendship remained <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n432/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0432-0413"/> and even increased. He was married in 1780 to
                    Elizabeth, second daughter of General Philip Schuyler, a distinguished soldier
                    and statesman of the Revolution. For a brief space Hamilton occupied his time in
                    exposing the inherent defects of the existing confederation by a series of
                    excellent papers known as <hi rend="italic">The Continentalist.</hi> But the
                    country once more needed his more active aid; he returned to the army, led one
                    most brilliant attack, and was present with a command at the surrender of Lord
                    Cornwallis.</p>
                <p>The war to maintain the declaration of independence was fought, but it did not
                    make nor leave the United Colonies a nation. A new system of government and “a
                    coercive union” were insisted upon by Hamilton and other foremost men as
                    necessary. But many obstacles stood in the way. Historical prejudice and the
                    selfishness of local interests were against concessions to a union of the
                    States. Traditional dread of centralized government, traditional dread of an
                    hereditary aristocracy, dread that a national legislature, if allowed full
                    authority, might assert and act upon the repudiated doctrine of an omnipotence
                    of parliament, dread that a supreme general government might absorb, or even
                    usurp, under the plea of care for the public welfare, those local interests
                    which the States were now able to maintain, and which the Confederation was
                    meant to protect—the concurrence of these several causes contributed to bring
                    out opposition whenever a more perfect union was proposed.</p>
                <p>The first suggestion towards the establishment of an adequate and permanent
                    government came, as it is now conceded, from Hamilton. It was contained in a
                    letter written by him, September 3, 1780, to James Duane, a delegate from New
                    York to the Congress at Philadelphia. He wrote a yet more remarkable letter the
                    following year (April 30) to Robert Morris, the famous financier of the
                    Revolution, in which not a mere suggestion but a matured and complete scheme of
                    national finance, including a plan for a United States bank, was discussed and
                    laid out. These letters are, indeed, the <hi rend="italic">principia</hi> of the
                    American government in its organization and administration. When the convention
                    of delegates met at Annapolis, Maryland, in September 1786, the influence of
                    Hamilton upon the destinies of his country began to be favoured by
                    circumstances. Although the object of that convention was limited to simply
                    commercial projects, yet, under his and Madison’s prudent management, an address
                    was finally issued which brought about the great and conclusive convention of
                    1787 at Philadelphia. The form of government then instituted is, in its
                    groundwork and its principal features, a restoration and perfecting of the
                    ancient constitutional liberties of England. While the particular plan proposed
                    by Hamilton was, as were other projects, laid aside, yet it was the spirit of
                    the system conceived by him which then prevailed and has since been a
                    controlling principle in the administration of government. Guizot says of him
                    that “there is not in the constitution of the United States an element of order,
                    of force, of duration, which he did not powerfully contribute to introduce into
                    it and to cause to predominate.” It was at this period that Hamilton, in
                    association with John Jay and James Madison, wrote his parts of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Federalist.</hi></p>
                <p>At the convention, called by the State of New York, which met at Poughkeepsie, on
                    the Hudson River, June 1788, to ratify the proposed National Constitution, the
                    superb ability . of Hamilton for organizing and leading intelligent public
                    opinion displayed itself fully. The utility of candid, earnest, reasonable
                    debate has seldom been more approved by its results. A most disheartening
                    minority of the delegates when the convention first met were in favour of the
                    Constitution. When Hamilton ceased his efforts, not only had he gained to his
                    support a majority, but even ultimately he had the aid and vote of his most
                    eloquent and most powerful antagonist. At length Hamilton arose in the
                    convention, and, stating that Virginia had ratified the Constitution, and that
                    the Union was thereby an accomplished fact, moved that they cease their
                    contentions and add New York to the new empire of republican states. That day
                    his labours culminated in entire success.</p>
                <p>Washington, when forming the cabinet for his first presidential administration,
                    naturally turned to Robert Morris as the proper person to take the secretaryship
                    of the treasury; but Morris declined, insisting that Hamilton was “the one man
                    in the United States” fitted by studies and ability to create a public credit
                    and bring the resources of the country into active efficiency. Washington found
                    his former military secretary more than equal to the task. The fiscal affairs of
                    the country were at once organized, and prosperity quickly came. Hamilton
                    achieved an immediate success which all agree is without parallel. He also was
                    really the organizer of the administration of the new Government, and in its
                    chief department it remains to this day without change. His state papers,
                    written during the two presidential terms of Washington, are regarded as of the
                    highest character for knowledge of the case, wisdom, and practical method; and
                    his report on the constitutionality of a national bank, in which he fully
                    develops his favourite policy of the implied powers of the Government, and the
                    other report, nominally upon manufactures, which embraces in its range every
                    pursuit of human industry susceptible of encouragement under such a government
                    as he wished to see that of the United States, are those productions in which
                    the rare qualities of his mind abundantly manifest their force and precision.
                    President Van Buren declared the latter paper to be “Hamilton’s
                    masterpiece.”</p>
                <p>After these labours Hamilton, though offered the position of chief-justice of the
                    United States, remained at the bar of his adopted State. He soon rose to its
                    highest rank, and was esteemed its unrivalled leader. As a citizen, and without
                    the desire of public office, he continued always actively interested in public
                    affairs. His intense and uncompromising moral nature engendered many political
                    antipathies, though personally few were more loved for amiability and respected
                    for their honour. Among those men whom he deemed it a patriotic duty to defeat
                    in a personal ambition was Aaron Burr, the vice-president of the United States.
                    Party lines were marked and party spirit fierce. Burr appreciated what would be
                    the effect of Hamilton’s continued opposition to his political designs, and knew
                    that he was a man to be neither conciliated in this respect or outmanoeuvred. He
                    eagerly watched for an opportunity to impute offence. A trivial and inadequate
                    occasion soon came. An indiscreet person repeated a remark which he said
                    Hamilton made in a familiar conversation at the house of a common friend, to the
                    purport that he had a “despicable” opinion of Burr. Upon this gossip Burr acted;
                    and so subtle was the manner with which he managed the correspondence for his
                    determined purpose that he, according to the tone of society at that time, made
                    it, in Hamilton’s misconception, an obligation, due to his continued usefulness
                    in public affairs, to accept a challenge. They met early on the morning of July
                    11, 1804, at a sequestered place beneath the hills of Weehawken, on the west
                    bank of the Hudson River, opposite to the city of New York. Hamilton was
                    mortally wounded at the first fire. As he fell, his own pistol was by accident
                    discharged, and the ball struck the ground near him. He did not himself intend
                    to fire. He died the following day, in the forty-eighth year of his age. His
                    death was considered a national calamity. Eight of his children, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n433/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0433-0414"/> four boys and four girls, were left to his
                    widow’s care. She survived him half a century, dying at the age of ninety-seven,
                    and during all that time she remained attired in the widow’s dress of the early
                    times.</p>
                <p>The peculiarity of Hamilton’s genius consisted of qualities which eminently
                    distinguish him from the other great personages of his time. The epithet
                    precocious was never applicable to him, for whatever he did, even in his
                    boyhood, was accomplished with facility, and resulted in a perfection that the
                    works of latter years did not exceed. He was ever mature. His intellect pierced
                    through the most subtle and profound problems, and apparently without the labour
                    of experiment. He “could see consequents yet dormant in their principles,” or,
                    as Talleyrand said of him on more than one occasion, “he divined.” “Hamilton
                    avait dmW l’Europe,” was the reason given by the prince when he compared him to
                    Fox and Napoleon. His industry was marvellous, and his learning equal to the
                    creative faculty of his mind. The fecundity, power, vigour, and maturity of his
                    intellectual works as fully impressed his contemporaries as they have since
                    impressed posterity.</p>
                <p>His political writings seem, in the estimation of judicious’and eminent writers
                    in America, Great Britain, and France, to place him in the first rank of master
                    minds. The most widely known of these writings are those contained in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Federalist.</hi> Translations of them were published at
                    Paris (the first as early as 1792), and were studied by the chief public men of
                    that period. It has been asserted that they exhibit an extent and precision of
                    information, a profundity of research, and an accurateness of understanding
                    which would have done honour to the most illustrious statesmen of ancient or
                    modern times, that for comprehensiveness of design, strength, clearness, and
                    simplicity they have no parallel <hi rend="italic">{Blackwood s Magazine,</hi>
                    January 1825, and <hi rend="italic">The Edinburgh Review,</hi> No. 24).
                    Talleyrand called the attention of European statesmen to the merits of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Federalist</hi> as a copious source of correct maxims and
                    profound thought; and Guizot says that, “in the application of elementary
                    principles of government to practical administration, it was the greatest work
                    known to him.” Laboulaye has expressed at great length his deliberate judgment
                    of Hamilton’s genius and wisdom, and of the consummate ability with which he
                    called into existence a new system of government and organized its
                    administration <hi rend="italic">{Histoire des États-Unis,</hi> tome iii.). And
                    Hamilton’s own countrymen have not been less emphatic in grateful
                    acknowledgment, especially Chief-Justice Marshall, the judicial interpreter and
                    expounder of the principles of the American Constitution.</p>
                <p>In person Hamilton was below the medium height, slender, almost delicate in
                    frame, instinct with life, erect and quick in gait; his general address was
                    graceful and nervous, indicating the energy, exactness, and activity of his
                    mind. His complexion was bright and ruddy, his hair light, and the whole
                    countenance decidedly Scottish in form and expression. His political enemies
                    frankly spoke of his manner and conversation, and regretted its irresistible
                    charm. The best portraits of him are by Trumbull, Weimar, Ames, and there is a
                    good bust by Cerrachi.</p>
                <p>For full memoirs of Hamilton, see the elaborate <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> in 7
                    vols., by John Church Hamilton, one of his sons, New York, 1857; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Life</hi> by Dr Renwick, published in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Harper's Family Library; Life</hi> by Morse, 2 vol«., Boston, 1876; Edouard
                    Laboulaye’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire des États-Unis,</hi> tome iii., Paris,
                    1870; Curtis’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Constitution of the United
                        States,</hi> 2 vols., New York, 1858; Reithmüller’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hamilton and his Contemporaries,</hi> London, 1864; Bancroft’s <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the United States,</hi> in the 7th and succeeding
                    vols.; and Shea’s <hi rend="italic">Life and Epoch of Hamilton,</hi> 2d ed., New
                    York, 1880. (G. SH.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
