<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0567-0534-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAWK (9th edition, volume 11, page 534)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952093">Hawks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919997">Falcons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919988">Falconers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128737">Sparrows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878236">Cooperativeness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw3f">Hawking</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qj2t">Hawks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb7f">Falcons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n567/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAWK</label> (Anglo-Saxon, <hi rend="italic">Hafoc),</hi> a
                    word of somewhat indefinite meaning, being often used to signify all diurnal
                    Birds-of-prey which are neither Vultures nor Eagles, and again more exclusively
                    for those of the remainder which are not Buzzards, Falcons, Harriers, or Kites.
                    Even with this restriction it is comprehensive enough, and will include more
                    than a hundred species, which have been arrayed in genera varying in number from
                    a dozen to above a score, according to the fancy of the systematizer. Speaking
                    generally, Hawks may be characterized by possessing comparatively short wings
                    and long legs, a bill which begins to decurve directly from the cere (or soft
                    bare skin that covers its base), and has the cutting edges of its maxilla (or
                    upper mandible) sinuated<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>In one form, <hi rend="italic">Nisοides,</hi> which on that account
                            has been generically separated, they are said to be perfectly
                            straight.</p></note> but never notched. To these may be added as
                    characters, structurally perhaps of less value, but in other respects quite as
                    important, that the sexes differ very greatly in size, that in most species the
                    irides are yellow, deepening with age into orange or even red, and that the
                    immature plumage is almost invariably more or less striped or mottled with
                    heart-shaped spots beneath, while that of the adults is generally much barred,
                    though the old males have in many instances the breast and belly quite free from
                    markings. Nearly all are of small or moderate size—the largest among them being
                    the Gos- <hi rend="smallcaps">Hawk</hi> (vol. X. p. 788) and its immediate
                    allies, and the male of the smallest, <hi rend="italic">Accipiter</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">times,</hi> is not bigger than a Song-Thrush. They are all
                    birds of great boldness in attacking a quarry, but if foiled in the first
                    attempt they are apt to leave the pursuit. Thoroughly arboreal in their habits,
                    they seek their prey, chiefly consisting of birds (though reptiles and small
                    mammals are also taken), among trees or bushes, patiently waiting for a victim
                    to shew itself, anl gliding upon it when it appears to be unwary with a rapid
                    swoop, clutching it in their talons, and bearing it away to eat it in some
                    convenient spot.</p>
                <p>It is of course impossible here to enter into details of the numerous forms
                    which, notwithstanding the limitation above adopted, are to be called Hawks, or
                    to describe the distinguishing characters, so far as any have been given, of the
                    different groups or sections into which it has pleased systematic ornithologists
                    to break them up, since hardly any two are agreed in the latter respect. There
                    is at the outset a difference of opinion as to the scientific name which the
                    largest and best known of these sections should bear—some authors terming it <hi
                        rend="italic">Nisus,</hi> and others, who seem to have the most justice on
                    their side, <hi rend="italic">Accipiter.</hi> In Europe there are two
                    species—first, <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi rend="italic">nisus,</hi> the common
                    Sparrow-Hawk, which has a wide distribution from Ireland to Japan, extending
                    also to northern India, Egypt, and Algeria, and secondly, <hi rend="italic">A.
                        δreviyes</hi> (by some placed in the group <hi rend="italic">Micro-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">nisus</hi> and by others called an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Astur),</hi> which only appears in the south-east, and the adjoining parts
                    of Asia Minor and Persia. In North America the place of the former is taken by
                    two very distinct species, a small one, <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">fuscus,</hi> usually known in Canada and the United States as
                    the Sharp-shinned Hawk, and Stanley’s or Cooper’s Hawk, <hi rend="italic"
                        >A.</hi><hi rend="italic">cooperi</hi> (by some placed in another genus, <hi
                        rend="italic">Cooperastur),</hi> which is larger and has not so northerly a
                    range. In South America there are four or five more, including <hi rend="italic"
                        >A.</hi><hi rend="italic">tinus,</hi> before mentioned as the smallest of
                    all, while a species not much larger, <hi rend="italic">A. miηullus,</hi>
                    together with several others of greater size, inhabits South Africa. Madagascar
                    and its neighbouring islands have three or four species sufficiently distinct,
                    and India has <hi rend="italic">A. badius.</hi> A good many more forms are found
                    in South-eastern Asia, in the Indo-Malay Archipelago, and in Australia three or
                    four species, of which <hi rend="italic">A. cirrhocephalus</hi> most nearly
                    represents the Sparrow-Hawk of Europe and Northern Asia, while <hi rend="italic"
                        >A. radiatus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >approximans</hi> shew some affinity to the Cos-Hawks <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Astur)</hi> with which they are often classed. The differences between all
                    the forms above named and the much larger number here unnamed are such as can be
                    only appreciated by the specialist, and could not possibly be pointed out within
                    the limits of this article. It may be observed in conclusion that the so-called
                    “Sparrow-Hawk” of New Zealand <hi rend="italic">(Hieracidea)</hi> does not
                    belong to this group of birds at all, and by many authors has been deemed akin
                    to the Falcons. For Hawking, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Falconry. (a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
