<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0671-0638-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HELPS, Sir Arthur</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 638</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n671/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HELPS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Arthur</hi></label>
                    (1813-1875), fourth and youngest son of Thomas and Ann Frisquett Helps, was born
                    at Balham Hill, in the parish of Streatham and county of Surrey, on the 10th of
                    July 1813. His father was then and for many years afterwards head of a large
                    mercantile house in the city of London, and for the last thirteen years of his
                    life treasurer of St Bartholomew’s Hospital. His mother was the only surviving
                    child of John, fourth son of the Rev. Charles Plucknett, M.A., of Wincanton.
                    After the usual preliminary training at Eton, young Helps went to Trinity
                    College, Cambridge, passing as B.A. in 1835, when he came out 31st wrangler in
                    the mathematical tripos, and taking his M.A. degree in 1839. Although he took no
                    high honours at the university,—and indeed he <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n672/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0672-0639"/> had not health sufficiently robust, even if he
                    had possessed the ambition, to achieve them,—he was recognized by the ablest of
                    his contemporaries there as a man of superior gifts, and likely to make his mark
                    in after life. They showed this by electing him as a member of the Conversazione
                    Society, better known as the Apostles, a society which had been established in
                    1820 for the purposes of discussion on social and literary questions by a few
                    young men attracted to each other by a common taste for literature and
                    speculation. A body which in its early days included the names of Charles
                    Buller, Frederick Maurice, Richard Chenevix Trench, Monckton Milnes, Arthur
                    Hallam, and Alfred Tennyson had in it every element to make its gatherings
                    delightful as well as useful. To be elected into its limited circle was a
                    distinction of which Arthur Helps was proud then and to the close of his life;
                    and, familiar as he was with the best and most intellectual society of his time,
                    the social hours passed year by year with the Cambridge Apostles were always
                    counted by him among his happiest, both in anticipation and in remembrance.</p>
                <p>In the discussions of these and later days Helps may have found the suggestions
                    for the dialogues of the <hi rend="italic">Friends in Council,</hi> in which his
                    genius appears at his best. But his first literary effort, which appeared under
                    the title of <hi rend="italic">Thoughts in the Cloister and the Crowd</hi> in
                    1835, the year he took his B.A. degree, assumes a very different but scarcely
                    less ambitious form, that of a series of aphorisms upon life, character,
                    politics, and manners. As a rule, such things are only valuable when they come
                    as the fruits of wide experience and matured thought. Still in this volume are
                    to be found passages which may take their place beside the sayings of
                    Vauvenargues, Chamfort, and other masters of aphorism of the second rank, and
                    are quite equal in quality to the many pithy quotable sayings scattered through
                    Helps’s later works.</p>
                <p>Soon after leaving the university, where he had established many valuable
                    friendships, Arthur Helps became private secretary to Mr Spring Rice (afterwards
                    Lord Monteagle), then chancellor of the exchequer in Lord Melbourne’s
                    administration. This appointment he filled till 1840, when he went to Ireland as
                    the private secretary of Lord Morpeth (afterwards earl of Carlisle), then the
                    chief secretary of state for Ireland, where he remained until his principal left
                    Ireland in 1841, on the Government passing from Lord Melbourne into the hands of
                    Sir Robert Peel. In the meanwhile (28th October 1836) Helps had married Miss
                    Bessy Fuller, a young Irish lady. He was also appointed one of the commissioners
                    for the settlement of certain Danish claims which dated so far back as the siege
                    of Copenhagen; but with the fall of the Melbourne administration his official
                    experience closed for a period of nearly twenty years. The character which he
                    had established for himself by his tact, sagacity, and business habits was not,
                    however, forgotten by his political friends. And combined as these qualities
                    were with an admirable manner which invited confidence while it repelled
                    intrusion, and with a reticence and discretion on which absolute reliance could
                    be placed, his fitnes3 for official life was unmistakable. When therefore the
                    clerkship of the Privy Council became vacant in 1860, on the resignation of the
                    Hon. W. L. Bathurst, he was recommended for the appointment by his old friend
                    Lord Granville, who knew that for ability, tact, and discretion it could not be
                    in safer bands.</p>
                <p>During his early official career Helps cultivated literature with varying
                    success. His <hi rend="italic">Essays written in the Intervals of Business,</hi>
                    published in 1841, and his <hi rend="italic">Claims of Labour, an Essay on the
                    Duties of the Employers to the Employed,</hi> published in 1844, continue to
                    interest, and are likely to keep their place in well-selected libraries. But two
                    plays, <hi rend="italic">King Henry the Second, an Historical Drama,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Catherine</hi><hi rend="italic">Douglas, a Tragedy,</hi> both
                    published in 1843, have no particular merit. Neither in these, nor in his only
                    other dramatic effort, <hi rend="italic">Culita the Serf,</hi> published in
                    1858, a work far superior, however, to his earlier efforts of the same kind, are
                    to be found the sense of dramatic situation and movement, the sharp outlines and
                    contrast of character, or the fitness and concise force of diction which alone
                    justify the selection by an author of the dramatic form as the vehicle for his
                    thoughts. Helps possessed, however, just enough dramatic power to give life and
                    individuality to the dialogues which he introduced with excellent effect to
                    enliven many of his other books. His first effort in this direction was in <hi
                    rend="italic">Friends in Council, a Series of Headings and Discourse
                    thereon,</hi> published in 1847 and 1851. The plan of this book seems to have
                    been suggested by a passage in Bacon’s essay <hi rend="italic">Of
                    Discourse,</hi> which appears as the motto of it. “It is good in discourse and
                    speech of conversation to vary and intermingle speech of the present occasion
                    with arguments, tales with reasons, asking of questions with telling of
                    opinions, and jest with earnest; for it is a dull thing to tire, and, as we say
                    now, to jade anything too far.” The variety and conflict of opinion, the play of
                    character, the flashes of humour, got by submitting the formal essays on social
                    and moral questions wdιich made the staple of these volumes to be criticized and
                    pulled to pieces by the imaginary personages, who, under the names of Milverton,
                    Ellesmere, and Dunsford, grew to be almost as real to Helps’s readers as they
                    certainly became to himself, gave a special charm to a book which, by its
                    richness of suggestion, its sweetness of tone, and beauty of style, made for its
                    author a high and enduring reputation. The same expedient was resorted to for
                    the discussion of the ideas of social and philanthropic improvement on which
                    Helps’s mind was always at work, in a second series of <hi rend="italic">Friends
                    in Council,</hi> published in 1859, and again in <hi rend="italic">Conversations
                    on War and General Culture,</hi> published in 1871. The old familiar speakers,
                    with others added, also appeared in his <hi rend="italic">Ileal·mah,</hi> and
                    finally in wdιat certainly must alw ays rank as the best of its author’s later
                    works, <hi rend="italic">Talk about Animals and their Masters,</hi> published in
                    1873.</p>
                <p>The subject of slavery was one which had a peculiar fascination for Helps. A long
                    essay is devoted to it in the first series of <hi rend="italic">Friends in
                    Council.</hi> This was subsequently elaborated into a work in two volumes
                    published in 1848 and 1852, called <hi rend="italic">The Conquerors of the New
                    World and their Bondsmen.</hi> Helps’s interest in the subject led him into
                    further investigations into the history of the conquest of America by the
                    Spaniards, and he went to Spain in 1847 for the special purpose of examining the
                    numerous MSS. bearing upon the subject at Madrid. The fruits of these researches
                    were embodied in an historical work based upon his <hi rend="italic">Conquerors
                    of the New World,</hi> and called <hi rend="italic">The Spanish Conquest in
                    America, and its Delation to the History of Slavery and the Government of
                    Colonies.</hi> This appeared in four volumes during the years 1855, 1857, and
                    1861. No pains were spared by its author to secure the most scrupulous accuracy
                    as to the facts with wdιich he dealt. He had found, as most inquirers into the
                    sources of history have found, that this accuracy is rarely to be met with in
                    accepted histories. On this point he was determined that he should not be open
                    to censure; and so anxious was he that fact should not be coloured or distorted
                    by imagination that he deliberately resisted the temptation to use the
                    picturesque method of treatment by which other writers on the same subject have
                    secured popularity. The success of this work with the public was injured by
                    other peculiarities. History, like fiction, will not bear to be written with an
                    obtrusively moral purpose, as this book was written. Its merits in a literary
                    point of view were also diminished by the author’s tendency to suspend the
                    onward movement of the narrative, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n673/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0673-0640"/> whilst he pauses to analyse character, to
                    investigate motives, and to philosophize upon results.</p>
                <p>This book, the result of years of research and meditation, was not a success. But
                    the excellence of the studies of the great pioneers of Spanish conquest which it
                    contained was quickly perceived when some years afterwards they were recast and
                    published as separate biographies. Thus <hi rend="italic">The Life of Las Casas,
                    the Apostle of the Indians,</hi> appeared in 1868, <hi rend="italic">The Life of
                    Columbus</hi> in 1869, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Pizarro</hi> in the same
                    year, and <hi rend="italic">The Life of Hernando Cortes</hi> in 1871. In this
                    form all that is most important as well as attractive in the larger historical
                    work has been placed within the reach of a wide circle of readers, to whom the
                    result of Helps’s researches otherwise would have been unknown.</p>
                <p>From the time of his appointment as Clerk of the Council in 1860 to his death,
                    Helps continued to add to the already considerable list of books, all dealing in
                    one form or another with questions of social, sanitary, or political reform,
                    which he had most earnestly at heart. No man felt more strongly that, in the
                    words of Lamennais <hi rend="italic">{Livre du Peuple,</hi> cap. i.), “things in
                    this world are not as they ought to be.” No man was more eager to do what he
                    might towards obviating or curing the folly, stupidity, ignorance, lethargy, and
                    selfishness to which so much of the misery, the ill-health, the suffering, and
                    the sin of the world is due. It was a matter of conscience to do what he could
                    towards “the relief of man’s estate,” by putting again and again before the
                    world the results of his observation and thought upon its defective social and
                    sanitary arrangements, and in this the reason is to be found for nearly all his
                    books. Besides those which have been already mentioned the following may be
                    named to complete the list :— <hi rend="italic">Organization in Daily Life, an
                    Essay</hi> (1862), <hi rend="italic">Real·mah</hi> (2 vols. 1869), <hi
                    rend="italic">Casimir Haremma</hi> (1870), <hi rend="italic">Brevia,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Short Essays and Aphorisms</hi> (1871), <hi rend="italic">Thoughts
                    upon Government</hi> (1872), <hi rend="italic">Life and Labours of Hr Thomas
                    Brassey</hi> (1872), <hi rend="italic">Ivan de Biron</hi> (1874), <hi
                    rend="italic">Social Pressure</hi> (1875).</p>
                <p>His appointment as Clerk of the Council brought him into personal communication
                    with the Queen, and also with the late Prince Consort. They were not slow to
                    find how valuable a servant they had obtained in him. His powers of mind, his
                    gentle, reserved manners, and his tender almost chivalrous devotion to the
                    sovereign, not demonstrated yet subtly making itself felt, produced their
                    natural effect in winning the confidence and respect of these high personages.
                    After the Prince’s death, the Queen early turned to Helps to prepare such a
                    sketch of the prince’s character as might make her people aware how much they as
                    well as herself had lost by his early death. The task was undertaken by Helps,
                    and performed with all the excellence which might have been anticipated from his
                    sympathy with the great aims and objects of the Prince’s life, and his practised
                    skill in the analysis and portrayal of character. His introduction to the
                    collection, published in 1862, of the Prince Consort’s speeches and addresses
                    was the first, and will probably always be the standard, attempt to sketch in
                    clear and vivid outlines the varied characteristics of this remarkable man.
                    Helps some years afterwards edited and wrote an introductory preface to the
                    series of extracts from the Queen’s diary, which were published in 1868 under
                    the title <hi rend="italic">Leaves from a Journal of Our Life in the
                    Highlands.</hi> In 1864 he received the honorary degree of D.C.L. from the
                    university of Oxford. He was made a C.B. in 1871, and K.C.B. in the following
                    year.</p>
                <p>At no time of his life very strong, an obvious decline of vital strength,
                    accelerated probably by anxiety from embarrassments in which his later years
                    were involved by unfortunate speculations in the purchase of land, was visible
                    to Sir Arthur Helps’s friends for some years before his death. This came after
                    only a few days’ illness on the 7th of March 1ø75.</p>
                <p>Sir Arthur Helps was of middle height, slender, dark in complexion, with a high
                    well-defined forehead, deep-set eyes, and a mouth the habitually grave
                    expression of which was tempered by a pleasant smile, when his fancy was touched
                    by the humorous suggestions of his own mind, or the playfulness or wit of
                    others, to which he was peculiarly sensitive. Something of the delicacy of his
                    frame entered into his manner and conversation, which were marked by an
                    avoidance of eveιything approaching vehemence or even emphasis. He loved good
                    talk, and his low vibrant voice and grave playfulness'of mind were very
                    pleasant, when among trusted friends he was tempted into taking an active part
                    in the give and take of easy conversation. But he was in manhood what he was in
                    youth, when we are told by one who knew him well, “he had not the physical force
                    or the animal spirits which predispose novices to oral controversy.” As a rule,
                    he was more ready in general society to listen than to talk,—especially when
                    people were present whose character was worth studying, or whose ideas were
                    fresh and based upon experience or comprehensive study. He was always learning,
                    and a new thought or pregnant suggestion dropped by a friend in conversation was
                    often to be found soon afterwards in his writings carefully developed, and
                    illustrated from his own fertile stores of reading and research. As might be
                    expected from his books, there was a sympathetic charm in his familiar
                    intercourse which was peculiarly fascinating. His sensitiveness to pain,
                    especially to moral pain, -was extreme, and would have unfitted him for much of
                    the rough work and ways of the world. As an orator, a character for which he had
                    many intellectual qualities, he could scarcely have failed to attain a high
                    rank. He was himself not unconscious of his gifts in this direction; but he was
                    altogether of too fine a fibre for the hard hitting and the fiery struggle of
                    the political arena, in which alone he would have coveted distinction. Wisely,
                    therefore, he made for himself, as was well said by a friend at the time of his
                    death, “work of another sort, applying his gentle ever busy mind to such
                    discussion as purifies the thought, informs the pity, and confirms the
                    forbearance of mankind.” To the last his mind retained its vigour as well as its
                    delicacy of perception. Nor would he have regarded it as among the least happy
                    circumstances of his lot on earth that he was taken away before either of these
                    had been touched by the palsy of decay—taken, moreover, swiftly and by no
                    lingering illness to wear out the spirits of himself and those to whom he was
                    dear. (T. MA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
