<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0685-0652-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENGSTENBERG, Ernst Wilhelm</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 652</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:824216">Autumn</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1174110">Westphalians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785p59">Autumn</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9t650">Apocrypha</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n685/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENGSTENBERG, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernst Wilhelm</hi></label>
                    (1802-1869), for more than forty years one of the most conspicuous and able
                    champions of the strictest Lutheran orthodoxy, was born at Fröndenberg, a
                    Westphalian village near Hamm and not far from the Ruhr, on October 20, 1802;
                    received his entire school education under the roof of his father, who was a
                    minister of the Reformed Church, and head of the Fröndenberg Fräuleinstift; and
                    entered the university of Bonn in 1819, shortly before the completion of his
                    seventeenth year. There he attended the lectures of Frey tag and Gieseler on Old
                    Testament exegesis and church history, but his energies were principally devoted
                    to philosophy and philology, and his earliest publication was an edition of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Moallakah</hi> of Amru’ 1’ Kais <hi rend="italic">(Amrulkeisi
                    Moallakah cum scholiis Zuzenii</hi><hi rend="italic">edidit,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">latine</hi><hi rend="italic">vertit, et illustravit</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">JE. G. H,</hi> 1823), which gained for him the prize at his
                    graduation in the philosophical faculty, and the public commendation of
                    Sylvestre de Sacy. This was followed in 1824 by a German translation of
                    Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">AIetaphysica.</hi> On quitting Bonn it had been
                    Hengstenberg’s wish to complete his theological studies under Neander and
                    Tholuck in Berlin; but finding himself without the means of doing so, he
                    accepted for a year a situation at Basel as tutor in Oriental languages to J. J.
                    Stähelin. Then it was that, suffering much from ill-health and deeply mourning
                    the loss of his mother, he began to direct his attention, with an ardour
                    formerly unknown to him, to the spiritual truths of the Bible. His studies and
                    experiences at this crisis resulted in a conviction, never afterwards shaken,
                    not only of the divine character ot evangelical religion, but also of the
                    unapproachable adequacy of its expression in the Augsburg Confession. Taking as
                    his motto Psalm cxviii. 17, he resolved thenceforward to devote himself to the
                    uncompromising defence of that creed. In the autumn of 1824 he joined the
                    philosophical faculty of Berlin as a privat-docent, and in the following year he
                    became a licentiate in theology, his theses even then being remarkable for their
                    evangelical fervour and for their emphatic protest against every form of
                    “rationalism,” especially in questions of Old Testament criticism. In 1826 he
                    became professor extraordinarius in theology; and in July 1827 appeared under
                    Hengstenberg’s editorship the first number of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Evangelische</hi><hi rend="italic">Kirchemeitung,</hi> a “reactionary’’journal
                    which in his hands was destined to acquire an almost unique reputation as an
                    organ of religious, theological, and ecclesiastical controversy. It did not,
                    however, attain to great notoriety until in 1830 an anonymous article (by E. L.
                    von Gerlach) appeared, which openly charged Professors Gesenius and Wegscheider
                    with infidelity and profanity, and on the ground of these accusations
                    advocated<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n686/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0686-0653"/> the interposition of the civil power, thus giving
                    rise to the prolonged “Haifische Streit” as it was called, which was at least
                    effectual in giving the public a due impression of the energy and zeal of the
                    new “evangelical” school. In 1828 the first volume of Hengstenberg’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Christologie</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Alten</hi><hi rend="italic">Testaments</hi> passed through the press; in the
                    autumn of that year he was promoted to the dignity of professor ordinarius in
                    theology; and in 1829 he married. The remainder of his life, apart from the
                    excitement which its various literary activities imparted to it, was uneventful.
                    He died on the 28th of May 1869.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of the principal works of Hengstenberg:— <hi
                    rend="italic">Christologie des Alten Testaments</hi> (1829-35; 2d ed., 1854-57;
                    Eng. transi, by R. Keith, 1835-39, also in Clark’s “Foreign Theological
                    Library,” by Th. Meyer and J. Martin, 1854-58), a work of much ingenuity and
                    considerable learning, but which will be differently va'ued according to the
                    hermeneutical principles of the individual critic; <hi rend="italic">Beiträge
                    zur Einleitung</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">das Alte
                    Testament</hi> (1831-39; Engl, transi., “Dissertations on the Genuineness of
                    Daniel and the Integrity of Zechariah,” Edin., 1848, and “Dissertations on the
                    Genuineness of the Pentateuch,” Edin., 1847), in which the traditional view on
                    each question is strongly upheld, and much capital is made of the absence of
                    harmony among the negative critics; <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bücher</hi><hi rend="italic">Mosis</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Aegypten</hi> (1841), spoken of by Diestel as “perhaps
                    Hengstenberg’s most meritorious work;” <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte Bileams</hi><hi rend="italic">u. seiner</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Weissagungen</hi> (1842; translated into English along with the
                    Dissertations on Daniel and Zechariah mentioned above); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentar</hi><hi rend="italic">über</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Psalmen</hi> (1842-45; 2d ed. 1849-52; Eng. transi, by Fairbairn
                    and Thomson, Edin., 1844-48), which shares the merits and defects of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Christologie</hi><hi rend="italic">; Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Offenbarung Johannis erläutert</hi> (1841-51; 2d ed. 1861-62; Eng. transi, by
                    Fairbairn, also in Clark’s “Foreign Theological Library,” 1851-52); <hi
                    rend="italic">Das Hohe</hi><hi rend="italic">Lied</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ausgelegt</hi> (1853); <hi rend="italic">Der Prediger Salomo ausgelegt</hi>
                    (1859); <hi rend="italic">Das Evangelium Johannis erläutert</hi> (1861-63; 2d
                    ed. 1867-71; Eng. transi. 1865), and <hi rend="italic">Die Weissagungen
                    des</hi><hi rend="italic">Prop)heten</hi><hi rend="italic">Ezechiel
                    erläutert</hi> (1867-68). Of minor importance are <hi rend="italic">De
                    rebus</hi><hi rend="italic">Tyriorum commentatio academica</hi> (1832); <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber den Tag des Herrn</hi> (1852); <hi rend="italic">Das</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Passa,</hi><hi rend="italic">ein Vortrag</hi> (1853); and <hi
                    rend="italic">Die Opfer der heiligen Schrift</hi> (1859). Several series of
                    papers also, as, for example, on “The Retention of the Apocrypha,”
                    “Freemasonry,” “Duelling,” and “The Relation between the Jews and the Christian
                    church,” which originally appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Kirchenzeitung,</hi>
                    were afterwards printed in a separate form. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Reiches</hi><hi rend="italic">Gottes unter dem Alten
                    Bunde</hi> (1869-70), <hi rend="italic">Das Buch Hiob erläutert</hi> (1870-75),
                    and <hi rend="italic">Vorlesungen über die Leidensgeschichte</hi> (1875) were
                    published, from Hengstenberg’s papers, posthumously. See Bachmann’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ernst Wilhelm</hi><hi rend="italic">Hengstenberg</hi> (1876-79);
                    also his article in Herzog and Plitt’s <hi rend="italic">Encyklopädie</hi>
                    (1879).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
