<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0704-0671-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENRY IV</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 671</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z22r">Hardness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:951374">Hardness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n704/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENRY IV</label>. (1553-1610), king of France, was born in
                    the castle of Pau in 1553, being son of Antony of Bourbon, king of Navarre and
                    duke of Vendome, and Jeanne of Albret. By his father he was tenth in descent
                    from Saint Louis, and only a very distant cousin to his predecessor, Henry III.
                    His mother, a grand and noble lady, brought him up as a Calvinist. His education
                    was rough and hard, and fostered that originality of character which so marked
                    his life; his military training was under the great captain, Gaspard of Coligny.
                    In 1571 he was wedded to the daughter of Catherine de’ Medici, Margaret of
                    Valois; and on his mother’s death in 1572 he became king of Navarre.</p>
                <p>The massacre of St Bartholomew found him in Paris; but his life was spared on his
                    making a profession of Catholicism, which lasted till he succeeded in escaping
                    from court in 1575. Thenceforward he became acknowledged head of the Huguenots,
                    and by his dashing bravery kept life in their dispirited forces. No man was
                    better fitted for such work; he had all the equalities of a guerilla leader,
                    though he was not a great general. His success at Coutras (1587) and the
                    joyousness and generosity of his character endeared him to his followers, while
                    it secured the respect even of his opponents. After the death of Henry III. he
                    was recognized as king of France by only a portion of the army then besieging
                    Paris (August 4, 1589); the Catholic “Politiques” in the army stood aloof and
                    disbanded; the Huguenots formed the only sound nucleus of his power. At Arques
                    (1589) and Ivry (1590) he brilliantly defeated the Leaguers, and resumed the
                    siege of Paris; Alexander of Parma, however, prevented him from taking Rouen
                    (1592); much less could he take Paris. Finding affairs hard, and desiring to be
                    a king and not a guerilla-captain, in 1593 Henry allowed himself to be converted
                    to Catholicism. By this step he struck a deadly blow at the League and made
                    powerless the intrigues of Philip II. For between the fanatical Catholics on one
                    side and the Huguenots on the other lay the great bulk of Frenchmen; the
                    “Politique” party had become more and more powerful, until at length it was felt
                    to be the true national party. The only thing which kept it from Henry was the
                    difference of faith; that barrier removed, all France at once joyfully accepted
                    him as king. The Leaguers became almost a foreign body; the Huguenots gloomily
                    accepted his triumph, bought, as they held, at cost of principle. After the
                    battle of Fontaine-Française in 1595 the Spanish and Leaguers were driven out of
                    Burgundy, and the recovery of Amiens from the Spaniards in 1596 secured Picardy
                    and the northern frontier. The <hi rend="italic">Satire Menippee,</hi> published
                    in 1593 and 1594, had already condemned the Leaguers as hirelings of the Spanish
                    king; and in April 1598 by the edict of Nantes Henry assured their position to
                    his old Huguenot followers, while by the peace of Vervins (May 1598) he ended
                    the Spanish war, and took from the League its last source of strength.</p>
                <p>After 1598 the energies of Henry IV. were given to the restoration of his
                    country, which in nearly forty years of civil war had suffered terribly; the
                    organizing genius of Maximilian of Bethune, duke of Sully, restored the
                    finances; agriculture, manufactures, and commerce made marvellous advances.
                    Henry also upheld the authority of France; in 1601 he acquired Bresse, Bugey,
                    and Valromey from Savoy. He supported the Netherlands against Spain, and he was
                    preparing a great army, which, in combination with the Dutch under Maurice of
                    Nassau, was to interfere in the tangled Cleves-Juliers question, when he was
                    assassinated by Ravaillac on the 14th of May 1610. For his character see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">France,</hi> vol. ix. p. 566.</p>
                <p>Henry IV. left no children by his first wife Margaret of Valois; by his second,
                    Marie de’ Medici, he had three sons and three daughters,—Louis, who succeeded
                    him as Louis XIII.; a child who died in 1611; Gaston, duke of Orleans, the
                    meanest of the race; Elizabeth, wife of Plιilip IV. king of Spain; Christine,
                    wife of Victor Amadeus, duke of Savoy; and lastly Henriette Marie, queen of
                    England, spouse of Charles I. He also left behind him several natural children,
                    of whom the most celebrated was César, duke of Vendôme, son of the famous
                    Gabrielle d’Estrées.</p>
                <p>See Pierre ΓEstoile, <hi rend="italic">Journal du règne de Henri</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">IV.</hi>; Péréfixe, <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">du</hi><hi rend="italic">roi Henri</hi><hi rend="italic">le
                    Grand</hi>; Xivrey, <hi rend="italic">Recueil des lettres missives de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Henri IV.</hi> (1839-53); Palma Cayet, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronologie novennaire;</hi><hi rend="italic">Mémoires de Tavanmes;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires de Vieilleville</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires de</hi><hi rend="italic">Castelnau·,</hi> Sully, <hi
                    rend="italic">(Economies royales</hi>; Cimber and Danjou, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Archives curieuses</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Art de
                    vérifier les dates,</hi> série ii. tom. vi. The reader is also referred to the
                    documents cited by Von Ranke in his <hi rend="italic">Französische
                    Geschichte,</hi> and to Olivier de Serres’s <hi rend="italic">Théâtre
                    d'agriculture et</hi><hi rend="italic">mesnage des champs.</hi> (G. W. K. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
