<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0784-0749-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERMES (9th edition, volume 11, page 749)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888385">Dead</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175820">Winds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896265">Dogs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0743s">Winds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd61">Dog</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n784/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERMES</label> is the name of a Greek god (corresponding to
                    the Roman Mercury) whose origin and real character are perhaps more difficult to
                    define than is the case with any other Greek deity; here it is possible only to
                    give an outline of one definite theory, and refer the reader to the works quoted
                    at the end. He was not a god worshipped by the pure Doric or Ionic races, but is
                    found in most places where Aeolian, Achaean, and Pelasgic tribes can be traced.
                    If we begin with the rudest races, summed up generally under the title of
                    Pelasgic, we find Hermes often connected with the mysterious Cabiri. These
                    deities, in the accounts we have, vary in number and sex, being sometimes two,
                    sometimes three or four. We may conclude that originally they were a pair, male
                    and female, whom we may compare with Uranus and Gaea, or with Cronus and Rhea.
                    Often the female is doubled, as mother and daughter, resembling the relation of
                    Demeter and Persephone; while the male also is transformed either into twin
                    brothers, or into a father and his son by one of the female deities. Certainly
                    the male deity seems sometimes to be regarded as Hermes, sometimes as Hephaestus
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Hephaestus),</hi> while in other places the two are
                    associated. Hermes and Hephaestus are perhaps local varieties of one type, which
                    after having acquired distinct individuality in their separate homes were
                    brought beside each other by subsequent intercourse. Hence we may understand how
                    the epithet &lt;xγγ∈λoς and the office of messenger between gods and men, which
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Pig Veda</hi> belong to Agni, the fire, are in Greek
                    mythology attached to Hermes. This Pelasgic Hermes is an ithyphallic deity, the
                    god of fertility and reproductive power, and bestower of riches in flocks and
                    herds. Corresponding to this religious conception we have in mythology such
                    epithets as ∈pιoυvιoς, <hi rend="italic">ίκάκητα,</hi> &amp;c.; and in the hymn
                    to Aphrodite (written perhaps in Aeolis in the 9th century B.c.), Hermes and the
                    Sileni (Latin <hi rend="italic">Silvani)</hi> are the companions of the mountain
                    nymphs. So in Arcadia, one of the chief seats of his worship, where on Cyllene
                    his birthplace was shown, he was by Penelope the father of Pan. Penelope, the
                    “torch-eyed” (Ahrens in <hi rend="italic">Philol.,</hi> 1879, p. 205), is a form
                    of Athene, Odysseus of Hermes; and Hermes and Athene are associated as
                    Hephaestus with Athene in Attica. In the very mixed Attic people, it is not
                    surprising to find the worship of Hermes widespread; it is sometimes said to
                    have been introduced from Samothrace. In Athens Hermes is the god of social life
                    and intercourse in general, of streets and doorways, and of the palaestra. He is
                    worshipped as αγοραίος and <hi rend="italic">πρoπνλαιoς</hi>; and Hermae,
                    pillars supporting a bearded head and furnished with a phallus, stood all over
                    the city. In Boeotia also we find Hermes, especially at Tanagra, where Hermes
                    the champion, and Hermes <hi rend="italic">κρωψόρος,</hi> the averter of
                    diseases, were worshipped. The Doric god Apollo, with the titles Agyieus and
                    Paion, corresponds most closely to these last aspects of Hermes. As god of
                    social intercourse he easily grows into the impersonation of cleverness, and at
                    last into the patron of thieves. If we pass from religion to mythology, where we
                    find all the successive ways of expressing views of nature preserved to us side
                    by side, we find an immense variety of traditions. The most common subject in
                    these tales is the struggle between darkness and light. When it is said that
                    Hermes stole the oxen of Apollo, and after killing two of them nailed their
                    skins on a rock, we have one of a class of myths described at length by Kuhn <hi
                        rend="italic">(Entwickelungsstufen der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Mythologie).</hi> The slain animal is the sun, who is killed every evening;
                    and the hide, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the sky of night, is either hung up
                    on the tree of heaven (as is the Golden Fleece) or fastened with the starheaded
                    nails. Again, when Io, the moon, is watched by the hundred-eyed Argus (Sanskrit
                        <hi rend="italic">rajas,</hi> “darkness”), the star-studded sky, Hermes
                    slays Argus with a stone, the same which Cadmus and Jason use, viz., the rising
                    sun. In both cases Hermes is the sun-god as hidden during the night away among
                    the souls of the dead; hence the Chthonian character <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n785/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0785-0750"/> so frequently attached to him. The rod with
                    which he lulls men to sleep is the same sceptre that the ruler of the dead, Yama
                    or Rhadamanthus, Minos or Hades, always bears (Kuhn in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Zft.,</hi> iv. p. 123); he is also the sender of dreams; we find him
                    worshipped among the Chthonian deities at Cnidus, and on vases accompanied by
                    the Chthonian dog. We are now able to understand a fact which is perhaps the
                    most interesting point connected with Hermes. Kuhn first pointed out the
                    identity of the Greek 'Ep/z·etas with the Sanskrit Sârameyas, and though the
                    connexion has been doubted by various writers, as Mannhardt <hi rend="italic"
                        >[Wald-und Feld-Kulte,</hi> ii. pref.) and others, yet no valid objection
                    has ever been offered on etymological grounds (see Benfey in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Abhandl. Gott. Ges.,</hi> 1877). Amid the difficulties which still envelop
                    the translation and the mythology of the Vedas, it is, however, even more
                    difficult to discover the original character of the two Sârameyau and their
                    mother Saramâ, than it is to determine the nature of Hermes. The two Sârameyau
                    are mentioned twice in the <hi rend="italic">Rig Veda</hi> (vii. 55; x. 14);
                    they are two dogs, are said both to guard the way to the abode of the dead and
                    refuse a passage to the impious, and also to act as the messengers of Yama,
                    carrying away the souls when the time of death has arrived. Saramâ also seems to
                    be regarded as the messenger or the dog of Indra; and Hermes appears regularly
                    as the companion and helper of all the light-heroes on their adventures. One
                    epithet of these dogs is Çarvara, spotted, which in its Greek form Cerberus
                    (Benfey, <hi rend="italic">Vedica,</hi> p. 149) is the name of the dog that
                    guards the gate of the lower world. Now we find in Rome that two <hi
                        rend="italic">lares</hi><hi rend="italic">proestites,</hi> children of
                    Mercury and Egeria, are said to guard dwellings and streets in the form of dogs;
                    and in the German legend the dog who attends the wild huntsman Wuotan, <hi
                        rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the sun hidden during the seven winter months, is
                    closely related to the dwarfs or spirits of the dead, and is called by their
                    name (Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">Westf.</hi><hi rend="italic">Sagen,</hi> i. p.
                    69c). So Hermes, whom we have seen as king of the dead, is as <hi rend="italic"
                        >ψυχοπομπός</hi> also the conductor of souls to their future home; we may
                    therefore count the dog (or dogs) as ultimately identical in character with the
                    king of the dead. Sonne (on Charis in Kuhn’s <hi rend="italic">Zft.,</hi> x.)has
                    pointed out how these primitive conceptions commonly pass through the stage of
                    animals before reaching that of gods; and in mythology we have the two stages
                    preserved side by side as distinct beings. The Hindu Kubera, lord of the
                    treasures of the lower world, who may be identified with Pluto or with Hermes,
                    is styled “Lord of the hosts of the Sârameyas.”</p>
                <p>In this account there has been no room left for the idea of Hermes as connected
                    with the wind. The sun, after he has set at night, is the same as the sun hidden
                    during the dreary months of winter, who then rides abroad in the tempest. The
                    wind is then easily conceived as his servant and messenger, and is often
                    considered to carry away the souls of the dead (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Harpies).</hi> From his connexion with the wind, Hermes is represented with
                    winged shoes. But with Roscher <hi rend="italic">(Hermes der</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Wind-Gott)</hi> to see in Hermes simply the wind is to take a
                    narrow view and to ignore the character of primitive Aryan thought.</p>
                <p>In art, besides the Hermae already described, Hermes is in the archaic time
                    represented as a man with pointed beard, wearing a chlamys and the broad hat
                    called petasus; his symbols are the staff <hi rend="italic">(κηρυκeιοv)</hi> and
                    the winged shoes (talaria). The ideal type of Hermes was probably modelled after
                    the statue by Praxiteles in the Heraion at Olympia. This statue, which was
                    recently discovered by the German expedition, represented the god leaning with
                    his left arm on a rock and supporting on it the infant Bacchus. The right arm,
                    which is lost, probably held the caduceus. The form shows a perfect combination
                    of agility and strength.</p>
                <p>See the works on mythology or religion by Weicker, Gerhard, Rinek, Stuhr,
                    Schwenck, 0. Müller, Eckermann, H. D. Müller, Lauer, Schwartz, Max Müller,
                    Preller, Hartung, Braun, Maury, &amp;c.; also Lehrs, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pοpulαrische</hi><hi rend="italic">Aufsätze</hi>; Schümann, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ηesiοd. Theog.;</hi> Gottling in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hermes,</hi> xxix.; Mehlis, <hi rend="italic">Grundidee</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">des Hermes</hi>; Myri-antheus, <hi rend="italic">Açvins</hi>;
                    Haupt in <hi rend="italic">Ζft. f. Alterth.,</hi> 1842; Oestermann, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hermes-Odysseus·,</hi> H.D. Müllerin <hi rend="italic"
                        >Philologus,</hi> xiv.; Kuhn in Haupt’s <hi rend="italic">Zft. f D.
                        Alterth.,</hi> vi.; Von Hahn, <hi rend="italic">Sagwissensch.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Studien·,</hi> Roscher, <hi rend="italic">Hermes.</hi> As
                    usual, the fullest list of ancient authorities is to be found in Jacobi, <hi
                        rend="italic">Handwörterbuch der Mythologie.</hi> (W. Μ. RA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
