<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0658-0625-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEINE, Heinrich (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    625)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p104">Messiah</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n658/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HEINE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Heinrich</hi></label>
                    (1799-1856), poet and journalist, was born, according to the most trustworthy
                    accounts, on the 13th December 1799, at Diisseldorf, of Jewish parents. His
                    father, after various vicissitudes in business, had finally settled in that
                    town, and his mother, who seems to have possessed much energy of character, was
                    the daughter of a physician of the same place. Heine received the rudiments of
                    his education at the gymnasium or <hi rend="italic">lycee</hi> (as it was called
                    during the foreign occupation) of his native town, and, although not an
                    especially apt or diligent pupil, he acquired while there a good knowledge of
                    French and English,—he tells us that <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi>
                    in the original was one of the favourite books of his childhood,—as well as some
                    tincture of the classics and Hebrew. But if the influence upon him of his
                    teachers and their teaching was unimportant, not so that of the public events
                    amid which he grew up. His early years coincided with the most brilliant period
                    of Napoleon’s career; and the boundless veneration which he is never tired of
                    expressing for the emperor throughout his writings shows that his true
                    schoolmasters were rather the drummers and troopers of a victorious army than
                    the Jesuit fathers of the <hi rend="italic">lycee;</hi> while, if to the vivid
                    personal impression produced upon him by the pomp and circumstance of the
                    imperial garrison in his birthplace there be added the public, and in a manner
                    national, enthusiasm for Napoleon which he must often have heard vented by his
                    elder co-religionists—who hailed the conqueror as a temporal Messiah—the weighty
                    bearing of his boyhood upon his subsequent fortunes becomes fully apparent. Upon
                    his quitting school, attempts were made to engage him in commerce, but his
                    father and uncle, the latter a wealthy banker of Hamburg, soon perceived that he
                    was bent upon travelling a different path from that which they had followed. It
                    speaks well for both these men that they should have refrained from coercion
                    upon making this discovery; and Solomon Heine, the banker, at once gave his
                    nephew an earnest of the generous treatment the latter was subsequently to
                    experience at his hands, for he came forward with money to enable his young
                    kinsman to go to a university, his sole stipulation being that his protégé
                    should study with the view of entering the legal profession. Heine gladly
                    accepted his uncle’s terms, and entered the university of Bonn in the spring of
                    1819. During his stay there he was an eager student; but the subjects to which
                    he devoted himself had no connexion with the profession which had been chosen
                    for him. He seems to have attended no lectures save those on literature and
                    history—notably A. W. von Schlegel’s; and he not long afterwards acknowledged
                    his obligations to Schlegel by dedicating a sonnet to him—a tribute which he
                    recalled in later days by a wanton and outrageous attack upon the veteran critic
                    in <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Romantische Schule.</hi> Why
                    Heine left Bonn does not clearly appear, but it is at Göttingen that we find him
                    in the autumn of 1820. His stay here was even shorter than at Bonn. In February
                    1821 the authorities of the “Georgia Augusta” rusticated him for some infraction
                    of the duelling laws. Although from these beginnings Heine’s academical career
                    promised to pursue no very even course, he nevertheless determined, after his
                    residence at Göttingen had been cut short, to seek a third university; and it
                    was to Berlin that he now repaired, where Hegel was at the zenith of his renown.
                    Whether or not the lectures of this philosopher benefited him in any way —by
                    giving him, for instance, as some have supposed, a certain dialectical precision
                    of style—he has himself confessed that he seldom understood them; and in after
                    years Hegel’s ultra-conservatism and orthodoxy made him the constant butt of his
                    former pupil’s ridicule and sarcasm. But the interest of Heine’s life in Berlin
                    was social and not academic. He enjoyed the privilege of mixing in the best
                    literary circles of the capital. He was on terms of intimacy with Varnhagen von
                    Ense and his wife, the celebrated Jewess, Rahel, and at their house—the
                    rendezvous of Germany’s geuius and learning—he frequently met such men as the
                    Humboldts, Hegel himself, and Schleiermacher; while he lived on a still more
                    familiar footing with a number of his own co-religionists, who, without having
                    acquired European reputation, were men of varied and approved abilities. In an
                    atmosphere of such geniality as this his gifts were rapidly displayed. He began
                    ere long to contribute poems to the <hi rend="italic">Berliner</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Gesellschafter,</hi> many of which were subsequently
                    incorporated in the <hi rend="italic">Buch der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Lieder,</hi> and in 1822 a volume came from the press entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Gedichte</hi><hi rend="italic">von Heinrich Heine,</hi> his
                    first avowed act of authorship. He was still further employed at this time as
                    the correspondent of a Rhenish newspaper, as well as in completing his tragedies
                        <hi rend="italic">Almansor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">William Ratcliff,</hi>
                    which were published in 1823 with small success. He was now, indeed, fairly
                    embarked upon his literary course. But he was still largely dependent upon his
                    uncle; and in order so far to fulfil his engagements tow ards his benefactor, he
                    returned to Göttingen in 1825, and shortly afterwards took his degree in law,
                    having previously qualified himself for practice by publicly professing
                    Christianity.</p>
                <p>This act of “apostasy,” as it has been called, calls for something more than a
                    mere passing reference; for it not <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n659/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0659-0626"/> only laid Heine open to contumely while
                    alive, but has provoked adverse criticism of special severity since his death.
                    That he was guilty of “apostasy” is no doubt verbally true; but there are two
                    circumstances in this connexion which should always be remembered. The one is
                    that Heine was wholly wanting in the religious sense—that he never was a Jew
                    save nominally and by the accident of birth —so that he cannot, with any real
                    propriety, be said to have forsaken the creed of his race; the other, that his
                    family, by encouraging him to adopt a profession which could not be entered
                    except by the gateway of “apostasy,” tacitly left him free to take that step. In
                    short, Heine’s “apostasy” was a purely secular act; and, although there will
                    doubtless be found many to stigmatize him all the more blackly for this very
                    reason, candour appears rather to require that this change of faith, if such it
                    can be called, should be classed as one of his most venial offences, being the
                    plainly outward act of one who throughout life made himself peculiarly obnoxious
                    to the imputation of malice and bad-heartedness.</p>
                <p>Heine seems never to have made any serious attempt to practise law. His life from
                    the year 1826 until his death was devoted entirely to literature, and more
                    especially to journalism, which alone indeed was the main source of his income
                    for many years. At first he lived in Hamburg, and then it was that, besides the
                        <hi rend="italic">Buch der Lieder,</hi> the earlier portions of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Reisebilder</hi> appeared, both of which, but particularly the
                    latter, at once created an immense sensation throughout Germany, not only among
                    the youthful and enthusiastic, who found their own sentiments expressed by the
                    new writer with the happiest audacity, but amongst such dignified and <hi
                        rend="italic">ranges</hi> personages as Metternich and Gentz. In 1827 Baron
                    Cotta, the Bavarian publisher, offered Heine, who had risen at a bound into
                    celebrity, the joint-editorship of the <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Politische
                        Annalen.</hi> The young author accepted the offer, and betook himself to
                    Munich in the winter of that year, after having paid a visit to London, where he
                    found every person and everything detestable save Canning and his policy—and it
                    may be said here in passing that a most violent hatred of England forms a marked
                    feature of all Heine’s writings. He remained for a considerable period in the
                    South-German capital, and it was owing, not to any disagreement with his
                    employer, but to the demands of the court of Prussia, which was not long of
                    taking umbrage at his freedom of opinion, that his editorial function ceased so
                    abruptly as it did. What the secret history of the next two or three years of
                    his life was— whether from the very first he really was an object of especial
                    disfavour at Berlin, or whether, as is quite as likely, taking his vanity and
                    love of publicity into account, he exaggerated his powers of offence beyond the
                    endurance of the Government there, and forced it into what seemed a petty
                    persecution—he presently perceived that he must either quit Germany altogether
                    or prepare for a life-time perhaps of fortress-imprisonment. He did not long
                    hesitate between these two alternatives; and on the 1st of May 1831 Heinrich
                    Heine left his native land for Paris, where he lived for the rest of his life,
                    only once recrossing the Rhine, in 1843.</p>
                <p>Just as his adoption of Christianity ha3 led to Heine’s being pronounced
                    “apostate,” so has his self-expatriation caused German writers to denounce him
                    as “renegade.” But the one accusation is as groundless as the other. In the
                    first place Heine was a Jew, in spite of his Christianization, and cannot
                    therefore rightly be called a “renegade” against Germany—least of all when the
                    degraded social and political status of his race in that country at the date Df
                    his emigration is recollected. Then again his writings were systematically
                    subjected to the cruellest mutilations, and it is tolerably certain that had he
                    remained in the “Fatherland,” he would sooner or later have been deprived of all
                    power of public speech. Was it any wonder, seeing that he had adopted the
                    profession of letters, that he should have turned his back upon such a prospect?
                    He at any rate was the best judge; and it ill becomes Germans to call him
                    “renegade,” when, had he continued to tarry among them, their literature would
                    probably have suffered an irreparable loss. At the same time, and for the same
                    reasons, it is equally inept to assert that he was in the essential qualities of
                    his mind a Frenchman who gravitated towards Paris by a sort of intellectual
                    necessity. The necessity (to use that word) was physical. Heine would never have
                    left Germany could he have freely expressed his opinions there.</p>
                <p>After settling in his new home, where his life for many years must have been as
                    gay and brilliant as latterly it was sad and sombre, and where he speedily
                    became more or less intimate with such writers as Balzac, Dumas the elder,
                    George Sand, Victor Hugo, and Théophile Gautier, Heine devoted himself more
                    exclusively than ever to journalism; and from 1831 until 1847, he was an active
                    and indefatigable publicist. The two series of papers entitled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Französische Zustände</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lutetia</hi> contain a
                    selection from his press-contributions during these years; and even at this date
                    they well repay perusal, not only by the brilliancy of wit and elegance of style
                    which they possess in common with almost all his writings, but also by the
                    remarkable sagacity of their political <hi rend="italic">aperçus.</hi> Alongside
                    of this main stream of journalism, he also kept up a subsidiary current of
                    literature in its more proper sense—although it may be said that all his
                    writings are of an occasional nature—and to this we owe the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Salon</hi> (1833-39), which comprises among other pieces a series of
                    articles, “Zur Geschichte der Religion und Philosophie in Deutschland,” which
                    had originally appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Revτιe des deux Mondes,</hi>
                    and in which Heine came forward as the introducer of German thought to the
                    reading world of Paris. The <hi rend="italic">Salon</hi> also contains several
                    admirable papers in art-criticism, and a strange, fragmentary medley of
                    sentiment and satire, iu its author’s most characteristic vein—“Die
                    Florentinische Nächte.” To this period, too, belongs <hi rend="italic"
                        >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Romantische Schule,</hi> to which reference has
                    already been made, and the substance of which is sufficiently indicated by its
                    name. In 1839 <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare’s</hi><hi rend="italic">Mädchen
                        und</hi><hi rend="italic">Frauen</hi> appeared— Heine acting in this slight
                    work as cicerone through a gallery of Shakespeare’s heroines. The year 1840 was
                    signalized by the publication of <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Heine uber Ludwig
                        Borne,</hi> a brochure of the wittiest and most trenchant satire, in which
                    the German refugees in Paris—a fraternity whom Heine always anxiously
                    avoided—were far more severely handled than was the defunct agitator whose name
                    it bore, and who, it may be noted, was himself a Jew. In 1844 <hi rend="italic"
                        >Deutschland, ein</hi><hi rend="italic">Wintermärchen,</hi> came forth—the
                    result of the visit to Germany which has been alluded to as the sole journey of
                    the kind which Heine undertook; and this effusion may be ranked, along with a
                    similar performance, <hi rend="italic">Atta Troll</hi> (1846), as belonging to
                    his most inferior writings. It was in 1848 that Heine, in the very hey-day of
                    his activity, and with gigantic projects seething within him for the foundation
                    of a journal, was suddenly prostrated by the disease which finally carried him
                    off, though not before it had confined him for seven years upon the
                    “mattress-grave” of mournful notoriety. His sufferings throughout that time are
                    reported to have been frequently excruciating, and he at length grew so
                    habituated to the use of opium that the very largest doses failed to afford him
                    relief. But when his malady—a softening of the spinal cord—allowed him a
                    respite, his intellect was as clear and vivacious as ever; and it is to these
                    closing years of his life, harassing as they were, that we are indebted for the
                    finest and most finished of all his poems—for the two collections, that is to
                    say, <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n660/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0660-0627"/><hi rend="italic">Romanzero</hi> (1851) and
                        <hi rend="italic">Neτιeste</hi><hi rend="italic">Gedichte</hi> (1853-54), as
                    well as for the various pieces posthumously published in <hi rend="italic">H.
                        Heine's</hi><hi rend="italic">Letzte Gedichte und Gedanken.</hi> It was from
                    his “mattress-grave” too that the dying man put forth his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geständnisse</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Confessions,</hi> the psychological
                    interest of which is very great, whatever their claim to trustworthiness may be.
                    Heine bore the misery of his protracted death-bed with fortitude, nay, with
                    cheerfulness, assiduously attended by his wife Mathilde, and towards the end by
                    that mysterious lady whom he called “Die Mouche,” and who was, it now appears, a
                    Madame Krinitz; and there are many anecdotes on record of his bearing in the
                    midst of his trials—and heavier trials seldom fell to the lot of man—which go
                    far to prove that he possessed a healthy <hi rend="italic">fond gaillard,</hi>
                    for which his writings are scarcely likely to gain him credit. He died on the
                    17th February 1856 in Paris, in the Rue d’Amsterdam, and lies buried in the
                    cemetery of Montmartre.</p>
                <p>We have called Heine “poet and journalist”; but his reputation has, naturally
                    enough, now come to rest almost exclusively upon his poetry, and above all upon
                    his songs —the <hi rend="italic">Buch der Lieder</hi> having passed through
                    upwards of twenty-five editions. This great popularity may no doubt (and
                    especially in foreign countries) be attributable, to a certain extent, to the
                    singular good fortune which has wedded to very many of these songs the music of
                    such composers as Schumann and Mendelssohn. But still, when all deiuctions upon
                    this score are made,—and the true view of the matter probably is that the poet
                    and his composers are mutually obliged,—the fact remains that Heine is one of
                    the great song-writers of the world, not unworthy of a place beeide Burns and
                    Béranger, although far less masculine and passionate than the one, and far less
                    jovial and debonair than the other. The intense individualism which prevented
                    him from ever becoming a literary artist in any other department—his dramas and
                    essays in fiction are worthless—stood him in excellent stead in the lyric field,
                    —was a positive and essential strength indeed, for, after all, a song to appeal
                    to men’s hearts must be an utterance of personal experience. And this condition
                    is amply fulfilled in the <hi rend="italic">Buch der Lieder,</hi> the greater
                    portion of which was the direct outcome of a sentiment entertained by the poet
                    for one of his cousins—a sentiment, by the way, which has been alluded to by
                    German writers as a mere <hi rend="italic">Cousinen-</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >schivärmerei,</hi> while others (not Germans) have affirmed that all
                    Heine’s bitterness and cynicism in after life arose from its hiving remained
                    unrequited. On the whole, Heine as a song-writer is a fit descendant of Walther
                    von der Vogelweide and those old <hi rend="italic">Minnesänger</hi> who of yore
                    assembled in the halls of princes, and recounted their sorrows and their joys—of
                    those nameless bards, too, who sang the <hi rend="italic">Volkslieder</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> and when all his other writings are forgotten, he will
                    be remembered by such imperishable gems as “Die Rose, die Lilie, die Taube, die
                    Sonne;” “Auf Flügeln des Gesanges ;” and “Du bist wie eine Blume.” There is
                    much, too, of great beauty in many of his ballads and narrative pieces; witness
                    among others, “Spanische Atriden,” “Die Prinzessin Sabbat,” “Jehuda-ben-Halevy,”
                    “Böses Geträume”—a piece of the most exquisite path03 and simplicity—and “Die
                    Insel Bimini.” But too often, no matter how sweet a chord is struck at the
                    beginning, a dissonance creeps in, to end in a crashing discord, and the
                    outraged reader starts like one who should suddenly see Romeo and Juliet fall to
                    grimacing and squeaking like Punch and Judy. Heine’s confession that poetry was
                    no more than his “holy plaything” would have been entitled to our unqualified
                    acceptance had he omitted the adjective.</p>
                <p>But when we turn to his prose-writings—to his “journalism, ’ that is to say, for,
                    as we have remarked, almost all his prose falls under this category, in its
                    widest acceptation —we see the man Heine indeed, not perhaps, as he was
                    ambitious of being regarded by posterity, in the full panoply of a “soldier of
                    human emancipation,” but at any rate as no contemptible assailant of
                    obscurantism and philistinism. Beside such a redoubtable champion of the
                    catholic reason of mankind as Lessing “of theponderous battle-axe,” he looks
                    somewhat small, it is true, and his rapier somewhat gim-crack. But ridicule will
                    often reach whither heavier weapons cannot, and pierce the elephantine hide of
                    pedantry and dulness, after these have been attacked in vain by battering-rams;
                    and Heine was a master of it. The worst is that in unscrupulous hands—and no one
                    was more unscrupulous than he—it may be turned to illegitimate uses, and come to
                    be indulged in finally for its own sake. How easily Heine became the slave of
                    his propensity in this direction may be seen in the two works—which seem his
                    best and most characteristic writings, notwithstanding— <hi rend="italic">Zur
                        Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic">Religion</hi><hi rend="italic">und
                        Philosophie in Deutschland</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Die Romantische
                        Schule.</hi> Both these abound in the most irreverent passages, especially
                    the former, wherein such philosophers as Kant, Fichte, and Schelling scarcely
                    serve a higher purpose than to be used as pegs whereon the writer may hang his
                    jests. And admirable these are. Nothing can be better, for instance, than his
                    account of how Kant (who is parenthetically described as a man whom Nature
                    intended to sell coffee and sugar across a counter) came to postulate a Deity in
                    his practical, after having exploded that idea in his theoretical, system. He
                    did this, says Heine (most adroitly hitting one of the chief <hi rend="italic"
                        >opprobria,</hi> scientifically regarded, of the critical philosophy), for
                    the sake of his old man-servant Lampe, who looked so dismally at the conclusions
                    of the Pure Reason that the philosopher was moved to compassion! The <hi
                        rend="italic">Romantische Schule,</hi> being concerned for the most part
                    with its author’s contemporaries, is far more virulent than the treatise just
                    mentioned, but equally happy; and it aimed a death-blow at a school which
                    rivalled the wildest and most licentious ravings of a Monk Lewis and the most
                    stilted horrors of an Ann Radcliff. And here it may be said, in connexion with
                    the attack upon Schlegel occurring in this essay, that Heine’s onslaughts were
                    always open and above-board, unmerciful and sometimes grossly brutal as they
                    were. He was a literary swashbuckler, it may be (though that term is singularly
                    inapplicable to one who wrote in such a style), but he was neither a literary
                    assassin nor a literary ghoul. Even his attack upon Börne was really aimed, as
                    we have said, at men who were alive to resent it; and it was resented, though
                    from a strange quarter. Börne’s widow’s husband challenged Heine, and the latter
                    was slightly wounded in the encounter.</p>
                <p>Of the <hi rend="italic">Reisebilder,</hi> Heine’s most voluminous and best-known
                    prose work, and that which originally gave him fame, small space remains to
                    speak. But if we except its first and third books, it has been greatly
                    overrated. It is easy to understand the popularity it acquired upon its first
                    appearance, falling as it did like a breath of genuine life upon a land
                    well-nigh asphyxiated by high art and the “Hübsch-Objectiv ”—but nowadays,
                    notwithstanding its undoubted mirth-provoking qualities, it chiefly serves to
                    point out the gulf which was fixed between its author and him who took the <hi
                        rend="italic">Sentimental Journey.</hi> The most that can be said for it is
                    that Sterne might have written it had he been a German Jew.</p>
                <p>The best edition of Heine’s works is that published by Hoffmann and Campe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Heinrich Heine's Sαmmtliche</hi><hi rend="italic">Werke,</hi>
                    20 vols., Hamburg, 1865. Another edition has appeared in America, <hi
                        rend="italic">Heinrich Heine's</hi><hi rend="italic">Sämmtliche Werke,</hi>
                    in 7 vols. <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Heine's</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben,</hi>
                    by Adolph Strodtmann, Berlin, 1870, is the only Life of Heine entitled to
                    consideration, although the pleasure of reading it is certainly marred by its
                    length. A biography of the poet has also appeared in England, <hi rend="italic"
                        >L·ife and Opinions of Heinrich Heine,</hi> by W. Stιgand, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n661/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0661-0628"/> 1876. Mr Matthew Arnold has, in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Essays in Criticism,</hi> handled Heine with his accustomed
                    grace and felicity. Mention may also be made of <hi rend="italic">Wit, Wisdom,
                        and Pathos of</hi><hi rend="italic">Heinrich</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Heine,</hi> by J. Snodgrass, London, 1879, a collection of extracts from
                    Heine’s works in an English dress. A translation, <hi rend="italic">Heine's
                        Poems, Complete,</hi> by Edgar A. Bowring, C.B., was issued in Bohn’s
                    Standard Library. His prose works have not as yet received adequate renderings,
                    although a version of the <hi rend="italic">Reisebilder</hi> has been put forth
                    in America. (J. W. F. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
