<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0847-0810-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HIGH PLACE (9th edition, volume 11, page 810)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806095">Altars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jq0sv10">Altars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HIGH PLACE</label> is the rendering invariably given in the
                    authorized English version of the Old Testament Scriptures to a Hebrew word HÇ3
                    of uncertain derivation but with much plausibility connected by Gesenius with
                    the IndoGermanic root which appears in the Persian <hi rend="italic">bam</hi>
                    (roof, summit), and in the Greek <hi rend="italic">βω</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >∣</hi><hi rend="italic">H&gt;&lt;s</hi> (compare <hi rend="italic"
                        >βηpα,</hi> Doric <hi rend="italic">βiipα).</hi> By the LXX. the word is
                    sometimes left untouched <hi rend="italic">(βαμA</hi> in 1 Sam. ix. 13 and
                    elsewhere); the prevalent rendering of the plural, when a translation is
                    hazarded at all, is in the Pentateuch &lt;m∕λ&lt;u, in the historical books τα
                        <hi rend="italic">υψηλά, τα</hi><hi rend="italic">υψη,</hi> and in the
                    prophetical writings <hi rend="italic">βωpol.</hi> The Vulgate invariably gives
                    either <hi rend="italic">excelsa</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fana.</hi> The habit
                    so widely diffused among primitive peoples of selecting the tops of mountains,
                    or at least elevated sites, as suitable from their comparative isolation from
                    the world and their supposed nearness to the sky for the erection of altars and
                    sacred pillars, is so obviously natural as to require no explanation. Along with
                    that of worshipping under trees or groves (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Grove),</hi>
                    it was fully participated in by the Israelites from an early period, and
                    continued to assert itself down to a very late date, as is abundantly shown by
                    the frequency with which <hi rend="italic">bamah</hi> and other words <hi
                        rend="italic">(liar, yib</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ah, ramaK)</hi> signifying height occur in connexion with
                    their public and private worship, whether Jehovistic or idolatrous. Thus one of
                    our earliest notices with regard to Abraham after his departure from Haran is
                    that after setting up a sanctuary at Sichem at the oak of Moreh, he “removed
                    unto a mountain on the east of Bethel, and there builded an altar unto the Lord”
                    (Gen. xii. 8). It was on a mountain (Ebal) that the first altar to Jehovah was
                    raised by Joshua after the conquest of Canaan had begun (Josh, viii. 30; <hi
                        rend="italic">cf.</hi> Deut, xxvii. 4, 5); and many other “high places,”
                    some of them (e.y., Beth-Shemesh, or Ir-Heres, and Ashtaro th Karnaim)
                    apparently taken over directly from the Canaanites, speedily obtained
                    recognition as sanctuaries. A few of these, such as Shiloh, early became
                    important pilgrimage centres, but this was not regarded as inconsistent with the
                    right of each town or village-community to have its own high place, or with the
                    view that Palestine as a whole was the “house” or peculiar territory of God, and
                    that it was therefore lawful on suitable occasions to erect new and extempore
                    altars or high places within its limits. For example, we find in 1 Sam. x., xL
                    repeated references made to the <hi rend="italic">bamαh</hi> of Samuel’s native
                    village as if it were a thing of course; from 2 Sam. xv. 32 (Hebt.) we gather
                    that even in David’s time the top of Mount Olivet was a place “where God was
                    wont to be worshipped ;” while at a later period we read of Elijah repairing the
                    altar on Mount Carmel that had been broken down, and complaining of the
                    violation of God’s covenant of which those persons had been guilty who had
                    thrown down the altars and slain the prophets (1 Kings xviii. 30; xix. 10, 14).
                    And we read of new altars, generally on high places, being set up by Gideon
                    (Judg. vi. 26, 27), by Manoah (Judg. xiii. 19, 20), and repeatedly by Saul (1
                    Sam. xiv. 35). The comparatively late author of the books of Kings expressly
                    states, on the one hand, that before the days of Solomon the people “sacrificed
                    in high places because there was no house built unto the name of the Lord” (1
                    Kings iii. 2), and, on the other hand, that after that king the high places were
                    removed neither by Asa (1 Kings xiv. 15), nor by Jehoshaphat (xxii. 44), Joash
                    (2 Kings xii. 3), Amaziah (xiv. 4), Uzziah (xv. 4), or Jotham (xv. 35). The
                    still later author of the books of Chronicles, indeed, states of Asa (2 Chr.
                    xiv. 5) and Jehoshaphat (xvii. 6) that they did take away the high places “out
                    of all the cities of Judah but this apparent contradiction can best be explained
                    if we assume that the chronicler is alluding only to those high places where
                    heathen deities were worshipped or idolatrous practices allowed, while the
                    earlier author had in view the Jehovistic high places which, during many of the
                    earlier reigns at least, were not discountenanced either in the northern or in
                    the southern kingdom. In reading such a passage as Amos vii. 9, it would be a
                    mistake to interpret it as meaning that the multiplicity of <hi rend="italic"
                        >bamoth</hi> was regarded as wrong in itself; the prophet’s zeal is directed
                    not against the places but against the cultus and the false value that was
                    attached to it. Hezekiah is the first monarch of whom in the earlier record we
                    read that with some risk to his popularity he removed the high places and altars
                    of Jehovah, and “said to Judah and Jerusalem, ye shall worship before this altar
                    in Jerusalem” (2 Kings xviii. 4 compared with xviii. 22). But it was not until
                    the reign of Josiah that the high places were finally repressed, not on the
                    ground of direct prophetic revelation, but on that of ħ strict written law. Even
                    then, however, a distinction was made between the “high places” of the southern
                    kingdom, sacred to Jehovah, and those of the northern, dedicated to a mixed
                    worship; the priests of the former were brought to Jerusalem, and, though not
                    allowed to officiate at the altar there, were permitted to share the priests’
                    portion along with their brethren, while those of the latter were put to death
                    (2 Kings xxiii. 8, 20). As for the altars built upon the high places, their
                    construe tion appears to have been regulated by the law provided for the case in
                    Ex. xx. 24, 25; very often <hi rend="italic">ma&lt;χeboth</hi> or pillars were
                    erected beside them (see Ex. xxiv. 4; Josh, xxiv. 26; <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi>
                    Isa. xix. 19; Hosea iii. 4); and sometimes they were enclosed in “houses” or
                    “temples” (1 Kings xii. 31, xiii. 32; Amos vii. 13). For the bearing of the
                    facts contained <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n848/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0848-0811"/> in this article on the criticism of the
                    Pentateuch and of its legislation, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Pentateuch.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
