<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0428-0409-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAMILCAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 409</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n428/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAMILCAR</label>. BARCA, the most illustrious of all the
                    Carthaginian generals and statesmen, next to his son, the great Hannibal. The
                    surname Barca is the same as the Hebrew <hi rend="italic">Barak,</hi> and
                    signifies “lightning.” It was in the eighteenth year of the First Punic War, 247
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> that Hamilcar first greatly distinguished
                    himself. He had been known before as a young officer of promise who had made
                    raids on the southern coasts of Italy in the neighbourhood of Locri and Cumae.
                    Suddenly he appeared with a squadron off the north-west of Sicily, and seized a
                    strong position on Mount Ercte, now known as Mount Pellegrino, near Palermo. He
                    had but a small force of mercenaries, which his military genius soon made into a
                    well-disciplined body of troops. For three years he maintained himself on Mount
                    Ercte, during which time the Romans were in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n429/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0429-0410"/> possession of the whole of Sicily with the
                    exception of the two strongholds of Drepanum and Lilybaeum, and these they were
                    blockading. They tried their utmost to drive Hamilcar from his position, but in
                    vain. At last he quitted his stronghold, and in 244 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> landed at Mount Eryx, on the western coast, now Mount S. Giuliano, 2
                    miles from the shore and about 6 from Drepanum. A famous temple of Venus crowned
                    the summit, and half-way up the slope was the city, which itself had the name of
                    Eryx. This Hamilcar seized and occupied. His object was to compel the Romans to
                    give up the blockade of Drepanum and Lilybaeum. They could not drive him out of
                    the town, and for two more years he held his position, keeping open his
                    communications by sea with the Carthaginian garrison of Drepanum. Hamilcar’s
                    chief difficulty was with his mercenaries, who were little better than savages
                    and without an idea of loyalty or good faith. Yet he continued to hold them well
                    in hand. It was a harassing and monotonous warfare, so much so that Polybius,
                    here our chief authority, compares it to a boxing match between two skilful
                    pugilists, the blows in which are delivered in such rapid succession that a
                    spectator could hardly see, much less describe them. The Romans, feeling it
                    necessary to make a supreme effort, in 242 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    equipped a fleet, under the command of the consul Lutatius Catulus, and
                    despatched it to the western shores of Sicily. The battle off the Aegates
                    followed, and the Roman victory decided the First Punic War in 241 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Peace had now to be concluded. The cession of Sicily
                    to the Romans was a matter of course. But though Hamilcar had to surrender the
                    island, he refused to comply with the Roman demand that his army should pass
                    under the yoke. The demand was not persisted in, and Hamilcar and his men were
                    allowed to embark from Lilybaeum for Africa.</p>
                <p>No sooner had peace been concluded than there broke out the so-called African or
                    Libyan War. It was a most formidable mutiny or insurrection. Hamilcar’s
                    mercenaries on their return looked for the pay which he had promised them, but
                    had not been able to furnish while he was cooped in within his lines on Mount
                    Eryx. The stupidity of the home Government soon caused trouble. The peace party
                    at Carthage, headed by Hanno, who hated Hamilcar, was foolish enough to raise a
                    dispute about the pay of the troops. The result wa3 a furious mutiny, which
                    Hanno, who was sent to quiet them, could not appease. The men to the number of
                    20,000 began to march on Carthage itself, and encamped near Tunis. The mutineers
                    were led by Spendiαs, a fugitive slave from Campania, and by Matho, an African
                    who had served with distinction under Hamilcar in Sicily. These two men incited
                    all the neighbouring tribes to rise against the dominion of Carthage. Carthage
                    itself was soon cut off from all communication with the interior. Hanno was
                    called to take the command, but it was only to meet with defeat and disaster.
                    The rebels surprised and captured his camp. The Government was now thoroughly
                    frightened, and begged Hamilcar to save them from the consequences of their own
                    folly. With a force of only 10,000 men he had to face what must now have grown
                    into a very formidable host. It would seem that his personal influence led many
                    of the rebels to return to his standard, and he was also skilful enough to
                    secure the friendship and aid of the Numidian sheiks. One especially, Naravas,
                    helped him very materially; and with his assistance he was able to achieve a
                    decisive victory over the mutineers. At last he so effectually hemmed in
                    Spendius within his camp near Tunis that the rebel leader was obliged to throw
                    himself on his mercy. With nine of his brother leaders he sought an interview
                    with Hamilcar. Hamilcar’s demand was the surrender of ten of the rebels, whom he
                    was to name himself. This being agreed, he seized Spendιus and his nine
                    companions, a proceeding which the mutineers furiously resented. But they were
                    soon surrounded and cut off to a man, to the number, it is said, of 40,000. The
                    war, which had lasted three years and four months, was now over in the year 238
                    B.c.</p>
                <p>One would have supposed that Hamilcar would be at once recognized as the right
                    man to direct the future policy of the state. But it was not so. Hanno’s party,
                    the peace party, was as shortsighted as ever, and actually dared to say that
                    Hamilcar had been the cause of the late war by having made promises which he was
                    not able to fulfil. But by this folly they injured and weake.∖ed themselves. The
                    patriotic party, the “Barcine faction,” as it was called by its opponents,
                    prevailed so far as to raise their leader to a position answering as nearly as
                    possible to a dictatorship among the Romans. Hamilcar was made commander-inchief
                    of the Carthaginian army in Africa, and invested with a power which could be
                    taken from him only by the popular assembly. He was still a young man, under
                    thirty years of age. For a short time he employed himself in overawing the
                    Numidian tribes bordering on Carthaginian territory, but his main object was to
                    form the nucleus of an efficient army out of his Libyan mercenaries. Meanwhile
                    he was maturing a great plan which soon afterwards on his own responsibility he
                    carried into execution, Spain was a country the coasts of which at least were
                    well known to the Carthaginians. Spaniards too had served among Hamilcar’s
                    troops. To Spain he decided to go; there, he felt sure, he could find material
                    for an army and abundant means of providing pay. He had now three sons, the
                    “lion’s brood,” as he called them, Hannibal, Hasdrubal, Mago. Wishing with all
                    his heart that they should be like minded with himself, he made the eldest,
                    Hannibal, then a little boy of nine, swear on the altar of the supreme
                    Carthaginian deity eternal hatred and enmity to Rome. This was just before he
                    left Carthage, probably in the spring of 236 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    Suddenly there came tidings to the home Government that their commander-in-chief
                    was, without their orders, carrying on war in Spain. He had, however, done his
                    work so thoroughly in Africa that the troublesome Numidian tribes were now
                    submissive to Carthage, and for the most part paid tribute. He never returned.
                    The last eight years of his life he devoted to the great work of reducing Spain
                    to a Carthaginian province. He penetrated into the interior of the country,
                    subduing some of the tribes by force of arms and drawing others into friendly
                    relations by negotiation. It was not to mere conquest that he aspired; he did
                    his best to win the good-will of the Spaniards and to attach them to Carthage.
                    Spain was to be a compensation to Carthage for the loss of Sicily and Sardinia.
                    But, above all, its possession was to be subordinate to Hamilcar’s great design
                    of some day renewing the war with Rome. For this he would have felt himself
                    prepared when, in addition to his Numidian cavalry, he had organized a force of
                    Spanish infantry. Had his life been prolonged, he would doubtless, as Livy says
                    (xxi. 2), have invaded Italy at the head of a Carthaginian army. What he
                    accomplished in Spain so much impressed the elder Cato, who less than half a
                    century afterwards saw the traces of his work, that he declared that there was
                    no king like Hamilcar Barca. In the prime of his years he fell in battle in 228
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> fighting, it would seem, somewhere between the
                    Tagus and the Douro. Spain was now left in the hands of his son-in-law
                    Hasdrubal. (w. j. <hi rend="smallcaps">b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
