<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0527-0496-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARTFORD (9th edition, volume 11, page 496)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n527/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARTFORD</label>, a city in the United States of North
                    America, in 41° 45' 59" N. lat., 72° 40' 45" W. long., is the eastern portion of
                    the town of the same name, the county seat of Hartford county, and the capital
                    of the State of Connecticut. It is situated on the west bank of the Connecticut
                    river, 60 miles from Long Island Sound, at the head of steamboat and sloop
                    navigation, and 100 miles N.E. of New York and 95 W.S,W. of Boston by rail. An
                    important centre of railway communication, it has also regular lines of
                    steamboats and packets, besides some 200 sailing craft engaged in the coasting
                    trade. The river is usually closed from the middle of December to the <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0528-0497"/> middle of March, and at the breaking up of
                    the ice in spring sometimes rises 29 feet. The city is intersected by the
                    sluggish and dirty Park river, which is spanned by 10 bridges. A covered toll
                    bridge, 1000 feet long, across the Connecticut river connects the city with East
                    Hartford. There are about 80 miles of streets, mostly lighted with gas, well
                    drained, and macadamized or paved, and running north-and-south or east-and-west
                    with considerable regularity. The city is for the most part compactly built of
                    brick, granite, and freestone,—the public buildings and those of many private
                    corporations being elegant and substantial. The old State-house, a Doric
                    edifice, completed in 1795, has become the city-hall, w hile the State, since
                    1879, occupies a capacious new building of white marble in the modern Gothic
                    style, costing over $3,100,000, and standing conspicuously in the midst of the
                    city on a slight elevation at the south side of Bushnell Park (a beautiful area
                    of 46 acres). There are also in the city three other public squares. Of the
                    seven cemeteries the most noteworthy is Cedar Hill, in the south-west part of
                    the town, comprising 268 acres. Wadsworth’s tower on Talcott mountain, to the
                    north-west, affords one of the finest views in New England. Hartford is a
                    healthy city, and its mean annual temperature is 50° Fahr. The area of the city
                    is 10 square miles; and the population in 1870 was 37,180, of whom 10,817 were
                    foreigners. A careful estimate of the population in 1879 gives nearly
                    50,000.</p>
                <p>The city is divided into 8 wards, and is governed by a mayor and 16 aidermen
                    elected biennially, and 32 councilmen elected annually. The water supply is from
                    four reservoirs in West Hartford, with a capacity of 1,208,450,367 gallons. In
                    1873 a free public bathinghouse was established. Since 1864 the city has had a
                    paid fire-department, and now has seven steam fire-engines and a fire-alarm
                    telegraph with 26 miles of wire. The total real estate and personal property in
                    the city assessed for taxation, October 1, 1878, was $44,001,245. The debt of
                    the town in 1879 was $1,298,158, and of the city $2,152,308.</p>
                <p>The principal business of the city is insurance. In 1879 there were 9 fire
                    insurance companies, with assets of $19,104,603; 8 life insurance companies,
                    with assets of $101,101,368; and 1 accident insurance company, with assets,
                    $1,170,163. There were 16 banks and trust companies, with an aggregate capital
                    of over $8,000,000, and 4 savings banks, with deposits, October 1, 1878,
                    amounting to $9,528,893. There are also, exclusive of railroads, 73 mechanical
                    and manufacturing corporations, though several of the larger ones have their
                    works in adjacent towns. These have a capital of $17,347,000, and some of them a
                    world-wide reputation, as the Colt Firearms Company, with works occupying
                    grounds of 123 acres reclaimed by an extensive dike along the Connecticut river.
                    They also include carpet, linen, and silk works, and a manufactory of edgetools.
                    The publication of books too is a considerable interest. A very important branch
                    of trade is the sale of leaf tobacco, which is the chief crop of the Connecticut
                    river valley.</p>
                <p>In 1879 there were 36 churches and 15 chapels of all denominations, including a
                    fine Jewish synagogue. Here, too, is the seat of the Roman Catholic bishop, and
                    the headquarters, in the United States, of the Chinese educational commission.
                    Beside the 17 public schools and school-houses, which have cost $1,032,000, and
                    with their 163 teachers and 7680 pupils cost about $200,000 a year, there were
                    in 1879 43 educational and charitable corporations, several of them of notable
                    importance, especially Trinity College (Episcopal), founded in 1823 as
                    Washington College, which now has beautiful and commodious buildings in the
                    south part of the city; the Theological Institute of Connecticut
                    (Congregational), founded in 1834; the Hartford high and grammar school, founded
                    1655, the oldest educational institution in the State, and occupying one of the
                    finest school edifices in the country; the Watkιnson library of reference, with
                    34,000 volumes; the rooms and library of the Connecticut historical society,
                    with its valuable collections of relics, books, and MSS.; the young men’s
                    institute, a circulating library of 27,000 volumes (the last three, with a
                    picture gallery, occupy a roomy and accessible building known as the Wadsworth
                    Athenaeum); the very complete State law library at the State-house; the American
                    asylum for the deaf and dumb, retreat for the insane, Hartford hospital and
                    orphan asylum (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Connecticut,</hi> vol. vi. p. 287).
                    Thomas Green in 1764 opened the first printing-office in the city, and
                    established the <hi rend="italic">Connecticut</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Courant,</hi> which has ever since been regularly published. There were in
                    1879 three daily newspapers, seven weekly, and four monthly. In 1797 A. Kinsley
                    exhibited the first steam locomotive in Hartford streets; and a portion of the
                    Hartford and New Haven railroad was in operation in 1838. The railroads,
                    however, have not been pecuniarily successful, that to New Yoιk being the only
                    one of those meeting at Hartford which is in a prosperous condition.</p>
                <p>Hartford was known to the aborigines as Suckiang; it was first permanently
                    settled in 1635 by emigrants from eastern Massachusetts, and called Newtown. In
                    1637 it was named Hartford after Hertford in England. The Dutch had built a fort
                    there in 1633, but it passed wholly into English hands in 1654. The first town
                    meeting was held in 1635, and the first place of worship built, and school put
                    in operation, in 1638. In 1639 was written at Hartford the constitution for the
                    colony, the first framed in America, and embodying the characteristic features
                    of all which follow. The first code of laws was drawn up in 1650, reducing the
                    capital offences from 160 under English law to 15. In 1C87 Sir E. Andros came to
                    Hartford while the assembly was in session, and deriιanded the charter, but it
                    was concealed in the notorious Charter Oak by Captain Joseph Wadsworth, and
                    remained hidden till 1689. The historic tree survived till 1856. The city was
                    incorporated in 1784, and in 1785 it became the sole capital of Connecticut.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
