<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0800-0765-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERSCHEL, Sir Frederick William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 765</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1065127">Planets</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:954113">Heaven</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:828732">Baths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046845">Optics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j663">Planets</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tb93">Heaven</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rk78">Optics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n800/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERSCHEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Frederick
                    William</hi></label> (1738-1822), generally known as Sir William Herschel, one
                    of the most illustrious of astronomers, was born at Hanover, November 15, 1738.
                    His father was a musician employed as hautboy player in the Hanoverian guards.
                    The family had migrated from Bohemia in the early part öf the 17th century, on
                    account of religious troubles, they themselves being Protestants. Herschel’s
                    earlier education was necessarily of a very limited character, chiefly owing to
                    the troubles in which his country at that time was involved; but, being at all
                    times an indomitable student, he, by his own exertions, more than repaired this
                    deficiency of his youth. He became a very skilful musician, both theoretical and
                    practical; while his attainments as a self-taught mathematician were fully
                    adequate to the prosecution of those branches of astronomy which, by his labours
                    and his genius, he so eminently advanced and adorned. Whatever he did he did
                    methodically and thoroughly; and in this methodical thoroughness lay the secret
                    of what Arago very properly terms his astonishing scientific success.</p>
                <p>In 1755, at the age of seventeen, he joined the band of the Hanoverian guards,
                    and with his detachment visited England, accompanied by his father and eldest
                    brother; in the following year he returned to his native country, but two years
                    later, impelled by the troubles that surrounded him, he finally quitted Hanover
                    to seek his fortunes in England. As might have been expected, the earlier part
                    of his career in his adopted country was attended with formidable difficulties
                    and much privation. We find him engaged in several towns in the north of England
                    as organist and teacher of music, but these were occupations not attended with
                    any lucrative results. In 1766 the tide of his fortunes began to flow, inasmuch
                    as he obtained the appointment of organist to the Octagon Chapel in Bath, at
                    that time the resort of the wealth and fashion of the city, and of its numerous
                    distinguished visitors.</p>
                <p>The next five or six years of his life were spent in establishing his reputation
                    as a musician, and he thereby eventually became the leading musical authority in
                    the place, and the director of all the chief public musical entertainments. His
                    circumstances having thus become easier, he revisited Hanover for the purpose of
                    bringing back with him his sister Caroline, with the view of her rendering him
                    such services as she could in his multifarious undertakings. She arrived in Bath
                    with her brother in August 1772, being at that time in her twenty-third year.
                    She thus describes her brother’s life soon after her arrival :—“He used to
                    retire to bed with a bason of milk or a glass of water, with Smith’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Harmonics</hi> and Ferguson’s <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n801/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0801-0766"/><hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> &amp;c., and so
                    went to sleep buried under his favourite authors; and his first thoughts on
                    waking were how to obtain instruments for viewing those objects himself of which
                    he had been reading.” It is not without significance that we find him thus
                    reading Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Harmonics;</hi> to that study loyalty to his
                    profession would impel him; as a reward for his thoroughness this led him to
                    Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Optics</hi>; and this, by a natural sequence, again
                    led him to astronomy, for the purposes of which the chief optical instruments
                    were devised. It was in this way that he was introduced to the writings of
                    Ferguson and Keill, and subsequently to those of Lalande, whereby he was
                    educating himself for an astronomer and for undying fame. In those days
                    telescopes were very rare, very expensive, and not very efficient, for the
                    Dollonds had not as yet perfected even their beautiful little achromatics of 2f
                    inches aperture. So Herschel was obliged to content himself with hiring a small
                    Gregorian reflector of about 2 inches aperture, which he had seen exposed for
                    loan in a tradesman’s shop. Not satisfied with this implement, he procured a
                    small lens of about 18 feet focal length, and set his sister to work on a
                    pasteboard tube of that length, so as to make him a telescope. A tube of this
                    construction naturally bent, and it was useless for all purposes but for the
                    determined eyes of William Herschel. This material was soon displaced for tin,
                    and thus a sorry sort of vision was obtained of Jupiter and Saturn and the moon.
                    He then sought for a reflector of much larger dimensions from artists in London.
                    No such instrument, however, was for sale; and the terms demanded for the
                    construction of a reflecting telescope of 5 or 6 feet focal length he regarded
                    as too exorbitant even for the gratification of such desires as his own. So he
                    was driven to the only alternative that remained; he must construct a large
                    telescope for himself. His first step in this direction was to purchase the
                    debris of an amateur’s implements for grinding and polishing small mirrors; and
                    thus, by slow degrees, and by indomitable perseverance, he in 1774 had, as he
                    says, the satisfaction of viewing the heavens with a Newtonian telescope of 6
                    feet focal length constructed by his own hands. But he was not a man to be
                    contented with viewing the heavens as a mere star-gazer; on the contrary, he had
                    from the very first conceived the gigantic project and the hope of surveying the
                    entire heavens, and, if possible, of ascertaining the plan of their general
                    structure on a settled and systematic mode of procedure, if only he could but
                    provide himself with adequate instrumental means. With this view he, his
                    brother, and his sister toiled for many years at the grinding and polishing of
                    hundreds of specula, always retaining the best, and recasting the others, until
                    the best of the previous performances had been surpassed. This was the work of
                    the daylight in those seasons of the year when the fashionable visitors of Bath
                    had quitted the place, and had thus freed the family from professional duties.
                    After 1774 every available hour of the night was devoted to the long-hoped-for
                    scrutiny of the skies. In those days no machinery had been invented for the
                    construction of telescopic mirrors; the man who had the hardihood to undertake
                    the polishing doomed himself to walk leisurely and uniformly round an upright
                    post for many hours, without removing his hands from the mirror, until his work
                    was done. On these occasions Herschel received his food from the hands of his
                    faithful sister. But his reward was nigh.</p>
                <p>In May 1780 his first two papers containing some of the results of his
                    astronomical observations during the last six years were communicated to the
                    Royal Society through the influential introduction of Dr Watson. Herschel had
                    made the acquaintance of this excellent man and skilful physician in a
                    characteristic manner. In order to obtain a sight of the moon the astronomer had
                    taken his telescope into the street opposite his house; the physician happening
                    to pass at the time, and seeing his eye removed for a moment from the
                    instrument, requested permission to take his place. The mutual courtesies and
                    intelligent conversation which ensued soon ripened this casual acquaintance into
                    a solid and enduring regard.</p>
                <p>The subject of this first memoir was the varying lustre of several of the stars,
                    and especially that of Mira in the constellation of Cetus. It had been long
                    known to fade in brightness from nearly that of a star of the first magnitude
                    down to invisibility in such telescopes as then existed. Herschel had examined
                    it, and many other variable stars, for himself; it was not, however, a simple or
                    isolated phenomenon that engaged his attention; but, regarding the stars as so
                    many suns, he examined stellar phenomena as possibly leading him to some
                    intelligent conception of what might be occurring in our own sun. The sun, he
                    knew, rotated on its axis, and he knew that dark spots often exist on its
                    photosphere; the questions that he put to himself were—Are there dark spots also
                    on these variable stars Ido the stars also rotate on their axes I or are they
                    sometimes partially eclipsed by the intervention of some opaque and invisible
                    bodies? And then he asked himself— What are these singular spots upon the sun?
                    and have they any practical relation to us, the inhabitants of this planet? To
                    these questions he applied his telescopes and his thoughts; and as light from
                    time to time dawned upon his apprehension, he communicated the results to the
                    Royal Society in no less than six memoirs, occupying very many pages in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions,</hi> and extending in date from 1780
                    to 1801. It was in the latter year that these remarkable papers culminated in
                    the inquiry whether any relation could be traced in the recurrence of sun-spots,
                    regarded as evidences of solar activity (allied to volcanic), and the varying
                    seasons of our planet, as exhibited by the varying price of corn? Herschel’s
                    solution of the question was scarcely final, and the question has recently
                    cropped up again, with more than a renewal of its former interest.</p>
                <p>In the following year (1781) he communicated to the Royal Society the first of a
                    series of papers containing the results of his telescopic inquiries in relation
                    to the rotation of the planets and of their several satellites. The object which
                    he had in view was not so much to ascertain the velocities or times of their
                    rotation, as rather to discover whether those rotations are strictly uniform.
                    From the result he expected to gather, by analogy, the probability of an
                    alteration in the length of our own day. These inquiries occupy the greater part
                    of seven memoirs extending from 1781 to 1797. In the course of these telescopic
                    observations he lighted on the curious appearance of a white spot near to each
                    of the poles of the planet Mars. On investigating the inclination of its axis to
                    the plane of its orbit, and finding that it closely resembled that of our earth,
                    he concluded that its changes of climate also would resemble our own, and that
                    these white patches were probably polar snow. Modern investigations have
                    confirmed his conclusion. He also discovered that, as far as his observations
                    extended, the times of the rotations of the various satellites round their axes
                    are in analogy with our own moon, viz., equal to the times of their revolution
                    round their primaries. Here again we observe that his discoveries arise out of
                    the complete and systematic and comprehensive nature of the investigation in
                    which he is engaged. Nothing with such a man is accidental.</p>
                <p>In the same year (1781) Herschel made a discovery which, as we shall see, soon
                    completely altered the character of his professional life. In the course of his
                    systematic examination of the heavens with a view to the discovery of the plan
                    of their construction, he lighted on an object which at first he supposed to be
                    a comet, but which, by its subsequent<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n802/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0802-0767"/> motions and appearance, turned out to be a new
                    planet, moving outside of the orbit of Saturn. To this planet he in due time
                    assigned the name of Georgium Sidus; but this name has by general consent been
                    laid aside in favour of Uranus. It was discovered with a favourite 7-foot
                    reflector having an aperture of G√ inches; subsequently, when he had provided
                    himself with a much more powerful telescope, of 20 feet focal length, he
                    discovered what he believed to be no less than six satellites. Modern
                    observations have shorn this gloomy planet of four of these supposed attendants,
                    but at the same time have added two others apparently not observed by Herschel.
                    No less than seven memoirs on the subject were communicated by him te the Royal
                    Society, extending from the date of the discovery in 1781 to 1815. There is a
                    peculiarity worthy of notice in Herschel’s mode of observation which led to the
                    discovery of this planet. He had observed that the spurious diameters of stars
                    are not much affected by increasing the magnifying powers, but that the case is
                    different with other celestial objects; hence if anything in his telescopic
                    field attracted his notice by peculiarity of appearance, he immediately varied
                    the magnifying power in order to decide the nature of the object. Thus Uranus
                    was discovered; and had a similar method been applied to Neptune, that planet
                    would have been discovered at Cambridge some months before it was recognized at
                    Berlin.</p>
                <p>We now come to the commencement of Herschel’s most important series of
                    observations, culminating in what ought probably to be regarded as his most
                    capital discovery. A material part of the task which he had set himself as the
                    work of his astronomical life embraced the determination of the relative
                    distances of the stars from our sun and from each other. Now, in the course of
                    his scrutiny of the heavens, he had observed many stars in apparently very close
                    contiguity, but often greatly differing in their relative brightness. He
                    concluded that, on the average, the brighter star would be the nearer to us, and
                    the smaller enormously more distant. He considered that an astronomer on the
                    earth, in consequence of its immense orbital displacement of some 180 millions
                    of miles every six months, would see such a pair of stars under different
                    perspective aspects; and this variety of perspective aspect observed and
                    measured would, he thought, lead to an approximate determination of their
                    distance. With this view he mapped down the places and aspects of all the double
                    stars that he met with, and communicated in 1782 and 1785 very extensive
                    catalogues of the results. Indeed, the very last scientific memoir that he ever
                    wrote, sent to the Royal Astronomical Society in the year 1822, at the time when
                    he was its first president and already in the eighty-fourth year of his age,
                    related to these investigations. In the first of these memoirs he throws out the
                    hint that these apparently contiguous stars must, if constituted after the
                    material laws of our solar system, circulate round each other through the
                    effects of gravitation; but he significantly adds that the time had not yet
                    arrived for settling the question. Thus the philosopher abides his time in
                    patience and confidence, and a dozen years afterwards (1793) he remeasures the
                    relative positions of many of these contiguous pairs, and we may conceive what
                    his feelings must have been at finding the verification of his prediction. For
                    he found that some of these stars had circulated round each other, after the
                    manner required by the laws of gravitation. Thus Herschel had demonstrated the
                    action of the same mechanical laws among the distant members of the starry
                    firmament which bind together the harmonious motions of our solar system. This
                    sublime discovery would of itself suffice to immortalize his memory in the
                    respectful homage of all future races of intelligent men. If only Herschel had
                    lived long enough to learn the approximate distances of some of these binary
                    combinations, he would at once have been able to calculate their masses when
                    compared with that of our own sun; and thus, knowing, as we now do, that these
                    stars in their weights are strictly comparable with the weight of our own sun,
                    he would have found another of his analogical conjectures realized.</p>
                <p>In the year 1782, in consequence of his fame, Herschel was invited to Windsor by
                    George HL, and then accepted the offer made by the king to become his private
                    astronomer, and henceforth devote himself wholly to a scientific career. The
                    salary offered and accepted was £200 per annum, to which an addition of £50 per
                    annum was subsequently made for the astronomical assistance of his faithful
                    sister. Dr Watson, to whom alone the amount of this salary was mentioned, made
                    the natural remark, “Never before was honour purchased by a monarch at so cheap
                    a rate.” In this way the great philosophical astronomer removed from Bath first
                    to Datchet and soon afterwards permanently to Slough, within the easy access of
                    his royal patron at Windsor.</p>
                <p>The old pursuits at Bath were soon resumed at Slough, but with renewed vigour and
                    without the old professional interruptions. The greater part, in fact, of the
                    papers already referred to are dated from Datchet and Slough, for the
                    magnificent astronomical speculations in which he was engaged, though for the
                    most part conceived in the earlier portion of his philosophical career, required
                    years of patient observation before they could be fully examined and
                    realized.</p>
                <p>It was at Slough in 1783 that he wrote his first memorable paper on the “Motion
                    of the Solar System in Space,” —a sublime speculation, yet through his genius
                    realized by considerations of the utmost simplicity. He returned to the same
                    subject with fuller details in 1805. It was also after his removal to Slough
                    that he published his first memoir containing his speculative ideas on the
                    construction of the heavens, which from the first had been the chief aim of his
                    toils both of mind and body. In a long series of remarkable papers, addressed as
                    usual to the Royal Society, and extending from the year 1784 to 1818, when he
                    was eighty years of age, he demonstrated the fact that our sun is a star
                    situated not far from the bifurcation of the Milky Way, and that all the stars
                    visible to us lie more or less in clusters scattered throughout a comparatively
                    thin stratum, but in the other two dimensions stretching immeasurably further
                    into space. At one time he imagined that his powerful instruments had pierced
                    through this stellar stratum of the Milky Way, and that he had approximately
                    determined the form of some of its boundaries. In the last of his memoirs he had
                    convinced himself of his error, and he admitted that to his telescopes our
                    stratum of stars is “fathomless.” Over this stratum of stars and their planetary
                    attendants, the whole being in ceaseless motion round some common centre of
                    gravity as the resultant point of the combined gravitation, Herschel discovered
                    on either side a canopy of discrete nebulous masses, from the condensation of at
                    least a part of which the whole stellar universe had been formed,—a magnificent
                    conception, pursued with a force of genius and put to the practical test of
                    observation with an industry almost incredible. It was the work of a single
                    mind, carried to its termination with no assistance beyond that of a loyal
                    sister, almost as remarkable a personage as himself.</p>
                <p>Hitherto we have said nothing about that grand reflecting telescope, of 40 feet
                    focal length and 4 feet aperture, which is too often regarded as the chief
                    effort of his genius and his perseverance. The full description of this
                    celebrated instrument will be found in the 85th volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transactions</hi> of the Royal Society. Gigantic as it really <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n803/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0803-0768"/> was, we are disposed to regard it as among the
                    least of his great works. On the day that it was finished (August 28, 1789)
                    Herschel saw at the first view, in a grandeur not witnessed before, the
                    Saturnian system with all its six satellites, five of which had been discovered
                    long before by Huygens or Cassini, while the sixth, latterly named Enceladus, he
                    had, two years before, sighted by glimpses in his exquisite little telescope of
                    6⅜ inches aperture, but now saw in unmistakable brightness with the towering
                    giant he had just completed. On the 17th of September he discovered a seventh,
                    which proved to be the nearest of all the satellites of Saturn. It has since
                    that time received the name of Mimas. It is somewhat remarkable that,
                    notwithstanding his long and repeated scrutinies of this planet, the eighth
                    satellite, Hyperion, and the crape ring should have escaped him.</p>
                <p>Herschel married the widow of Mr John Pitt, a wealthy London merchant, on May 8,
                    1788, by whom he had an only son, John Frederick William. The prince regent
                    conferred a Hanoverian knighthood upon him in 1816. But a far more valued and
                    less tardy distinction was the Copley medal assigned to him by his associates in
                    the Royal Society in 1781.</p>
                <p>He died at Slough on August 25, 1822, in the eightyfourth year of his age, and
                    was buried under the tower of St Laurence Church, Upton, within a few hundred
                    yards of the old site of the 40-foot telescope. A mural tablet on the wall of
                    the church bears a Latin inscription from the pen of the late Dr Goodall,
                    provost of Eton College. A collected edition of bis astronomical memoirs would
                    speak of his genius in unmistakable language; but this has not yet been
                    published. <hi rend="italic">(B.</hi> R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
