<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0776-0741-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERMENEUTICS, Biblical (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    741)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n776/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERMENEUTICS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Biblical</hi></label>, is
                    that branch of theological science which treats of the principles of Scripture
                    interpretation. Variously described as the theory of the discovery and
                    communication of the thoughts of Holy Scripture (Lange), the science of
                    attaining clearness both in comprehending and in explaining the sense of the
                    Biblical authors (Ernesti), the methodological preparation for the interpreter
                    and for exegesis (Doedes), the science of the removal of differences between us
                    and the sacred writers (Immer), it has for its task to determine the laws of
                    valid exegetical practice. Schleiermacher and Klàusen have limited it to the
                    doctrine of what the interpreter has to observe in order to put <hi
                        rend="italic">himself</hi> in possession of the mind of Scripture. The
                    former defines it as a discipline which looks simply to the reader’s own
                    apprehension, not to the conveyance of the meaning ascertained to others; which
                    latter is to be regarded, he thinks, as but a particular division of the art of
                    speaking and writing. It has been <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n777/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0777-0742"/> generally taken, however, to have respect to
                    the communication as well as the acquisition of the thoughts of the Biblical
                    writers. This larger definition, which is as ancient at least as Augustine’s
                    statement of the two things “quibus nititur omnis tractatio Scripturae, modus
                    inveniendi quae intelligenda sunt et modus proferendi quae intellecta sunt” <hi
                        rend="italic">(De</hi><hi rend="italic">Doctr.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Christ.,</hi> i. 1), has been formally accepted or practically acted on by
                    most modern authorities. It is consonant with the currency of the terms <hi
                        rend="italic">ερμηνεύω, ερμηνεύω, ερμηνευτής</hi> (connected it may be with
                        <hi rend="italic">Hermes,</hi> but not derived from that, such use of a
                    deity’s name being probably unexampled).<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>See article <hi rend="smallcaps">Hermes,</hi> and
                            compare Curtius, <hi rend="italic">Greek Etymology,</hi> §
                        350.</p></note> These in the classics express both expounding (Pindar, <hi
                        rend="italic">O.,</hi> 2, 153) and interpreting or translating a foreign
                    language to others (Xen., <hi rend="italic">Anab.,</hi> i. 2, 17; Herod., ii.
                    125); while in the New Testament <hi rend="italic">ερμηνεύει*</hi> means to
                    translate (John i. 39, 43) and <hi rend="italic">διερμηνεύει*</hi> to expound,
                    interpret, or translate (Luke xxiv. 27, 1 Cor. xii. 30, Acts ix. 36). The
                    definition is in harmony too with the Protestant idea of exegesis as an art
                    which brings the contents of Scripture to the general understanding, and the
                    Protestant conception of the direct approach of God’s word to man’s heart by
                    Scripture. As the theory of the interpretative art hermeneutics is usually taken
                    to be an historical science, forming a subdivision of historical theology.
                    Where, however, a fourfold, instead of a threefold, distribution of theological
                    science is adopted, it is assigned to literary theology. It presupposes such
                    disciplines as textual criticism and Biblical introduction, while it may
                    exercise a reflex influence on some of the discussions with which these are
                    conversant. Although practice precedes theory, and only through the use of the
                    art of interpretation can the principles of interpretation be reached, as it is
                    out of Scripture itself that the laws of Scriptural exposition must be drawn,
                    theoretically this science precedes exegesis and forms an indispensable
                    preparation for Biblical theology. Much which it has been the custom to embrace
                    -within it belongs really to general hermeneutics. The limits properly
                    assignable to it are comparatively narrow, its immediate object being to decide
                    how the laws of general hermeneutics are related to the particular records known
                    as Scripture. The propriety of a special Biblical hermeneutic is established so
                    far as Scripture is proved to be more than an ordinary literature. The Christian
                    who comes to the Bible with the conviction that it is the record of divine
                    communications, and with the experience that it is the medium through which God
                    has spoken to him and led him into new relations to Himself, has to ask whether
                    the principles of ordinary hermeneutics have to be modified or supplemented when
                    applied to these books. Neither the Christian recognition of the spiritual
                    character of Scripture nor the Protestant assertion of the right of private
                    judgment, the perspicuity of Scripture, and the laity’s direct interest in the
                    Bible, warrants the extreme position assumed among some sects, that a scholarly
                    interpretation and, therefore, a science of hermeneutics are superfluous. Being
                    a literary record composed in languages which demand the exegetical <hi
                        rend="italic">praxis</hi> of translation, and produced under circumstances,
                    by writers, and for readers widely removed in date and character from our
                    present acquaintance, Scripture requires a scientific process for its
                    exposition, and the laws of that process must be verified. The peculiar value
                    which attaches to it as a holy literature makes this the more needful, the
                    exceptional position assigned it rendering its interpretation opener to the
                    invasion of prepossession and private religious ideas. The exclusive authority
                    ascribed to these books by the Protestant, who accepts them as the only rule of
                    faith and life, gives him a special interest in hermeneutics. The concrete and
                    historical form in which their spiritual teaching appears, the figurative,
                    typical, and symbolical terms so largely used in them, the numerous
                    presuppositions on which their statements of religious truth and fact proceed,
                    suggest the necessity of such a discipline. The qualities of Scripture which
                    render its appeal to the common understanding distinct and immediate are
                    arguments for scientific intelligence in educing from its declarations nothing
                    more and nothing less than their exact intention. The interpreter’s function
                    being, not to develop some meaning which the words might bear to present
                    students or which the first readers may have seen in them, but simply to
                    ascertain with precision and completeness the ideas which the writers themselves
                    meant to convey, it may be said with Schleiermacher that in a certain sense the
                    interpreter has to educe more than the author introduced. The former has to
                    bring out into clearness much that influenced the latter half-unconsciously in
                    his composition, and to give objective expression to much that underlies his
                    definite statements. Hence the special need for a scientific hermeneutic in the
                    case of a book like the Bible, in which there is so much that is implicit. The
                    vast variety of results reached in crucial passages, and the wide diversities of
                    method which have been pursued among individual exegetes and in exegetical
                    schools, make the propriety and utility of such a science the more apparent.</p>
                <p>Since Christopher Wolle <hi rend="italic">(Hermeneutica Novi Foedems
                        acroamaticodoymatica</hi><hi rend="italic">certissimis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >defecatoe</hi><hi rend="italic">philosophice principiis corroborata
                        eximiisque omnium Theologice Christianae partium usibus inserviens,</hi>
                    Leipsic, 1736) the hermeneutics of the New Testament, for the sake of
                    convenience or on grounds of scientific distinction, has often been separated
                    from the hermeneutics of the Old Testament. The scientific union or disjunction
                    of these disciplines depends on the view entertained of the mutual relations of
                    the Hebrew Scriptures and the Christian. Where the Bible is seen to constitute
                    an organic whole, the hermeneutical principles applicable to the two Testaments
                    are treated in connexion. It then becomes one great object of the science to
                    grasp the differences which are discovered within the unity of Scripture, and
                    exhibit what account has to be taken of these in the art of interpretation. A
                    distinct position, however, naturally belongs to Jewish hermeneutics, which
                    dealt with the Hebrew Scriptures as at once the entire written revelation of
                    God, and the repertory of the highest wisdom on all subjects of human inquiry.
                    The results of the scientific study of the Old Testament, which was carried on
                    with vast activity from Ezra’s time by numerous scribes and in great schools and
                    colleges (Jerusalem, Tiberias, Sura, Pumbeditha, Nahardea, &lt;fcc.), are seen
                    in the Talmudical writings, the <hi rend="italic">Mishna</hi> giving
                    authoritative enlargements and explanations of the law, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Gemara,</hi> in its twofold form of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jerusalem Talmud</hi> edited at Tiberias, and <hi rend="italic">Babylonian
                        Talmud</hi> proceeding from Sura, containing further commentaries, fantastic
                    definitions, and explanations of prior explanations (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Talmud).</hi> The most ancient Jewish interpretation of Scripture, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Hidrash</hi> (“study,” “investigation”), which assumed a fixed
                    character during the period of the second temple and gradually formed a
                    literature, ran out into two great branches, logical or legal exposition, and
                    practical or homiletical exposition. The former, designated “Halacha” (“rule by
                    which to walk,” “binding precept ”), brought the law to bear upon points of
                    religious or general interest on which there was no explicit declaration. It
                    confined itself chiefly to the Pentateuch, extracting from it by numerous
                    exegetical expedients a body of “Halachoth” or sopheric precepts <hi
                        rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Matt. xv. 2, Mark vii. 3), which were held
                    authoritative. These, after a long period of oral transmission, gradually
                    assumed written form, and passed finally through a process of compilation,
                    classification, and redaction which extended perhaps from about two centuries
                    before to two centuries after Christ. The latter, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n778/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0778-0743"/> styled “Hagada” (“opinion,” “free exposition
                    ”), was meant for edification, traversed the entire Old Testament, and occupied
                    itself with the application of Scripture to the purposes of practical
                    instruction in all manner of subjects, ethical, political, metaphysical,
                    theosophic, as well as religious. Its expositions were conveyed in forms,
                    symbolical, poetic, parabolic, such as were most likely to arrest attention,
                    and, though of no binding authority, it made itself so attractive to the people
                    that it was often known as “the Midrash” distinctively. The hermeneutical laws
                    followed in these two lines of exposition are sufficiently well known. Eliezer
                    ben Jose, the Galilaean, a distinguished rabbi of the 2d century of our era, has
                    embodied the results of a final redaction of the principles of the Hagadic
                    exegesis in a series of thirty-two rules. Some of these are sound, dealing, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.</hi>, with the use of brachylogy, repetition, parable,
                    the reconciliation of two discrepant texts by a third, &amp;c. Many of them are
                    wholly fantastic, prescribing how explanations are to be sought by reducing the
                    letters of a word to their numerical value, by the transposition of letters, by
                    the substitution of another word of the same numerical value for one which
                    yields no worthy sense, by studying the introduction of superfluous particles,
                    &amp;c. Such principles held a much smaller place in the Halachic exegesis,
                    which, as it aimed at something higher than applications of Scripture, could
                    indulge in fewer freedoms in certain directions, so far as it was true to its
                    idea. In the fixing of the Halachic hermeneutics Hillel I. (died 8 or 10 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> occupies a conspicuous place. He reduced the
                    traditional legal erudition of the Jews, with its bewildering multiplicity of
                    laws, from the 600 or 700 sections over which it is said previously to have
                    spread, to six capital “Sedarim”or orders, forming a manageable basis on which
                    his successors Αkiba, Simon HL, and Jehudah I. could work on to the final
                    codification of the <hi rend="italic">Mishna.</hi> He was also the first to
                    formulate definite rules by which the rabbinical development of the law should
                    proceed. These canons of interpretation were seven in number, afterwards
                    increased by Rabbi Ismael to thirteen by the addition of seven new rules and the
                    omission of the sixth, and looked to the construction of Biblical warrant for
                    precepts which it was wished to prove implicit in the law. These “Middoth” were
                    instructions to reason (1) <hi rend="italic">a minori</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ad</hi><hi rend="italic">majus,</hi><hi rend="italic">(T) ex</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">analogia,</hi> (3) by derivation of a principal proposition
                    from a single passage, (4) by derivation of a principal proposition from two
                    passages, (5) by limitation of the general through the particular, (6) by
                    explanation of one passage through another, (7) by the use of the context. The
                    idea that the Old Testament, preeminently the law, held hidden in it the highest
                    wisdom on all subjects, was naturally inimical to the rights of the literal
                    sense. The rabbinical hermeneutics drew inevitable distinctions between the
                    proper or innate sense (P□^∣P), which again was described as either verbal (BE⅛j
                    or figurative <hi rend="smallcaps">(-∏d),</hi> and the derivative or studied
                    sense (^ζ∙"!P, <hi rend="superscript"> f</hi> ψ7ι ’)&gt; which was to be sought
                    either by inference (tΛT) or by artificial conjunction (ÎÇ'J). The natural
                    sense, however, though practically robbed of its dues, was not professedly
                    ignored. This regard for it, which was never wholly disowned, ultimately took
                    shape in the improved rabbinical hermeneutics of the Middle Ages. In the
                    writings of such rabbis as Saadias Gaon, Jarchi, Rashi, Kimchi, Maimonides,
                    Abarbanel (a line of expositors extending from the 10th to the 16th century), we
                    find, alongside the traditional rules and explanations, a scientific recognition
                    of the interpreter’s duty to give the literal sense as well as a practical
                    application of the principles of grammatical and historical exegesis to the Old
                    Testament.</p>
                <p>The hermeneutics developed among the Hellenistic Jews had marked characteristics
                    of its own. These interpreters, departing from the exclusiveness of rabbinical
                    devotion to the Old Testament revelation, and from the pure Hebraism of native
                    Jews, brought to the study of the sacred books a range of ideas derived from
                    Hellenic culture. They had to devise a hermeneutical procedure which would
                    harmonize their new ethnic learning with the traditional estimate of the Jewish
                    Scriptures. To the theosophic Hellenist, and specially to the Alexandrian Jew,
                    acceptance of the plain sense was often an impossibility. A reconciliation was
                    sought by the use of allegorical interpretation. This method was also pursued by
                    the Rabbinical exegetes. It is embraced in the Halachic hermeneutics, and is
                    seen in the distinctions drawn by Palestinian Jews between the body and the soul
                    of texts. But while the allegorical interpretation of native Jews, in consonance
                    with their purer estimate of the Hebrew revelation, moved in the direction of
                    the typical, that of the Hellenists became rather mystical. The coryphaeus in
                    this hermeneutical practice was Philo (born perhaps about 20 B.C.), although he
                    .had predecessors in Aristobulus, pseudo-Josephus, and others. He devoted
                    himself mainly to the exposition to the Pentateuch, with the view of explaining
                    the realism and anthropomorphism of the Old Testament in a way to suit the
                    philosophy of the time. Wishful to retain the Alexandrian Jew’s regard for Moses
                    as the supremely inspired prophet of God and the oracle of all mysteries along
                    with adherence to the current Platonism and theosophy, he supposed that the
                    Mosaic writings contained a twofold mode of teaching, a popular representation
                    of God and divine things and a spiritual. It was the task of wisdom to penetrate
                    through the envelope of the literal history to the secret sense which it
                    shielded. The verbal sense was acknowledged, but held to be for the illiterate.
                    The outstanding facts in the records of the creation, the deluge, the careers of
                    the patriarchs and Moses, were accepted in an historic sense, but the details of
                    all these narratives were spiritualized. Sometimes the figurative meaning was
                    made the only meaning, but in other cases the objective meaning was allowed to
                    be the intended meaning. The hermeneutical rule, however, was to rise by
                    allegory from the superficial anthropomorphic sense <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(to</hi> ∣∕rυχικ⅛) to the higher or spiritual sense <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(to</hi><hi rend="italic">πvevpατu&lt;0v).</hi> The simple histories were
                    symbols of abstract truths. To the enlightened they were so many modes of soul
                    (τρόποι <hi rend="italic">ψvχηf)—</hi> Adam the figure of the sensuous nature,
                    Rebecca of patience, Leah of despised virtue, Egypt an emblem of the body, and
                    Canaan of piety.</p>
                <p>Two later chapters in the history of Jewish hermeneutics deserve notice. On the
                    one band the rabbinical procedure was decisively departed from by the Karaites,
                    among whom Japhet ben Heli, of Bussorah, belonging to the close of the 10th
                    century, and Aaron ben Joseph, of the 13th century, are notable. In their case
                    interpretation again sought the <hi rend="italic">via media</hi> between bald
                    literalism and arbitrary spiritualizing. It was prosecuted on the principles of
                    renouncing the quest after a variety of senses, abiding by the natural sense,
                    accepting metaphor where the figurative was intended, and conserving the
                    religious interest. On the other hand an extraordinary development was given to
                    the rabbinical hermeneutics by the Kabbalists of the Middle Ages, who used the
                    devices of artificial interpretation in order to find an Old Testament basis for
                    their mixed Neo-Platonist, Gnostic, and Sabaean culture. The Kabbala (“what has
                    been received,” “tradition,” see <hi rend="smallcaps">Kabbala)</hi> had its
                    roots in the ancient doctrine of numbers, for which the Jews were probably
                    indebted to the Chaldaeans. The use of the numerical power of letters as a key
                    to mysteries, which the Palestinian Jews had early favoured and which formed a
                    not inconsiderable element in the Hagadic exposition, expanded into a vast
                    system of fantastic Hebrew Gnosticism in the 8th century of the Christian era.
                    The written Word was regarded as a depository of secret doctrine <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n779/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0779-0744"/> and absolute truth which could be entered
                    only by the initiated. The mysteries hidden in its letters required for their
                    discovery processes of exchange, more or less intricate, between literal and
                    numerical values. By the combinations and permutations of letters, the
                    interchange of words of equal numerical value, and similar artifices, new
                    meanings were extracted where the proper sense seemed poor, and acceptable
                    meanings found where offence was felt. Where the text, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.,</hi> states (Numbers xii. 1) that Moses married an Ethiopian woman,
                    the veiled sense was shown to be that he married a woman of <hi rend="italic"
                        >beautiful countenanced</hi> and the offence against the law was thus
                    removed. For the letters of ΓP⅛*∙13 added together make the sum 736; the letters
                    in the expression <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> 5', “beautiful of countenance,”
                    yield the same sum; and the enlightened are able to read the latter idea in the
                    former appellative. Distinct titles came to be applied to different branches of
                    the art. The process of reaching hidden truths by the numerical equivalence of
                    letters (as when from the circumstance that χ occurs six times in the first and
                    last verses of the Old Testament it is inferred that the world is to last 6000
                    years) was styled “Gematria.” The process of forming new words out of the
                    several letters of some solemn term, or one new word by combining the first
                    letters of several words (as when the answer ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 7'
                        <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> P, “circumcision,” is discovered in the
                    question in Deut. xxx. 12, “Who shall go up for us to heaven <hi rend="italic"
                        >i”</hi> by bringing together the letters with which the several words in
                    the query commence), was called “Notarikon.” The use of the anagram or
                    permutation (as when by transposition of '2ξPP into ⅛C'P it is ascertained that
                    “mine angel” of Exod. xxiii. 23 was the angel Michael) was known as “Temurah.”
                    The hermeneutical practice of the Kabbalists increased in subtlety as the
                    theosophic system itself grew. Rules were elaborated for exchanging the powers
                    of letters, reading them in. a variety of orders, and otherwise conjuring with
                    the literal sense.</p>
                <p>The course which Biblical hermeneutics has run outside the purely Jewish pale has
                    been not less changeful or remarkable. The New Testament writings show at large
                    how the apostles and first followers of Christ viewed, interpreted, and quoted
                    the Old Testament. They give little in the shape of formal hermeneutical
                    principles, but allow much to be inferred from usage and example. Conclusions as
                    to authoritative canons of interpretation, so far as these are drawn from New
                    Testament employments of Old Testament Scripture, are weighted with the question
                    whether or how far currency is followed. It is affirmed on the one hand that
                    Paul, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in his hermeneutics, was a pure rabbinist,
                    while on the other the equally extreme position is held that his training is in
                    no way reflected in his use of the Hebrew Scriptures. The citation of the Old
                    Testament in the New, which forms a question by itself and one of great
                    intricacy, takes a variety of modes. Passages are reproduced as direct
                    prophecies of the Messiah and His kingdom (Acts ii. 34, Heb. i. 13), as mediate
                    references to the same through partial realizations of their idea (Heb. ii. 6-9,
                    12, 13), as illustrations or applications of principles common to both economies
                    (Rom. x. 6-8, 1 Tim. v. 18), as apt expressions, without the character of
                    explicit quotation, in which New Testament statements naturally embody
                    themselves (1 Pet. i. 24). The proper and immediate sense is adhered to. The
                    application of typology and symbolism (Heb. viii. 5, ix. 9) is at the same time
                    exemplified, and the existence of secondary or higher meanings in allegorical or
                    other forms (Gal. iv. 24, Eph. v. 32) is to a certain extent recognized. The
                    typical relation of the Old Testament to the New is everywhere presented. It is
                    exhibited both in the histories and in the institutions, and is developed alike
                    in ethical, didactic, and prophetic significance (1 Cor. x. 6, 11, Rom. vi. 17,
                    v. 14). The Hebrew revelation is interpreted as a divine preparation for the
                    Christian and as a continuous prophecy bearing onwards towards Christ (Acts. ii.
                    25). Its official personages and its saints, its ordinances and its events, are
                    real though imperfect exhibitions of Messiah arid the Messianic kingdom. Even
                    its minor occurrences and incidental utterances are anticipations or expressions
                    of the purposes of Jehovah realized in the Christian dispensation (Matt. ii. 15,
                    Heb. iv. 7, Eph. iv. 8-12). How far Biblical hermeneutics within the Christian
                    Church has gathered its principles from Scripture itself, and what use it has
                    made of the New Testament <hi rend="italic">praxis</hi> will appear from its
                    history. It will be enough here to deal with the capital ideas to which the
                    various conflicting methods seem capable of being reduced. We indicate which of
                    these prevailed on the whole in important schools and periods, without
                    attempting a chronological statement or detailing the exact relations of each
                    great name to this subject. It is not to be supposed, however, that any single
                    mode was exclusively dominant at any one time, or that the interpreters whose
                    names are connected with some particular procedure held by that only. On the
                    contrary, in the long-continued absence of a definite settlement of principles
                    the best writers swayed remarkably from method to method, and men who are
                    largely identified with vicious modes exhibit at the same time admirable
                    examples of the opposite. It may be said that three great hermeneutical
                    tendencies have been followed. These may be conveniently designated the
                    subjective, the dependent, the historical.</p>
                <p>1. The first, which we have distinguished as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Subjective</hi> tendency, embraces all those widely diverse schemes which
                    agree in passing beyond the objective intention of the words and seeking veiled
                    or underlying meanings. To this belong the different forms of the allegorical
                    method, by which is meant the imposition of a sense not designed by the writer.
                    It is the adding of a meaning foreign to the intention, rather than the
                    substitution of an improper for the proper sense. The first Christian
                    interpreters were under special temptations in this direction. The idea of the
                    need of exceptional principles of exposition in order to reach the deep
                    significance of divine communications had a great hold of the ancient mind,
                    Greek, Roman, Oriental, and Hebrew. The spell of this idea and the powerful
                    influence of the Rabbinical tradition, acting on the Christian conviction that
                    the Bible is a divine message, readily induced the notion that the ordinary laws
                    of interpretation are inadequate, and that Scripture is honoured when the
                    natural or “lower” sense is made the stepping-stone to a “higher” sense for
                    which special processes are required. Early Christian literature, although its
                    mysticism may sometimes be otherwise explained, adheres decidedly to this idea.
                    The apostolic fathers and the Apologists, while not entire strangers to sound
                    spiritual interpretation, are addicted to the allegorical. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Epistle of Barnabas</hi> confirms faith and perfects γvωσις by
                    spiritualizing the details of such narratives as that of the two goats in
                    Leviticus xvi. The <hi rend="italic">Shepherd of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Hermas</hi> contains various examples. Clement of Rome gives the figurative
                    application of the scarlet line suspended from Rahab’s window, which is adopted
                    by so many of the fathers. In this connexion great interest belongs to Justin
                    Martyr, who exhibits acquaintance with several of the distinct senses which were
                    subsequently formulated. Embracing Christianity as the only certain philosophy,
                    and carrying much of his old Platonism with him into his new faith, he dealt
                    with the Scriptures very much as he dealt with the classics. The histories of
                    the Old Testament (he seldom expounds the New) were a drapery covering broad
                    spiritual truths. As the piling of Pelion and Ossa was a Greek version of the
                    building of the tower of Babel, so Jacob’s marriage with Leah and Rachel denoted
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n780/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0780-0745"/> Jehovah’s revelation in the Jewish Church and
                    the Christian. Every particular in prophetic passages like Gen. xlix. 9-12 had a
                    mystical reference to Christ and His salvation, His passion being signified by
                    the washing of the garments in wine, the Jews by the ass, the Gentiles by the
                    colt.</p>
                <p>The allegorical method, which offers itself as a natural expedient for
                    harmonizing difficulties between religious faith and philosophical feeling, and
                    which had been freely applied to Homer by Plato, found a most congenial home in
                    Alexandria, where Philo’s influence was strong. It became a recognized principle
                    with the entire catechetical school, firmly rooted in the distinction which
                    there prevailed between ττiστιs. and <hi rend="italic">γvωσις.</hi> Clement of
                    Alexandria, who seems to have been the first to bring the New Testament no less
                    than the Old under its scope, finds a parabolic meaning in all Scripture, and
                    affirms that the literal sense carries us simply to the elementary stage of
                    Christian knowledge called faith, while it is only through the allegorical or
                    mystical interpretation that we can reach that higher wisdom which implies
                    insight into the essence, reason, and real relations of faith’s objects. He
                    speaks of a “tradition of the church,” an “ecclesiastical canon,” or “canon of
                    the truth,” which gives the key to the true understanding of Scripture, and is
                    identified with the γvωσιs or spiritual apprehension of divine mysteries as that
                    was first communicated by Christ to the apostles in oral form, and by them
                    transmitted to their successors. This canon is described as “the consent and
                    harmony of the law and the prophets with the covenant delivered during the
                    Lord’s presence.” In accordance with this Clement discovers in the Mosaic law
                    three senses in addition to the natural. The terms in which the precepts are
                    expressed are images of other things, rules for the direction of life, and
                    predictions of the future. The high priest’s robe is an emblem of the world of
                    sense; the bells upon it are a symbol of the acceptable year of the Lord. The
                    decalogue itself is spiritualized, the fifth commandment being taken to refer to
                    the Heavenly Father, and that divine Wisdom which is the mother of the
                        just.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See especially
                                <hi rend="italic">Strom.,</hi> vi. p. 676-89; also Baur, <hi
                                rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Christliche</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Gnosis,</hi> and Kaye, <hi rend="italic">Some Account
                                of the Writings and Opinions of Clement of
                        Alexandria.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>A position of commanding importance must be claimed for Origen, whose genius
                    secured wide and long-continued acceptance for his greatest extravagances. Exact
                    grammatical exegesis is by no means alien to his homilies and commentaries, and
                    many of his strangest uses of Scripture may be viewed as practical applications
                    rather than scholarly expositions. Fanciful modes, however, are so predominant
                    that he has been generally regarded as the chief allegorist of the Christian
                    Church. Yet the disservice thus done by his example cannot cloud the lustre of
                    his merits in Biblical studies. His Platonism, his adhesion to the Alexandrian
                    idea of γvωσις, his wish to defend and elucidate the Christian religion by
                    reason and philosophy, his exaggerated notion of inspiration, combined to
                    commend a mystical style of interpretation. In terms of the Platonic division of
                    man into body, soul, and spirit, he held that Scripture had a threefold sense,
                        <hi rend="italic">σωματικό·;, ψυχικός, πνευματικός.</hi> The first, or
                    obvious, sense was meant for the edification of the simple. The second, which
                    was to be sought for under the letter, and embodied the soul of Scripture,
                    exhibited the bearing of the word upon the practical needs of the moral life,
                    and addressed itself to the more advanced. The third, which lay still deeper,
                    and imparted the spirit of Scripture, disclosed pure unmixed truth, exercised
                    the speculative powers, and was intended only for the perfect, such as are
                    described in 1 Cor. ii. 6, 7. He has been sometimes credited with the
                    promulgation of the fourfold distinction afterwards so current, especially in
                    the Latin Church, and expressed in the couplet (given, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.a.,</hi> by Lyra):—</p>
                <p>Litera gesta docet, quid credas allegoria, Moralis quid agas, quo tendas
                    anagogia.</p>
                <p>Such terms, however, as tropological, mystical, allegorical, pneumatic,
                    anagogical, are rather interchangeable with him. The literal sense, too, is so
                    far from being dispensed with that he has even been regarded (e.y., by Ernesti)
                    as the first who secured for it its primary value, particularly in New Testament
                    exegesis. But, while he maintains that the spirit and the letter are generally
                    to be taken together, and admits that no small portion of the contents of
                    Scripture <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> the decalogue, precepts of universal
                    obligation, even many of the narratives) may not be allegorized, his practice is
                    greatly in the direction of esteeming the literal sense only as the protecting
                    shell of secret treasure. Wherever the letter yields a meaning which seems to
                    him unworthy, or opposed to reason and possibility, a mystical sense is
                    discovered. He stumbles at the record of creation when it introduces the sun
                    after the third day, at many of the Mosaic ordinances, at the realism of
                    Christ’s temptation. He finds mysteries or figures of spiritual things in Eden,
                    Abraham’s wives, Rebecca’s visit to the well, the waterpots at Cana, and many
                    other narratives. The later type of Alexandrian hermeneutics is seen in Cyril,
                    who, without wholly abandoning the literal sense, carries typical interpretation
                    into unqualified allegorical extremes in dogmatic and polemic interests.</p>
                <p>The Western Church exhibited the same tendency, not only in the marked
                    artificialities of such teachers as Hippolytus, Hilary, and Ambrose, but in the
                    eminent instance of Augustine. Though not the first to attempt a statement of
                    hermeneutical canons (having before him, for instance, the seven rules of
                    Tichonius, which he states and criticizes at length), he constructed more of a
                    system in this line of inquiry as in some others. Many of the principles which
                    are enunciated in different parts of his writings, and most definitely in his
                        <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Doctrina</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Christiana,</hi> are of permanent value. He conceives the object of
                    interpretation to be the discovery of the thoughts of the writer exactly as he
                    meant to express them. He shows that the real sense is often not to be got by
                    insisting merely on expressions as they stand by themselves; that they must be
                    compared with the immediate context, with similar passages elsewhere, and with
                    the essentials of Christian doctrine; that faith and the aids of the Holy Spirit
                    cannot supersede the use of science; that a reverent and sympathetic mind is
                    indispensable. But along with such rules as these he propounds others which
                    served as grounds for his allegorical procedure. He affirms, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.y.,</hi> that whatever cannot clearly be seen to bear upon honesty of
                    morals or the truth of faith must be taken figuratively. He speaks of several
                    different modes of interpretation,—the historical, the aetiological, the
                    analogical, the allegorical. He usually practises the first and the last of
                    these. His profound spiritual experience gave him a truer insight than his
                    canons indicated into many parts of Scripture, and above all into the Pauline
                    epistles. Yet over most even of the New Testament he allows the allegorical
                    fancy to range freely. His influence perpetuated the reign of the allegorical
                    method for many centuries throughout the Western Church. In Gregory the Great,
                    the Venerable Bede, Hrabanus Maurus, Hugo de S. Caro, and many others, we see it
                    steadily extending rather than merely maintaining its sway, until in Bonaventura
                    we find the current four senses—historical, tropological, allegorical,
                    anagogical—enlarged to seven by the addition of the symbolical, synecdochical,
                    and hyperbolical.</p>
                <p>2. The second great hermeneutical tendency, which we call the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dependent,</hi> has an equally instructive history. It is easy to
                    understand how extreme allegorizing would lead to a counter movement, and how
                    this would be helped by the exigencies of dealing with heretics who were
                    themselves <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n781/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0781-0746"/> advocates of γνώσις. The appeal soon came to
                    be made to a rule of faith which may at first have meant nothing more than the
                    harmony of Scripture teaching, but which was speedily identified with something
                    outside Scripture, with the contents of doctrinal summaries, or with the verdict
                    of exegetical tradition. The East and the West gave way alike to this bias, but
                    the West first and most positively. In both we find early mention of an
                    ecclesiastical canon or norm of truth. In the Church of the East, indeed, that
                    took originally the form of an authoritative γvωσιs or private exposition of the
                    esoteric meaning of Scripture handed down by careful tradition from Christ and
                    the apostles, while in the Church of the West it was rather the voice of the
                    church itself, and that soon the voice as formulated. Both churches, however,
                    more or less distinctly recognized an ecclesiastical tradition represented in
                    compends of doctrine which were used for catechetical and other purposes, and an
                    interpretative tradition embodied in the expositions of influential doctors. .
                    Thus hermeneutical independence was sacrificed. In Irenaeus and Tertullia·n we
                    see how a very natural reaction took this direction. The necessity of meeting
                    errorists who were greater adepts in arbitrary spiritualizing than any whom the
                    church could present led them to protest against the practice. They saw the
                    propriety of looking to Scripture itself for hermeneutical guidance, and of
                    rescuing it from the despotism of a mystical philosophy which threatened the
                    life of its cardinal doctrines. They adopted a simpler reading of its message,
                    and so far they deserve the name of pioneers in real historical interpretation.
                    But, as appears in their gross chiliastic expositions, their literalism was
                    carried to excess. It came into conflict with the deeper declarations of
                    Scripture, and this conflict they were tempted to compose by a relapse into
                    fanciful methods. It created difficulties in their controversy with Gnostic
                    opponents, and these they thought to remove by a final appeal. to an
                    authoritative tradition fixing the sense in which the sacred books which both
                    parties used as witnesses to their doctrine were to be understood. This was to
                    be found in its integrity in those ancient churches which had enjoyed direct
                    apostolic teaching, and, as Irenaeus conceived, in some special way in that of
                    Rome. Gradually the idea of a normative analogy of faith discovered within
                    Scripture was externalized, and the standard of interpretation was looked for in
                    ecclesiastical symbols and the formal decisions of the heads of the church. In
                    this process, which issued in the Tridentine definition of the ultimate
                    determination of the interpretation of Scripture as resident in the church, and
                    the more recent declaration of the infallibility of the pope as the voice of the
                    church, Vincent of Lerins claims particular notice. In his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Commonitorium,</hi> for which we are indebted to the Semi-Pelagian
                    controversy, he lays down rules for the attainment of certitude in belief. Faith
                    is to be settled by two things, the authority of Scripture and the tradition of
                    the church. The former is a perfect and adequate foundation. Yet the caprices of
                    interpretation require it to be supplemented by the latter. The sense of
                    Scripture is the sense in which the church understands it, and this tradition of
                    the Catholic Church, which is to be accepted as the canon of hermeneutics, is
                    defined as “quod ubique, quod semper, quod ab omnibus creditum est.” This
                    treatise, still retained in singular honour by large sections of the Christian
                    Church, exhibits the hermeneutics which had been winning acceptance since the
                    times of Irenaeus and Cyprian, and by which the Latin communion was led to bind
                    itself. The result of the deference paid to the fathers in both churches, and
                    especially in the West, was the renunciation of independent exegesis and the
                    production of compilations of patristic comments. These σeιpαι or <hi
                        rend="italic">Catenae</hi> epitomized the interpretations of most of the
                    great expositors, particularly Origen, Chrysostom, Jerome, and Augustine, and
                    were on the whole more successfully executed in the Greek Church than in the
                    Latin. They were in use by the end of the 5th or beginning of the 6th century.
                    Andreas of Caesarea, who belongs to the former period, or Olympiodorus, whose
                    date is about the beginning of the 7th century, has sometimes been recognized as
                    the earliest epitomizer; but the position is to be assigned rather to Procopius
                    of Gaza, who comes between thçse two. For many centuries the most eminent
                    divines took part in the preparation of <hi rend="italic">Catenae,</hi> such as
                    Cassiodorus (also a literalist), Bede (already cited as an allegorist), Alcuin,
                    Hrabanus Maurus (often honoured as the most learned interpreter of the 8th and
                    9th centuries), Haymo, Remigius, Sedulius, Theophylact, Oecumenius, Paschasius
                    Radbertus, and Aquinas. The <hi rend="italic">Catena</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >aurea</hi> of Aquinas on the gospels was of great value. Redactions of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Catenae</hi> were also made in course of time. These were
                    the <hi rend="italic">Glossae,</hi> which were known as <hi rend="italic"
                        >marginales</hi> or <hi rend="italic">extrvnse&lt;xe</hi> when the comments
                    were given on the margin, and <hi rend="italic">interlineares</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">intrinsecae</hi> when these were introduced in the text. The
                    most influential glossa of the second class was that of Anselm of Laon, who
                    belongs to the end of the 11th and the beginning of the 12th century. Of the
                    former the most important was the <hi rend="italic">Glossa ordinaria</hi> of
                    Walafrid Strabo, which was esteemed the chief exegetical manual for some six
                    centuries. Throughout the Middle Ages, full as these were of theological
                    activity, dogmatic and polemic, hermeneutics became more and more a tradition.
                    The less the Bible was studied in a free spirit, the more it became the subject
                    of strained panegyric. Aquinas, indeed, though his practice was often in
                    conflict with his theory, could still speak of the literal sense as that on
                    which all the senses of Scripture are founded, and of argument as to be drawn
                    only from that one literal sense and not from those senses which are expressed
                    according to allegory <hi rend="italic">(Sτιmma,</hi> i. 1, art 10). But at last
                    independence was so completely resigned that John Gerson, the illustrious
                    chancellor of Paris, was only the exponent of the prevalent opinion, when he
                    declared that those who did not take the literal sense as the church defined it
                    ought to be dealt with not by curious reasonings but by statutory penalties.</p>
                <p>3. But alongside these two hermeneutical tendencies there can be traced from the
                    earliest times, however obscurely or fitfully, a third which we term the <hi
                        rend="italic">Historical.</hi> Men like Irenaeus, Origen, Augustine,
                    &amp;c., were not wholly incapacitated for the exercise of a better method by
                    their allegorical or dogmatic bias. There has been a line of interpreters,
                    slender enough as that line has been at times, who have recognized it to be the
                    exegete’s object to discover the one sense intended by the writer himself, who
                    have allowed allegory therefore only where the writings themselves indicated
                    their mystical design, and who have laid the first importance on the grammatical
                    sense and on the capacity of transporting oneself into the writer’s position.
                    Even Alexandria presents in the great Athanasius and in Isidore notable
                    instances of interpreters who, though given to occasional spiritualizing,
                    proceed on the principle of the αυταpκ∈ια of Scripture (this specially in the
                    case of Athanasius), and on the necessity of considering the occasion of each
                    writing. But in direct antithesis to the allegorizing school of Alexandria stood
                    the school of Antioch, which was grammatical and historical, with a tendency to
                    an extreme literalism which yielded in not a few cases a jejune and unspiritual
                    exegesis. Theophilus and Julius Africanus may claim a place in this order. But
                    the acknowledged representatives of the Antiochene school are Lucian of
                    Samosata, who is sometimes reckoned its real founder, Diodorus of Tarsus,
                    Theodore of Mopsuestia, and above all John Chrysostom and Theodoret of the
                    Syrian Cyrrhus. The last two, while not less careful of the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n782/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0782-0747"/> objective sense, surpassed the others in
                    spiritual insight. Chrysostom abounds in sound hermeneutical statements which
                    strike a happy mean between Alexandrian arbitrariness and the unethical
                    superficiality into which extreme Antiochene interpretation sank. He withstands
                    the imposition of foreign senses as a practice dishonouring to the Word of God,
                    and yet shows how much there is that must be taken otherwise than as it stands.
                    He insists upon the importance of ascertaining the “scope” of a writing in order
                    to a correct judgment of its separate declarations, on the necessity of the
                    revelation of the Spirit, on the respect due to the harmony of Scripture with
                    itself. He lays it down as a general principle that, when allegory is employed,
                    the Bible also gives its interpretation as a check upon the unbridled desire of
                    those who wish to allegorize <hi rend="italic">(Hom. in Genes,</hi> v.).
                    Theodoret exhibits a kindred sobriety, and, though occasionally guilty of
                    seeking a secondary sense where the obvious sense seems too bald, ranks
                    deservedly among the very best of ancient exegetes. Principles similar to the
                    Antiochene prevailed for a long period also in the schools of Edessa and
                    Nisibis. The objective tendency found representatives, too, in men like Basil of
                    Caesarea, Gregory of Nazianzus, Gregory of Nyssa (although he was less decidedly
                    historical, and strongly advocated a non-literal reading of Canticles in
                    particular), Pelagius, and the laborious Jerome. This last-named ornament of the
                    Latin Church, although he too often drifted into fanciful and even puerile
                    interpretations, was strongly opposed both to the allegorists and the extreme
                    literalists. Against the former he affirmed that the grammatical and historical
                    sense must be held the fundamental thing. Against the latter he insisted that
                    the figurative interpretation is not necessarily equivalent to the allegorical,
                    and that the gospel is to be sought not in the words but in the sense of
                    Scripture, not in the surface but in the marrow, not in the leaves of discourses
                    but in the root of the idea <hi rend="italic">(Comm, in Habac.</hi> iii. 14; <hi
                        rend="italic">in Epist.</hi><hi rend="italic">ad Galat,</hi> i. 11). In the
                    unproductive centuries which followed, this purer hermeneutical tendency appears
                    occasionally in such instances as those of Druthmar, “the grammarian;”
                    Oecumenius, bishop of the Thessalian Tricca, who belongs to the 10th century;
                    Theophylact, bishop of Achrida in Bulgaria, “the last of the fathers Rupert of
                    Deutz and Euthymius Zigabenus, who carry us into the 12th century.</p>
                <p>A great impetus was given to independent hermeneutics by the Humanists and the
                    precursors of the Reformation. An eminent position is occupied by Nicolaus de
                    Lyra, to whose <hi rend="italic">Postillae,</hi> or brief commentaries on the
                    whole Bible, Luther and the Reformers owed a debt expressed in the familiar
                    distich, “Si Lyra non lyrasset, Lutherus non saltasset.” The current fourfold
                    division of the sense of Scripture still appeared in his writings, but for the
                    most part only as a theoretic division. He allowed occasional spiritualizing,
                    but that mostly in the form of professed practical application of the proper
                    sense. He declared anew the necessity of adhering to the plain objective
                    meaning, likening the mystical interpretation which departs from the solid basis
                    of the literal sense to a building which deviates from its foundation and
                    inclines to its fall. On the side of grammar and philology the reaction was
                    helped by Laurentius Valla and other Humanists, although the services of
                    Reuchlin in particular, great as they were in the assertion of exegetical
                    freedom and in the restoration of linguistic science, were impaired by
                    cabbalistic predilections <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> specially his <hi
                        rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">verbo mirifico).</hi> On the
                    religious side, something was achieved by men like Wycliffe, Huss, Wessel, who
                    all perceived the primary importance of the grammatical method, and Faber
                    Stapulensis (Lefèvre d’Étapies), who affirmed the sufficiency of the Word, and
                    practised an independent, non-dogmatic exegesis. It is matter of course that
                    Erasmus should claim special notice in this connexion. In this consummate
                    scholar and versatile genius, who continued and vastly excelled all that had
                    been attempted by Valla and others, and whose guidance the Reformers were wise
                    enough to follow, notwithstanding the frequent deficiencies of his exegesis in
                    depth and spiritual insight, we come at length upon a master hand that marks a
                    great epoch. Indecision clings indeed to his utterances on some subjects. He
                    speaks with caution on the infallibility of the church and the church’s head,
                    although he lets us see that he rejects it. He admits the existence of
                    occasional inaccuracies in the Scriptures. But he declares that these are so far
                    from being disadvantageous to the gospel that they are turned by the Spirit into
                    a help to faith. He adds at the same time that if the authority of the entire
                    Scripture should be supposed to be impaired by the presence of the smallest
                    error in it, it is more than probable that none of the copies now used by the
                    Catholic Church is so perfect as to be free from the intrusion of all mistakes,
                    accidental or intentional <hi rend="italic">(cf. Annot. in Matt.</hi> ii. 6).
                    But his clear enunciation of the interpreter’s independence and the inquirer’s
                    obligation to become bound by the authority of no one <hi rend="italic">(In
                        Luc.</hi> ii. 35), his advocacy of the translation and free circulation of
                    the Scriptures, his repudiation of any other sense than what was meant to be
                    conveyed, his sagacity in dealing with the figurative sections of both
                    Testaments, his recognition of the need of a “pia curiositas” and a “curiosa
                    pietas” in the exposition of the divine word <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Pref,
                    to <hi rend="italic">Paraph, in Evany.),</hi> his practice of the true
                    exegetical art in his <hi rend="italic">Paraphrases</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annotations,</hi> contributed powerfully to the diffusion of better
                    hermeneutical ideas.</p>
                <p>The mightiest impetus was given by the Reformers. They were the heirs of what was
                    best in the ancient school of Antioch and in the Humanistic revival. But they
                    added to the philology, the grammar, the history, and the independence which
                    were illustrated in these the spiritual insight and the personal religious
                    interest which were so often wanting. The process by which they won their own
                    way to a freer faith lifted them above tradition, mysticism, and unspiritual
                    literalism. Their profound religious experiences, intensified by the forces at
                    work in an unexampled mental upheaval, made the Bible a new thing to them. It
                    came to them as God’s message, and they received it as the only rule of faith
                    and life. It spoke immediately to their souls, and they saw it was to be
                    interpreted by itself. They found it a message conveyed in historical form, and
                    recognized the need of the appliances of language and history in order to read
                    it. They perceived it to be a spiritual message, and discovered that the full
                    reception of it could come only by spiritual enlightenment. Believing it to be a
                    message meant for all, they held it perspicuous to the general intelligence of
                    the prayerful in all that concerns faith and morals, and affirmed, with
                    Melanchthon, “unam et certam et simplicem sententiam ubique quaerendam esse
                    juxta praecepta grammaticae, dialectic«, et rhetoricae.” Each of the great
                    Reformers did something to advance this truer hermeneutical movement. Luther,
                    Zwingli, and Calvin were alike imbued with the historic sense, Luther excelling
                    in spiritual genius and a bold originality which carried him at times to
                    extremes in the independence of his treatment of Scripture, Zwingli in an
                    incisive perception which inclined strangely at times to subjective
                    interpretations, Calvin in a union of qualities which distinguished him as the
                    foremost exegete of the Reformation. Profoundly reverencing Scripture as God’s
                    word, submitting to it as authoritative, yet not binding himself to any theory
                    of its inspiration which would preclude the possibility of circumstantial
                    inaccuracies <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> on Matt, xxvii. 9, Acts vii. 16), the
                    Reformer of Geneva excelled all in freedom from arbitrary exposition, in reading
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n783/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0783-0748"/> thø Biblical statements in the light of
                    historical occasion and intention, in laying the foundations of a truer
                    typology, and in exhibiting with its Christward testimony the historical basis
                    of Messianic prophecy. The coryphaei of Protestant exegesis were aided by Beza,
                    Bucer, Bullinger, Oecolampadius, and others. At length the hermeneutics of the
                    Reformation found symbolical expression in the Protestant definitions of the
                    exclusive sufficiency of Scripture, its perspicuity under the use of the
                    ordinary means and with the teaching of the Holy Spirit, its possession of a
                    sense which is one and not manifold, and its interpretation by itself. In the
                        <hi rend="italic">Clavis</hi><hi rend="italic">Scriptura;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Sacrce</hi> of M. Flacius Illyricus it was cast for the first
                    time into systematic form, and dealt with theoretically.</p>
                <p>With the Reformation objective exegesis may be said to have been firmly
                    established. The conditions were also laid for further hermeneutical progress.
                    Since then the principles of true grammatico-historical interpretation have been
                    gradually coming to be better understood and more successfully applied. This has
                    not been the case, however, without frequent relapses. In various schools there
                    have been revivals of old errors. There has been a return to the subjective
                    tendency, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> in the
                    “moral interpretation” of Kant, as well as in various forms of rationalistic and
                    Socinian exegesis. In accordance with his ideas of the empiric and local order
                    of an historical faith, and his definition of morality as the essence of
                    religion, Kant held that the judgments of the pure reason must be the test of
                    religious truth, and that the literal sense, when it seems to convey a meaning
                    adverse to morality, inconsistent with reason, or unworthy of God, must have a
                    new meaning found for it. His hermeneutics, therefore, did not profess to rest
                    with the sense intended by the writer, but reckoned it legitimate to adopt any
                    possible sense which should be conformable to the interests of perfect morality.
                    To the same tendency belong the “psychological interpretation” of Paulus and
                    Eichhorn, and the mythical interpretation of Weisse and Strauss. Of these the
                    former proposed to hermeneutics the task of distinguishing the realities from
                    the inexact impressions formed of facts by the sacred writers, while the latter
                    sought principles by which the idea might be disentangled from the narrative
                    vesture which it had woven for itself. Pietism, too, although its leaders,
                    Spener and Francke, were of a better spirit, degenerated through its straining
                    after “edifying” interpretation into mystic and chiliastic licence. The
                    dependent tendency, again, formulated in the symbolical definitions on the
                    subject of the Vulgate as the basis of exegesis, the church as the authoritative
                    interpreter, and the pope as the infallible exponent of the church in official
                    declarations on faith and morals, has become so firmly seated in the Roman
                    Catholic communion that the interpreter’s attitude to the church is capable of
                    being compared by a Catholic author to that of a diplomatist acting in the
                    spirit and interest of his prince. <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> It is
                    followed, too, by that section of the English Church which defers to primitive
                    tradition or the consent of the fathers of the first four centuries. Even among
                    those who adhere to the Protestant positions there has been partial reaction in
                    both directions. The subjective tendency has reasserted itself, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in the artificial typology of the Cocceian school,
                    although Cocceius himself rather deserves the credit of making Protestant
                    theology, after it had entered its scholastic period, again more Biblical, and
                    of enforcing the importance of a literal, contextual interpretation. The
                    dependent tendency has reappeared where the “analogy of faith,” instead of being
                    kept to the original idea of the general contents of Scripture as gathered from
                    the lucid passages and used for a help to the understanding of the obscurer, has
                    been identified with the creeds and employed as an external standard of
                    interpretation.</p>
                <p>But with partial retrogression there has been an advance on the whole in
                    Protestant hermeneutics. To this interpreters of very different schools have
                    contributed. Among these are to be mentioned Sal. Glassius, the author of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Philologia</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacra,</hi> Hugo Grotius,
                    Abr. Calov, G. Calixtus, J. J. Rambach, whose <hi rend="italic"
                        >Institutiones</hi><hi rend="italic">Hermeneutical</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Sacroe</hi> exercised a salutary influence, notwithstanding bis inclination
                    to the pietist principle of “emphasis” in interpretation <hi rend="italic">; J.
                        A.</hi> Bengel, in whose <hi rend="italic">Gnomon</hi> a happy union was
                    effected between pietism and science; and J. S. Semler, who did much for the
                    expansion of historical interpretation, notwithstanding the injurious results of
                    his theory of accommodation. Of still greater importance are J. A. Ernesti, to
                    whose celebrated <hi rend="italic">Institutio Interpretis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Novi</hi><hi rend="italic">Testamenti</hi> last century was indebted for
                    the scientific presentation of the soundest hermeneutical principles on the
                    philological side; Friedr. Schleiermacher, whose <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hermeneutik</hi> abounds in fertile suggestions, and brings out for the
                    first time the necessity of recognizing a specifically Christian element in the
                    language of the New Testament; and F. Lücke, who illustrates the just
                    combination of the strictest scientific method with the primary qualification of
                    spiritual sympathy with the Word in the true interpreter. Extensions of
                    hermeneutical method have been attempted, in the form of defining a special
                    “psychological” (Stäudlin), “theological” (Klausen, Länderer), or “dogmatic”
                    (Doedes) interpretation, or in the form of proposing new modes of
                    interpretation, such as the “aesthetical” of Pareau, the “pneumatical” of Beck,
                    the “panharmonic” of German But whatever is valid in these schemes comes within
                    the ordinary grammatico-historical method. Properly understood, the historical
                    side of that method covers all that concerns the transportation of the exegete,
                    not only into the times and circumstances of the composition of the books, but
                    also into the position and personality of the authors. It embraces therefore
                    that subjective quality which, however variously designated as the religious
                    preparation, sympathy with the writers and their message, spiritual tact, or the
                    illumination of the Holy Spirit, has been recognized by the best interpreters to
                    be a primary and essential requisite. The development of these principles has
                    been greatly helped by the grammatical studies of men like Gesenius, Ewald,
                    Olshausen, and Böttcher in Hebrew, and Winerand Buttmann in Greek; by the
                    literary, historical, critical, and theological investigations of Herder, Baur,
                    Rothe, Hofmann, and many others; and above all by the exegetical practice of
                    scientific expositors such as De Wette, Bleek, Hupfeld, Lücke, Meyer, Godet,
                    Ellicott, Lightfoot, and Delitzsch. Results are thus being gathered which will
                    issue in new enlargements of hermeneutical method. A clearer insight is being
                    gained into the genius of the languages, which has already rescued New Testament
                    Greek from purist and Hebraist extremes, and into the nature of typology, the
                    laws of prophecy, the relation of the two Testaments to each other, the
                    historical delivery and development of their contents, the unity (so
                    distinguishable from uniformity) which animates their different sections. In
                    these directions there is the promise of further progress in hermeneutics. More
                    exact inquiry into the presuppositions which underlie the Biblical doctrines
                    will also tell upon the laws of interpretation. Differences in hermeneutical
                    method, however, run up finally into differences of conception on the origin of
                    the sacred literature, its intention, and the spirit which animates it.
                    Uncertainty of view on the subject of what Scripture is and what its inspiration
                    covers, as seen in the symbols of the churches and in the widely divergent
                    positions affirmed by representative theologians of different schools <hi
                        rend="italic">(cf., e.g.,</hi> those expounded respectively by Chemnitz, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n784/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0784-0749"/> Beck, Schleiermacher, Martensen, Hodge,
                    Ewald, Rothe, Hofmann), exercises a disturbing influence. More determinate
                    conclusions on the definition of Scripture, such as can be the result only of
                    completer historical investigation into the rise and object of the several
                    books, must yet be reached before a thorough adjustment is possible between the
                    religious interest and the scientific in Biblical hermeneutics.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.</hi> —On the history generally Buddaeus, <hi
                        rend="italic">Isagoge</hi><hi rend="italic">hist, theok,</hi> &amp;e., 1730;
                    Hartmann, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">enge Verbindung</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">des A. T. mit</hi><hi rend="italic">dem</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >N.</hi><hi rend="italic">T.,</hi> 1831; J. G. Rosenmüller, <hi
                        rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">interp.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >libr. sacr. in eccles. Christ.,</hi> 5 vols., 1795-1814; G. W. Meyer, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte der Schrifterklänrng seit der Wiederherstellung der
                        Wissenschaften,</hi> 5 vols., 1802-8; L. Diestel, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geschichte des alten Testaments in der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >christ.</hi><hi rend="italic">Kirche,</hi> 1869; also the notices in
                    Reuss’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der heil. Schriften N. Test.</hi>; the
                    Introductions to the Old Testament by Keil and Bleek, and De Wette’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Lehrbuch der historisch-kritischen Einleitung in das Alte und
                        Neue Testament</hi> (edited by Schrader), 1869; and the sketches in
                    Klausen’s <hi rend="italic">Hermeneutik des</hi><hi rend="italic">N.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">T.</hi> (German edition, Leipsic), 1841; J. L. Lutz’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Biblische Hermeneutik,</hi> 1861; S. Davidson’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Sacred Hermeneutics,</hi> 1843. On the Rabbinical Hermeneutics
                    :—Surenhusius, Bij3λos καταλλαγτjs, 1713; Zunz, <hi rend="italic">Die
                        gottesdienstl.</hi><hi rend="italic">Vorträge</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Juden,</hi> 1832; PresseΓs article “Rabbinismus,”
                    in Herzog’s <hi rend="italic">Real-</hi><hi rend="italic">Encyclopädie·,</hi>
                    Hirschfeld, <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic">Geist</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">talmudischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Auslegung der Bibel</hi> (Erster Theil, “Halachische Exegese,” 1840), and
                        <hi rend="italic">Der Geist der ersten Schriftauslegungen, oder die
                        hagadische Exegese,</hi> 1847; Frankel, <hi rend="italic">Vorstudien zu der
                        Septuaginta,</hi> 1841; E. Deutsch, <hi rend="italic">Literary Remains,</hi>
                    1874; and the sections in Jost's <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">des Jτιdcnthums</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">seiner Secten,</hi> Gratz’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                        Juden,</hi> Derenbourg’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Palestine,</hi>
                    Hausrath’s <hi rend="italic">Neutestamentlichc</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Zeitgeschichte,</hi> Schürer’s <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Ncutcstamentliclien</hi><hi rend="italic">Zeitgeschichte,</hi>
                    and Gfrorer’s <hi rend="italic">Jahrhundert des Heils.</hi> On the Kabbala also:
                    —Delitzsch, <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der Jüdischen Poesie,</hi> 1836;
                    Jellinek, <hi rend="italic">Moses ben Sehern Tob de Leon und sein Verhältniss
                        zum Zohar,</hi> 1851; Ginsburg, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Kabbalah, its Doctrines,</hi><hi rend="italic">Development,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">and Literature,</hi> 1865. On the Alexandrian School
                    :—Gfrörer, <hi rend="italic">Philo</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">alexandrinische Theosophie,</hi>
                    1831; Keim, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte Jesu von</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Nazara,</hi> vol. i.; Siegfried, <hi rend="italic">Philo</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">von Alexandria als Ausleger des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >A.</hi><hi rend="italic">T.,</hi> 1875; Frankel, <hi rend="italic">Uebcr
                        den Einfluss der palästinischen Exegese auf die alexandrinische
                        Hermeneutik,</hi> 1851 and <hi rend="italic">lieber palästinische und
                        alexandrinische Schriftforschung,</hi> 1854; the monographs by Kaye on
                    Clement and Thomasius, and Redepenning on Origen; C. R. Hagenbach, <hi
                        rend="italic">Obs. circa Origenis</hi><hi rend="italic">methodum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">interp.,</hi> 1823; J. J. Bochinger, <hi rend="italic">De
                        Origenis allegorica S.S.</hi><hi rend="italic">interpretatione,</hi> 1829.
                    On the Antiochene School :—Hergenrother, <hi rend="italic">Die Antioch.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Schule und ihre Bedeutung auf exeg. Gebiete,</hi> 1866; Kihn,
                        <hi rend="italic">Die Bedeutung der</hi><hi rend="italic">Antioch.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Schule auf dem exeget. Gebiete,</hi> 1867; Specht, <hi
                        rend="italic">Der exeg. Standpunkt des Theodor von Mopsuestia und Theodoret
                        von Kyros in der Auslegung mess. Weissag.,</hi> 1871; also the monographs on
                    Chrysostom by Neander, Meyer, Forster, and Stephens. Of the treatises referred
                    to above, the following are of special importance:—Μ. Flacius, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Glavis</hi><hi rend="italic">S. Scripturas</hi> (by Musaeus), 1674;
                    Rambach, <hi rend="italic">Institutiones</hi><hi rend="italic">Her-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">meneuticae,</hi> 1723; Eraesti, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Institutio</hi><hi rend="italic">interpr.</hi><hi rend="italic">N.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">T.</hi> (in English by Terrot, 1843); Schleiermacher, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hermeneutik und Kritik mit besond. Beziehung auf das</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">N.</hi><hi rend="italic">T.</hi> (by Lücke), 1838; Fr. Lücke,
                        <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der Neutest. Hermeneutik,</hi> 1817. In addition
                    these also deserve notice:—S. F. N. Morus, <hi rend="italic">Super Hemneneutica
                        N.</hi><hi rend="italic">T. acroases</hi><hi rend="italic">academ.,</hi>
                    1797-1802; Olshausen, <hi rend="italic">Ein Wort über tiefem Schriftsinn,</hi>
                    1824; Kuenen, <hi rend="italic">Criticcs et Hermeneutices</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >librorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Novi Foederis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >lineamenta,</hi> 1858; Döpke, <hi rend="italic">Hermeneutik der Neutest.
                        Schriftsteller,</hi> 1829; Wilke, <hi rend="italic">Die Hermeneutik des N.
                        T. systematisch dargestellt,</hi> 1843-44; Immer, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hermeneutik des</hi><hi rend="italic">N.</hi><hi rend="italic">T.,</hi>
                    1873, English edition by Newman, Andover, 1877; Cellerier, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Manuel d'Her-meneutigue</hi><hi rend="italic">biblique,</hi> 1852; Doedes,
                        <hi rend="italic">Manual</hi><hi rend="italic">of Hermeneutics,</hi> 1867;
                    Lange, <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der bibk Hermeneutik,</hi> 1878. On the
                    Hermeneutics of the Roman Catholic Church, in addition to Loehnis, there may be
                    mentioned—J. Jahn, <hi rend="italic">Enchiridion Hermeneutical</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">generalis</hi><hi rend="italic">tabularum Vet.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">N. T.,</hi> 1812; Ranolder, <hi
                        rend="italic">Herm. bibl. gen.</hi><hi rend="italic">principia
                        rationalia,</hi> 1839; Kohlgruber, <hi rend="italic">Herrn,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">bibl.</hi><hi rend="italic">gener.,</hi> 1850; Güntner, <hi
                        rend="italic">Herrn, bibk</hi><hi rend="italic">gener.,</hi> 1851; Setwin,
                        <hi rend="italic">Herm. bibk</hi><hi rend="italic">institutiones,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Ύ?&gt;Τ2.·,</hi> Reithmayr, <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der
                        bibk Herrn.,</hi> 1874; Friedlieb, <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">zur bibk Hermen.,</hi> 1868; Wilke, <hi rend="italic">Bibi.
                        Hermen.,</hi> 1853. Important discussions of sections of the subject are
                    found in Seyffarth, <hi rend="italic">Uebcr</hi><hi rend="italic">Begriff,
                        Anordnung, und Umfang der</hi><hi rend="italic">Herm.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >des N. T.,</hi> 1824; J. C. K. von Hofmann, <hi rend="italic">Vermischte
                        Aufsätze,</hi> 1878: John Keble, <hi rend="italic">Primitive
                        Tradition</hi><hi rend="italic">recognized</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Holy Scripture,</hi> 1837, and <hi rend="italic">On the
                        Mysticism attributed to the Early Fathers of the Church,</hi> 1868; Merx,
                        <hi rend="italic">Eine Rede vom Auslegen</hi><hi rend="italic">ins
                        besondre</hi><hi rend="italic">des Alten</hi><hi rend="italic">Tests.,</hi>
                    1879. (S. D. F. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
