<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0403-0384-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HALIFAX (9th edition, volume 11, page 384)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q67d">Costs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053705">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n403/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HALIFAX</label>, a municipal and parliamentary borough and
                    market-town of England, in the northern division of the West Riding of
                    Yorkshire, is situated on a gentle acclivity almost surrounded by hills, on the
                    small river Hebble near its junction with the Calder, 7 miles south-west of
                    Bradford. Originally its streets were narrow and irregular, but many of the
                    older houses have been pulled down and new streets opened up, while the constant
                    additions made to it through the rapid increase of population have completely
                    changed its appearance. The principal buildings are the parish church of St
                    John, the restoration of which was completedin 1879 at a cost of £16,000, a
                    structure in the Perpendicular style, of different dates, and having the western
                    tower 117 feet in height; All Souls Church, begun in 1859 from the designs of
                    Sir Gilbert Scott, and erected at the expense of Mr Edward Akroyd, in theEarly
                    Decorated style, very richly ornamented with statues and carvings in Italian
                    marble, serpentine, and alabaster, and consisting of nave, aisles, transepts,
                    and chancel, with a very graceful tower and spire at the north-west angle 236
                    feet in height, and a sacristy at the north-east; the Square Church, erected by
                    the Congregationalists in 1857 at a cost of £16,000, an ornate cruciform
                    building with a tower and elaborate crocketed spire rising to a height of 235
                    feet; the town-hall, completed in 1863 after the designs of Sir Charles Barry at
                    a cost of £40,000; the infirmary, a large and elegant building in which medical
                    and surgical aid is afforded to outdoor as well as indoor patients; the
                    Waterhouse charity school, a handsome set of buildings forming three sides of a
                    quadrangle, erected in 1855; the Crossley almshouses, erected and endowed by Sir
                    Francis and Mr Joseph Crossley; the piecehall, a large quadrangular structure
                    occupying more than 2 acres of ground, erected in 1799 for the lodgment and sale
                    of piece goods, but now used as a market for fish and vegetables; the free
                    grammar school, founded in 1585 under royal charter for instruction in the
                    classical languages; the Crossley orphan home and school, built by the Crossley
                    brothers at a cost of £46,000; the museum, the oddfellows’ hall, the working
                    men’s college, the mechanics’ institute, the assembly and concert rooms, and the
                    theatre. There are three public parks, viz., Savile Park, 50 acres in extent;
                    the People’s Park, 12 j acres, laid out in a highly ornamental style from the
                    designs of Sir Joseph Paxton, and presented to the town in 1858 by Sir Francis
                    Crossley; and the Shrogg’s Park, 25 acres, opened in 1877. The North Bridge, a
                    fine structure of iron, spans the Hebble valley in two arches. Halifax derives
                    its importance from its manufactures of cloth, which began in the 15th century.
                    It ranks in Yorkshire with Leeds, Bradford, and Huddersfield as a seat of the
                    woollen and worsted manufacture. The principal staples are carpets, cashmeres,
                    Orleanses, coburgs, merinoes, lastings, alpacas, damasks, baizes, broad and
                    narrow cloths, kerseymeres, blankets, muslin-de-laines, shalloons, and figured
                    vestings. A considerable number of persons are employed in irom works, machine
                    works, and chemical works, and in the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n404/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0404-0385"/> neighbouring coal-mines and stone quarries.
                    The borough sends two members to parliament. The parish is the largest in Great
                    Britain, embracing 79,200 acres. The population of the municipal and
                    parliamentary borough in 1861 was 37,014, and in 1871 (with an extended area of
                    3704 acres) 65,510.</p>
                <p>Two derivations are given for the name Halifax. According to Camden it means
                    “holy hair,” and he accounts for the origin of the name from the fact that the
                    head of a virgin who had been murdered by a wicked clerk was suspended on a tree
                    in the neighbourhood, which came to be much resorted to by pilgrims. According
                    to another account, the name means “holy face,” and is derived from an image of
                    St John once preserved in a neighbouring hermitage. The first mention of the
                    town is in the 12th century, when its church was granted by William, earl of
                    Warren, to the priory of Lewes in Sussex. When its manufactures commenced in the
                    beginning of the 15th century the number of its houses was only 15, but they had
                    increased in 1540 to 520. It is said to have received a considerable accession
                    to its inhabitants and impulse to its prosperity from the merchants who fled
                    from the Netherlands to escape the persecution carried out under the auspices of
                    the duke of Alva. In 1642 it was garrisoned by the forces of the parliament, and
                    near it at a place still called the Bloody Field an engagement took place
                    between them and the royalists. In the forest of Hardwick, then coextensive with
                    the parish of Halifax, there at one time existed a custom called the “Gibbet
                    Law, ’’ according to which any person suspected to be in the unlawful possession
                    of goods to the value of 13⅛d. was tried by the frith-burghers of the liberty,
                    and if condemned was executed on a market day by a kind of axe resembling the
                    modern guillotine. The last execution took place in 1650. A number of eminent
                    men have been born in the town or neighbourhood of Halifax, including the
                    mathematician Henry Briggs, Archbishop Tillotson, Sir Henry Savile, and John
                    Foster. Daniel Defoe resided for some time in the town.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
