<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0688-0655-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENRY I</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 655</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:828821">Bats</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23f50">Fat</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34ms27">Bats</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm20">Pipe</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gk5r">Fats</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n688/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENRY I</label>. (1068-1135), king of England, fourth and
                    youngest son of William the Conqueror and Matilda of Flanders, was born some
                    time in the autumn of 1068. Local tradition fixes his birthplace at Selby in
                    Yorkshire. Little is known of his earlier life, except that he received an
                    unusually good education, and attained a proficiency rare among the princes of
                    his day. In 1086 he was dubbed knight. Next year his father bequeathed to him on
                    his death-bed a sum of five thousand pounds, and is said to have foretold that
                    he would eventually be king. Condemned, by the division of the Conqueror’s
                    territories, to a position of inferiority to his two brothers, he used lιis
                    legacy to improve that position. Robert, being in need of money, sold him the
                    districts of the Cotentin and the Avranchin, which he held of his brother as a
                    fief. His relations with Robert were not always friendly, but he defended
                    Normandy against Rufus, and aided his liege lord in putting down a revolt in
                    Rouen. Nevertheless, in the treaty between William and Robert made in 1091, he
                    was excluded from the succession, and soon afterwards was deprived of his lands
                    in Normandy.</p>
                <p>The treatment he met with from Robert was not likely to make him support the
                    terms of the treaty of 1091. Immediately after the death of Rufus, he rode to
                    Winchester, and seized the royal hoard in that city. Next day (August 3, 1100)
                    he was elected king by such of the witan as were present, and on Sunday, August
                    5th, he was crowned at Westminster. In order to conciliate the clergy and the
                    nation, he recalled Anselm, imprisoned Ranulf Flambard, and issued a
                    comprehensive charter of liberties. Before the year was out he married Matilda,
                    daughter of Malcolm and Margaret, and great-granddaughter of Edmund Ironside, a
                    step which greatly strengthened his otherwise insecure title to the crown. The
                    alliance thus contracted with the church and the nation was his constant support
                    in the struggle with his brother and his unruly vassals, which began
                    immediately. It resulted in the conquest of Normandy, the temporary suppression
                    of feudalism, and the consolidation of royal power on both sides of the Channel.
                    Robert, as soon as he returned from the Holy Land, attempted with the aid of a
                    conspiracy in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n689/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0689-0656"/> England to wrest the crown from the usurper. He
                    landed at Portsmouth (August 1, 1101), but before a blow was struck the brothers
                    came to terms. Robert recognized Henry as king of England, and returned to
                    Normandy. Henry’s vengeance fell upon bis brother’s partisans, and R &gt;bert of
                    Belesme and several others were banished from the country and lost their English
                    estates. Secure in England, Henry carried the war into the enemy’s country. His
                    brother’s misgovernment gave him both pretext and opportunity. After two or
                    three expeditions, the struggle was brought to a close by the battle of
                    Tenchebrai (September 28, 1106), in which Robert was taken prisoner. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Hj</hi> remained in captivity till his death in 1134, and
                    Normandy passed into the possession of the English king. This conquest at once
                    brought Henry into collision with France. Louis the Fat was a constant supporter
                    of Henry’s rebellious vassals, and of his rival and nephew, William, son of
                    Robert. Henceforward Henry had to spend most of his time in the duchy. A war
                    with France (1111-1113) ended in a peace which brought some advantages to Henry.
                    Louis gave up his claim to the sovereignty of Maine and Brittany, and Henry was
                    able to carry his old opponent, Robert of Belesme, to England, where he was
                    imprisoned for the rest of his life. Henry had already, though in vain,
                    attempted to secure the aid of Flanders by two treaties with Count Robert (1103,
                    1108). He now sought a mightier ally in the emperor Henry V., to whom he married
                    his daughter Matilda (January 7, 1114). Another war with France, which broke out
                    in 1116, and in which Louis took up the cause of William, son of Robert, against
                    his uncle, was marked by the battle of Noyon (1119). Ata council at Rheims
                    (1119) Louis accused Henry before Pope Calixtus of rebellion and usurpation.
                    Henry, however, pleaded his own cause before the pope at Gisors so persuasively
                    that Calixtus brought about a peace between the two kings (1120) on the basis of
                    a mutual restoration of conquests. During the war Henry had suffered a severe
                    loss in the death of his queen Matilda. He now felt it more than ever necessary
                    to take measures for securing the succession to his only son William. The
                    baronage of Normandy and England were made to do homage to the young prince
                    (1119), who shortly afterwards married Matilda, daughter of Fulk of Anjou, an
                    alliance by which Henry hoped to turn a dangerous foe into a firm friend, and to
                    secure at least the chance of a rich inheritance. All these hopes were, however,
                    shattered by the death of William (1120). Deprived of an heir to his throne,
                    Henry now married Adeliza, daughter of Godfrey, count of Louvain (1121), but the
                    marriage unfortunately proved childless. Shortly afterwards another rebellion,
                    headed by Count Waleran of Meulan, broke out in Normandy (1123). The rebels were
                    emboldened by the assistance of the king of France and the count of Anjou, but
                    were entirely defeated at Bourgtheroulde (1124). The terrible vengeance taken by
                    Henry on this occasion, together with the death of William, son of Robert, in
                    1128, seems to have finally crushed the opposition in Normandy. The death of
                    Duke Robert in 1134 removed the last object round which the schemes of rebellion
                    or the intrigues of France could centre. Meanwhile Henry had recalled his
                    daughter Matilda, now a widow, from Germany. In default of an heir to the
                    throDe, he made the witan swear to accept her as Lady of England and Normandy
                    (Christmas 1126). Next year he gave her in marriage to Geoffrey, son of Fulk,
                    count of Anjou, hoping thereby to secure the objects frustrated by the death of
                    his son. Fate, however, thwarted the immediate success of these schemes.</p>
                <p>The annals of England, after the expulsion of Robert of Belesme, are uneventful.
                    In his ecclesiastical policy Henry, without giving up the control over the
                    church which his father had asserted, was forced to recognize to a certain
                    extent the advancing claims of Rome. His dispute with Anselm was conducted with
                    good temper on both sides, and was brought to a satisfactory conclusion. Anselm
                    had made no objection to the ecclesiastical supremacy claimed by Rufus, but the
                    decrees of the Lateran Council (1099) obliged him to resist a similar claim when
                    put forward by Henry I. He refused to do homage to his new king, or to
                    consecrate the bishops whom Henry invested, according to ancient custom, with
                    the symbols of ecclesiastical dignity. Neither side would give way. Henry
                    continued to make bishops as before, and Anselm refused to consecrate them. In
                    1103 he left England. For the next three years the affairs of Normandy hindered
                    the settlement of the question, but a compromise was effected in 1107. The pope,
                    Paschal II., consented that homage should be done to the king, while Henry gave
                    up his claim to investiture with the ring and staff. The question thus settled
                    was not reopened till the days of Becket. In other respects Henry acquiesced in
                    the tendency of the time towards ecclesiastical separatism, and countenanced the
                    decrees of the synod of 1102, which forbade the marriage of the clergy and the
                    tenure of temporal offices by ecclesiastics. He showed his care for the church
                    by the establishment of two new sees, those of Ely (1109) and Carlisle (1133),
                    taken respectively from the unwieldy dioceses of Lincoln and York. In the old
                    quarrel between York and Canterbury, Henry supported the claims of the southern
                    metropolitan against Archbishop Thurstan. On Anselm’s death, Henry was guilty of
                    leaving the see vacant for five years, but in his other dealings with the church
                    he seems to have been actuated by worthy motives. He refused, however, to open
                    her high places to Englishmen, and till near the end of his reign no native
                    attained the dignity of prelate. The same exclusive spirit made itself felt in
                    the appointments to temporal office. But although political liberty and
                    influence were not granted to Englishmen under Henry I., the English nation as a
                    whole acquiesced gladly in his rule. Its chief wants were justice and order, and
                    protection from feudal tyranny; and these blessings it obtained. The necessities
                    of his position compelled Henry to rely mainly on his English subjects. As a
                    counterpoise to the local influence of the baronage, he did his best to restore
                    to activity the old popular institutions of the hundred and the county-court, of
                    tithings and frankpledge, of w atch and ward. His frequent progresses through
                    the country, for judicial and other purposes, form a link between the annual
                    courts held by the Conqueror and the regular circuits of the justices
                    established by Henry II. In the administration of justice and the toils of
                    government he relied on new men, raised from the ranks and dependent on himself
                    for their position. The older baronage he habitually depressed, and every
                    unsuccessful rebellion thinned the ranks of the feudal nobility, while it
                    tightened the link between the king and the nation.</p>
                <p>Thus secure at home, Henry was dreaded by his neighbours within the four seas.
                    Over Scotland, Ireland, and Wales a sort of ecclesiastical supremacy was
                    recognized. On the northern frontier there was peace throughout the reign; on
                    the western there was more disturbance. Henry settled a colony of Flemings in
                    Pembroke (1111), and made two expeditions into Wales (1114, 1121), in one of
                    which he received the submission of several Welsh princes. The profound peace
                    which England enjoyed for a period of thirty-four years is the best testimony to
                    Henry’s merits as a king. As a man his character is not admirable, nor yet
                    wholly to be condemned. He was hard, merciless, and unforgiving, but not
                    wantonly cruel. He sometimes displayed a grim humour which reminds one of his
                    father; but he never gave "way to the vices and brutality of Rufus, nor to the
                    jovial good-humour which was so winning in his <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n690/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0690-0657"/> eldest brother. Regarded as the “Lion of Justice”
                    by his people, and bitterly regretted after he was gone, he was not a popular
                    king. He died, after bequeathing his crown to his daughter Matilda, near Rouen
                    (December 1, 1135). His body was carried to England, and buried in the abbey he
                    had founded at Reading.</p>
                <p>The following <hi rend="italic">general authorities</hi> may be consulted for
                    this and the next five reigns here noticed :— <hi rend="italic">Statutes of the
                    Realm</hi>; Rymer’s <hi rend="italic">Faedera</hi>; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pipe-Rolls,</hi><hi rend="italic">Rotuli</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Cartarum,</hi><hi rend="italic">Rotuli Litterarum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bat.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Claus.</hi> &amp;c. (ed. Hardy); Lappenberg and
                    Pauli, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">von England;</hi>
                    Stubbs, <hi rend="italic">Constitutional History of England</hi>; Stubbs, <hi
                    rend="italic">Documents illustrative of English History</hi> (for Henry I., II.,
                    III.); Lingard, <hi rend="italic">History of England</hi>; Green, <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the English People.</hi></p>
                <p>For this reign, <hi rend="italic">original authorities :—A nglo-Saxon
                    Chronicle;</hi> Florence of Worcester, <hi rend="italic">Chronicon ex</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicis,</hi> with its <hi rend="italic">continuation</hi>;
                    Simeon of Durham, <hi rend="italic">De Regibus Anglorum,</hi> &amp;c.; Ordericus
                    Vitalis, <hi rend="italic">Historia Ecclesiastica</hi>; William of Malmesbury,
                    <hi rend="italic">Gesta Pontificum</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglorum,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Gesta</hi><hi rend="italic">Regum Anglorum,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Novella·,</hi> Eadmer, <hi
                    rend="italic">Vita Aιιselmi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Historia Novorum;</hi>
                    Robert du Mont, <hi rend="italic">Chronica,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >continuation</hi> of William of Jumiéges; the <hi rend="italic">Magnus Rotulus
                    Scaccarii,</hi> 1131 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> (ed. Hunter).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Modern authorities.—</hi> Freeman, <hi rend="italic">History of
                    the Norman Conquest,</hi> vol. V.; Church, <hi rend="italic">Life of
                    Anselm;</hi> Palgrave, <hi rend="italic">History of Normandy and England.</hi>
                    (G. W. P. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
