<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0374-0355-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAARLEM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 355</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dp5n">Communion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:881621">Courantes</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:927691">Florin</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n374/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAARLEM</label>, a city of the Netherlands, the chief town of
                    the province of North Holland. By rail it is 11 miles W. of Amsterdam, 19 S. of
                    Alkmaar, and 20 N. of Leyden. Distant about 5 miles from the German Ocean, it
                    communicates with the Zuyder-Zee by the Spaarne and the Ij. The railway to
                    Amsterdam was opened in 1839, and that to Alkmaar in 1867.</p>
                <p>Haarlem is a typical Dutch town. The branches of the Spaarne and an extensive
                    system of canals bring the shiptraffic into the heart of it, and turn its
                    streets into so many quays. The roadways are paved with bricks; the houses have
                    gable-ends with old-fashioned crow-steps; and everything wears a decent and
                    quiet aspect, which to one man is dulness and to another “aristocratic gravity
                    and modest coquetry.” What the city lacks in liveliness it makes up by the
                    interest of its historical associations and the number of its scientific and
                    artistic institutions. The great market place especially has much that is worth
                    seeing: the town-house and the cathedral of St Bavo; the old meat market, a
                    building of the end of the 16th century in the old Dutch style; the stadsdoelen,
                    or place where in former times the burgesses used to assemble in arms; and the
                    statue erected to Koster in 1856, when in Holland he was still generally
                    considered the inventor of printing. St Bavo’s is one of the most famous
                    churches in the Netherlands. It is a cruciform structure completed in 1538, and
                    makes a considerable impression on the spectator by the great length (about 426
                    feet) of its main axis and the height and steepness of the roof. The tower is
                    about 255 feet high. Within the lofty vaulting is supported by twenty very light
                    columns, and there is a good deal of beauty about the perspective of its aisles.
                    The organ, built by Christian Muller of A msterdam between 1735 and 1738, was
                    for some time the largest in the world, and is still celebrated for the
                    sweetness of its tone, especially in the vox humana stop. It possesses four
                    key-boards, 64 stops, and 5000 pipes, the largest of which is 15 inches in
                    diameter. Among the monuments in the church are those of Bilderdijk the poet and
                    the hydraulic engineers Christiaan Brünings and Fredrik William Conrad, the
                    latter the projector of the sluices at Katwijk. In the belfry are the <hi
                    rend="italic">damiaatjes,</hi> small bells presented to the town according to
                    tradition by William I., the conqueror of Damietta. At the head of the
                    scientific institutions of Haarlem may be placed the Dutch society of sciences
                    <hi rend="italic">(HoUandsche Maatschappij van Wetenschappeη)</hi> founded in
                    1752, which possesses very valuable collections in botany, natural history, and
                    geology. Teyler’s foundation (Teyler’s Stichting), instituted in accordance with
                    the last will of Pietre Teyler van der Hulst for the study of theology, natural
                    philosophy, poetry, history, drawing, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n375/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0375-0356"/> numismatics, has various auxiliary collections in
                    the founder’s former residence, The Dutch society of industry, founded in 1777,
                    is still active and flourishing, with branches established all over the country.
                    In 1871 it instituted a colonial museum, which along with the royal museum of
                    modern art is accommodated in the pavilion formerly the residence of an
                    Amsterdam banker, Hope, and acquired for the crown by King Louis Napoleon. The
                    colonial museum presents a complete survey of the manifold products of the Dutch
                    possessions in the East Indian Archipelago, and the royal mueeum lias a
                    collection of 250 pictures. Among the benevolent institutions of the city it is
                    enough to mention the hospital for old men founded in 1608, and the beautiful
                    Teyler’s Hospital.</p>
                <p>The staple industries of Haarlem have been greatly modified in the course of
                    time. Under the counts of Holland cloth-weaving and brewing were in a very
                    thriving condition; but under Charles V. they lost enormously in importance.
                    While 2000 pieces of cloth had been manufactured annually in the end of the 15th
                    century, 800 or 900 was the number for 1515; and the breweries diminished from
                    120 in 1494 to 95 in 1503, and by 1513 were no more than 77. After the
                    revocation of the edict of Nantes, silk, lace, anl damask-weaving were
                    introduced by French refugees, and in course of time these industries gave
                    employment to 10,000 of the population. About the close of the 18th century this
                    remarkable prosperity was a thing of the past; and it was not till after the
                    Belgian revolution that Haarlem began to turn its attention to the various
                    departments of manufacture in which it is now engaged. Cotton factories,
                    carriage-works, bleach-works, cotton and silk dye-works, a famous type-foundry,
                    oil-works, soap-works, breweries, and a factory for preserved meats are among
                    the more important establishments. The extensive workshops of the Dutch railway
                    company are also of value to the town. One of the printing establishments has
                    the reputation of being the oldest in the Netherlands, and publishes the oldest
                    Dutch paper, <hi rend="italic">De Opragte Haarlemmer</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Courant.</hi> As market gardening, especially in the flower department, is
                    largely carried on in the immediate vicinity, Haarlem is the seat of a
                    flourishing trade in “Dutch roots,” especially in hyacinths, tulips,
                    fritillaries, spiraeas, and japυnicas. A considerable business is also done in
                    the butter, cheese, and other agricultural produce from the surrounding
                    country.</p>
                <p>Though the population of Haarlem has been steadily increasing since the beginning
                    of the present century, it has not become so great as it was in the 17th. In
                    1570 the total was 20,772 souls, of whom 1836 were Dutchmen capable of bearing
                    arms, 1215 Englishmen and Frenchmen, 1856 Germans, and 15,865 women and
                    children. By 1622 it had increased to 39,455. A rapid decline took place in the
                    18th century; from 26,281 in 1748 the number sank to 21,227 in 1796, and by 1815
                    it was not more than 17,432. Seven years later we find 18,453 inhabitants,
                    21,667 in 1830, 24,012 in 1840, 25,852 in 1850, and 27,534 in 1860. The year
                    1874 showed 32,758, and three years later the number was no less than 35,692. In
                    1869 -1870 there were 14,471 members of the Dutch Reformed Communion, 11,574
                    Roman Catholics, and 565 Jews.</p>
                <p>Haarlem is mentioned in a register of the 10th century as Haralem. From Count
                    William II. it obtained a charter in 1245, andin the course of the following
                    centuries it rapidly advanced in prosperity. In 1492 the insurgents called the
                    “bread and cheese folk” got possession of the town, but before the year was out
                    it was recovered by the imperial general Duke Albert of Saxony. The year 1493
                    was witness of a great conflagration, and in 1509 the plague claimed its many
                    victims. In 1559 Haarlem became a bishop’s see. The prominent part that its
                    inhabitants took in the revolt of the Netherlands brought upon it an
                    unparalleled disaster. Don Frederick son of the duke of Alva invested the town
                    with 30,000 men in December 1573, and after a siege, in which the burghers
                    defended themselves with admirable and pertinacious heroism, it was obliged to
                    capitulate in July 1573. The conquerors, in spite of their promise of mercy,
                    took barbarous vengeance, and it was not till July 1677 that the town was
                    recovered from their grasp by the prince of Orange. In its subsequent history
                    the main events are the inundations of 1775 and 1791, the arrival of the
                    Prussians in 1787, and the quatercentenary celebration of the invention of
                    printing in 1823.</p>
                <p>See F. Allan, <hi rend="italic">Geschιcdenis</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">beschrijving van Haarlem van de vroogste tijden tot op</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">onze</hi><hi rend="italic">dagcn onder medewerking van Ekema,
                    Enschede,</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi rend="italic">Geelings.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Haarlem Lake,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Harlemmer Meer,</hi>
                    a commune of the province of North Holland, constituted by the law of 16th July
                    1855. It has an area of about 46,000 acres, and its population has increased
                    from 7000 in 1860 to 13,602 in 1878. As its name indicates, the commune was
                    formerly a lake, and, according to Amersfoordt, this lake was a relic of a
                    northern arm of the Rhine which passed through the district in the time of the
                    Romans. In 1531 the Haarlemmer Meer had an area of 6430 acres, and in its
                    vicinity were three smaller sheets of water—the Leid’sehe Meer or Leyden Lake,
                    the Spieling Meer, and the Oude Meer or Old Lake—with a united area of about
                    7600 acres. The four lakes were ultimately incorporated into one by successive
                    inundations, and by 1647 the new Haarlem Lake had an area of 36,400 acres, which
                    by 1740 was increased to 42,000. As early as 1643 Jan Adriaanszoon Leeghwater
                    proposed to endyke and drain the lake; and similar schemes, among which those of
                    Nikolaas Samuel Cruquius in 1742 and of Baron van Lijnden van Hemmen in 1821 are
                    worthy of special mention, were brought forward from time to time. But it was
                    not till 1836, when one furious hurricane on the 9th of November drove the
                    waters as far as the gates of Amsterdam, and another on the 25th of December
                    sent them in the opposite direction to submerge the streets of Leyden, that the
                    mind of the nation was turned seriously to the matter. In August 1837 the king
                    appointed a royal commission of inquiry; the scheme proposed by the commission
                    received the sanction of the second chamber in March 1839, and in the following
                    May the necessary law was passed. The first business was to dig a canal round
                    the lake for the reception of the water and the accommodation of the great
                    traffic which had previously been carried on. The canal was made 38 miles in
                    length, with a depth of 9 feet, and a width of 130 feet on the west side of the
                    lake and 115 feet on the east side. The preliminary works were not completed
                    till 1845. The area enclosed by the canal was rather more than 70 square miles;
                    the average depth of the lake was 13 feet l <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 44
                    inches; and as the water had no natural outfall it was calculated that probably
                    1000 million tons would have to be raised by mechanical means. A gigantic
                    steam-engine designed by Messrs J. Gibb and A. Dean of London was erected and
                    named in honour of Leeghwater. It could raise 112 tons at each stroke and
                    discharge 1,000,000 tons in 25⅜ hours. The total weight of iron used for the
                    engine, pumps, &amp;c., was 640 tons, and the cost of the machinery and
                    buildings amounted to £36,000. Two other engines of equal size and power were
                    afterwards constructed by Messrs Harvey of Hayle and Messrs Fox and Co. of
                    Perran, in Cornwall, the makers of the “Leeghwater.” Thej <hi rend="superscript"
                    > r</hi> were named respectively the Cruquius and the Van Lijnden. Pumping
                    commenced in 1848, and the lake was dry by the 1st of July 1852. At the first
                    sale of the highest lands along the banks on August 16, 1853, 784 hectares were
                    bought for 575,000 florins, or 733 florins per hectare; but the average price
                    afterwards was less. The whole area of 42,000 acres recovered from the waters
                    has brought in 9,400,000 florins or about £780,000, so that the actual cost to
                    the nation has only been 4,400,000 florins or £300,000, though the expense of
                    the enterprise amounted to 13,787,377 florins or £1,080,000. The soil is of
                    various kinds, loam, clay, sand, and peat; most of it is sufficiently fertile,
                    though in the lower portions there are barren patches where the scanty
                    vegetation is covered with an ochreous deposit. Com, seeds, cattle, butter, and
                    cheese are the principal produce. The roads which traverse the commune are
                    bordered by plcasant-looking farm-houses built after the varioue styles of
                    Holland, Friesland, or Brabant. Hoofddorp, Venneperdorp or Nieuw Vennep,
                    Abbenes, and the vicinities of the three great steam-engines arc the spots where
                    the population has clustered most thickly. The first church was built in 1855;
                    in 1877 there were seven. In 1854 the city of Leyden laid claim to the
                    possession of the new territory, but the courts decided in favour of the
                    nation.</p>
                <p>A list of works on the Haarlem Lake is given by Gevers van Endegeest, <hi
                    rend="italic">Du dessèchement</hi><hi rend="italic">du Lac de Harlem</hi> (The
                    Hague, 1849-1861, 3 parts, with plates). See also J. P. Amersfoordt, <hi
                    rend="italic">Het Harlemmer-meer,</hi> Haarlem, 1857, published by the Amsterdam
                    <hi rend="italic">Maatschappij Felix</hi><hi rend="italic">Meritis.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
