<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0703-0670-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENRY II</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 670</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1157239">Triumph</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n703/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENRY II</label>. (1519-1559), king of France, the second son
                    of Francis I. and Claude, succeeded to the throne in 1547. When only seven years
                    old he was sent by his father, with his brotheι∙ the dauphin Francis, as a
                    hostage to Spain in 1526, whence they returned after the conclusion of the peace
                    of Caιnbray in 1529. Henry was too young to have carried away any abiding
                    impressions, yet throughout his life his character, dress, and bearing were far
                    more Spanish than French. In 1533 his father married him to Catherine de’
                    Medici, from which match, as he said, Francis hoped to gain great advantage,
                    even though it might be somewhat of a misalliance. He did not then think that
                    the dauphin would die so soon, and Catherine thereby become queen of France.
                    Italian manners and politics entered with her into France, and long affected the
                    history and fortunes of the country. Henry gathered round him a court which
                    contrasted strongly with that of his father. Francis, with all his grave faults
                    and selfishness, had fostered learning, had treated his people kindly, and had
                    rarely checked even the Reformers. But Henry, under the influence of Diana of
                    Poitiers, headed the strict Catholic movement; the escape of the learned from
                    Paris to Geneva at his accession showed that not merely Huguenot doctrines but
                    Renaissance studies were in peril. His court underwent an immediate change: the
                    old officers were dismissed, and men whom Francis had disliked or banished
                    returned. Immorality did not take flight, for Diana of Poitiers and Catherine
                    de’ Medici were at court, but it ceased to be gay and bright; men must be grave
                    and severe, even in their vices. At first Diana of Poitiers and the grim old
                    soldier Anne of Montmorency swayed the king; later, the two brothers Francis,
                    duke of Guise, and Charles, cardinal of Lorraine, rose to power, with the
                    marshal St André; everything was done and given through one or other of these
                    men. Catherine de’ Medici was as yet completely in the background.</p>
                <p>The final union of Brittany with France marks the opening year of the reign. In
                    1518 Henry won a great diplomatic triumph over the ministers of Edward VI. of
                    England, by getting possession of Mary queen of Scots, then only six years old;
                    he had her educated in France, and eventually married to his son the dauphin
                    Francis. In 1549 he appeared in Paris for the first time, and marked his
                    presence by a great burning of Calvinists; and soon after he claimed back
                    Boulogne, which had been pro. αised to Francis I. by Henry VIII. After a
                    successful campaign, he made the English Government, then extremely weak, cede
                    Boulogne, and Henry entered the place in May 1550.</p>
                <p>Hitherto he had not come into collision with Charles V.; the time was now
                    approaching when he would enter into contest with him, and permanently advance
                    the borders of his kingdom, while he inflicted a great blow on the emperor.
                    Though early in his reign he had dealt with the German Protestants, and with the
                    Ottoman power, he had taken no active steps; now the league of German princes,
                    headed by Maurice of Saxony, offered an opportunity not to be missed; Henry made
                    a compact with the Swiss and Turks, and concluded a secret treaty (September 3,
                    1550) with the German princes; in 1552, by the league of Chambord, he undertook
                    to seize the three bishoprics,—Metz, Verdun, and Toul. And so while Maurice
                    drove the emperor from Innsbruck, Henry sent Montmorency into Lorraine. The
                    bishoprics were won almost without a blow, and Henry was acknowledged as
                    “avenger of Germanic liberty”; an attempt on Strasburg failed. After the siege
                    of Metz by Charles V. in the winter of 1552-53, this district, French-speaking,
                    though feudally under the empire, remained in French hands,—Metz till 1870, Toul
                    and Verdun to this day.</p>
                <p>In 1556 Henry, supporting the anti-Spanish policy of the “Theatine” pope, Paul
                    IV., again made war with Spain. Francis of Guise was sent early in 1557 into
                    Italy to oppose the duke of Alva. Anne of Montmorency went to the northern
                    frontier; Gaspard of Coligny, who commanded in Picardy, was ordered to begin
                    hostilities. These led to the disastrous battle of St Quentin, in which the
                    French were utterly defeated (August 10, 1557); it was followed by the fall of
                    the town, at that time the chief bulwark of France to the north. Francis of
                    Guise, recalled in haste from Italy, redressed the balance at the expense of
                    England by the capture of Calais (January 1558), and the triumph of the house of
                    Guise seemed complete when Mary Stewart was married to the dauphin in the same
                    year; their niece, with her claims on the Scottish and English crowns, would now
                    ascend the throne of France. The defeat of the French at Gravelines, the desire
                    of Montmorency to escape from captivity, the wish of the High Catholics to have
                    leisure to extirpate heresy, the sympathy of Philip with that aim, the accession
                    of Elizabeth of England—all these things made peace necessary, and the treaty of
                    Cateau Cambresis (April 1559) closed the war. As a sequel to the peace dιigh
                    feast was held at Paris to celebrate the marriage of Henry’s two daughters; in a
                    tournament he received his death-wound from the captain of his Scottish guards,
                    Montgomery. So ended Henry II., in his forty-first year. Handsome, brave, and
                    cold, he left little mark on his age; he is all but forgotten in the stormy days
                    which followed. By Catherine de’ Medici he had ten children, three of whom
                    succeeded to the throne,—Francis II., Charles IX., and Henry III. The
                    legislation of his reign was slight; he reduced the number of secretaries of
                    state to four, and arranged their functions afresh; he issued an edict in behalf
                    of a better coinage, reserved to himself the exclusive sale of salt, and
                    permitted the foundation of the university of Rheims. In 1555 we find the first
                    French Reformed churches established at Paris; these were quickly followed by
                    others. The reign saw the close of the struggle between the crowns of Spain and
                    France.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de Montluc;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de Tavanncs;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de Vieillcville;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de Villars; Art</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    vérifier les</hi><hi rend="italic">dates,</hi> série ii., torn vi.; Brantôme,
                    <hi rend="italic">Vies</hi><hi rend="italic">des Hommes illustres,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Davies</hi><hi rend="italic">illustres</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Francoises;</hi><hi rend="italic">Commentaires de François</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Rabutin</hi>; Thuanus (De Thou), <hi rend="italic">Hist, sui
                    temp.</hi><hi rend="italic">Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">CXXV.</hi> (G. W.
                    K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
