<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0416-0397-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HALLEY, Edmund</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 397</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:871385">Compassion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1131648">Stars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:871379">Compass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1064341">Pinks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1064324">Pink</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40v89k12">Compassion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4086357g">Stars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g04r">Compass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j598">Charts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n416/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HALLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edmund</hi></label> (1656-1742),
                    an eminent astronomer, was born at Haggerston, near London, October 29, 1656.
                    His father, a wealthy soapboiler, desiring to give his only son an education
                    suitable to his promising genius, placed him at St Paul’s School, where he was
                    equally distinguished for classical as for mathematical ability. Before leaving
                    it fer Queen’s College, Oxford, which he entered as commoner in 1673, he had
                    observed the change in the variation of the compass, and, at the age of
                    nineteen, he supplied a new and improved method of determining the elements of
                    the planetary orbits. His detection of considerable errors in the tables then in
                    use led him to the conclusion that a more accurate ascertainment of the places
                    of the fixed stars was indispensable to the progress of astronomy; and, finding
                    that Flamsteed and Hevelius had already undertaken to catalogue those visible in
                    northern latitudes, he assumed to himself the task of making observations in the
                    southern hemisphere. A recommendation from Charles II. to the East India Company
                    procured for him an apparently suitable, though, as it proved, ill-chosen
                    station, and in November 1676 he embarked for St Helena. On the voyage he
                    noticed the retardation of the pendulum in approaching the equator: and during
                    his stay on the island he observed the transit of Mercury, which suggested to
                    him the important idea of employing similar phenomena for the calculation of the
                    solar distance. He returned to England in November 1678, having by the
                    registration of 360 stars won the title of the “Southern Tycho,” and by the
                    translation to the heavens of the “Royal Oak,” earned a degree of master of
                    arts, conferred at Oxford by the king’s command December 3, 1678, almost
                    simultaneously with his election as fellow of the Royal Society. Six months
                    later, the indefatigable astronomer started for Dantzic to set at rest a dispute
                    of long standing between Hooke and Hevelius as to the respective merits of plain
                    or telescopic sights; and towards the end of 1680 he proceeded on a Continental
                    tour. In Paris he observed with Cassini the great comet of 1680 after its
                    perihelion passage; and having returned to England, he married in 1682 Mary,
                    daughter of Mr Tooke, auditor of the exchequer, with whom he lived harmoniously
                    for fifty-five years. He now fixed his residence at Islington, engaged chiefly
                    upon lunar observations, with a view to the great desideratum of a method of
                    finding the longitude at sea. His mind, however, was also busy with the
                    momentous problem of gravity. Having reached so far as to perceive that the
                    central force of the solar system must decrease inversely as the square of the
                    distance, and applied vainly to Wren and Hooke for further elucidation, he made
                    in August 1684 that journey to Cambridge for the purpose of consulting Newton,
                    which resulted in the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Principia.</hi> The
                    labour and expense of passing this great work through the press devolved upon
                    Halley, who also wrote the prefixed hexameters ending with the well-known
                    line—</p>
                <p>Nec fas est propius mortali attingere divos.</p>
                <p>In 1696 he was, although a zealous Tory, appointed comptroller of the mint at
                    Chester, and (August 19, 1698) he received a commission as captain of the
                    “Paramour Pink” for the purpose of making extensive observations on the
                    conditions of terrestrial magnetism. This task he accomplished in a voyage which
                    lasted two years, and extended <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n417/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0417-0398"/> to the 52d degree of S. latitude. The results
                    were published in a <hi rend="italic">General Chart of the Variation of the
                    Compass</hi> in 1701 j and immediately afterwards he executed by royal command a
                    careful survey of the tides and coasts of the British Channel, an elaborate map
                    of which he produced in 1702. On his return from a journey to Dalmatia, for the
                    purpose of selecting and fortifying the port of Trieste, he was nominated,
                    November 1703, Savilian professor of geometry at Oxford, and received an
                    honorary degree of doctor of laws. Between 1713 and 1721 he acted as secretary
                    to the Royal Society, hiving previously during eight years (1685-93) filled the
                    same office, and early in 1720 he succeeded Flamsteed as astronomer-royal.
                    Although in his sixtyfourth year, he undertook to observe the moon through an
                    entire revolution of her nodes (eighteen years), and actually carried out his
                    purpose. He died in the full possession of his faculties, January 14, 1742, at
                    the age of eighty-five.</p>
                <p>Halley’s most notable scientific achievements were—his detection of the “long
                    inequality”of Jupiter and Saturn,and of the acceleration of the moon’s mean
                    motion; his discovery of the proper motions of the fixed stars; his theory of
                    variation, including the hypothesis of four magnetic poles, revived by Hansteen
                    in 1819, and his suggestion of the magnetic origin of the aurora borealis; his
                    calculation of the orbit of the 1682 comet (the first ever attempted), coupled
                    with a prediction of its return, strikingly verified in 1759 and 1835; and his
                    indication · (in 1716, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> No. 348) of a method
                    still used for determining the solar parallax by means of the transits of
                    Venus.</p>
                <p>His principal works are <hi rend="italic">Catalogus Stellarum Australium,</hi>
                    London, 1679, the substance of which was embodied in vol. iii. of Flamsteed’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Historia Coelestis,</hi> 1725; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Synopsis</hi><hi rend="italic">Astronomiae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Cometicae,</hi> Oxford, 1705; <hi rend="italic">Astronomical Tables,</hi>
                    London, 1752; also eighty-one miscellaneous papers of considerable interest,
                    scattered through, the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions.</hi> To
                    these should be added his version from the Arabic (which language he acquired
                    for the purpose) of the treatise of Apollonius <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sectione rationis,</hi> with a restoration of his two lost books
                    <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">sectione spatii,</hi> both published
                    at Oxford in 1706; also his fine edition of the <hi rend="italic">Conics</hi> of
                    Apollonius, with the treatise by Serenus <hi rend="italic">De sections</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">cylindri</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">coni,</hi>
                    Oxford, 1710, folio. His edition of the <hi rend="italic">Spherics</hi> of
                    Menelaus was published by his friend Dr Costard in 1758.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
