<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0540-0509-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HASDRUBAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 509</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1009087">Marching</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1009043">Marches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n540/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HASDRUBAL</label>. Of the bearers of this very common
                    Carthaginian name the most famous are the following :—</p>
                <p>1, One of the leaders of the popular party at the close of the First Punic War.
                    He was conspicuous for his dexterous management in politics and his conciliatory
                    manners. He married the daughter of Hamilcar Barca; and his skilful and cordial
                    co-operation was of enormous consequence to Hamilcar during his Spanish wars. He
                    went to Spain with his father-in-law, but soon returned to Carthage, where his t
                    dents were specially needed to conduct the party at home. He was, however, in
                    Spain when Hamilcar fell (229); and was soon formally appointed by the home
                    Government to the command which he had at once assumed. Devoting himself most
                    successfully to the task of consolidating the Carthaginian power in Spain, he
                    founded New Carthage as the Spanish capital, and married the daughter of a
                    Spanish chief. His kindly and generous manner attached the natives to him, and
                    brought many over to the Carthaginian alliance. In 221 he fell by the hand of an
                    assassin. The account given of him by Polybiu3 is much more favourable and far
                    more trustworthy than that of the Roman author Fabius whom he refers to.</p>
                <p>2. The second son of the great Hamilcar. He was left by Hannibal as commander in
                    Spain (219 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>), where he had to contend with the two
                    Scipios, Cneius and Publius. Three years were spent in desultory warfare, in
                    which the Romans were generally successful. After the battle of Cannae,
                    Hasdrubal was ordered to march into Italy, while Himilco was sent from Carthage
                    with a fresh army to supply his place. But a decisive battle on the Ebro, in
                    which he was totally defeated, checked his northward march. It is hardly
                    possible to exaggerate the importance of this battle. Had a fresh Carthaginian
                    army joined Hannibal in Italy for the campaign of 215 or 214, the danger to Rome
                    would have been infinitely increased. Several years now passed, marked by the
                    Roman historians with fresh Roman victories; and it is certain that the struggle
                    continued doubtful till 212, when both the Scipios were defeated and slain. In
                    spite of this great success, Hasdrubal was not at the moment able to begin the
                    march on Italy. The Romans were skilfully rallied by Lucius Marcius, and in 211
                    a fresh army under the praetor Nero landed in Spain. At the same time there
                    seems to have been no co-operation among the Carthaginian generals; and when the
                    younger Scipio landed in Spain (210) he found their armies widely separated.
                    Taking advantage of this, Scipio by a sudden attack (209) captured New Carthage,
                    which contained vast military stores, all the Spanish hostages, and 10,000
                    captives. To achieve this brilliant success he had to leave the road northwards
                    undefended; and although he rapidly returned and (according to the Roman
                    accounts) defeated Hasdrubal at Baecula in Andalusia, the Carthaginian general
                    was able to make his way with a strong army to the Pyrenees, which he crossed in
                    safety near the western extremity. The whole course of the Spanish wars, and
                    especially the chronology of these later events, are very obscure. At all events
                    Hasdrubal, after a very rapid and skilful march across the whole breadth of
                    Gaul, appeared early in 207 in the north of Italy. When once he had succeeded in
                    getting out of Spain, this brilliant march proved Hasdrubal worthy of his father
                    and his brother; and long as it had taken to carry out his plan, we must
                    remember that after the Romans perceived the necessity of keeping him back from
                    Italy the difficulties in his way were enormous. On hearing of the passage of
                    the Pyrenees, the Romans raised extraordinary levies, but before they had taken
                    any steps to meet him, Hasdrubal was already in Cisalpine Gaul. Hannibal was
                    still in Apulia, perhaps not expecting his brother so soon; Hasdrubal sent to
                    meet him two Numidian horsemen with four Gauls, who almost at the end of their
                    perilous journey fell into the hands of the consul Nero. In the meantime
                    Hasdrubal had advanced into Umbria, where the plebeian consul Livius was
                    excamped near Sena. Nero, with 7000 men, left his own camp, and by a rapid
                    march, which must be ranked among the most important events of the war, joined
                    his colleague. The united army was much too strong for Hasdrubal. He tried to
                    avoid a battle, but his guides failed him, and he w as forced to fight on the
                    south bank of the Metaurus. A long and bloody conflict resulted in the complete
                    defeat of the Carthaginians, and Hasdrubal, after all was lost, fell sword in
                    hand in the midst of the enemy. His head, which was thrown by Nero’s soldiers
                    into Hannibal’s camp, first revealed to the latter his brother’s defeat and the
                    ruin of the Carthaginian cause.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n541/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0541-0510"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
