<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0512-0481-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARMONIC ANALYSIS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 481</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc1k">Waves</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq8b">Tides</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1172900">Waves</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:936106">Functions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n512/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARMONIC ANALYSIS</label> is the name given by Sir William
                    Thomson and Professor Tait in their treatise on <hi rend="italic">Natural
                    Philosophy</hi> to a general method of investigating physical questions, the
                    earliest applications of which seem to have been suggested by the study of the
                    vibrations of strings and the analysis of these vibrations into their
                    fundamental tone and its harmonics or overtones.</p>
                <p>The motion of a uniform stretched string fixed at both ends is a periodic motion;
                    that is to say, after a certain interval of time, called the fundamental period
                    of the motion, the form of the string and the velocity of every part of it are
                    the same as before, provided that the energy of the motion has not been sensibly
                    dissipated during the period.</p>
                <p>There are two distinct methods of investigating the motion of a Uniform stretched
                    string. One of these may be called the wave method, and the other the harmonic
                    method. The wave method is founded on the theorem that in a stretched string of
                    infinite length a wave of any form may be propagated in either direction with a
                    certain velocity, V, which we may define as the “velocity of propagation.” If a
                    wave of any form travelling in the positive direction meets another travelling
                    in the opposite direction, the form of which is such that the lines joining
                    corresponding points of the two waves are all bisected in a fixed point in the
                    line of the string, then the point of the string corresponding to this point
                    will remain fixed, while the two waves pass it in opposite directions. If we now
                    suppose that the form of the waves travelling in the positive direction is
                    periodic, that is to say, that after the wave has travelled forward a distance
                    <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> the position of every par. ticle of the string is the
                    same as it was at first, then <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is called the
                    wave-length, and the time of travelling a wavelength is called the periodic
                    time, which we shall denote by T, so that</p>
                <p>Z=VT.</p>
                <p>If we now suppose a set of waves similar to these, but reversed in position, to
                    be travelling in the opposite direction, there will be a series of points,
                    distant jZ from each other, at which there will be no motion of the string; it
                    will therefore make no difference to the motion of the string if we suppose the
                    string fastened to fixed supports at any two of these points, and we may then
                    suppose the parts of the string beyond these points to be removed, as it cannot
                    affect the motion of the part which is between them. We have thus arrived at the
                    case of a uniform string stretched between tw,o fixed supports, and we conclude
                    that the motion of the string may be completely represented as the resultant of
                    two sets of periodic waves travelling in opposite directions, their wave-lengths
                    being either twice the distance between the fixed points or a submultiple of
                    this wavelength, and the form of these waves, subject to this condition, being
                    perfectly arbitrary.</p>
                <p>To make the problema definite one, we may suppose the initial displacement and
                    velocity of every particle of the string given in terms of its distance from one
                    end of the string, and from these data it is easy to calculate the form which is
                    common to all the travelling waves. The form of the string at any subsequent
                    time may then be deduced by calculating the positions of the two sets of waves
                    at that time, and compounding their displacements.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n513/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0513-0482"/>
                <p>Thus in the wave method the actual motion of the string is considered as the
                    resultant of two wave motions, neither of which is of itself, and without the
                    other, consistent with the condition that the ends of the string are fixed. Each
                    of the wave motions is periodic with a wave-length equal to twice the distance
                    between the fixed points, and the one set of waves is the reverse of the other
                    in respect of displacement and velocity and direction of propagation; but,
                    subject to these conditions, the form of the wave is perfectly arbitrary. The
                    motion of a particle of the string, being determined by the two waves which pass
                    over it in opposite directions, is of an equally arbitrary type.</p>
                <p>In the harmonic method, on the other hand, the motion of the string is regarded
                    as compounded of a series of vibratory motions which may be infinite in number,
                    but each of which is perfectly definite in type, and is in fact a particular
                    solution of the problem of the motion of a string with its ends fixed.</p>
                <p>A simple harmonic motion is thus defined by Thomson and Tait (§ 53) :—When a
                    point Q moves uniformly in a circle, the perpendicular QP, drawn from its
                    position at any instant to a fixed diameter AA' of the circle, intersects the
                    diameter in a point P whose position changes by a <hi rend="italic">simple
                    harmonic motion.</hi></p>
                <p>The amplitude of a simple harmonic motion is the range on one side or the other
                    of the middle point of the course.</p>
                <p>The period of a simple harmonic motion is the time which elapses from any instant
                    until the moving-point again moves in the same direction through the same
                    position.</p>
                <p>The phase of a simple harmonic motion at any instant is the fraction of the whole
                    period which has elapsed since the moving point last passed through its middle
                    position in the positive direction.</p>
                <p>In the case of the stretched string, it is only in certain particular cases that
                    the motion of a particle of the string is a simple harmonic motion. In these
                    particular cases the form of the string at any instant is that of a curve of
                    sines having the line joining the fixed points for its axis, and passing through
                    these two points, and therefore having for its wave-length either twice the
                    length of the string or some submultiple of this wave-length. The amplitude of
                    the curve of sines is a simple harmonic function of the time, the period being
                    either the fundamental period or some submultiple of the fundamental period.
                    Every one of these modes of vibration is dynamically possible by itself, and any
                    number of them may coexist independently of each other.</p>
                <p>By a proper adjustment of the initial amplitude and phase of each of these modes
                    of vibration, so that their resultant shall represent the initial state of the
                    string, we obtain a new representation of the whole motion of the string, in
                    which it is seen to be the resultant of a series of simple harmonic vibrations
                    whose periods are the fundamental period and its· submultiples. The
                    determination of the amplitudes and phases of the several simple harmonic
                    vibrations’ so as to satisfy the initial conditions is an example of harmonic
                    analysis.</p>
                <p>We have thus two methods of solving the partial differential equation of the
                    motion of a string. The first, which we have called the wave method, exhibits
                    the solution in the form containing an arbitrary function, the nature of which
                    must be determined from the initial conditions. The second, or harmonic method,
                    leads to a series of terms involving sines and cosines, the coefficients of
                    which have to be determined. The harmonic method may be defined in a more
                    general manner as a method by which the solution of any actual problem may be
                    obtained as the sum or resultant of a number of terms, each of which is a
                    solution of a particular case of the problem. The nature of these particular
                    cases is defined by the condition that any one of them must be conjugate to any
                    other.</p>
                <p>The mathematical test of conjugacy is that the energy of the system arising from
                    two of the harmonics existing together is equal to the sum of the energy arising
                    from the two harmonics taken separately. In other words, no part of the energy
                    depends on the product of the amplitudes of two different harmonics. When two
                    modes of motion of the same system are conjugate to each other, the existence of
                    one of them does not affect the other.</p>
                <p>The simplest case of harmonic analysis, that of which the treatment of the
                    vibrating string is an example, is completely investigated in what is known as
                    Fourier’s theorem.</p>
                <p>Fourier’s theorem asserts that any periodic function of a single variable period
                    <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> which does not become infinite at any phase, can be
                    expanded in the form of a series consisting of a constant term, together with a
                    double series of terms, one set involving cosines and the other sines of
                    multiples of the phase.</p>
                <p>Thus if φ(⅛) is a periodic function of the variable £ having a period <hi
                    rend="italic">p,</hi> then it may be expanded as follows:</p>
                <p>φ(ξ) = A <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> + S∙A <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> cos +
                    Sj°B <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> sin · · (O∙</p>
                <p>The part of the theorem which is most frequently required, and which also is the
                    easiest to investigate, is the determination of the values of the coefficients A
                    <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi>, A <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi>-, B <hi
                    rend="subscript"> a</hi> ∙. These are</p>
                <p>A <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> =L∕&gt;≠(ξ)dξj</p>
                <p>This part of the theorem may be verified at once by multi- 2t*7ri plying both
                    sides of (1) by <hi rend="italic">dξ,</hi> by cos <hi rend="italic">——- dξ,</hi>
                    or by sin <hi rend="italic">—_ dξ,</hi> and in each case integrating from 0 to
                    <hi rend="italic">p.</hi><hi rend="italic">P</hi><hi rend="italic"/></p>
                <p>The series is evidently single-valued for any given value of <hi rend="italic"
                    >ξ.</hi> It cannot therefore represent a function of <hi rend="italic">ξ</hi>
                    which has more than one value, or which becomes imaginary for any value of <hi
                    rend="italic">ξ.</hi> It is convergent, approaching to the true value of
                    &lt;/&gt;(£) for all values of <hi rend="italic">ξ</hi> such that if <hi
                    rend="italic">ξ</hi> varies infinitesimally the function also varies
                    infinitesimally.</p>
                <p>Sir W. Thomson, availing himself of the disk, globe, and cylinder integrating
                    machine invented by his brother, Professor James Thomson, has constructed a
                    machine by which eight of the integrals required for the expression of Fourier’s
                    series can be obtained simultaneously from the recorded trace of any
                    periodically variable quantity, such as th·e height of the tide, the temperature
                    or pressure of the atmosphere, or the intensity of the different components of
                    terrestrial magnetism. If it were not on account of the waste of time, instead
                    of having a curve drawn by the action of the tide, and the curve afterwards
                    acted on by the machine, the time axis of the machine itself might be driven by
                    a clock, and the tide itself might work the second variable of the machine, but
                    his would involve the constant presence of an expensive machine at every tidal
                    station.</p>
                <p>It would not be devoid of interest, had we opportunity for it, to trace the
                    analogy between these mathematical and mechanical methods of harmonic analysis
                    and the dynamical processes which go on when a compound ray of light is analysed
                    into its simple vibrations by a prism, when a particular overtone is selected
                    from a complex tone by a resonator, and when the enormously complicated
                    soundwave of an orchestra, or even the discordant clamours of a crowd, are
                    interpreted into intelligible music or language by the attentive listener, armed
                    with the harp of three thousand strings, the resonance of which, as it hangs in
                    the gateway of his ear, discriminates the multifold components of the waves of
                    the aerial ocean. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> c. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >μ.)</hi><pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n514/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0514-0483"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
