<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0662-0629-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HELENA (9th edition, volume 11, page 629)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944180">Goddesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820856">Attics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n662/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HELENA</label>, daughter of Zeus and of Leda the wife of
                    Tyndareus king of Sparta, was sister of Castor, Pollux, and Clyternnestra, and
                    was married to Menelaus. According to Homer she was obliged by Aphrodite to flee
                    with Paris to Troy; and after the Trojan War she returned with Menelaus and
                    lived with him as queen in Sparta. She had only one child, a daughter named
                    Hermione, who was married to Neoptolemus. In the Homeric poems her character is
                    drawn with marvellous skill; forced by the gods to do what she regrets, she
                    seems to be separated from the wrong that she does, and remains always an object
                    of interest and respect.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Most appreciative and sympathetic analyses may be found in
                            Gladstone’s <hi rend="italic">Homeric Studies</hi> and Mure’s <hi
                                rend="italic">History of Greek Literature.</hi></p></note> Goethe
                        <hi rend="italic">(Faust,</hi> part ii.) introduces Helena apparently to
                    symbolize the Greek spirit acting on the modern mind. Among later poets the
                    tales of Helen are much more complicated. She was carried off by Theseus to
                    Attica in her childhood, but was recovered by her brothers. Her character often
                    suffers much in the tales followed by lyric and tragic poets. Stesichorus and
                    Euripides <hi rend="italic">(Helena),</hi> however, relate that Paris on his
                    homeward voyage was driven by stress of wind to Egypt. Proteus, king of Egypt,
                    learning the facts, detained the real Helen in Egypt, while a shadowy Helen was
                    taken to Troy and fought for. Menelaus on his way home from Troy was also driven
                    to Egypt, and there found his true wife. After the death of Paris she is also
                    said to have been married to his brother Deiphobus.</p>
                <p>If we turn to the religious ceremonies and the genuine popular tales, we find
                    traces of a more archaic Helen. At Rhamnus in Attica she was connected with the
                    worship of Nemesis, whose daughter she was considered to be. In Argos she was
                    counted mother of Iphigenia, and was said to have founded a temple of
                    Eileithyia, the goddess of birth. At Sparta she was honoured as presiding over
                    the care of children, and festivals were celebrated in her honour by the
                    maidens. A tree appears to have been connected with her worship there (see <hi
                        rend="italic">Τheocr.,</hi> xviii.); and in Rhodes sl:e was worshipped by
                    maidens with the epithet δevδpcrιs, a relic of the very oldest kind of worship,
                    where a sacred tree was worshi] ped as the embodiment of the god. In most of
                    these cults connexion with a moon-goddess, the most important of whose functions
                    was the care over child-birth, is apparent; and we are led to regard <hi
                        rend="italic">ίλίνη</hi> as an epithet of the moon, which has gradually been
                    severed from it and raised to an independent existence (c∕. the account given of
                    Gorgophone under <hi rend="smallcaps">Gorgon).</hi> Beauty is a specially common
                    attribute of the moon and of moon-goddesses, such as Hera. This makes it most
                    probable that the word, like <hi rend="italic">σtK∙i,ν∙η, ⅛</hi> connected with
                    the root <hi rend="italic">svαr,</hi> to shine. The tales connecting Helena with
                    Achilles, who is clearly a sun-god originally, which are known already to the
                    writer of the <hi rend="italic">Cypria,</hi> are also very instructive. Over the
                    Black Sea coasts Achilles and Helena were worshipped as united in the Elysian
                    fields. With this we must compare the story of Cadmus and Harmonia (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Harmonia),</hi> and of Hades and Persephone; and we must
                    remember that these colonies of Miletus were closely connected with Attica. We
                    may then look on it as probable that the rape of Helena by Theseus is merely a
                    device of harmonizing skill to connect the Helena cf Spartan religion with the
                    Helena worshipped in Attica. Probably a similar reason has contributed to mould
                    the tale which has formt d itself round the undoubtedly historical fact of the
                    destruction of Troy by a Greek tribe or army. The worship cf Aphrodite, the
                    goddess whose influence in the story of Paris and Helena is so great, was common
                    to Troy and Cythera. Many facts also point to a close connexion between
                    Aphrodite and Helena. The swan from whose egg she is born is the bird of
                    Aphrodite. By the author of the <hi rend="italic">Cypria</hi> and in Attic
                    tradition Helen is made the daughter of Nemesis; but Nemesis as a goddess of
                    fate is clearly a dawn-goddess (see Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">Zft.,</hi> iii.
                    449), and therefore may be identified in origin with Aphrodite. We have here
                    another instance of the intimate relation of the moon and dawn goddesses, and
                    the impossibility of dividing them by any broad line (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Hebe, Hera).</hi> It would be at once a most instructive and a most
                    interesting task <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n663/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0663-0630"/> to trace the steps by which the antique pre-G
                    reek goddess was gradually transformed into the charming heroine round whom the
                    action of the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> revolves. The data for reconstructing
                    the history of this figure are more than usually full, and are so clear that
                    writers of the most opposite schools (as Weicker, Gerhard, Mannhardt, Maury,
                    Roscher) have recognized in Helena the ancient goddess.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
