<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0875-0836-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HINCMAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 836</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r392">Baldness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kr4b">Falsehood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:825760">Baldness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1035984">Nephews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n875/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HINCMAR</label> (c. 806-882), archbishop of Rheims from 845
                    to 882, a prominent figure in most of the theological and ecclesiastical
                    struggles of his day, and perhaps the most vigorous and influential prelate
                    France has ever produced, belonged to a noble West Frankish family, and was born
                    about the year 806. Other forms of the name are Ingumar, Ingmar, and Igmar. His
                    early education was received at the abbey of St Denis under Hilduin∙ (the author
                    of <hi rend="italic">Areopagitica),</hi> whom he followed to Corvey, Westphalia,
                    when banished by Louis the Pious in 830 for having joined the party of Lothair.
                    Returning about two years afterwards along with his superior to St Denis, of
                    which he had become a canon, he resided partly there and partly at court, where
                    he rapidly rose high in the royal favour. He was with Louis at the “Field of
                    Falsehood” (Campus mendacii) in Alsace, and was one of the few· who remained
                    faithful when the majority of the prelates and nobles went over to the other
                    side. After the death of Louis (840), he equally gained the confidence of
                    Charles the Bald, through whose influence, after he had successively held the
                    abbacies of St Mary’s, of Compiègne, and of St Germer, he was in 845 elected to
                    succeed the deposed Ebbo or Ebo in the archiépiscopal see of Rheims. Having
                    exacted from Charles a full restitution of all the church property which had
                    belonged to the diocese, and a further promise that it should never again be
                    alienated, he at once entered on the duties of his office, and took a leading
                    part in the council of Meaux (C. Meldense), the reforming decrees of which so
                    strongly roused the opposition of the king. Some attempt having been made to
                    revive the claims of Ebo, Hincmar’s title to the archbishopric was confirmed by
                    a synod of French bishops at Paris, and ultimately settled by Leo IV.’s
                    transmission of the pallium in 847. Apart from the ordinary affairs of his
                    diocese, which included the completion and adornment of the cathedral begun by
                    his predecessor, he now became deeply involved in the discussions which arose
                    out of the predestinarianism of Gottschalk (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Gottschalk),</hi> whom Hrabanus Maurus at the synod of Mainz (848) had caused
                    to be relegated to Hincmar as his metropolitan. At a synod held at Quierzy on
                    the Oise (Carisiacum), in the diocese of Soissons, in 849, Hincmar had united
                    with Wenilo of Sens and other prelates in condemning the refractory monk to
                    degradation, scourging, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n876/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0876-0837"/> and imprisonment; but in a short refutation of
                    the “predestinarian heresy,” which he himself shortly afterwards wrote and
                    circulated, he so failed to do justice to the orthodox faith as to elicit the
                    censure of Ratramnus of Corvey, who was afterwards supported by Prudentius of
                    Troyes, Lupus of Ferrières, and a large Augustinian party (850). Hincmar now
                    summoned the dialectic skill of John Scotus Erigena to his aid, and the
                    controversy became general. Another synod held at Quierzy in 853 passed the four
                    “Capitula Carisiaca,” which in substance taught that there is but one divine
                    predestination; that free will, lost by the fall, is restored by the preventing
                    and assisting grace of Christ; that God wills generally that all men should be
                    saved; and that the blood of Christ was shed for all. These were answered by the
                    six canons of the (Lotharingiah) synod of Valence, which elicited from Hincmar,
                    two years afterwards, the <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Praedestinatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Dei</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Libero</hi><hi rend="italic">Arbitrio Libri tres,</hi> of which
                    all that is now extant is the prefatory letter to the king. By the synod of
                    Langres (S. Lingonensis, 859), however, the articles of Valence were
                    confirmed,—a decision which was afterwards supported by the general synod held
                    at Savona or Savon-nières, otherwise known ’ as the Concilium Tullense (859).
                    Hincmar now published the <hi rend="italic">Posterior de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Praedestinatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Dei</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Libero</hi><hi rend="italic">Arbitrio Dissertatio,</hi> but
                    without influencing the voice of the church; nor was he more successful in his
                    controversy with Gottschalk on the Trinity, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collectio</hi><hi rend="italic">ex Sanctis</hi><hi rend="italic">Scripturis et
                    Orthodoxorum Dictis</hi> against the phrase “Trina Deitas” having been totally
                    disregarded; he had, however, the satisfaction of preventing the release of
                    Gottschalk, who died in prison in 863. While these speculative controversies
                    were doubtfully raging, Hincmar found scope for his greater practical talent in
                    the events which followed the death of the emperor Lothair in 855, and which
                    chiefly resulted in the strengthening of clerical ascendency. Having saved
                    Charles from the hands of his own nobles and of the Germans, the great
                    metropolitan was in a position at last to say, “If kings rule after God’s will,
                    they are subject to none; if they be great sinners then is their judgment in the
                    hands of the bishops.” In 860 began the divorce suit in which the interests of
                    Thietberga, the oppressed queen of Lothair II., were involved; and here,
                    undoubtedly, the whole weight of Hincmar ’ s influence was thrown into the scale
                    of morality and right. His contribution to the discussion is still extant in the
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Divortio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lotarii</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Teutbergαs</hi><hi rend="italic">Reginae</hi> (860). While this controversy
                    still remained unsettled, Hincmar became involved in a struggle with the pope
                    (Nicholas I.), which is of very considerable historical importance from the part
                    which was played in it by the newly introduced “Isidorian” decretals, and from
                    the effect which it had in limiting the rights of metropolitans. Rothad, bishop
                    of Soissons, having been deposed for acts of insubordination and violations of
                    duty at a synod of Soissons presided over by Hincmar in 863, had appealed to
                    Rome; the appeal had been sustained; and ultimately in 865 orders were given
                    that the judgment of Hincmar should be reversed, and that his suffragan should
                    be restored to his office. The decision, which, though not without murmuring and
                    contentions, was acquiesced in by Hincmar, was an important step in the
                    development of the hierarchical monarchy of Rome. Hincmar was somewhat more
                    successful when he found himself in opposition to the successor of Nicholas,
                    Adrian II. This pope, who highly disapproved of the action of the archbishop in
                    crowning Charles as the successor of King Lothair of Lorraine in 869, had
                    fulminated threats of excommunication against all who had been concerned in that
                    action; Hincmar replied that the Roman see had no right to interfere in such a
                    matter, and that the impending ban would have no validity; and the actual result
                    was that, notwithstanding alike the protest of the emperor and the prohibition
                    of the pope, Charles the Bald and Louis the German quietly divided the dominions
                    of their nephew. Again, when Hincmar of Laon, his nephew and suffragan, had
                    defied his authority and appealed to the pope, a long controversy resulted in
                    the appellant’s being imprisoned, degraded, and sentenced to the loss of his
                    eyes (871). Of the remaining years of Hincmar’s life few incidents are recorded;
                    in 882 he was compelled by Norman invasion to transfer his see to Epernay, where
                    in the same year he died.</p>
                <p>The works of Hincmar, which include, besides these already mentioned, a variety
                    of capitula and other occasional pieces, were first edited by Sirmond in 2 vols.
                    fol. (1645). They are reprinted in Migne’s <hi rend="italic">Cursus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pair. Cοmρ.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Bertiniani</hi> from 861 to 882 are also by Hincmar. See Gess, <hi
                    rend="italic">Merkwürdigkeiten aus dem Leben und Schriften Hincmars</hi> (1806);
                    Prichard, <hi rend="italic">The Life and Times</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Hincmar</hi> (1849); and Noorden, <hi rend="italic">Hincmar,
                    Erzbischof von Rheims</hi> (1863).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
