<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0445-0426-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAMMER-PURGSTALL, Joseph von (9th edition, volume 11,
                    page 426)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49w0934b">Germs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vk4z">Orientation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:950782">Hammers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1894857">Orienteers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048147">Orientation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n445/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAMMER-PURGSTALL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph
                        von</hi></label> (1774-1856), was born at Gratz in 1774, and after some
                    training in the Oriental academy of Vienna entered the Austrian diplomatic
                    service. He was the son of Joseph Johann von Hammer, and it was not till 1835,
                    when he had inherited the estates of the countess of Purgstall (in Styria), that
                    he received the title Baron von Hammer-Purgstall, by which he is generally
                    known. His youth and early manhood were passed in the Levant, where he bent all
                    his energies to the task of improving his acquaintance with Oriental literature,
                    in which as early as 1796 he proved his interest by the translation of a Turkish
                    poem. He did not again come forward as an author till 1804, when his <hi
                        rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Oriental Learning</hi> appeared, a work whose
                    ambitious character was so diffidently felt by its author that he feared to put
                    his name to it. From that time there was little pause in his literary
                    productiveness. For fifty years he wrote incessantly on the most diverse
                    subjects, and his works were composed in most of the languages of Europe. He
                    published numerous texts and translations of Arabic, Persian, and Turkish
                    authors; compiled histories of Persian poetry, Turkish poetry, and Arabic
                    literature; brought the poems of Hâfiz, Mutanebbi, Baki, and Ibn-el-Fâridh
                    within the reach of European readers; published travels in Turkey and Austria;
                    wrote the history of the Tatar races, the Krim Khans, the Golden Horde, the
                    Russians, and the Ottoman Turks; formed a biographical gallery of Eastern
                    celebrities; put forth theories about every possible subject in the wide range
                    of Oriental learning, discussing the <hi rend="italic">Arabian Hights,</hi> Arab
                    music, Mahometan theology, Egyptian papyri, gnostic coffrets, Arabic grammar,
                    Eastern antiquities, the sect of the Assassins, the sieges of Vienna, the
                    Knights Templars, and Spenser’s sonnets, which he translated into German. Von
                    Hammer did for Germany the same work that Sir William <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n446/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0446-0427"/> Jones did for England. He showed that
                    Oriental subjects were not to be studied merely so far as they were connected
                    with biblical theology, but were a worthy object of research for their own sake.
                    For more than fifty years he persisted in introducing Eastern authors and
                    Eastern topics to the general reader, and there was a time when no Orientalist
                    was more widely known and admired. As Jules Mohl said—“C’était le doyen de la
                    littérature orientale, le premier associé que la Société (Asiatique de Paris)
                    ait tenu à l’honneur d’inscrire sur sa liste, et le plus zélé, le plus fertile,
                    et le plus célèbre des hommes qui se sont voués, de nôtres temps, à la culture
                    des lettres orientales.”</p>
                <p>It was natural that a scholar who traversed so large a field and wrote so rapidly
                    should lay himself open to the criticism of specialists, and no man was more
                    severely handled by his critics than Von Hammer, to whom Diez, for example (in
                        <hi rend="italic">Unfug und Betrug,</hi> 1815), devotes nearly 600 pages of
                    heavy abuse. Von Hammer was undoubtedly inaccurate and superficial at times; he
                    attempted more than he could possibly achieve with thoroughness, and was in the
                    habit of giving his own whimsical view of matters about which he knew next to
                    nothing; and he used to offend his critics as much by his Oriental florid style
                    and want of method as by the occasional inaccuracy of his facts and the
                    inconsequence of his deductions. But in spite of his faults he did more for
                    Oriental studies than most of his critics put together.</p>
                <p>When he was seventy-six years of age he planned a second edition of his <hi
                        rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Oriental Learning</hi>, and designed a
                    “preliminary” series of twelve volumes which should clear the ground by
                    expounding the history of Arabic literature, aud for the last seven years of his
                    life he regularly put forth his annual volume. Jules Mohl, going to see him,
                    found the old man hard at work, helped by no colleague, and disdaining the aid
                    of an amanuensis. His early travels in the Levant, and then bis busy life at
                    Vienna, where he held the post of court-interpreter, saved him from the crushing
                    influence of solitary study; and to the last he maintained his singular buoyancy
                    of mind. “C’était un homme généreux, franc jusqu’à l’imprudence, hardi,
                    bouillonnant d’esprit, aimable jusqu’à la coquetterie, doué d’une faculté de
                    travail rare, ambitieux dans les grandes et les petites choses, et d’une
                    vivacité inconcevable—vivacité qui fut la source de sa bonne et do sa mauvaise
                    fortune.” So Mohl pictured him in his address to the Société Asiatique in 1857,
                    when he recorded the death of Von Hammer on November 23, 1856, at the age of
                    eighty-two, a hard worker to the last, like his younger but greater English
                    contemporary Lane, with whom he came into collision in a friendly way on the
                    subject of the origin of <hi rend="italic">The Thousand and One Hights.</hi></p>
                <p>Von Hammer’s principal works are his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des
                        osmanischen</hi><hi rend="italic">Reiches,</hi> 10 vols., 1827 (2d ed.,
                    1834-6), translated into French (1835 and 1840); <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                        der osmanischen Dichtkunst,</hi> 4 vols., 1836; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Literatur-Geschichte der Araber</hi> (unfinished), 7 vols., 1850-6; <hi
                        rend="italic">Les Origines Russes,</hi> 1827; <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                        der Goldenen Horde,</hi> 1840; <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                        Ilchane,</hi> 1842; <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Chane der Krim,</hi>
                    1856; <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Assassincn,</hi> 1818; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Constantinopolis und der Bosporos,</hi> 1822; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Enzyklopädische Uebersicht der Wissenschaften des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Orients,</hi> 1804. Texts and translations of— <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eth-ΤhaΛlabi,</hi> Arab, and Germ., 1829; <hi rend="italic">Ibn Wahshiyah,
                        History of the Mongols,</hi> Arab, and Engl., 1806; <hi rend="italic"
                        >El-Wassâf,</hi> Pers, and Germ., 1856; <hi rend="italic">Esch-Schebistani’s
                        Rosenflor</hi><hi rend="italic">des Geheimnisses,</hi> Pers, and Germ.,
                    1838; <hi rend="italic">Ez-Zam-akhsheri,</hi><hi rend="italic">Goldene
                        Halzbändcr,</hi> Arab, and Germ., 1835; <hi rend="italic"
                        >El-GhazzΛli,</hi><hi rend="italic">Hujjet-el-Islàm,</hi> Arab, and Germ.,
                    1838; <hi rend="italic">El-Hamawi, Das arab.</hi><hi rend="italic">Hohe</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Lied</hi><hi rend="italic">der Liebe,</hi> Arab, and Germ.,
                    1854. Translations of— <hi rend="italic">El-Mutancbbi</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">s
                        Poems; Er-Rcsmi's A ccount of his Em bassy,</hi> 1809; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Contes inédits</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi> 1001 <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nuits,</hi> 1828. Besides these and smaller works, Von Hammer contributed
                    numerous essays and criticisms to the <hi rend="italic">Fundgrτιbcn des
                        Orients,</hi> which he edited; to the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Asiatique;</hi> and to many other learned journals; above all
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of the Akademie der Wissenschaften of
                    Vienna, of which he was mainly the founder; and he translated</p>
                <p>Evliya Effendi’s <hi rend="italic">Travels in Europe,</hi> for the English
                    Oriental Translation Fund. For a fuller list of his works, which amount in all
                    to nearly 100 volumes, see <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus</hi> of the Acad,
                    des Inscr. et des Belles Lettres, 1857. (S. L. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
