<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0421-0402-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAMANN, Johann Georg</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 402</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n421/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAMANN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann Georg</hi></label>
                    (1730-1788), a distinguished writer on philosophical and theological subjects,
                    was born at Königsberg in Prussia in 1730. His parents were of humble rank and
                    small means. The education he received was comprehensive but unsystematic, and
                    the want of definiteness in this early training doubtless tended to aggravate
                    the peculiar instability of character which troubled Hamann’s after life. In
                    1746 he began theological studies, but speedily deserted them and turned his
                    attention to law. That too was taken up in a desultory fashion and quickly
                    relinquished. Hamann seems at this time to have thought that any strenuous
                    devotion to “bread-and-butter” studies was lowering, and accordingly gave
                    himself entirely to reading, criticism, and philological inquiries. Such
                    studies, however, were pursued without any definite aim or systematic
                    arrangement, and consequently were productive of nothing. In 1752, constrained
                    to secure some position in the world, he accepted a tutorship in a family
                    resident in Livonia, but only retained it a few months. A similar situation in
                    Courlaud he also resigned after about a year. In both cases apparently the
                    rupture might be traced to the curious and unsatisfactory character of Hamann
                    himself. After leaving his second post he was received into the house of a
                    merchant at Riga named Berens, who contracted a great friendship for him and
                    selected him as his companion for a tour through Dantzic, Berlin, Hamburg,
                    Amsterdam, and London. Hamann, however, was quite unfitted for business, and,
                    when left in London, gave himself up entirely to his fancies, and was quickly
                    reduced to astate of extreme poverty and want. It was at this period of his
                    life, when his inner troubles of spirit harmonized with the unhappy external
                    conditions of his lot, that he began an earnest and prolonged study of the
                    Bible; and from this time dates the tone of extreme pietism which is
                    characteristic of his writings, and which undoubtedly alienated many of his
                    friends. He returned to Riga, and was well received by the Berens family, in
                    whose house he resided for some time. A quarrel, the precise nature of which is
                    not very clear though the occasion is evident, led to an entire separation from
                    these friends. In 1759 Hamann returned to Königsberg, and lived for several
                    years with his father, filling occasional postsin Königsberg and Mitau. In 1767
                    he obtained a situation as translator in the excise office, and ten years later
                    a post as storekeeper in a mercantile house. During this period of comparative
                    rest Hamann was able to indulge in the long correspondence with learned friends
                    which seems to have been his greatest pleasure. In 1784 the failure of some
                    commercial speculations greatly reduced his means, and about the same time he
                    was dismissed with a small pension from his situation. The kindness of friends,
                    however, supplied provision for his children, and enabled him to carry out the
                    long-cherished wish of visiting some of his philosophical allies. He spent some
                    time with Jacobi at Pempelfort and with Buchholz at Walbergen. At the latter
                    place he was seized with illness, and died on the 21st June 1788.</p>
                <p>Hamann’s works resemble his life and character. They are entirely unsystematic so
                    far as matter is concerned, chaotic and disjointed in style. To a reader not
                    acquainted with the peculiar nature of the man, which led him to regard what
                    commended itself to him as therefore objectively true, they must be moreover
                    entirely unintelligible and, from their peculiar pietistic tone and scriptural
                    jargon, probably offensive. A place in the history of philosophy can be yielded
                    to Hamann only because he expresses in uncouth, barbarous fashion an idea to
                    which other writers have given more effective shape. The fundamental thought is
                    with him the unsatisfactoriness of abstraction or onesidedness. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Aufklärung,</hi> with its rational theology, was to him the type
                    of abstraction. Even Epicureanism, which might appear concrete, was by him
                    rightly designated abstract. Quite naturally, then, Hamann is led to object
                    strongly to much of the Kantian philosophy. The separation of sense and
                    understanding is for him unjustifiable, and only paralleled by the extraordinary
                    blunder of severing matter and form. Concreteness, therefore, is the one demand
                    which Hamann expresses, and as representing his own thought he used to refer to
                    Giordano Bruno’s conception of the identity of contraries. The demand, however,
                    remains but a demand. Nothing that Hamann has given can be regarded as in the
                    slightest degree a response to it. His hatred of system, incapacity for abstract
                    thinking, and intense personality rendered it impossible for him to do more than
                    utter the disjointed, oracular, obscure dicta which gained for him among his
                    friends the name of “Magus of the North.” Two results only appear throughout his
                    writings,—first, the accentuation of belief, and, secondly, the transference of
                    many philosophical difficulties to language. Belief is, according to Hamann, the
                    groundwork of knowledge, and he accepts in all sincerity Hume’s analysis of
                    experience as being most helpful in constructing a theological view. In
                    language, which he appears to regard as somehow acquired, he finds a solution
                    for the problems of reason which Kant had discussed in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Critique.</hi> On the application of these thoughts to the Christian theology
                    one need not enter.</p>
                <p>None of Hamann’s writings are of great bulk; most are mere pamphlets of some
                    thirty or forty pages. A complete collection has been published by Roth <hi
                    rend="italic">{Schriften,</hi> 8vo, 1821-42), and by Gildemeister <hi
                    rend="italic">{Leben und Schriften,</hi> 6 vols., 1851-73). See also Petri, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hamann's</hi><hi rend="italic">Schriften</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >u.</hi> Ar⅛∕c, 4 vols. ,1872-3; Poel, <hi rend="italic">Hamann,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">Magus im Norden,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >sein Leben</hi><hi rend="italic">u.</hi><hi rend="italic">Mittheilungen aus
                    seinen Schriften,</hi> 2 vols., 1874-76. A very comprehensive essay on Hamann is
                    to be found in Hegel’s <hi rend="italic">Vermischte Schriften,</hi> ii. (<hi
                    rend="italic">Werke,</hi> bd. xvii. ).</p>
                <p>H AM AS AH (more correctly <hi rend="smallcaps">Hamâseh),</hi> the name of a
                    famous Arabian anthology compiled by Habib ibn Aus et-Tâî, surnamed Abû Temmâm
                    (corruptly <hi rend="smallcaps">Abu-Teman,</hi><hi rend="italic">q.vj).</hi> The
                    collection is so-called from the title Df its first book, containing poems
                    descriptive of constancy and valour in battle, patient endurance of calamity,
                    steadfastness in seeking vengeance, manfulness under reproach and temptation,
                    all which qualities make up the attribute called by the Arabs <hi rend="italic"
                    >hamaseh</hi> (briefly paraphrased by Et-Tebrizi as <hi rend="italic"
                    >esh-shiddeh fi-l-arnr').</hi> It consists of ten books or parts, containing in
                    all 881 poems or fragments of poems, and named respectively—(1) <hi
                    rend="italic">El-Hamâseh,</hi> 261 pieces; (2) <hi rend="italic"
                    >El-Marathi,</hi> “Dirges,” 169 pieces; (3) <hi rend="italic">El-Adab, “</hi>
                    Manners,” 54 pieces; (4) <hi rend="italic">En-Nesib,</hi> “The Beauty and Love
                    of Women,” 139 pieces; (5) <hi rend="italic">El-Hija,</hi> “Satires,” 80 pieces;
                    (6) <hi rend="italic">El-Adyaf</hi><hi rend="italic">U'ad-Medîh,</hi>
                    “Hospitality and Panegyric,” 143 pieces;</p>
                <p>(7) <hi rend="italic">Es-Sifat,</hi> “Miscellaneous Descriptions,” 3 pieces;</p>
                <p>(8) <hi rend="italic">Es-Seyr wa-n-Ndas,</hi> “Journeying and Drowsiness,” 9
                    pieces; (9) <hi rend="italic">El-Mulah,</hi> “Pleasantries,” 38 pieces; and (10)
                    <hi rend="italic">Medhemmet-en-nisa,</hi> “Dispraise of Women,” 18 pieces. Of
                    these books the first is by far the longest, both in the number and extent of
                    its poems, and the first two together make up more than half the bulk of the
                    work. The poems are for the most part fragments selected from longer
                    compositions, though a considerable number are probably entire. They are taken
                    from the works of Arab poets of all periods <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n422/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0422-0403"/> down to that of Abû Temmâm himself (the latest
                    ascertainable date being 832 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> but chiefly of the
                    poets of the Ante-Islamic time (&lt;7αΛ⅛7⅛yyi2re), those of the early days of
                    El-Islâm <hi rend="italic">{Mulchadrimûn),</hi> and those who flourished during
                    the reigns of the Umawι caliphs, 660-749 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">{Lslamiyyum).</hi> Perhaps the oldest in the collection are those
                    relating to the war of Basûs, a famous legendary strife which arose out of the
                    murder of Kuleyb, chief of the combined clans of Bekr and Teghlib, and lasted
                    for forty years, ending with the peace of Dhu-1-Mejâz, about 534 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Of the period of the 'Abbâsî caliphs, under whom Abû
                    Temmâm himself lived, there are probably not more than sixteen fragments.</p>
                <p>Most of the poems belong to the class of extempore or occasional utterances, as
                    distinguished from <hi rend="italic">qasîdehs,</hi> or elaborately finished
                    odes. While the latter abound with comparisons and long descriptions, in which
                    the skill of the poet is exhibited with much art and ingenuity, the poem3 of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Hamaseh</hi> are short, direct, and for the most part free
                    from comparisons: the transitions are easy, the metaphors simple, and the
                    purpose of the poem clearly indicated. It is due probably to the fact that this
                    style of composition was chiefly sought by Abû Temmâm in compiling his
                    collection that he has chosen hardly anything from the works of the most famous
                    poets of antiquity. Not a single piece from Imra’el-Qeys occurs in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Hamaseh,</hi> nor are there any from 'Alqameh, Zuheyr, or
                    El-A'shà; En-Nâbighah is represented only by two pieces (pp. 408 and 742 of
                    Freytag’s edition) of four aud three verses respectively, <hi rend="superscript"
                    > ,</hi> Antarah by two pieces of four verses each <hi rend="italic">{Id.,</hi>
                    pp. 206, 209), Tarafeh by one piece of five verses <hi rend="italic">{Id.,</hi>
                    p. 632), Lebid by one piece of three verses <hi rend="italic">{Id·,</hi> p.
                    468), and 'Amr son of Kulthûm by one piece of four verses <hi rend="italic"
                    >{I&lt;L,</hi> p. 236). The compilation is thus essentially an anthology of
                    minor poets, and exhibits (so far at least as the more ancient poems are
                    concerned) the general average of poetic utterance at a time when to speak in
                    verse was the daily habit of every warrior of the desert.</p>
                <p>To this description, however, there is an important exception in the book
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">En-Nesîb,</hi> containing verses relating to women
                    and love. In the classical age of Arab poetry it was the established rule that
                    all <hi rend="italic">qasîdehs,</hi> or finished odes, must begin with the
                    mention of women and their chirms <hi rend="italic">{teshbιb),</hi> in order, as
                    the old critics said, that the hearts of the heιrers might be softened and
                    inclined to regard kindly the theme which the poet proposed to unfold. The
                    fragments included in this part of the work are therefore generally taken from
                    the opening verses of <hi rend="italic">qasîdehs</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    where this is not the case, they are chiefly compositions of the early Islamic
                    period, when the school of exclusively erotic poetry (of which the greatest
                    representative was 'Omar son of Abû Rabî'ah) arose.</p>
                <p>The compiler was himself a distinguished poet in the style of his day, and
                    wandered through many provinces of the Muslim empire earning money and fame by
                    his skill in panegyric. About 220 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.</hi> he betook
                    himself to Khurâsân, then ruled by 'Abd-allâh son of Tâhir, whom he praised and
                    by whom he was rewarded; on his journey home to El-'Irâq he passed through
                    Hamadân, and was there detained for many months a guest of Abu-1-Wafâ son of
                    Selemeh, the road onward being blocked by heavy falls of snow. During his
                    residence at Hamadân Abû Temmâm is said to have compiled or composed, from the
                    materials which he found in Abu-1-Wafâ’s library, five poetical works, of which
                    one was the <hi rend="italic">Hamäseh.</hi> This collection remained as a
                    precious heirloom in the family of Abu-1- Wafâ until their fortunes decayed,
                    when it fell into the hands of a man of Dinawar named Abu-l-'Awâdhil, who
                    carried it to Isfahân and made it known to the learned of that city.</p>
                <p>The worth of the <hi rend="italic">Hamaseh</hi> as a store-house of ancient
                    legend, of faithful detail regarding the usages of the pagan time and early
                    simplicity of the Arab race, can hardly be exaggerated. The high level of
                    excellence which is found in its selections, both as to form and matter, is
                    remarkable, and caused it to be said that Abû Temmâm displayed higher qualities
                    as a poet in his choice of extracts from the ancients than in his own
                    compositions. What strikes us chiefly in the class of poetry of which the <hi
                    rend="italic">Hamäseh</hi> is a specimen, is its exceeding truth and reality,
                    its freedom from artificiality and hearsay, the evident firsthand experience
                    which the singers possessed of all of which they sang. For historical purposes
                    the value of the collection is not small; but most of all there shines forth
                    from it a complete portraiture of the hardy and manful nature, the strenuous
                    life of passion and battle, the lofty contempt of cowardice, niggardliness, and
                    servility, which marked the valiant stock who bore El-Islâm abroad in a flood of
                    new life over the out-worn civilizations of Persia, Egypt, and Byzantium. It has
                    the true stamp of the heroic time, of its -weaknesses and crime as of its
                    strength and beauty.</p>
                <p>No less than twenty commentaries on it are enumerated by Haji Khalifeh. Of these
                    the earliest was by Abû Riyâsli (otherwise Er-Riyâshî), who died in 257 A.H.;
                    excerpts from it, chiefly in elucidation of the circumstances in which the poems
                    were composed, are frequently given by Et-Tebrizi. He was followed by the famous
                    grammarian Abu-l-Fath ibn el-Jinni (died 392 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.),</hi>
                    and later by Shihâb ed-Din Ahmed el-Marzûqî of Isfahân (died 421 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.h.).</hi> Upon El-Marzûqî’s commentary is chiefly founded
                    that of Abû Zekerîyâ Yahyà. et-Tebrizi (born 421 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.,</hi>
                    died 502), which has been published by the late Professor G. W. Freytag of Bonn,
                    together with a Latin translation aud notes (1828-1851). This monumental work,
                    the labour of a life, is a treasure of information regarding the classical age
                    of Arab literature which has not perhaps its equal for extent, accuracy, and
                    minuteness of detail, in Europe. No other complete edition of the <hi
                    rend="italic">ΗαmAsch</hi> has been printed in the West; but in 1856 one
                    appeared at Calcutta under the names of Maulavî Ghulâm Rabbani and Kabiru-d-din
                    Ahmad. Though no acknowledgment of the fact is contained in this edition, it is
                    a simple reprint of Professor Freytag’s text (without Et-Tebrizi’s commentary),
                    and follows its original even in the misprints (corrected by Freytag at the end
                    of the second volume, which being in Latin the Calcutta editors do not seem to
                    have consulted). It is thus worthless as a fresh critical authority, and, owing
                    to the absence of a commentary, of little use to the student; its only merit is
                    that it contains in an appendix of 12 pages a collection of verses (and some
                    entire fragments) not found in Et-Tebrizi’s recension, but stated to exist in
                    some copies consulted by the editors; these are, however, very carelessly edited
                    and printed, and in many places .unintelligible.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Hamäseh</hi> has been rendered with the utmost skill and
                    spirit into German verse by the illustrious Friedrich Rückert (Stuttgart, 1846),
                    who has not only given translations of almost all the poems proper to the work,
                    but has added numerous fragments drawn from other sources, especially those
                    occurring in the <hi rend="italic">Scholia</hi> of Et-Tebrizi, as well as the
                    <hi rend="italic">Λfdallaqahs</hi> of Zuheyr and ’ Antarah, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Lâmiyyeh</hi> of Esh-Shenferà, and the <hi rend="italic">Baηet
                    So'act</hi> of Ka'b son of Zuheyr. No such faithful interpretation of the ways
                    and thoughts of the ancient Arabs exists to our knowledge in any modern European
                    language; it is comparable, for fidelity, spirit, and fluency, only to Lane’s
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Thousand and One Nights.</hi></p>
                <p>When the <hi rend="italic">Hamäseh</hi> is spoken of, that of Abû Temmâm, as the
                    first and most famous of the name, is meant; but several collections of a
                    similar kind, also called <hi rend="italic">Hamäseh,</hi> exist. The best known
                    and earliest of these is the <hi rend="italic">Hamäseh</hi> of El-Bohturi (died
                    284 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.),</hi> of which some fragments were published by
                    Theo. Noldeke in his <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Kenntniss</hi><hi rend="italic">der Poesie der alten Araber</hi> (Hanover,
                    1864). Four other works of the same name, formed on the model of Abû Temmâm’s
                    compilation, are mentioned by Hâjî Khalifeh. Besides these, a work entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Hamäset er-Räh</hi> (the Hamäseh of wine), was composed by
                    Abu-1-’Alâel-Ma'arrî (died 449 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.).</hi> (C. <hi
                    rend="italic">J. L.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
