<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0447-0428-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAMPDEN, John (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    428)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n447/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAMPDEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1594-1643),
                    the eldest son of William Hampden of Great Hampden in Buckinghamshire, by
                    Elizabeth, second daughter of Sir Henry Cromwell, and aunt of Oliver, the future
                    Protector, was born in 1594. By his father’s death, when he was but a child, he
                    became the owner of a good estate, and a ward of the crown. He was educated at
                    the grammar school at Thame, and in 1609 he became a commoner of Magdalen
                    College at Oxford. In 1613 he was admitted a student of the Γnner Temple, and in
                    1619 he married Elizabeth Symeon. He first sat in parliament for the borough of
                    Grampound in 1621. From that time he was a member of every succeeding parliament
                    till he died.</p>
                <p>To the biographer who does not wish to become an historian under the pretence of
                    narrating the incidents of his hero’s life, Hampden’s career must appear to give
                    little scope for narrative. The letters which he left behind him are few. His
                    speeches are scarcely more numerous and are extremely brief. In the early days
                    of his parliamentary career he was coûtent to be overshadowed by Eliot, as in
                    its later days he was content to be overshadowed by Pym, and to be commanded by
                    Essex. Yet it is Hampden, and not Eliot or Pym, who lives in the popular
                    imagination as the central figure of the English revolution in its earlier
                    stages. It is Hampden whose statue rather than that of Eliot or Pym has been
                    selected to take its place in St Stephen’s Hall as the noble3t type of the
                    parliamentary opposition, as Falkland’s has been selected as the noblest type of
                    parliamentary royalism.</p>
                <p>Something of Hampden’s fame no doubt is owing to the position which he took up as
                    the opponent of ship-money. But it is hardly possible that even resistance to
                    ship-money would have so distinguished him but for the mingled massiveness and
                    modesty of his character, his dislike of all pretences in himself or others, his
                    brave contempt of danger, and his charitable readiness to shield others as far
                    as possible from the evil consequences of their actions. Nor was he wanting in
                    that skill which enabled him to influence men towards the ends at which he
                    aimed, and which was spoken of as subtlety by those who disliked his ends.</p>
                <p>During the last two parliaments of James and the first three parliaments of
                    Charles, Hampden did not, so far as we know, open his lips in public debate, but
                    he was increasingly employed in committee work, for which he seems to have had a
                    special aptitude. In 1626 he took an active part in the preparation of the
                    charges against Buckingham. In January 1627 he was bound over to answer at the
                    council board for his refusal to pay the forced loan. Later in the year he was
                    committed to the gate-house, and then sent into confinement in Hampshire, from
                    which he was liberated just before the meeting of the third parliament of the
                    reign, in which he once more rendered useful but unobtrusive assistance to his
                    leaders.</p>
                <p>When the breach came in 1629 Hampden is found in epistolary correspondence with
                    the imprisoned Eliot, discussing with him the prospects of the Massachusetts
                    colony, or rendering hospitality and giving counsel to the patriot’s sons now
                    that they were deprived of a father’s personal care.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n448/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0448-0429"/>
                <p>It was not till 1637, however, that his resistance to the payment of ship-money
                    gained for his name the lustre which it has never since lost. Seven out of the
                    twelve judges sided against him, but the connexion between the rights of
                    property and the parliamentary system was firmly established in the popular
                    mind.</p>
                <p>In the Short Parliament of 1640 Hampden stood forth amongst the leaders. During
                    the eventful months which followed, when Strafford was striving in vain to force
                    England, in spite of its visible reluctance, to support the king in his Scottish
                    war, rumour has much to tell of Hampden’s activity in rousing opposition. It is
                    likely enough that the rumour is in the main true, but we are not possessed of
                    any satisfactory evidence on the subject.</p>
                <p>In the Long Parliament, though Hampden was by no means a frequent speaker, it is
                    possible to trace his course with sufficient distinctness. Unwearied in
                    attendance upon committees, he was in all things ready to second Pym, whom he
                    plainly regarded as his leader. In the earlier proceedings of the Commons there
                    was practically unanimity in the House, though a difference afterwards arose as
                    to the form in which the attack upon Strafford should be conducted. All were
                    agreed in desiring that the constitution should rest upon a combination between
                    the king and the two Houses, and that legal questions in which the king was
                    concerned should be decided only by the judges of the ordinary courts.</p>
                <p>There was another point on which there was no agreement. A large minority wished
                    to retain Episcopacy, and to keep the Common Prayer Book unaltered, whilst the
                    majority were at least willing to consider the question of abolishing the one
                    and modifying the other. On this subject the parties which ultimately divided
                    the House and the country itself were fully formed as early as February 8, 1641.
                    The details of the contest between Episcopacy and Presbyterianism will be more
                    fitly told in connexion with the life of Pym. It is enough to say that Hampden
                    fully shared in the counsels of the opponents of Episcopacy. It is not that he
                    was a theoretical Presbyterian, but the bishops had been in his days so fully
                    engaged in the imposition of obnoxious ceremonies that it was difficult if not
                    impossible to dissociate them from the cause in which they were embarked.
                    Closely connected with Hampden’s distrust of the bishops was his distrust of
                    monarchy as it then existed. The dispute about the church therefore soon
                    attained the form of an attack upon monarchy, and, when the majority of the
                    House of Lords arrayed itself on the side of Episcopacy and the Prayer Book, of
                    an attack upon the House of Lords as well.</p>
                <p>No serious importance therefore can be attached to the offers of advancement made
                    from time to time to Hampden and his friends. Charles would gladly have given
                    them office if they had been ready to desert their principles. Every day
                    Hampden’s conviction grew stronger that Charles would never abandon the position
                    which he had taken up. He was therefore a warm supporter of the Grand
                    Remonstrance, and was chosen out to be one of the five impeached members whose
                    attempted arrest brought at last the opposing parties into open collision. In
                    the angry scene which arose on the proposal to print the Grand Remonstrance it
                    was Hampden’s personal intervention which prevented an actual conflict, and it
                    was after the impeachment had been attempted that Hampden laid down the two
                    conditions under which resistance to the king became the duty of a good subject.
                    Those conditions were an attack upon religion, and an attack upon the
                    fundamental laws. There can be no doubt that Hampden fully believed that both
                    those conditions were fulfilled at the opening of 1642. <hi rend="superscript">
                        6</hi></p>
                <p>When the civil war began Hampden levied a regiment of Buckinghamshire men for the
                    parliamentary cause. In the earlier operations of the war, and in the undecided
                    fight of Edgehill, he bore himself gallantly and well. But it is not on his
                    skill as a regimental officer that Hampden’s fame rests. In war as in peace his
                    distinction lay in his power of disentangling the essential part from the
                    non-essential. In the previous constitutional struggle he had seen that the one
                    thing necessary was to establish the supremacy of the House of Commons. In the
                    military struggle which followed he saw, as Cromwell saw afterwards, that the
                    one thing necessary was to beat the enemy. He protested at once against Essex’s
                    hesitations and compromises. In the formation of the confederacy of the six
                    associated counties, which was to supply a basis for Cromwell’s operations, he
                    took an active part. His influence was felt alike in parliament and in the
                    field. But he was not in supreme command, and he had none of that impatience
                    which often leads able men to fail in the execution of orders of which they
                    disapprove. His precious life was a sacrifice to his unselfish devotion to the
                    call of discipline and duty. On June 18, 1643, when he was holding out on
                    Chalgrove Field against the superior numbers of Rupert till reinforcements
                    arrived, he received two carbine balls in the shoulder. Leaving the field he
                    reached Thame, and after nearly six days he died on the 24th praying for his
                    country and his king. (s. κ. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
