<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0514-0483-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARMONIUM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 483</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1175820">Winds</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1047777">Organization</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208387">Michigan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rn30c20">Harmonium</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0743s">Winds</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44746z94">Pitch</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n514/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARMONIUM</label>. Perhaps no musical instrument ever became
                    in a few years so widely known and used as the ha'rmonium. The reasons for this
                    may at once be found in the facilities it offers for playing easy music, and,
                    when simply constructed, its comparatively low price, which renders the purchase
                    of a tolerable harmonium possible when the cheapest pianoforte fairly playable
                    would be unattainable, and the real organ, although of chamber size, quite out
                    of the question. Besides being a convenient makeshift for an organ, the
                    harmonium can also be used in domestic concerted music, to play all or any of
                    the wind band parte of the orchestra; it may even be employed as a substitute
                    for the violin, and in such vicarious uses it is past all question one of the
                    handiest of deputies.</p>
                <p>It is true the tone of the harmonium is not in itself beautiful; the prominence
                    in sounds from reeds of certain overtones is irreconcilable with pleasure to the
                    ear unless by convention of habit, and the necessity of tuning according to
                    equal temperament all major thirds too sharp leads through this harmonic
                    peculiarity in the chords to an abnormally disagreeable quality, from which
                    those whose nerves are very sensitive or weak are not unfrequently painfully
                    affected. The American organ, a kind of harmonium of late years much in vogue,
                    owes its popularity to its being less pronounced and reedy in timbre (its softer
                    tone being nearer to that we are familiar with in the church organ), and to its
                    being easier to play for simple domestic use. Yet the real harmonium has more
                    independent character as an instrument, and is capable of higher treatment in
                    performance than the American organ.</p>
                <p>Both are known as “free-reed” instruments, the musical tones being produced by
                    tongues of brass, technically “vibrators,” set in oblong frames; the sides of
                    these they do not quite touch, but pass, when in movement, freely downwards,—the
                    “beating reeds” used in church organs covering the entire orifice. A reed or
                    vibrator, set in periodic motion by impact of a current of air, produces a
                    corresponding succession of air puffs, the rapidity of which determines the
                    pitch of the musical note. There is an essential difference between the
                    harmonium and the American organ in the direction of this current; in the former
                    the wind apparatus forces the current upwards, and in the latter sucks it
                    downwards, whence it becomes desirable to separate in description these
                    varieties of free-reed instruments.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Harmonium</hi> has a keyboard of five octaves compass when
                    complete, from C to C, and a simple action controlling the valves, &amp;c. The
                    necessary pressure of wind is generated by bellows worked by the feet of the
                    performer upon footboards or treadles. The air is thus forced up the wind-trunks
                    into an air-chamber called the wind-chest, the pressure of it being equalized by
                    a reservoir, which receives the excess of wind through an aperture, and permits
                    escape, when above a certain pressure, by a discharge valve or pallet. The
                    aperture admitting air to the reservoir may be closed by a drawstop named
                    “expression.” The character of the instrument is then entirely changed from a
                    mechanical response to the player’s touch to an expressive one, rendering what
                    emotion maybe communicated from the player by increase or diminution of sound
                    through the greater or less pressure of wind the reeds may be submitted to. The
                    drawstops bearing the names of the different registers in imitation of the
                    organ, admit, when drawn, the wind from the wind-chest to the corresponding reed
                    compartments, shutting them off when closed. These compartments are of about two
                    octaves and a half each, there being a division in the middle of the keyboard
                    scale dividing the stops into bass and treble. A stop being drawn and a key
                    pressed down wind is admitted by a corresponding valve to a reed or vibrator.
                    Above each reed in the so-called sound-board or pan is a channel, a small
                    air-chamber or cavity, the shape and capacity of which have greatly to do with
                    the colour of tone of the note it reinforces. The air in this resonator is
                    highly compressed at an even or a varying pressure as the expression-stop may
                    not be or may be drawn. The wind finally escapes by a small pallet-hole opened
                    by pressing down the corresponding key. In Mustel and other good harmoniums, the
                    reed compartments that form the scheme of the instrument are eight in number,
                    four bass and four treble, of three different pitches of octave and double
                    octave distance. The front bass and treble rows are the “diapason” of the pitch
                    known as 8 feet, and the bourdon (double diapason), 16 feet. These may be
                    regarded as the foundation stops, and are technically the front organ. The back
                    organ has solo and combination stops, the principal of 4 feet (octave higher
                    than diapason), and bassoon (bass) and oboe (treble), 8 feet. These may be
                    mechanically combined by a stop called full organ. Μ. Mustel, the French maker,
                    whose pre-eminence is universally acknowledged, has added other registers for
                    much admired effects of tone, viz.,—“harpe éolienne,” two bass rows of 2 feet
                    pitch, the one tuned a beat too sharp, the other a beat too flat, to produce a
                    waving tremulous tone that has a certain charm; “musette” and “voix celeste,” 16
                    feet; and “baryton,” a treble stop 32 feet, or two octaves lower than the normal
                    note-of the key. The “back organ” is usually covered by a swell box, containing
                    louvres or shutters similar to a Venetian blind, and divided into fortes
                    corresponding with the bass and treble division of the registers. The fortes are
                    governed by knee pedals which act by pneumatic pressure. Tuning the reeds is
                    effected by scraping them at the point to sharpen them, or near the shoulder or
                    heel to flatten them in pitch. Air pressure affects the pitch but slightly,
                    noticeable only in the larger reeds, and harmoniums long retain their tuning, a
                    decided advantage over the organ and the pianoforte. Mechanical contrivances in
                    the harmonium, of frequent or occasional employment, besides those already
                    referred to, are the “percussion,” a small pianoforte action of hammer and
                    escapement which, acting upon the reeds of the diapason rows at the moment air
                    is admitted to them, gives prompter response to the depression of the key, or
                    quicker speech; the “double expression,” a pneumatic balance in the wind
                    reservoir of great delicacy exactly maintaining by gradation equal pressure of
                    the wiud; and the “double touch,” by which the back organ registers speak sooner
                    than those of the front that are called upon by deeper pressure of the key, thus
                    allow prominence or accentuation of certain parts by an expert performer.
                    “Prolongement” permits selected notes to be sustained after the fingers have
                    quitted their keys. Dawes’s “melody attachment” is to give prominence to an air
                    or treble part by shutting off in certain registers all notes below it. This
                    notion has been adapted by inversion to a “pedal substitute” to strengthen the
                    lowest bass notes. The “tremolo” affects the wind in the vicinity of the reeds
                    by small bellows which increases the pulsation in rapidity according to
                    pressure; and the “sourdine” diminishes the supply of wind by controlling its
                    admission to the reeds.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">American Organ,</hi> as already said, acts by wind
                    exhaustion. A vacuum is practically created in the air-chamber by the exhausting
                    power of the footboards, and a current of air thus drawn downwards passes
                    through any reeds that are left open, setting them in vibration. This instrument
                    has therefore exhaust instead of force bellows. Valves in the board above the
                    air-chamber give communication to reeds, made more slender than those of the
                    harmonium and more or less bent, while the frames in which they are fixed are
                    also differently shaped, being hollowed rather in spoon fashion. The channels,
                    the resonators above the reeds, are not varied in size or shape as in the
                    harmonium; they exactly correspond with the reeds, and are collectively known as
                    the “tubeboard.” The swell “fortes” are in front of the openings of these tubes,
                    rails that open or close by the action of the knees upon what may be called knee
                    pedals. The tone of the American organ is softer than that of the harmonium;
                    this is sometimes aided by the use of extra resonators, as, for instance, in
                    Clough and Warren’s latest instraments (of Detroit, Michigan, U.S.), which they
                    call pipes or qualifying tubes. The blowing being also easier, ladies find it
                    much less fatiguing. To these differences we may attribute its increasing
                    popularity. The expression stop can have little power in the American organ, and
                    is generally absent; the “automatic swell” in the instruments of Mason and
                    Hamlin (of Boston, U.S.) is a contrivance that comes the nearest to it, though
                    far inferior. By it a swell shutter or rail is kept in constant movement,
                    proportioned to the force of the air-current. Another very clever improvement
                    introduced by these makers, who are the originators of the instrament itself, is
                    the “vox humana,” a smaller rail or fan, made to revolve rapidly by wind
                    pressure; its rotation, disturbing the air near the reeds, causes interferences
                    of vibration that produce a tremulous effect, not unlike the beatings heard from
                    combined voices, whence the name. This vibrato stop has found general adoption.
                    The arrangement of reed compartments in American organs does not essentially
                    differ from that of harmoniums; but there are often two keyboards, and then the
                    solo and combination stops-are found on the upper manual. The diapason treble
                    register is known as “melodia ”—different makers occasionally vary the use of
                    fancy names for other stops. The “subbass,” however, an octave of 16 feet pitch
                    and always apart from the other reeds, is used With great advantage for pedal
                    effects on the manual, the compass of American organs being usually down to F
                    (FF, 5 octaves). In large instraments there arc sometimes foot pedals as in an
                    organ, with their own reed boxes of 8 and 16 feet, the lowest note being then
                    CC. Blowing for pedal instruments has to be done by hand a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n515/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0515-0484"/> lever being attached ιor that purpose. The
                    “celeste” stop is managed as in the harmonium, by rows of reeds tuned not quite
                    in unison, or by a shade valve that alters the air-current and flattens one row
                    of reeds thereby.</p>
                <p>Harmoniums and American organs are the results of many experiments to play upon
                    free reeds by a keyboard, initiated by the “orgue expressif” of Grenié, a
                    Frenchman. During nearly the first half of this century various tantative
                    efforts in France and Germany, and subsequently in England, came to nothing more
                    valuable than the Viennese “physharmonica” of Häckel, the Parisian “melophone,”
                    and our own “seraphine.” The inventor of the harmonium was indubitably Alexandre
                    Debain, who took out a patent for it in Paris in 1840. He produced varied timbre
                    registers by modifying reed channels, and brought these registers on to one
                    keyboard. Unfortunately he patented too much, for he secured even the name
                    harmonium, obliging contemporary and future experimenters to shelter their
                    improvements under other names, and the venerable name of organ becoming
                    impressed into connexion with an inferior instrument, we have now to distinguish
                    between reed and pipe organs. The compromise of reed organ for the harmonium
                    class of instruments must therefore be accepted. Debain’s harmonium was at first
                    quite mechanical; it gained expression by the expression-stop already described.
                    The Alexandres, well-known French makers, by the ingenuity of one of their
                    workmen, Martin, added the percussion and the prolongement. The melody
                    attachment was the invention of an English engineer; the introduction of the
                    double touch, now used in the harmoniums of Mustel, Bauer, and others—also in
                    American organs—is due to Mr Tamplin, an English professor. Reference has
                    already been made to the improvements of M. Mustel, a maker imbued with true
                    artistic devotion.</p>
                <p>The principle of the American organ originated with the Alexandres, whose
                    earliest experiments are said to have been made with the view of constructing an
                    instrument to exhaust air. The realization of the idea proving to be more in
                    consonance with the genius of the American people, to whom what we may call the
                    devotional tone of the instrument appealed, the introduction of it by Messrs
                    Mason and Hamlin in 1861 was followed by remarkable success. They made it
                    generally known in Europe by exhibiting it at Paris in 1867, and from that time
                    instruments have been exported in large numbers by different makers. Harmoniums
                    are not entirely, although chiefly, of French make. Mr Bauer, one of the best
                    English makers, learned the trade in Paris, and employs chiefly French workmen.
                    As keyed instruments, reed organs of either principle cannot be expected to
                    compete musically with the older organ and pianoforte, yet the harmonium,
                    studied for itself with something like the devotion that is given to the other
                    keyed instruments, might be made more important than it is at present. Excepting
                    from a few isolated students who may be told upon the fingers, it has received
                    no true cultivation. Whether it will ever get this is a question that remains to
                    be answered. Commercially the harmonium and American organ have taken a much
                    more important place, although of course one not equal to that of the
                    pianoforte. For some years the Alexandres were sending annually 7000 harmoniums
                    to England. This afterwards, from various causes, diminished; the number,
                    however, of their instruments made up to 1879 has reached 110j000. A general
                    estimate of harmoniums made annually in France, Germany, and England is not
                    forthcoming; but the yearly production of American organs in the United States
                    has been stated at the large total of 40,000. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.j.
                    h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
