<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0789-0754-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEROD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 754</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45717w2f">Proof</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HEROD</label> was the name of a family of Idumaean origin,
                    which displaced the Asmoneans as the rulers of Judaea. The founder of the
                    dynasty, and its most notable representative in every way, was Herod the Great,
                    who was king of the Jews for about thirty-seven years, from 40 to 4 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Herod’s father was Antipater, who during the troubles
                    which broke out in the family of Alexander Jannaeus, attached himself to
                    Hyrcanus, the weak-minded son of Alexander. In this way Antipater, though an
                    Idumaean, soon became the most powerful man in Judaea, and in the Alexandrian
                    war gave such effectual help to Julius Caesar that the dictator made him
                    procurator of Judaea, Hyrcanus being high priest (47 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.).</hi> The same year, at the age of twenty-five, Herod was appointed
                    governor of Galilee by his father. He soon gave proof of the remarkable energy
                    of his character in rooting out the banditti who infested his province; but his
                    summary measures gave a handle to the enemies of his house at Jerusalem, and he
                    was summoned before the sanhedrin. There he appeared, not in the garb of an
                    accused person, but gorgeously attired, and attended by a guard of soldiers. He
                    found it expedient, however, to withdraw from Jerusalem without awaiting the
                    sentence. He retired to Syria, where he met with a gracious reception from
                    Sextus Caesar, who appointed him governor of Coele-Syria. Herod now marched with
                    an army against Jerusalem, but at the persuasion of his father and brother was
                    induced to depart without exacting vengeance on his enemies. After the death of
                    Caesar, the fortunes of Herod were affected by all the changes which befell the
                    Roman state. When Cassius took the command in the East, and began to gather his
                    strength for the final struggle which was decided at Philippi, Herod managed to
                    win his favour by the readiness with which he raised his share of the heavy
                    exactions imposed upon the East. About the same time his father was poisoned,
                    and to Herod fell the task of avenging his death, as well as of supporting the
                    interests of his house in Palestine. After Philippi he gained Antony over by
                    large presents of money. He and his brother Phasael were appointed tetrarchs of
                    Judaea. In 40 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> the Parthians appeared upon the
                    scene, overran the whole of Syria, and placed on the throne of Judaea Antigonus,
                    son of Aristobulus, and representative of the rival branch of the Asmonean
                    house. Herod was completely overpowered; and, after placing his relatives in
                    safety, so far as he could, he hastened to Rome to lay his case before Antony
                    and Octavianus. He succeeded beyond his expectation, for, while he meant only to
                    advocate the claims of Hyrcanus the Asmonean, the two heads of the state made
                    him king of Judaea. Herod returned home without delay, and set about the task of
                    winning the kingdom allotted to him. Owing chiefly to the slackness of the Roman
                    generals who should have helped him, it was three years before he succeeded in
                    taking Jerusalem (37 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> Before that event he had
                    married the beautiful Mariamne, a princess of the Asmonean house, a
                    granddaughter both of Aristobulus and Hyrcanus. Herod’s early measures were
                    cruel; he put to death all the members of the sanhedrin except two, and spared
                    no one that was likely to stand in his way. Aristobulus, the youthful brother of
                    Mariamne, whom he had appointed high priest, he caused to be treacherously
                    drowned because he was too popular with the patriotic party. On this occasion
                    Alexandra, mother of Aristobulus, induced Cleopatra to take her part, and Herod
                    had to appear before Antony to answer the charge of murdering the prince. Again
                    Herod knew how to gain the Roman, and he returned home with confirmed power.
                    During the war of Actium, Herod had the good fortune to be engaged in a war with
                    the king of Arabia on Antony’s behalf, and so escaped the risk of fighting
                    against Octavianus. Yet he recognized the danger of his position as the friend
                    of Antony, and faced it with his usual courage and foresight. Hastening to
                    Rhodes (30 B.C.), he appeared in the presence of the conqueror, and avowing his
                    loyalty to his friend Antony, proffered the same faithful service to Octavianus.
                    Octavianus was graciou⅝ and remained the constant friend and patron of Herod to
                    the end. This was the last crisis of Herod’s life; he was henceforward
                    undisputed king of Judaea, and next to Agrippa the most trusted friend of
                    Augustus. But while the friend of the great, and prosperous in all external
                    relations, Nemesis pursued him in his family. When summoned to answer for
                    himself before Antony, and again on his journey to Rhodes, he left the beautiful
                    and beloved Mariamne in charge of one of his friends, but with the cruel
                    injunction that she should be put to death should anything serious befall
                    himself. On both occasions Mariamne discovered the secret, and, instead <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n790/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0790-0755"/> of regarding the command as a proof of his
                    jealous love, abhorred it as another instance of the cruelty which had not
                    spared so many of her nearest relatives. A horrible tragedy ensued: Mariamne
                    openly expressed her disgust; and Herod, furious with rage, jealousy, and
                    rejected love, ordered her death. The violence of his feelings threw him into a
                    dangerous malady, and even drove him to the verge of insanity. His mind never
                    recovered its healthy tone, and in later years the avenger again overtook him.
                    In the meantime his government was marked by the greatest magnificence and
                    apparent success. His turbulent subjects were kept tolerably quiet in spite of
                    heavy taxes. He managed to gratify his love for Greek and Roman life; and yet he
                    avoided wounding too deeply the susceptibilities of the Jews. The magnificent
                    buildings which he raised were the most brilliant products of his reign. He
                    rebuilt Samaria, calling it Sebaste, from the Greek name for Augustus. He
                    converted the small town of Strato’s Tower into a magnificent seaport with an
                    artificial harbour, under the name of Caesarea. These and other towns which he
                    built were furnished with temples, theatres, aqueducts, and all the other
                    ornamental and useful appliances of Greek and Roman life. In the city of
                    Jerusalem even he built a theatre, and an amphitheatre outside of it. A more
                    patriotic work was the rebuilding of the temple (begun 20 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi>), which had suffered greatly during the late troubles; it was on a
                    very magnificent scale, and lasted nine years and a half, even then being
                    unfinished. Equally necessary and equally significant of his relation to his
                    subjects was the construction of strong fortresses in various parts of the
                    country. The last years of Herod’s life were darkened by the return of those
                    family troubles which had previously overcast it. His two sons by Mariamne had
                    been educated at Rome, and returned, 17 B,c., to Judaea. Their Asmonean descent,
                    their youth, beauty, and accomplishments, and their too interesting history
                    gained them the most enthusiastic popularity among the Jews. Their father
                    himself was proud of them. But Pheroras and Salome, brother and sister of Herod,
                    did all they could to sow jealousy and suspicion. Herod’s mind was too painfully
                    open to dark insinuations, and he recalled his eldest son Antipater to
                    counterbalance the influence of the Asmonean princes. After the arrival of
                    Antipater, who was a most unscrupulous plotter, there was no more peace or
                    security at the court of Herod; things went from bad to worse, till after many
                    years of the darkest intrigue and the bitterest domestic contention, the two
                    sons of Mariamne were strangled at Sebaste. Soon after the clearest proof was
                    discovered of a conspiracy which Antipater had formed with Pheroras against the
                    life of Herod himself. The order for the death of Antipater was given by Herod
                    from his death-bed. His health had long been failing; after the cruellest
                    torments of both mind and body, he died 4 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The
                    birth of Christ took place in the same year as Herod’s death, but this, as is
                    well known, occurred four years before the date fixed as the beginning of the
                    Christian era. The massacre of the little children at Bethlehem is not mentioned
                    by Josephus among the horrors of Herod’s last days. He was buried with great
                    magnificence. His will, by which the greater part of his dominions was
                    bequeathed to his sons by Malthace, a Samaritan, was confirmed by Augustus.</p>
                <p>Herod’s name is doubtless one of the most repulsive in history. He was a man of
                    wonderful energy and sagacity. He saw clearly that Rome was the hinge on which
                    everything turned, and that no policy could be successful which did not depend
                    upon her leading men. His skill in understanding these men, in conciliating
                    them, and making himself useful to them, was very great. Thus he made the
                    successive masters of the world his willing friends, and out of all the crises
                    of his fate emerged victorious. But his hands were red with the blood of his own
                    household; when his position or his interests were touched no scruple could
                    arrest him. All that can be said in his favour is that many of his cruel
                    measures cost him unspeakable agony of mind, and that he was simply more expert
                    than his rivals at the weapons which were in common use in the political life of
                    the time.</p>
                <p>The great source for the life of Herod is Josephus; but such writers as Strabo or
                    Dion Cassius are of service in further illustrating it. Useful modern works are
                    Hausrath, <hi rend="italic">Neutestamentliche</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Zeitgeschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the work of the same name by
                    Schürer; Ewald, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Volkes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Israel,</hi> vol. iv.; Keim, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte Jesu von</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Nazara,</hi> vol. i.; and Milman’s <hi rend="italic">History of
                    the Jews,</hi> vol. ii. (T. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
