<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0414-0395-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HALLE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 395</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n414/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HALLE</label> (formerly called, to distinguish it from other
                    towns of the same name, Halle in Sachsen, but now generally known as Halle an
                    der Saale), a city of Prussian Saxony, government district of Merseburg, is
                    situated on the right bank of the Saale and at the junction of six railways, 20
                    miles N.W. of Leipsic. It consists of the old town, or Halle proper, with five
                    suburbs, and the two small towns of Glauchau and Neumarkt, which were added to
                    it in 1817. Halle is under the immediate jurisdiction of the crown, and is the
                    seat of the imperial chief office of mines for the provinces of Saxony,
                    Brandenburg, and Pomerania, of a head tax-office, of a circle court, and of a
                    provincial office. The greater part of the town is irregularly built, and
                    presents a somewhat unattractive appearance to the eye of a stranger; but of
                    late years it has been much improved by the construction of new promenades on
                    the site of the old fortifications, and by the repaving of many of the streets
                    and the addition of new buildings. Its well-known university was founded by King
                    Frederick I. in 1694 in behalf of the jurist Thomasius, whom many students
                    followed to Halle when he was expelled from Leipsic through the enmity of his
                    fellow professors. It was closed by Napoleon <hi rend="superscript"> lu</hi>
                    1806, and again in 1813; and in 1815 it was united with that of Wittenberg. It
                    has faculties of theology, law, medicine, and philosophy. From the beginning it
                    has been recognized as one of the principal schools of Protestant theology, and
                    has numbered among its professors some of the most eminent names of Germany. Its
                    maximum number of students occurred in 1829 when they exceeded 1300.
                    Subsequently the number declined below 600, but at present the average
                    attendance is between 900 and 1000. The present buildings were erected in 1834.
                    In connexion with the university there are a botanical garden, a theological and
                    normal seminary, a medical and surgical clinical institute, a maternity
                    hospital, an observatory, and a library of over 100,000 volumes, which also
                    contains collections of coins and engravings. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Franchdsche</hi><hi rend="italic">Stiftungen</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    founded in 1691 by August Hermann Francke, a bronze statue of whom by Rauch was
                    erected in 1829 in the inner court of the building—embrace an orphanage, a
                    laboratory where medicines are prepared and distributed, a Bible press from
                    which Bibles are issued at a cheap rate, and a number of schools of various
                    grades, viz., a Latin school, a higher real-school, a citizen school, a higher
                    female school, and a free school, attended in all by over 3000 pupils. The
                    principal other institutions are the city gymnasium, the provincial trade
                    school, the provincial lunatic asylum, the penitentiary, the town hospital and
                    infirmary, and the deaf and dumb institute. Among the other public buildings may
                    be mentioned the church of St Mary, containing some fine paintings, an
                    interesting Gothic structure of the 16th century, with four towers, two of which
                    are connected by a bridge; the church of St Maurice, dating from the 12th
                    century, with interesting wood-carvings and sculptures; the church of St Ulrich,
                    dating from the 14th century; the cathedral, founded in the 16th century, and
                    containing an altar-piece representing Duke Augustus of Saxony and his family;
                    the red clock tower in the market-place, 276 feet in height; the old town-house;
                    the ruins of the castle of Moritzburg, erected in 1484, formerly the residence
                    of the archbishops of Magdeburg, but destroyed by fire during the Thirty Years’
                    War, with the exception of the left wing, which is now used for military
                    purposes; the lodge of the freemasons; and the theatre. In 1859 a bronze statue
                    was erected in the market-place to Handel, who was born at Halle in 1685; and in
                    the outskirts of the town there is a monument to the Germans who fell at the
                    battle of Leipsic in 1813. The salt-springs of Halle have been known from a very
                    early period. Some rise within the town and others on an island in the Saale;
                    and together their annual yield of salt is about 12,000 tons. The workmen
                    employed in connexion with the manufacture are a peculiar and distinct race
                    known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Halloren,</hi> probably descended from an
                    old Frankish colony. They observe several ancient customs, and enjoy certain
                    special exemptions and privileges. The principal other industries of Halle are
                    the manufacture of starch, beetroot-sugar, chemicals, lignite, candles,
                    potterywares, sausages, oil, machines and waggons, sugar-refining, brewing,
                    printing, and bookbinding. Considerable trade, especially in corn, is now
                    carried on by means of the railways, but the shipping trade is unimportant. The
                    population has increased with great rapidity during the last quarter of a
                    century, for while the numbers in 1831 were 25,594, they had risen in 1849 to
                    33,848 and in 1875 to 60,503.</p>
                <p>Halle was first mentioned in 806 as the fortress of Halla erected by Charlemagne.
                    The place was, however, in existence before the Christian era, and owes its
                    origin as well as its name to its saltsprings. Otto the Great presented it in
                    965 along with the saltsprings to the bishopric of Magdeburg, and in 981 Otto
                    II. raised it to the rank of a town. At the beginning.of the 12th century it had
                    attained considerable importance, and in the 13th and 14th centuries as a member
                    of the Hanseatic League it carried on successful wars with the archbishops of
                    Magdeburg; and in 1435 it resisted an army of 30,000 men under the elector of
                    Saxony. On account, however, of internal feuds between the democracy and the
                    patricians it <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n415/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0415-0396"/> was subdued in 1478 by Archbishop Ernest, who in
                    order to hold it in check built the castle of Moritzburg. Notwithstanding the
                    efforts of the archbishops of Mainz and Magdeburg, the Reformation found an
                    entrance into the city in 1522; and in 1541 a Lutheran superintendent was
                    appointed. After the peace of Westphalia in 1648 the city came into the
                    possession of the house of Brandenburg. In 1806 it was stormed and taken by the
                    French, after which, at the peace of Tilsit, it was united to the new kingdom of
                    Westphalia. After the battle between the Prussians and French, May 2, 1813, it
                    was taken by the Prussians. The rise of Leipsic was for a long time hurtful to
                    the prosperity of Halle, and its present rapid increase in population and trade
                    is principally due to its position as the centre of a network of railways.</p>
                <p>See Dreyhaupt, <hi rend="italic">Ausführliche Beschreibung</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >des</hi><hi rend="italic">Saalkreises,</hi> Halle, 2 vols., 1755 (2d edition,
                    1771-73; 3d edition, 1842-44); Hoff-bauer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                    Universität zu Halle,</hi> 1806; <hi rend="italic">Halle in Vorzeit und
                    Gegenwart,</hi> 1851; Knauth, <hi rend="italic">Kurze Geschichte und
                    Beschreibung der Stadt Halle,</hi> 3d edition, 1861; Vom Hagen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Die Stadt Halle,</hi> 1866- 67; Hertzberg, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte der Vereinigung der Universitäten von Wittenberg und Halle,</hi>
                    1867; Voss, <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der Autonomie der Stadt Halle,</hi>
                    1874; A. Kirchkoff, “Ueber die Lagenverhältnisse der Stadt Halle,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Mittheilungen des Vereins für Erdkunde zu Halle,</hi> Halle,
                    1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
