<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0382-0363-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HADRIAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 363</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205364">Mauritania</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1054016">Parthians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100796">Roxolani</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n382/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HADRIAN</label>, Roman emperor (117-138 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.),</hi> distinguished for the peace and beneficent energy of his
                    government, was born at Rome 76 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> His full name was
                    Publius Aelius Hadrianus; his ancestors, originally from Picenum, had been
                    settled at Italica in Spain since the time of the Scipios. He lost his father at
                    the age of ten, and was placed under the guardianship of Trajan, a cousin of his
                    father and also a native of Italica, who was already a conspicuous man in the
                    Roman army. We know little of Hadrian’s youth; but he gave early promise of the
                    readiness and versatility which distinguished him in later life, for he was so
                    ardent a student of Greek that men nicknamed him Graeculus. At fifteen he
                    entered on the practical career of war and government which befitted a Roman,
                    and grew fond of the chase even to excess. Patronized by Trajan and assisted by
                    powerful friends he rose rapidly, filling successively all the civil and
                    military offices, which now, as under the republic, were open to young men of
                    good birth. On Trajan’s elevation to the empire Hadrian was the first to
                    congratulate him. He served with distinction in both the Dacian campaigns; in
                    the latter Trajan presented him with the ring he had received from Nerva, a
                    proof of his regard which justified him in aspiring to be his successor. If
                    Trajan was not always favourably disposed towards Hadrian, the good-will of the
                    empress Plotina never failed him, and was particularly helpful in some of the
                    most critical turning points of his career. She it was who secured his alliance
                    with Sabina, granddaughter of the emperor’s sister, a marriage, however, which
                    proved anything but happy. She, it was thought, did him still more effectual
                    service at Trajan’s death, even determining the question of the succession in
                    his favour. When that emperor returned from his victorious war in Parthia, the
                    succession was still undecided; and we are assured on the express testimony of
                    Dion Cassius that Plotina and her friends concealed his death for several days
                    in order to facilitate the elevation of Hadrian. Whatever may have been the
                    truth of such stories, Hadrian’s claim to the empire rested on the
                    unquestionable fact that he was the fittest man. His position as prefect of
                    Syria, and commander of the legions with which Trajan had prostrated the
                    Parthian empire, made him supreme in the army, while his peaceful disposition
                    and civil demeanour must have made him acceptable to the senate. Yet he was not
                    unconscious of the insecurity of his position; for he hastened to propitiate the
                    army by a donation of twice the usual amount, and to excuse his abrupt elevation
                    to the senate by alleging the impatient zeal of the soldiers and the welfare of
                    the state, which could not exist without an “imperator.” The first important act
                    of Hadrian was to abandon the late conquests of Trajan, and again to make the
                    Euphrates the eastern boundary of the empire. At his elevation the provinces
                    were unsettled, and the barbarians on the frontier restless and menacing. He was
                    convinced that the old limits of Augustus offered the most defensible frontier,
                    and that the energy of the emperor was sufficiently occupied in governing the
                    provinces already won. This policy of renunciation was ascribed to jealousy of
                    Trajan; but history has recognized its wisdom. While arranging the affairs of
                    the East, Hadrian had an opportunity of pardoning some eminent citizens who were
                    accused of hostility to him, and after his return to Rome he confirmed his
                    popularity by many gracious acts. Modestly declining the honours heaped upon
                    himself, he carefully rendered the last offices to the deceased emperor, and
                    considerably lightened the burdens of the citizens. During an absence in Moesia,
                    where he had gone to compose some troubles with the Sarmatae and Roxolani, a
                    formidable conspiracy was formed against him. The details are obscure; but four
                    consular men, among the most eminent of Rome., were accused of being concerned
                    in it, and were put to death. Some, however, went so far as to say that the
                    conspiracy was a scheme devised by Hadrian for getting rid of dreaded rivals. It
                    was a dark transaction which threw a suspicion on bis character. On his return
                    to Rome he exerted himself to undo the evil effects of it by a generous and
                    popular policy. Towards the senate he expressed the utmost deference and
                    consideration; he admitted the most eminent of its members to familiar
                    intercourse, raised them to the highest honours, and supplied the indigent with
                    means to maintain their position. He was equally liberal to the body of the
                    people, granting them a large donation of money, remitting the arrears of taxes
                    for the last fifteen years, and increasing the funds which Trajan had devoted to
                    the alimentation of poor children. These measures of Hadrian might be criticized
                    as the calculating policy of one who felt his position to be insecure, and who
                    could afford to be generous to the city out of the revenues of the empire But
                    such a theory could not apply to what is most characteristic in hi3 rule,—his
                    unwearying-care for the provinces and for the empire as a whole. He understood
                    the true task of a Roman emperor better perhaps than any of his predecessors.
                    More clearly than any of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n383/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0383-0364"/> them he saw that the period of conquest was past,
                    that an extension of the frontiers would only weaken the defensive power of the
                    empire, that the time for consolidation and for softening the distinction
                    between Rome and the provinces was come. While Trajan had been guilty of the
                    anachronism of rivalling Alexander the Great, Hadrian made it the work of his
                    life to become acquainted with the provinces, to learn their needs and
                    resources, to improve and benefit them; he sought to be the effective ruler of
                    the empire as a whole, and so was the first to realize the cosmopolitan task
                    which his position imposed. For this end he sought to obtain a personal
                    knowledge of the people he had undertaken to govern. Leaving Rome in 119, he
                    visited probably every province of the empire. After traversing Gaul he
                    inspected the legions on the Rhine, and then crossed to Britain, where he built
                    (121) the great rampart from the Tyne to the Solway which bears his name. He
                    returned through Gaul into Spain, and then proceeded to Mauritania, where he
                    suppressed an insurrection. We next find him in the East averting a war with
                    Parthia by a timely interview with the king. From the Parthian frontier he
                    travelled through Asia Minor and the islands to Athens, where he sojourned a
                    consider ιble time, and so returned by Sicily to Rome, having made the circuit
                    of the empire. After some stay at Rome he resumed his travels. It is impossible
                    to fix the details of this second progress with any exactness. It was chiefly in
                    the East; and he did not finally return to Rome till 134. Everywhere he left
                    lasting traces of his restless and beneficent energy; he built aqueducts and
                    temples, and raised fortifications in suitable places; he inspected the details
                    of the administration, learned to know the offi iials, and made himself at home
                    in the military encampments. He was accompanied by a body of architects and
                    artizιns organized like a legion, whom he employed to gratify his passion for
                    building in a truly imperial manner. Athens was the favoured scene of his
                    architectural labours; he added a new quarter to the city, and finished the
                    temple of the Olympian Zeus. While Hadrian spent his life in inspecting the
                    provinces, and was not disinclined to purchase peace by a subsidy to the
                    restless tribes on the frontiers, he did not neglect the army. All along the
                    frontier his legions stood in constant preparation for battle. He maintained a
                    rigorous discipline; the rules he drew up for the army long served as a kind of
                    military code. He trained them to the severest exercises, and anticipated all
                    complaint by sharing in their fatigues, walking bare-headed on a march of 20
                    miles a day, and partaking of their coarse fare of cheese, lard, and sour wine.
                    The only important war in which this army was tested was the great rebellion of
                    the Jews, which broke out in 131, and lasted for several years. The founding of
                    a Roman colony on the site of Jerusalem, an 1 an order of Hadrian forbidding the
                    rite of circumcision, were the causes of the war. The Jews fought with the most
                    resolute despair, and they were crushed only by a powerful army commanded by the
                    best general of the empire. According to Dion, 580,000 Jews fell in battle. The
                    whole country was reduced to a wilderness. But the loss of the Roman legions was
                    so severe that in writing to the senate Hadrian omitted the customary
                    formula:—“If you and your children are well, it is well; I and the army are
                    well.” In the later years of his life Hadrian discontinued his travels, and
                    lived at Rome or near it. His health, which had been impaired by long exposure
                    to the extremes of heat and cold, began to fail; and, what was worse, the dark
                    and suspicious moods which had broken out occasionally in his earlier years
                    became more frequent and fatal. His aged brother-in-law Servianus fell a victim
                    to his jealousy; his wife Sabina died, not without a rumour of poisoning. Most
                    of those who had been his familiar friends, and had been raised by him to the
                    highest offioes, were superseded, or banished, or put to death. But his passion
                    for architecture did not abate. He built for his residence the great villa of
                    Tibur, which was eight miles in circuit, and was a kind of epitome of the world,
                    with miniatures of the most celebrated places in the provinces, and even of
                    Hades. He built a splendid mausoleum, which has been the nucleus of the castle
                    of St Angelo, and rebuilt several edifices at Rome. In these years he had to
                    choose a successor. His first choice was Aelius Verus, who did nothing to
                    justify such a distinction. The next was Antoninus Pius, so called from the
                    filial assiduity with which he cherished the last days and the memory of his
                    adopted father. Antoninus saved him from suicide, to which his physical
                    sufferings impelled him, and from imbruing his hands in the blood of many noble
                    Romans, who had provoked his moody and fickle temper. Hadrian died at Baiae, 138
                    A.n. The cruelty of his latter life had so eclipsed the lustre of his early rule
                    that the senate at first refused him divine honours, and were prevailed upon to
                    grant" them only at the urgent solicitation of Antoninus. In the travels and
                    administrative energy of Hadrian we see only one side of his character. He had a
                    versatile and many-sided mind, in which the faculty for command, speculative
                    curiosity, and literary ambition were strangely blended. Not satisfied with the
                    toils imposed on the laborious autocrat of the world, he sought to excel the
                    Greek professors and artists each in his own special walk. In painting,
                    sculpture, and music, in rhetoric and philosophy, he considered himself the
                    competent rival and critic of men who had made these pursuits the work of a
                    lifetime. The architect Apollodorus atoned for his frankness with his life. The
                    more politic Favorinus, when reproached for yielding too readily to the emperor
                    in some grammatical discussion, replied that it was unwise to dispute with the
                    master of thirty legions. The product of Hadrian’s pen which has been most
                    celebrated is the dying address to his soul :—</p>
                <p>“Animula vagula, blandula, Hospes comesque corporis, Quae nunc abibis in loca
                    Pallidula, rigida, nudula; Nec, ut soles, dabis jocos ?”</p>
                <p>Under Hadrian Salvius Julianus composed a “perpetua! edict,” which is supposed to
                    have been a fixed code of some kind, but the exact significance of the edict is
                    disputed. Still there can be no doubt that Roman law owes much to Hadrian.</p>
                <p>The sources for Hadrian’s life are unsatisfactory; the chief are Spartianus in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Scriptores</hi><hi rend="italic">Historioe Augustae,</hi>
                    and Dion Cassius as abridged by Xiphilinus, lib. lxix; see also Aurelius Victor
                    <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">Caesaribus,</hi> and Eutropius; for
                    modern works consult Merivale’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Romans under
                    the Empire</hi>; Gregorovius, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. Hadrians·,</hi> and W. W.
                    Capes’s “Age of the Antonines” in the series <hi rend="italic">Epochs of Ancient
                    History.</hi> (T. K. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
