<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0766-0731-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEREROLAND, or Damaraland</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 731</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45w0g">Hereros</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f766919">Damaras</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639k810">Ovum</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dt2t">Hottentots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110447">Seasons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1049494">Ovum</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799932">Africanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n766/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HEREROLAND, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Damaraland</hi></label>,
                    a region of SouthWestern Africa, stretching north from the Kuisip to the Cunene,
                    so called from the native race known to the Namaqua as Herero and to the Cape
                    colonists as Damara (Damra, or Dama). The north-west portion is also known as
                    Kaokoland.</p>
                <p>According to the treaty of Okahandya, by which, in 1876, the country came in some
                    sort under British protection,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Damara and Namaqua Land: Report of W.
                    Coates Palgrave, Esq., special commissioner to the tribes north of the Orange
                    River, of his mission to Damaraland and Great Namaqualand in</hi> 1876, Cape
                    Town, 1877.</p></note> the boundary line is fixed as coinciding in the south
                    with the line of latitude passing through Rehoboth or Annis (a mission station
                    in 17° 5' E. long, and about 165 miles from the coast), thence in a straight
                    line to Otyimbinde (Tunobis or Riet Fontein), in 20° 53' E. long, and 22° 5' S.
                    lat., thence northwards to Otyiondarmie, and finally from that place westwards
                    along the 0muramba Ovambo to the Cunene. The territory thus defined has an
                    estimated area of 100,000 square miles; and of this about 35,000 square miles
                    were marked out as a British reservation, bounded by a line drawn from Rehoboth
                    to Otyimbinde, thence north-west to Otyituo, about 19° E. long, and 20° S. lat.,
                    thence west to Otyahevita, and south to the neighbourhood of Mount Erongo.
                    According to Palgrave the total population of Hereroland is 121,150, of whom
                    85,000 are Hetero proper, 30,000 Hill Damara, 3000 Bushmen, 1500 Namaqua, 1500
                    Bastards, and 150 Europeans. In a paper in <hi rend="italic">Petermaun's</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mittheilungen,</hi> 1878, based on information from the Rhenish
                    missionaries, the total is given as 184,000, of whom 110,000 are Herero (80,000
                    Ova Herero and 30,000 Ova-mbanderu), <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n767/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0767-0732"/> 50,000 Hill Damara, 2500 Namaqua, 2000 Bastards,
                    20,000 Bushmen, and 300 whites.</p>
                <p>Hereroland has a coast-line of 460 miles, but the only point where it offers
                    shelter and access to ships is Walfish Bay, a safe but comparatively shallow
                    harbour formed by Pelican Point immediately to the south of the mouth of the
                    Kuisip. The country consists of three distinct physical regions—first, a long
                    and narrow coast district backed by a very regular line of hills, of which the
                    highest point appears to be Mount Messum or Dourissa; secondly, a broad
                    mountainous tract, containing in the south such peaks as Omatako, 8800 feet,
                    Ombotozu (Diambotodzu), 7300, Etyo, 4000, and far in the north Etendeka, 4000;
                    and thirdly, a steppe region which stretches away into the Kalahari desert. The
                    rivers of Hereroland, of which the most important, passing from south to north,
                    are the Tsoachaub, the Eisib or Omaruru, the Ugab, and the Huab, are mere
                    wadies, which only at intervals succeed in bringing water as far as the sea.
                    Except in the half-dry river-beds, the coast district is almost destitute of
                    vegetation, the only edible fruit being the <hi rend="italic">nara,</hi> which
                    grows on the sand-downs, and is, according to Anderson, eaten by oxen, mice,
                    men, ostriches, and lions. In the mountainous tract there are places of
                    considerable fertility; large trees, as sycamores, &amp;c., grow along the
                    river-beds, and euphorbias, tamarisks, and a variety of strong-spined bushes
                    prevail. In a few favoured spots wheat can be cultivated, and from a single
                    grain as many as 150 stalks may be produced. The coast range and many of the
                    mountains, such as Okonyonyo and Amatako, are composed of granite and gneiss,
                    broken by intrusive quartz and porphyry; further east limestone formations, both
                    Carboniferous and Oolitic, are predominant; and these again give place to
                    sandstone strata, which are weathered into table-shaped eminences. The granite
                    and gneiss are being disintegrated with great rapidity. Both iron and copper are
                    said to occur in considerable abundance, though the mineral exploitation of the
                    country has had no satisfactory result. About 25 mineral springs, both hot and
                    cold, are known to exist among the mountains.</p>
                <p>An interesting sketch of the climate was contributed by Dr A. von Danckelmann to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschr.</hi><hi rend="italic">der öslerr.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Gesellsch. fur Meteor.,</hi> 1878. Owing, it would appear, to the
                    cold current in the neighbouring sea, the coast region is almost rainless;
                    though occasionally, in the rainy season of the interior, storm-clouds with
                    thunder and lightning come from the east, and from September to March south-west
                    winds laden with heavy mist blow almost without interruption. In the interior
                    the year is divided into a regular dry and wet season, the former lasting from
                    May to November. From September onwards the air is so clear that the planet
                    Venus can be distinguished at midday, and every object looks so distinct that it
                    is almost impossible to calculate distances correctly. Even during the rainy
                    season the nights are usually cloudless. Not unfrequently before the beginning
                    of the rains “sand-spouts,” or, as they are called by the natives, Kumb’anhara
                    or “rain-beggars,” drive across the country. No support is afforded by the
                    observations in Hereroland to the theory of the periodicity of African rain in
                    accordance with the changes of the sun spots; but there would seem to be a
                    gradual decrease of atmospheric precipitation. From September to December the
                    east wind usually blows in the morning, but it passes round to the north-west in
                    the forenoon. From. December to April the east is decidedly predominant. Snow is
                    extremely rare, but night frosts occur several times a year, and ice has been
                    found inch thick. In the dry season the daily range of the thermometer is from
                    32° or 36° Fahr, to 75° or 79°; in the rainy season from 86° or 95° to 68° or
                    82°.</p>
                <p>The Herero are the dominant race. They are well-formed, of good stature, and of
                    regular features. Their complexion is usually dark but not black; but there is
                    sufficient variety to lead them to classify themselves into the Ovathorondu or
                    “red folks” andtheθvatherandu or “dark folks.” Their scanty clothingconsists
                    mainly of skins and leather thongs, and both their garments and their bodies are
                    thickly smeared with ochre and grease. The women’s head-dress is a curious
                    three-eared helmet. Assegais, bows and arrows, and knobsticks or kieries are the
                    native weapons, but guns and even breechloaders are growing not uncommon. The
                    whole race is in the pastoral etage, and some of the chiefs possess very
                    extensive property in cattle. The various clans or “uandas” have each its own
                    totem; and thus to one man it is a sin to partake of the flesh of a red cow and
                    to another a one-horned sheep is equally sacred. By their language (Otyiherero)
                    the Herero belong to the great Bantu family. For our acquaintance with it we are
                    mainly indebted to the Rhenish missionaries, and more particularly to Dr Hahn,
                    who published <hi rend="italic">Grτιηdzuge</hi><hi rend="italic">einer Grammatik
                    der Herero,</hi> Berlin, 1857. A spelling book (Cape Town, 1848) appears to be
                    the earliest work printed in the tongue.</p>
                <p>The Herero would seem to have come from the north, and tl·xey probably first
                    appeared to the south of the Cunene about 150 years ago, to the dismay of the
                    Hill Damara (Houquoin, lhaukoin, Ova-zoratu, or Ghoudamoup), a peculiar race who
                    now occupy the fastnesses of the country, and speak the Nama or Hottentot
                    language with a foreign accent, though there is no tradition of their having
                    used any other. The Herero were subjugated by Jonker Afrikaner, and for a time
                    were scattered among the Namaqua tribes, but about 1865 they recovered their
                    independence. They are still unfriendly to the Hill Damara, who steal their
                    cattle, and they are beginning to hunt down the Bushmen. A single tribe of the
                    Namaqua, which sided with them in their war of liberty, is still settled near
                    Mount Erongo.</p>
                <p>Besides the works already mentioned, and the travels of Baines, Galton, and
                    Anderson, see Hahn, “Die Ova-Herero." in <hi rend="italic">Zeitsch.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">für Erdkunde,</hi> Berlin, 1868 and 1869, and “Reise im Lande der
                    Herero," in Petermann’s <hi rend="italic">Mittheilungen,</hi> 1873.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
