<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0785-0750-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERMES TRISMEGISTUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 750</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4f76698p">Epithets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dj58r59">Tatting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61d88">Judaism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1143545">Tats</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109393">Scribes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n785/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERMES TRISMEGISTUS</label>. The Egyptian Thoth, Tauut, or
                    Tat (see vol. vii. p. 718), who was identified by the Greeks more or less
                    completely with their own Hermes, is described in the hieroglyphics by various
                    epithets, among which occurs that of “the great great” or twice great, with an
                    added hieroglyphic (a kite) also signifying “great.” To him as scribe of the
                    gods, “Lord of the divine words,” “Scribe of truth,” was attributed the
                    authorship of all the strictly sacred books generally called by Greek authors
                    Hermetic. These, according to Clemens Alexandrinus, our sole ancient authority
                    <hi rend="italic">(Strom.,</hi> vi. p. 268 <hi rend="italic">sq.},</hi> were
                    forty-two<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n786/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0786-0751"/> in number, and were subdivided into six
                    divisions, of which the first, containing the ten books “of the prophets,” dealt
                    with laws, deities, and the education of priests; the second, consisting of the
                    ten books of the “stolistes,” or official whose duty it was to dress and
                    ornament the statues of the gods, treated of sacrifices and offerings, prayers,
                    hymns, festive processions; the third, “of the hierogram-matist,” also in ten
                    books, was a repertory of hieroglyphical, cosmographical, geographical, and
                    topographical information; the four books “of the horoscopus” were devoted to
                    astronomy and astrology; the two books “of the chanter” contained respectively a
                    collection of songs in honour of the gods and a description of the royal life
                    and its duties; while the sixth and last division, consisting of the six books
                    “of the pastophor,” was medical. Of this canon, which according to the generally
                    received opinion of Bunsen must have been closed at latest in the time of the
                    Psanιmetichi but probably earlier, numerous small fragments are to be found in
                    the works of Stobaeus and other ancient writers. The now well-known <hi
                    rend="italic">Book of the Dead,</hi> according to Bunsen, originally had its
                    place among the ten ceremonial books of the “stolistes,” but this is denied by
                    Lepsius; an ancient papyrus recently deciphered by Ebers is believed by that
                    author to date from about the year 1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and to
                    have formed part of one of the books of the pastophor.</p>
                <p>The epithet Trismegistus (ό <hi rend="italic">τpισμεyιστος,</hi> or
                    “superlatively” greatest), as applied to Hermes, is of comparatively late
                    origin, and cannot be traced to any author earlier than the 2d Christian
                    century. Most probably it arose out of the earlier forms p,εγας και p,εγας or
                    μέγιστος, derived by the Greeks from early Egyptian sources; but various other
                    explanations of the appellation have been offered, such as that of the author of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Chronicοn</hi><hi rend="italic">Alexandrinum</hi> (47 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a,d.),</hi> who maintains that it was because Hermes, while
                    maintaining the unity of God, had also asserted the existence of three supreme
                    or greatest powers that he was called by the Egyptians Trismegistus. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> This view, which is also adopted by Suidas, seems
                    preferable at least to that met with in Nicolai’s <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Greek Literature,</hi> according to which an apocryphal author named Hermes was
                    called τpισμε∙ γιστιoς, simply in order to indicate that he had succeeded and
                    outdone a certain Megistias of Smyrna in astrological, physiognomical, and
                    alchemistic theories. The name of Hermes seems during the third and following
                    centuries to have been regarded as a convenient pseudonym to place at the head
                    of the numerous syncretistic writings in which it was sought to combine
                    Neo-Platonic philosophy, Philonic Judaism, and cabbalistic theosophy, and so
                    provide the world with some acceptable substitute for the Christianity which had
                    even at that time begun to give indications of the ascendency it was destined
                    afterwards to attain. Of these pseudepigraphic Hermetic writings some have come
                    down to us in the original Greek; others survive in Latin or Arabic
                    translations; but the majority appear to have perished. That which is best known
                    and has been most frequently edited is the <hi rend="italic">ποιμάνδρης</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sive</hi><hi rend="italic">De Potestate</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">Sapientia Divina</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(ποιμάνδρης</hi> being the Divine Intelligence <hi rend="italic">τrοιμην
                    αv8pωv),</hi> which consists of fifteen chapters treating of such subjects as
                    the nature of God, the origin of the world, the creation and fall of man, and
                    the divine illumination which is the sole means of his deliverance. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Editio Princeps</hi> appeared in Paris in 1554; and there has been
                    a recent edition by Parthey (1854); the work has also been translated into
                    German by Tiedemann (1781). Along with it are usually printed the certainly
                    later δpoι or <hi rend="italic">Definitions</hi> of Asclepius, which have
                    sometimes but erroneously been attributed to Apuleius. Other Hermetic writings
                    which have been preserved, and which have been for the most part collected by
                    Patricius in the <hi rend="italic">Nova de</hi><hi rend="italic">Universis
                    Philosophia</hi> (1593), are (in Greek) <hi rend="italic">'laτρομaθημaτικa
                    πρδς</hi> *Aμμωvα Αιγύπτιον, ∏εpι κaτaκλισεως <hi rend="italic">νοσονντων</hi> π
                    <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> εpιγvωστικa, Εκ <hi rend="italic">της μαθηματικής
                    επιστήμης προς</hi><hi rend="italic">*Aμμωva</hi> (in Latin) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aphorismi sive</hi><hi rend="italic">Centiloquium, Cyranides</hi>; (in Arabic,
                    but doubtless from a Greek original) an address to the human soul, which has
                    been translated by Fleischer <hi rend="italic">(An die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >menschliche Seele,</hi> 1870). The connexion of the name of Hermes with alchemy
                    will explain what is meant by hermetic sealing, and will account for the use of
                    the phrase “hermetic medicine” by Paracelsus, as also for the so-called
                    “hermetic freemasonry” of the Middle Ages.</p>
                <p>See Ursinus, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Zoroastre,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ηerrnete,</hi> &amp;c., Nuremberg, 1661; Lenglet Dufresnoy, <hi
                    rend="italic">L’Histoire de la Philosophie Hermétique,</hi> Paris, 1742;
                    Baumgarten-Cmsius, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">librorum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">hermeticorum</hi><hi rend="italic">origine atque</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">indole,</hi> Jena, 1827; Hilger, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Hermetis</hi><hi rend="italic">Trismegisti</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Poërnandro,</hi> 1855; Ménard, <hi rend="italic">Hermès Trismégiste: Traduction
                    complète, précédée d'une étude sur l’origine des livres hermétiques,</hi> 1866;
                    Pietschmann, <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Trismegistus,</hi><hi rend="italic">nach</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Aegyptischen,</hi><hi rend="italic">Griechischem, und Orientalischen
                    Ueberlieferungen,</hi> 1875.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
