<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0857-0820-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HILL TIPPERAH (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    820)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bg6t">Mussulmans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937529">Games</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837525">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837522">Brahman</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837534">Brahmans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n857/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HILL TIPPERAH</label>, a native state adjoining the British
                    district of Tipperah, Bengal, lying between 22° 59' and 24° 3Γ N. lat., and
                    between 91° 12' and 92° 24' E. long., with an area of about 3867 square miles,
                    and population (1878) 75,792. It is bounded on the N. by the Assam district of
                    Sylhet, on the W. by the Bengal districts of Tipperah and Noâkhâlt, on the S. by
                    Noâkhâli and Chittagong districts, and on the E. by the Lushâi country and the
                    Chittagong Hill Tracts. As its name implies the country is hilly. Five or six
                    ranges of hills run parallel from north to south, at an average distance of
                    about 12 miles from each other. The hills are covered for the most part with
                    bamboo jungle, while the low ground abounds with trees of various kinds,
                    canebrakes, and swamps. The principal ranges are, beginning from the east, the
                    Jâmpui, Sakkankhang, Langtarâi, and Athâramurâ. The chief rivers are the Gumti,
                    Hâorâ, Khozâi, Dulâi, Manu, and Pheni. During the heavy rains the people in the
                    plains use boats as almost the sole means of conveyance. The forests give
                    shelter to numbers of wild elephants and other large game. Small game of various
                    kinds are met with.</p>
                <p>The history of the state relates to two distinct periods—the traditional period
                    described in the <hi rend="italic">Rαjmαld,</hi> or “Chronicles of the Kings of
                    Tipperah," and the period since 1407 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> The <hi
                        rend="italic">Ràjmdlà</hi> is a history in Bengali verse, compiled by the
                    Brahmans of the court of Tripura. In the early history of the state, the râjâs
                    were in a state of chronic feud with all the neighbouring countries. The worship
                    of the All-destroyer was here, as elsewhere in India, associated with the
                    practice of human sacrifice, and in no part of India were more victims offered
                    up. It was not until thebeginning of the 17th century that the Mughals obtained
                    any footing in this country. By dint of constant invasions and continual
                    intrigues, the Mahometans gradually established themselves, and Tipperah soon
                    became a mere Mughal province under a Mussulman governor. The raja still
                    remained in possession of the hilly tracts, but subject to the nawâb of
                    Murshi&lt;labad. When the East India Company obtained the <hi rend="italic"
                        >diwdni</hi> of Bengal in 1765, so much of Tipperah as had been placed on
                    the rent-roll came under British rule. Since 1808, each successive ruler has
                    received investiture from the British Government, and has been required to pay
                    the usual <hi rend="italic">nαzαr</hi> or tribute on accession. The state has a
                    chronological era of its own, adopted by Râjâ Bir-râj, from whom the present
                    raja is 92d in descent. The year 1875 corresponded with 1285 of the Tipperah
                    era.</p>
                <p>Both as regards its constitution and its relations to the British Government, the
                    state of Hill Tipperah differs alike from the independent native states of India
                    and from those which are tributary and dependent. Besides being the ruler of
                    Hill Tipperah, the raja holds an estate in the British district of Tipperah,
                    called <hi rend="italic">chaklâ</hi> Roshnâbâd, which is by far the most
                    valuable of his possessions. The form of government is despotic and patriarchal.
                    The raja’s word is law, without appeal. In 1871 an English officer was appointed
                    as political agent to protect British interests and advise with the raja. The
                    most important hill tribe is that of the Tipperahs, who were estimated in
                    1874-75 to number 34,727. There are no towns in Hill Tipperah. Agartala, the
                    capital of the state and residence of the râjâ, is merely a moderate-sized
                    village situated on the north bank of the Haurâ.</p>
                <p>The principal crop and main food staple is rice. The other articles of produce
                    are cotton, chillies, and vegetables. The chief exports are cotton, timber, <hi
                        rend="italic">til,</hi> bamboo canes, thatching-grass, and firewood.
                    Occasionally small imports are required from the neighbouring districts. The
                    total revenue in 1874-75 was £18,693. Besides this, the râjâ’s estates in
                    Tipperah and Sylhet yield about £50,000 and £1400 respectively. His total annual
                    income, therefore, is about £70,000. The police force (1874-75) consisted of 102
                    men, and the râjâ maintains a force of 277 officers and men. The state has only
                    2 schools, and only 103 boys are being educated. The climate of Hill Tipperah is
                    generally pleasant; the annual rainfall is 60 inches. The chief endemic diseases
                    are bowel complaints, remittent and intermittent fevers, and rheumatism; the
                    principal epidemic is cholera.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
