<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0510-0479-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARIRI</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 479</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h9v">Pearls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1056116">Pearls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:895693">Divers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071040">Poor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n510/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARIRI</label>. Abu Mohammed al Kasim ibn 'Ali Ibn Mohammed
                    ibn Othman, surnamed <hi rend="smallcaps">el Hariri,</hi> was born at Bussorah
                    1054-55 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> and died in 1121 or 1123, being therefore
                    contemporary with the first crusade. His native city was renowned for its school
                    of grammar, a most important<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n511/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0511-0480"/> science amongst a people whose every rule of
                    religion and of life depended upon the accurate interpretation of some word or
                    passage of the Koran, or some saying of the prophet. The rival school of Kufa
                    was the only one that approached it in fame or glory, and in all the numerous
                    disputes that took place between the two academies Bussorah is generally allowed
                    to have had the advantage. His name Hariri signifies silk-merchant, and was
                    probably derived from his father’s occupation, as, in spite of the assertion of
                    his biographers to that effect, he appears not to have ever engaged in trade,
                    but to have devoted himself exclusively to literary pursuits. His great object
                    was to investigate the niceties of the Arabic language, and he composed several
                    treatises on the subject, amongst which the best known are <hi rend="italic"
                    >Molhat el 'Irab</hi> (Beauties of Desinential Syntax) and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Durrat el Ghaιvιvas</hi> (The Diver’s Pearl), in which he criticizes certain
                    common faults of language in vogue amongst the educated. Portions of both these
                    works have been published by De Sacy in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chrestomathie,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Durrat el Chaw wds</hi> has been
                    edited by H. Thorbecke (Leipsic, 1871). But his great work is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Hαkdmdt,</hi> or “Assemblies,” in which a series of anecdotes of a
                    very slight character in the career of an imaginary learned vagabond afford the
                    opportunity for the display of vast philological and literary learning. The plan
                    was not original, having been already invented and used by Badi' az Zamân el
                    Hamadâni, who died about 1008. The composition of Hariri’s own <hi rend="italic"
                    >Afakdmdt</hi> is attributed to the following circumstance. Being one day in the
                    mosque of the Beni Haram, in the quarter of Bussorah in which he resided, he
                    noticed an old man enter, shabby and worn with travel, who in answer to the
                    questions of the persons present gave his name as Abu Zeid, and said that he
                    came from Serùj, a city near Edessa, which had recently been devastated by the
                    crusaders. The old man related the incidents of the destruction of his native
                    city and his own domestic losses and exile in so eloquent a strain as to excite
                    general admiration and compassion. On reaching his home Hariri wrote out the
                    incident in the form of a makâmeh or assembly, in the style of El Hamadâni’s
                    work, and it now forms the 48th of his book. When subsequently elaborating the
                    idea he modelled the successive chapters on the same theme; a simple-minded Arab
                    gentleman, El Harith ibn el Hammâm, on his travels constantly meets with a
                    vagabond old improvisatore, Abu Zeid, who, under different characters and
                    disguises, always succeeds in eliciting the sympathy and alms of his audience
                    and the approbation of El Harith himself. Abu Zeid is always poor, ill-dressed,
                    and crafty, but eloquent in the extreme, and his fraudulently-obtained gains are
                    always spent in some forbidden enjoyment; yet there is ever a good side to his
                    character, and he is not without an exhibition of true feeling, especially when
                    he alludes to the circumstances of his expulsion from his home, and the loss of
                    his daughter, who nad been made captive by the marauding Franks. The improvised
                    speeches of Abu Zeid are masterpieces of Arabic learning, every sentence being
                    made to introduce some allusion to Arab history, poetry, or tradition, or the
                    discussion and elucidation of some difficult point of rhetoric or grammar. It is
                    this that gives the value to the book and makes it with its commentary a
                    complete encyclopaedia of classical Arabic literature and philology. It is
                    written in rhymed and rhythmical prose, such as is used in the Koran itself,
                    interspersed with verses of poetry of which the merit is more often in the
                    language than the thought.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Mαkcl'mAt</hi> have been edited by Silvestre de Sacy, with
                    a select Arabic commentary (Paris, 1822), and a new edition of this edition,
                    with numerous French notes, was issued by MM. Reinaud and Derenbourg (Paι∙is,
                    1853). An English translation of some select “Assemblies” was made by Theodore
                    Preston for the Oriental Translation Fund (London,1850), and an admirable
                    translation of the first twenty-six assemblies by T. Chenery (London, 1867),
                    containing an introduction and notes, and a resume of all the literature of the
                    subject. Of the numerous imitations of the <hi rend="italic">Makàrnât</hi> of
                    Hariri, the best known are the <hi rend="italic">Machbcrοth Ithiel,</hi> a
                    Hebrew work by Yehudah ben Shelomoh al Kharizi, edited by T. Chenery (London,
                    1872), and the <hi rend="italic">Majma</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">al Bahrain</hi>
                    (Confluence of the Two Seas), by Nasyf el Yaziji (Beyrout, 1853), an excellent
                    work in Arabic, displaying an immense acquaintance with the ancient literature
                    of the language. (E. H. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
