<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0051-0038-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LUCAS of Leyden (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    38)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j62t">Legends</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995592">Legends</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1201065">Publications</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1083449">Publicity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1072324">Portraits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n51/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LUCAS <hi rend="smallcaps">of Leyden</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(c.</hi> 1494-1533) was born at Leyden, where his father Hugh
                    Jacobsz gave him the first lessons in art. He then entered the painting-room of
                    Cornelis Engelbrechtszen of Leyden, and soon became known for his capacity in
                    making designs for glass, engraving copperplates, painting pictures, portraits,
                    and landscapes in oil and distemper. According to Van Mander he was born in
                    1494, and painted at the age of twelve a Legend of St Hubert, for which as many
                    florins were paid to him as he numbered years. He was only fourteen when he
                    finished a plate representing Mohammed taking the life of a friar, and at
                    fifteen he produced a series of nine plates for a Passion, a Temptation of St
                    Anthony, and a Conversion of St Paul. The list of his engravings in 1510, when,
                    according to Van Mander, he was only sixteen, includes a celebrated Ecce Homo,
                    Adam and Eve expelled from Paradise, a herdsman and a milkmaid with three cows,
                    and a little naked girl running away from a barking dog. It will be seen to what
                    a variety of tastes the youthful artist was asked to cater. Whatever may be
                    thought of the tradition embodied in Van Mander’s pages as to the true age of
                    Lucas of Leyden, there is no doubt that, as early as 1508, he was a master of
                    name as a copper-plate engraver, and had launched his boat in the current which
                    in those days led to wealth and to fame. The period of the great masters of
                    etching, which had not yet come for Holland, was being preceded by the period of
                    the great masters in the use of the graver. It was the time when art readily
                    found its patrons amongst the large public that could ill afford to buy
                    pictures, yet had enough interest in culture to wish to educate itself by means
                    of prints. Lucas of Leyden became the representative man for the great public of
                    Holland as Dürer became the representative man for the great public of Germany;
                    and.a rivalry grew up between the two engravers, which came to be so close that
                    on the neutral market of Italy the products of each were all but evenly quoted.
                    Vasari devoted almost equal attention to both, affirming indeed that Durer
                    surpassed Lucas as a designer, but that in the use of the graver they were both
                    unsurpassed, a sentence which has not been reversed by the criticism of our day.
                    But the rivalry of the two artists was friendly. About the time when Dürer
                    visited the Netherlands Lucas came to Antwerp, which then flourished greatly as
                    an international mart for productions of the pencil and the graver, and it is
                    thought, not without reason, that he was the master who took the freedom of the
                    Antwerp guild in 1521 under the name of Lucas the Hollander. In the diary which
                    Dürer faithfully kept during his travels in the Low Countries, we find that at
                    Antwerp he met Lucas, who asked him to dinner, and that Dürer accepted the
                    invitation, and was much surprised at the smallness of the Dutchman’s stature.
                    But he valued the art of Lucas at its true figure, and exchanged the Dutchman’s
                    prints for eight florins’ worth' of his own. In course of time Lucas rose to
                    more than a competence. In 1527 he made a tour of the Netherlands, giving
                    dinners to the painters of the guilds of Middleburg, Ghent, Malines, and
                    Antwerp. He was accompanied during the trip by Mabuse, whom he imitated in his
                    style as well as in his love of rich costume. But festive cheer and banquets
                    disagreed with Lucas. On his return home he fell sick and remained ailing till
                    his death in 1533, and when he died he did so with the firm belief that poison
                    had been administered to him by some envious comrade.</p>
                <p>As an engraver Lucas of Leyden deserves his reputation. He has not the genius,
                    nor had he the tact, of Durer; and he displays more cleverness of expression
                    than skill in distribution or refinement in details. But his power in handling
                    the graver is very great, and some of his portraits, especially his own, are
                    equal to anything that was done by the master of Nuremberg. Much that he
                    accomplished as a painter has been lost, because he worked a good deal upon
                    cloth in distemper. But some pictures have been preserved which fairly manifest
                    the influences under which he became productive. In 1522 he painted the Virgin
                    and Child with the Magdalen and a kneeling donor, now preserved in the gallery
                    of Munich. His manner was then very much akin to that of Mabuse. The Last
                    Judgment in the town-hall, now the town-gallery of Leyden, is composed on the
                    traditional lines of Cristus and Memling, furnished with monsters in the style
                    of Jerome Bosch, and figures in the stilted attitudes of the South German
                    school; the scale of colours in yellow, white, and grey is at once pale and
                    gaudy; the quaintest contrasts are produced by the juxtaposition of alabaster
                    flesh in females and bronzed skin in males, or black hair by the side of yellow,
                    or rose-coloured drapery set sharply against apple-green or black, yet some of
                    the heads are painted with great delicacy and modelled with exquisite feeling.
                    Dr Waagen gave a most favourable opinion of a triptych now at the Hermitage at
                    St Petersburg, executed, according to Van Mander, in 1531, representing the
                    blind man of Jericho healed by Jesus Christ in the presence of the apostles.
                    Here too the great German critic observed the union of faulty composition with
                    great finish and warm flesh-tints with a gaudy scale of harmonies. The same
                    defects and qualities will be found in such specimens of the master’s art as are
                    still preserved in public collections, amongst which may be mentioned the Card
                    Party at Wilton House, the Penitent St Jerome in the gallery of Berlin, and the
                    hermits Paul and Anthony in the Lichtenstein collection at Vienna.</p>
                <p>A few days before his death Lucas van Leyden was informed of the birth of a
                    grandson, firstborn of his only daughter Gretchen. Gretchen’s fourth son Jean de
                    Hoey followed the profession of his grandfather, and became well known at the
                    Parisian court as painter and chamberlain to the king of France, Henry IV.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
