<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0075-0062-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LUKE (9th edition, volume 15, page 62)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829879">Beginning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n75/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LUKE</label>, whose name is traditionally attached to the
                    Third Gospel, appears to have been one of the companions of Paul, being
                    mentioned as such in Col. iv. 14, Philem. 24, and 2 Tim. iv. 11; even if, as
                    some critics suppose, these epistles were not written by Paul himself, they are
                    at any rate likely to have preserved the local colouring. Assuming, as is
                    probable, that the same person is intended in all three passages, we gather (1)
                    that Luke was not a born Jew, since in Col. iv. 11, “those who are of the
                    circumcision” appear to be separated from those, among whom is Luke, who are
                    mentioned afterwards (but there is nothing to determine the question, which has
                    since been raised, whether he had been a Jewish proselyte or a Gentile), and (2)
                    that he was a physician. There was an early belief, first mentioned by Irenaeus,
                    that he is spoken of, though not mentioned by name, in 2 Cor. viii. 18, as “the
                    brother whose praise is in the gospel throughout all the churches ”; and the
                    subscription of that epistle in some MSS., and in the Peschito and other
                    versions, embodies this belief. Of his birth and country nothing is positively
                    known; but it is a possible inference from his name <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lucas,</hi> which is a contraction of <hi rend="italic">Lucanus</hi> (the full
                    form occurs in some early MSS. of the Itala), that he was of Italian (Lucanian)
                    descent.</p>
                <p>From the time of Irenaeus, whose testimony is soon followed by that of Clement of
                    Alexandria, Tertullian, and Origen, this companion of Paul has generally been
                    considered to be the author of the third canonical Gospel and of the Acts of the
                    Apostles; but no other facts are mentioned by early writers as to his personal
                    history, except such as may be gathered from the writings which are attributed
                    to him. Tertullian, for example, speaks of him as “non apostolus sed
                    apostolicus,” and as “posterioris· apostoli sectator”(,4cZw. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Marcion.,</hi> 4, 2); and the Muratorian fragment says that he had not seen the
                    Lord in the flesh. The most important of these biographical inferences are those
                    which were made by Eusebius, who, translating, or mistranslating,
                    ζταρ/κολου^κότι τrασι, in the preface to the Gospel, by “having accompanied
                    all,” z.e., the “eyewitnesses and ministers of the word,” infers that Luke was a
                    companion not of Paul only but also of the other apostles, and, probably
                    referring to Acts xiii. 1, says that he was “one of those from Antioch.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Some have thought that, like
                    the persons who are mentioned by Origen, <hi rend="italic">Comm, in Rom.,</hi>
                    chap. x. (vol. iv. p. 686, ed. De la Rue), Eusebius here confuses the two names
                    Lucas and Lucius.</p></note> These inferences of Eusebius are further elaborated
                    by Jerome, who adds, without quoting any authority, that he wrote the Gospel in
                    Achaia or Boeotia (many MSS. have Bithynia), and the Acts at Rome.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Viris</hi><hi rend="italic">lllustr.,</hi> chap. vii.; <hi
                    rend="italic">Comm, in</hi><hi rend="italic">Matth.</hi>, pref., vol. vii.
                    p.?</p></note></p>
                <p>Those who accept this tradition of his having been the author of the Acts of the
                    Apostles usually infer from the sections of that work in which the pronoun “we”
                    is employed that he accompanied Paul on part of his second and third missionary
                    journeys, and also on his voyage to Rome. The first of these sections begins
                    with the apostle’s determination to go into Macedonia, and ends when he has left
                    Philippi (Acts xvi. 10-40); the second begins when the apostle returns to
                    Philippi, and ends with his arrival at Jerusalem (Acts xx. 6-xxi. 18); the third
                    begins with his sailing from Caesarea, and ends with his arrival at Rome (Acts
                    xxvii. 1-xxviii. 16). Even some of those who assign the greater part of the book
                    to a much later date think that these sections may be extracts from an original
                    diary of a companion of Paul, and that this companion may have been Luke.
                    Others, however, think it improbable that Luke, without being specially
                    mentioned either in them or elsewhere, should have accompanied Paul on his
                    voyage to Rome, and assign these sections to Timothy, or Titus, or Silas (some
                    have added the very improbable conjecture that Luke and Silas are the same
                    person).</p>
                <p>The other biographical details which are found in patristic literature, and which
                    are not inferences from the New Testament, rest upon no certain evidence, and
                    are frequently at variance not only with one another but also with earlier
                    documents. It is sometimes stated that he was one of the seventy disciples; this
                    statement is found in Epiphanias <hi rend="italic">(Haeres.,</hi> Ii. 11), in
                    pseudo-Origen <hi rend="italic">(De recta in Deum fide,</hi> ed. De la Rue, vol.
                    i. p. 806), in Gregory the Great <hi rend="italic">(Moral.</hi> i. 1), and
                    elsewhere; but it is inconsistent, not only with Tertullian and the Muratorian
                    fragment, but also with the clear inference from the preface to the Gospel that
                    its author was not himself an eyewitness of what he narrates. It is also stated
                    that he was one of the two disciples who went to Emmaus (S. Greg. Magn., <hi
                    rend="italic">Moral,</hi> i. 1; Paul. Diacon., <hi rend="italic">Homil.</hi> 59
                    <hi rend="italic">in Natali</hi><hi rend="italic">S. Lucae</hi>; and others);
                    but this statement is discredited by the same facts as the preceding. Like all
                    the other disciples whose names are mentioned in the New Testament, he is said
                    to have gone forth as a preacher of the gospel; but statements vary widely as to
                    the place in which he preached: Gregory of Nazianzus says Achaia; Epiphanias
                    says Dalmatia, Gaul, Italy, and Macedonia; Oecumenius says Africa; later legends
                    mention his having been at Enns in Austria (Hansiz, <hi rend="italic">Germ.
                    Sacra,</hi> vol. i. p. 15). And also, like most of the other early disciples, he
                    is said not only to have preached the gospel but also to have suffered death for
                    its sake. Gaudentius of Brescia says that this occurred at Patra in Achaia, and
                    Nicephoros specifies as the manner of his martyrdom that he was hung on an olive
                    tree. But elsewhere it is stated or implied that he died an ordinary death,
                    either at Thebes in Boeotia <hi rend="italic">(Martyrol. Basil.),</hi> or in
                    Bithynia (Paulus Diaconus, Isidore of Seville, and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Martyrologies</hi> of Ado and Usuardi). Most traditions agree in stating that
                    his body was transferred by Constantins to Constantinople (“Chrom Hierom,” ap.
                    Mai, <hi rend="italic">Nov. Script. Coll</hi>; Prosper Aquitanus, Paulus
                    Diaconus, Nicephonιs, and others), but its place of burial seems to have been
                    forgotten, and Procopius <hi rend="italic">(De aedif.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Justin.,</hi> i. 4) mentions that it was discovered in Justinian’s time in
                    digging the foundations of a new <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n76/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0076-0063"/> church; a subsequent tradition stated that it was
                    afterwards removed to Italy, and in the 15th century Pius II. commissioned
                    Cardinal Bessarion to decide upon a violent controversy between the Minorite
                    monastery of S. Job at Venice and the Benedictine monastery of S. Giustina at
                    Padua, each of which claimed to possess the perfect relics of the
                    evangelist.</p>
                <p>A late tradition represents Luke to have been a painter as well as a physician;
                    the.tradition first appears in a doubtful fragment of an author of doubtful
                    date, Theodorus Lector (printed in H. Valois’s edition of Theodoret, p. 618),
                    who mentions that the empress Eudocia sent to Pulcheria, from Jerusalem to
                    Constantinople, a picture of the Virgin painted by Luke. The same story is
                    mentioned in an almost certainly spurious oration of John of Damascus <hi
                    rend="italic">{Orat. in Constant. Coprom,</hi> c. 6., vol. i. p. 618, ed. Le
                    Quien); and the first certain authorities for the tradition are Symeon
                    Metaphrastes and the <hi rend="italic">Menologiïim</hi> of Basil the younger,
                    both of which belong to the 10th century. That the tradition is not of much
                    earlier growth is proved by the fact that, if it had existed, it could not fail
                    to have been largely used in the iconoclastic controversy.</p>
                <p>The martyrologies and calendars for the most part agree in fixing Luke’s festival
                    on October 18; but a doubt is expressed whether that day should be regarded as
                    the anniversary of his birth or of the translation of his remains to
                    Constantinople.</p>
                <p>In Christian art he is usually symbolized by an ox (with reference to Ezekiel i.
                    10, Revelation iv. 7), on the significance of which symbol various statements
                    were made by both Eastern and Western writers (some of them will be found quoted
                    by Ciampini, <hi rend="italic">Vet. Monum.,</hi> vol. i. 192). (E. HA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
