<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0121-0106-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LYNDSAY, Sir David (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    106)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n121/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LYNDSAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir David</hi></label> (c.
                    1490-1555), for about two centuries and a half perhaps the most popular poet of
                    Scotland, was born about 1490, probably either at the family estate of The
                    Mount, in the parish of Monimail, near Cupar in Fife, or at Garleton near
                    Haddington in East Lothian, where the ruins of an old mansion house of the
                    Lyndsays still remain. Little is known of his boyhood, but he is understood to
                    have entered the university of St Andrews about 1505, and he became one of the
                    <hi rend="italic">incorporati</hi> of St Salvator’s College in 1508 or 1509.
                    After leaving college there is reason to think that he went abroad fora year or
                    two, visiting, it is supposed, both France and Italy; but of this there is no
                    certain information. In 1511 he must have been attached in some way to the court
                    of James IV., as in the October of that year an entry appears in the royal
                    treasurer’s accounts for the sum of <hi rend="italic">£3,</hi> 4s. for “blue and
                    yellow taffities to be a play coat to David Lyudsay for the play playit in the
                    king and queen’s presence in the Abbey of Holyrood,”—so that even at that early
                    period Lyndsay would seem to have developed his taste for masques and mummeries,
                    play-acting and tale-telling. After this his name occurs in the treasurer’s
                    accounts for a regular salary of £40 a year; and on the birth of James V. in
                    1512 he was appointed to be the personal attendant of the young prince, in which
                    situation he remained till James had attained his twelfth year in 1524—sometimes
                    under the title of “keeper of the kingis grace,” sometimes as the “kingis
                    maister usher,” and sometimes as “the kingis maister of houshald,” but
                    throughout with the yearly salary of £40. Lyndsay’s close connexion with the
                    court led to his being present at the remarkable scene just before Flodden, in
                    the church of Linlithgow, when the so-called apparition came in “calling loudly
                    for the king,” and, after warning him against proceeding on his ill-judged
                    expedition against England, vanishing away “as it had been a blink of the sun or
                    ane whiss of the whirlwind.” The incident is related both by Pitscottie and by
                    Buchanan, expressly on the authority of Sir David; and Tytler shrewdly remarks
                    that possibly Lyndsay knew more of the affair than he cared to confess, a
                    conjecture which both Lyndsay’s well-known prudence and sagacity in political
                    affairs and his skill in arranging masques and stage plays renders exceedingly
                    probable. In 1522 Sir David married Janet Douglas, of whom we know nothing
                    except that she also was attached to the king’s court, and was employed as
                    sempstress to “his grace,”—various payments to her being entered in the accounts
                    for her diligence in the humble office of “sewing the kingis sarkis.” It is
                    evident from many passages in Lyndsay’s poems that his good sense and sweet
                    temper, his varied accomplishments, and his skill in mingling amusement with
                    instruction had greatly endeared him to the young king, and it would have been
                    well for James if he had never listened to other and worse counsels than those
                    of his wise and affectionate “maister usher.” <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n122/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0122-0107"/> It is to the credit of the king, however, and
                    characteristic of the generous disposition of the earlier Stuarts, that he never
                    forgot or forsook the friend of his infant and boyish years. For when he fell
                    under the power of the Douglases in 1524, and when Lyndsay had to take his
                    dismissal from court, James took care that his salary should continue to be paid
                    him; and no sooner did he escape from their domination than Lyndsay was at once
                    recalled, and the appointment of lyon-king conferred upon him. This was in 1529,
                    and it is a remarkable proof of the reputation which Lyndsay had by this time
                    acquired for prudence and sterling practical ability that he was at various
                    times sent abroad in connexion with embassies from Scotland. In 1531 he went to
                    the Netherlands to renew the commercial treaty with that country. On this
                    occasion the embassy had a personal interview with the emperor Charles V., and
                    the mission was perfectly successful. A few years afterwards (in 1536) he formed
                    one of the envoys sent to France to conclude a treaty of marriage between the
                    Scottish king and Marie de Bourbon, daughter of the Duc de Vendôme. It is
                    evident therefore that Lyndsay’s position and employments must have enabled him
                    to gather much experience of life, and to obtain a somewhat varied knowledge
                    both of men and things. His last sad office to his beloved sovereign -was to
                    attend at his bedside when the poor king was dying of a broken heart at
                    Falkland, in December 1542. Lyndsay survived the king about thirteen years. At
                    the time of Cardinal Beaton’s assassination he held a seat in parliament as
                    commissioner for the burgh of Cupar. In 1548 he was despatched to Denmark to
                    negotiate a free trade, particularly in grain, for the Scottish merchants, which
                    -was readily granted. Mr Laing, on the authority of an entry in the Privy Seal
                    Register, states that his death must have taken place early in 1555.</p>
                <p>When Lyndsay was driven from the court by the advent of the Douglases to power,
                    he no doubt felt it as a bitter misfortune and a disappointment of all his
                    highest hopes. But we are greatly mistaken if he did not ere long come to regard
                    it in a very different light. Like most men of genius, he had evidently two
                    sides to his character. On the one side he had a taste for pleasure, sociality,
                    pageantry, and frivolous amusements; and a few years more of these might have
                    deadened his nature to everything else, and converted him into a mere dangler
                    after royalty. But he had also elements of a better kind. He was well educated
                    and accomplished; he had read somewdιat extensively, and was master of most of
                    the knowledge to be had in books at that time. He had seen not a little of the
                    world, both in Scotland and in foreign countries; he was an acute discerner of
                    character, and had both knowledge of and skill in affairs. Now then was just the
                    time for a man like him, arrived at the full maturity of his intellect, to turn
                    all these varied acquisitions to account. Lyndsay therefore, we may infer,
                    retired to his country seat, either at The Mount, or as we fancy more likely to
                    Garleton (that he might be more within call should a change take place in the
                    political situation at Edinburgh), and there, after the first dull pang of
                    disappointment was over, he doubtless found that there was no lack of subjects
                    to engage his best thoughts. One of the great crises in the history of Europe
                    and in the progress of human thought had just arisen. The trumpet of the
                    Reformation had been sounded in Germany, and its reverberation had already been
                    heard in Scotland, where both political and ecclesiastical disorder had nearly
                    reached their worst, and were becoming the source of deep anxiety and desire for
                    redress to all good men. For Lyndsay, therefore, there was something else to do
                    than to brood moodily over his own private griefs. He had to make up his mind on
                    a variety of great public questions, as well perhaps as to settle the great
                    personal question of his own religious faith; and in his earliest work, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Dreme,</hi> which seems to have been composed at this time, we
                    have a somewhat vivid picture of the turn his thoughts took.</p>
                <p>He represents himself as having spent the long winter night without sleep,
                    “through heavy thought, remembering of divers thingis gone.” On getting up and
                    walking out, he finds the dull winter season, with its bitter blasts and sharp
                    sleety showers, but ill-fitted to console him, and only too much in harmony with
                    his own melancholy. He goes down to the sea-shore, but things are no better
                    there; for the “weltering of the waves” at once associates itself in his mind
                    with “this false warld’s instability.” Thus far, then, his meditations seem to
                    have had a merely personal reference. But by and by, on retiring into a cave
                    near the shore, he falls into a trance, in which his thoughts take a wider
                    range. The miserable state of his country, from misgovernment on the part of its
                    rulers and the vices of both clergy and laity, fills his mind, and, reflecting
                    on the ultimate fate of such men, he finds himself in the twinkling of an eye in
                    hell, where he sees wicked popes, kings, conquerors, princes, and lords
                    temporal, with no end of churchmen, “mansworn merchants,” “unleil laboraris,”
                    craftsmen “out of number,” “hurdaris of gold and common occararis,” all
                    “tormentit with pains intolerable.” Then, leaving this “dolorous dongeon,” he
                    has a passing sight of purgatory, though apparently with some misgiving as to
                    its reality, his significant remark being—</p>
                <p>“Sic things to be great clerkis does conclude, Howbeit my hope stands most in
                    Christis Mood."</p>
                <p>Proceeding then to the realms of bliss, he sees something of the rewards of good
                    and just rulers and righteous men; and by arid by returning to the earth, and at
                    length looking down upon Scotland, he sees a region both good and fair, its seas
                    abounding in fish, its mountains covered with pasture, the valleys fit for corn,
                    the forests full of game, mines with gold and silver, the people fair,
                    intelligent, strong, and noble-minded,—and yet with all this, the country poor
                    and the inhabitants miserable. What could be the cause? and the answer given is
                    that the realm wants good government, impartial administration of justice, and
                    freedom from war and discord. Viewing the country all over—on the borders</p>
                <p>“Betwixt the Merse and Lochmaben, He could not knaw a leil man from a thief.</p>
                <p>To show their reif, theft, murther and mischief, And vicious works, it would
                    infest the air.”</p>
                <p>In the Highlands it was no better :—</p>
                <p>“Unthrift, sweirness, falset, poverty, and strife Put policy in danger of her
                    life.”</p>
                <p>And even in the Lowlands, where better things might be expected, it was
                    impossible for a poor man to live by his industry. If he settledin the towns,
                    “singular profet” (by which we understand him to mean the system of monopolies
                    and of close trade corporations, which everywhere prevailed) “gart him soon
                    dislodge.” And if he attempted to get redress to his wrongs there was no help
                    for him anywhere. The spiritual state, plunged in simony, covetousness, pride,
                    ambition, sensuality, and the love of pomp and pleasure, “held him at disdain”;
                    and among the nobility and gentry “liberality and lawté both are lost,” knightly
                    courage is “turnit in brag and boast,” and disorder and civil war have produced
                    a state of things in which “there is nocht else hot ilk man for himself.” The
                    moral of the whole is—“Woe to the land that has ouer young ane king!”—“theresail
                    na Scot have comforting till that I seethe country guided by wisdom of ane gude
                    auld prudent king.” The poet is then awakened by the sound of cannon from a ship
                    of war approaching the coast,—the suggestion, as we imagine, being that the
                    existing state of things can only end in violence and uproar, in tumult and
                    rebellion, most probably in foreign invasion and revolution.</p>
                <p>On the whole <hi rend="italic">The Dreme</hi> appears the most finished and
                    artistic of Lyndsay’s works. It has a tone of greater seriousness, bears the
                    marks of more care and elaboration in the composition; and, though it has a good
                    deal of the crudeness of a first attempt, we think we can discover an effort at
                    least at a finer proportion and harmony of parts than in any of his subsequent
                    poems. In its subjectmatter it strikes the keynote of almost all that he
                    afterwards wrote. The evils, the wrongs, the misgovernment of his country
                    evidently filled his whole soul with grief, indignation, and the desire for
                    reform; and we almost doubt if there is to be found anywhere except in the old
                    Hebrew prophets a purer or more earnest breathing of the patriotic spirit.
                    Indeed if we may judge from the mottσ prefixed to his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dreme</hi> we should almost fancy that he had made them his model :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Prophetias nolite spernere.</hi><hi rend="italic">Omnia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">autem</hi><hi rend="italic">probate: &lt;puod</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">bonum</hi><hi rend="italic">est</hi><hi rend="italic">tvnete.</hi>
                    Lyndsay accordingly is to be judged of less as a poet than as a great political
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n123/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0123-0108"/> and ecclesiastical reformer. That his works are
                    written in verse is merely incidental. Though not destitute of poetical genius,
                    this was scarcely the special characteristic of his mind. His greatest work, and
                    the only one to which it is necessary here to make further allusion, was his <hi
                    rend="italic">Satire of the Three Estates.</hi> It is a drama, and may be said
                    to be in some respects one of the most remarkable that ever was written. The <hi
                    rend="italic">dramatis personae</hi> are chiefly allegorical, and under the
                    names of Rex Humanitas, Wantonness, the Vices (Flattery, Falset, and Deceit) in
                    the habit of friars, King Correction, Good Counsel, Temporality, Sensuality,
                    Chastity, Verity, John the Commonweal, &lt;fcc., the most bitter and unsparing
                    exposure is made of the wickedness and corruption of all classes of the
                    community. King, clergy, lords, merchants, craftsmen —no one escapes the
                    severest censure and the most unmitigated ridicule. And yet this extraordinary
                    production was acted on the borough muir of Edinburgh before the king himself,
                    many of the highest nobility and clergy, and an immense crowd of all classes of
                    the people. How the author escaped being torn in pieces by the mob or burnt at
                    the stake by the ruling powers it is difficult to understand. Perhaps the
                    explanation is that each class saw every other brought under the lash equally
                    with itself, and felt consoled for its own shame by enjoying the infliction
                    visited on its neighbours. Very likely too the grotesque wit and the fun with
                    which the serious matter of the play was so largely spiced charmed the audience
                    into good humour, and left them unable to think of vengeance. It may be somewhat
                    confidently inferred too that the dramatist so exactly expressed the public
                    feeling of the time as to the evils and corruption under which the state was
                    rapidly going to destruction that, even when his stinging reproaches most nearly
                    touched themselves, their consciences were smitten and they were compelled to
                    assent to the perfect truth and justness of his rebukes. But be this as it may,
                    there can hardly be a doubt that this most singular drama formed one of the
                    chief means by which the way was paved for the Reformation afterwards carried
                    out by Knox and his coadjutors.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Ellis, <hi rend="italic">Original Letters,</hi> 3d
                    series, vol. iii. p. 280; and Row, <hi rend="italic">History of the Kirk of
                    Scotland,</hi> p. 7.</p></note> One thing is especially remarkable in Lyudsay’s
                    politics both civil and ecclesiastical, that, hopeless and depressing as the
                    condition of the country must have been to a man like him, his opinions never
                    end in mere negations, but are throughout constructive in their character. And
                    yet more thoroughgoing radicalism it would be difficult elsewhere to find. He
                    does not for example scruple to declare that kings who govern ill should be
                    deposed. This, however, was merely a speculative opinion, and it is of more
                    interest to ascertain what his practical suggestions were. Among them we find
                    the following :—that the king should on no account attempt to do anything
                    without the advice of his council and parliament; that John the Commonweal
                    should have a greater voice in parliament, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> in our
                    modern phrase, that there should be a considerable extension of the franchise;
                    that (as already mentioned) all close corporatiohs and monopolies should be
                    abolished; that temporal lands should be set in feu to the tenants on condition
                    of their duly rendering the prescribed services to the state, a measure not very
                    dissimilar in principle (if we understand it aright) to that lately introduced
                    into Ireland; that lords should be responsible for thieves who find refuge on
                    their lands, and make restitution to the poor who have been plundered by them;
                    that courts of justice should be established in the remoter parts of the
                    country, such as Elgin and Inverness, in order to avoid the expense attendant on
                    the transference of pleas to the metropolis, and, to provide for their
                    maintenance, the nunneries in that αuarter to be abolished and their revenues
                    sequestrated, the reason given being—</p>
                <p>“Thir wanton nuns are na way necessair Till common·weill, nor yet to the glorie
                    Of Christis kirk, thocht they be fat and fair, And als that fragile order
                    feminine Will nocht be missit in Christ’s religion.”</p>
                <p>No less stringent and sweeping are his proposals for the reform of the church.
                    The religion of Christ must be purged of all deceit and hypocrisy. The
                    consistorial courts are to have no jurisdiction in matters temporal. No
                    clergyman is to be admitted to office unless duly qualified in learning and
                    piety. Celibacy is to be abolished. Bishops and priests must be compelled to
                    preach regularly and “take better tent to souls under their dominion.” Benefices
                    are not to be purchased either from prince or pope, nor is money to be permitted
                    to go to Rome for bulls and pleas. Pluralities and patronage are to be
                    abolished, residence is to be enforced, and the people are to have a voice in
                    the choice of their spiritual guides. In fact many of Lyndsay’s proposals of
                    reform have quite a modern look, and this perhaps explains in some degree the
                    long-continued popularity of his works among his countrymen, which otherwise it
                    is rather difficult to account for. They have none of the chivalric
                    spirit-stirring power of many of our ancient songs and ballads, none of the
                    tender love and melancholy which form the charm of Burns’s lyrics, none of the
                    joyous abandon of convivial or amorous ditties, and none of the fascination
                    which springs from well-constructed tales or narrative poems, like those of
                    Chaucer or Scott. It is difficult to suppose that even the humour which pervades
                    them, seldom of the most refined kind and often very much the reverse, can have
                    been in any great degree pleasing to readers of a later age than the author’s
                    own. The only explanation, we suspect, is that Lyndsay’s intense and
                    uncompromising love of liberty, his strong sympathy with the poor, his love of
                    justice, his keen hatred of tyranny, wrong, and oppression, and his shrewd
                    common sense easily found a responsive chord in Scottish bosoms. Nor was the
                    interest which his works so long retained among the Scottish peasantry merely of
                    a sentimental kind. For many of the evils against which he directed his severest
                    invectives continued long afterwards to afflict his country, and even when
                    somewhat changed in their aspect still reappeared in analogous forms or
                    character. Prelatic usurpation and cruelty were as rife as ever in the century
                    which succeeded that in which Lyndsay wrote; aristocratic venality and
                    heartlessness have perhaps even yet hardly ceased out of the land; church
                    patronage, always hateful to religious-minded Scotsmen, was hardly abolished
                    before it was reimposed. And then such incidents as the massacre of Glencoe, the
                    union with England, a measure intensely disliked by the great mass of the
                    Scottish people, the infamous treatment of the Darien colonization scheme, the
                    barbarities which followed the two Jacobite rebellions, the deprivation up to
                    1832 of any true parliamentary representation, and the continuance of close
                    municipal and trade corporations, all tended to keep up a bitter sense of wrong
                    to which Lyndsay’s satires gave point and expression.</p>
                <p>The best accessible editions of Lyndsay’s works are those of George Chalmers, in
                    3 vols., London, 1806, and of David Laing, also in 3 vols., Edinburgh, 1879.
                    These, with the Early English Text Society’s edition, leave little to be desired
                    for the establishment of a correct text, and for purely antiquarian
                    illustration. In Warton’s <hi rend="italic">History of English Poetry,</hi> and
                    in Irving’s <hi rend="italic">History of Scottish Poetry,</hi> good critical
                    estimates will be found of Lyndsay’s place as a poet. It is possible, however,
                    that something yet remains to be done in order to determine his exact position
                    as a great political and religious reformer, and to illustrate the effect which
                    his works have had in directing popular feeling and opinion in Scotland. (J. T.
                    BR.) <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n124/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0124-0109"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
