<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-9199-0008-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GROTTO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 8</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p851">Grottoes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sn8w">Pool</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sn3j">Pools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb15">Cams</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:958715">Holes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:845034">Cams</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100272">Roofing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100315">Roofs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193639199" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GROTTO</label> ^ or <hi rend="smallcaps">Grotta,</hi> a large
                    deep cavern or den in a mountain or rock. The word is Italian, <hi rend="italic"
                    >grotto,</hi> formed, according to Menage, from the Latin <hi rend="italic"
                    >crypta.</hi> Ducange observes, that <hi rend="italic">grotta</hi> was used in
                    the same sense in the corrupt Latin. The ancient anchorites retired into dens
                    and grottoes, to apply themselves the more attentively to meditation.</p>
                <p>Amongst the natural caverns or grottoes of England, Okey-hole, Elden-hole,
                    Peak’s-hole, and Pool’s-hole, are famous.</p>
                <p>The entrance to Okey-hole, on the south side of the Mendip Hills, is in the fall
                    of those hills, is beset all round with rocks, and has near it a precipitous
                    descent of near twelve fathoms deep, at the bottom of which there continually
                    issues from the rocks a considerable current of water. The naked rocks above the
                    entrance show themselves about thirty fathoms high, and the whole ascent of the
                    hill above is about a mile, and very steep. On entering this vault, you proceed
                    at first upon a level, but advancing farther, the way becomes rocky and uneven,
                    sometimes ascending and sometimes descending. The roof of this cavern, in the
                    highest parts, is about eight fathoms from the ground, but in many places it is
                    so low that a man must stoop to get along. The breadth is not less various than
                    the height, for in some places it is five or six fathoms wide, and in others not
                    more than one or two. It extends in length about two hundred yards. People talk
                    much of certain stones in it, resembling men and women, and other things; but
                    there is little that is curious in these, which are only shapeless lumps of
                    common spar. At the farthest part of the cavern there is a good stream of water,
                    large enough to drive a mill, which passes all along one side, and at length
                    glides down about six or eight fathoms amongst the rocks, and then pressing
                    through their clefts, discharges itself into the valley. The river within the
                    cavern is well stored with eels, and has in it some trouts; which can scarcely
                    have come from without, as there is a considerable fall near the entrance. In
                    dry summers, a great number of frogs are seen all along this cavern, even to the
                    farthest part of it; and on the roof of it, at certain places, hang vast numbers
                    of bats. The cattle that feed in the pastures through which this river runs have
                    been known to die suddenly sometimes after a flood; which is probably owing to
                    the waters having been impregnated, either naturally or accidentally, with lead
                    ore.</p>
                <p>Elden-hole is a huge profound perpendicular chasm, three miles from Buxton, and
                    ranked amongst the natural wonders of the Peak. Its depth is unknown. Cotton
                    tells us he sounded 884 yards, yet the plummet still drew. But he might easily
                    be deceived, unless his plummet was very heavy; for the weight of a rope of that
                    length might render the landing of the plummet scarcely perceptible.</p>
                <p>Peak’s-hole and Pool’s-hole are two very remarkable horizontal caverns under
                    mountains; the one situated near Castleton, and the other close by Buxton. They
                    seem to have owed their origin to the springs which flow through them; for when
                    the water had forced its way through the horizontal fissures of the strata, and
                    had carried the loose earth away with it, the loose stones would of course fall
                    down; but where the strata had few or no fissures, they remained entire, and
                    thus formed those very irregular arches, which are now so much admired for their
                    grotesque appearance. The water which passes through Pool’s-hole is impregnated
                    with particles of limestone, and has incrusted the whole cavern in such a manner
                    that it appears as one solid rock.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Grotto</hi><hi rend="italic">del Cam,</hi> a little
                    cavern near Pozzuoli, four leagues from Naples, the air of which is of a
                    mephitical or noxious quality; whence it is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >l&gt;occa</hi><hi rend="italic">venenosa,</hi> the poisonous mouth.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Grotto</hi><hi rend="italic">del Serpi,</hi> is a
                    subterranean cavern near the village of Sassa, eight miles from the city of
                    Braccano in Italy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Milky</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Grotto,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Crypta Lactea,</hi> a mile distant from the ancient village of
                    Bethlehem, is said to have been thus denominated on occasion of the blessed
                    Virgin letting fall some drops of milk whilst suckling Jesus in this grotto; and
                    hence it has been commonly supposed that the earth of this cavern has the virtue
                    of restoring milk to women who have grown dry, and even of curing fevers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Grotto</hi> is also used to signify a little artificial
                    edifice made in a garden, in imitation of a natural grotto. The exterior of
                    these grottoes is usually adorned with rustic architecture, and the interior
                    with shell-work, fossils, and the like, finished likewise with jets d’eau or
                    fountains.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
