<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9550-0035-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">GUN-MAKING</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 35</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="11" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098971">Robins</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1130432">Sports</term><term n="34" ref="fasttopic:827746">Barrels</term><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:925697">Fires</term><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:925173">Fire</term><term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1074177">Powders</term><term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1130905">Spring</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="34" ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b72x">Barrels</term><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term><term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b45717w2f">Proof</term><term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4222rd9g">Robin</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn54">Sports</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193639550" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">GUN-MAKING</label>.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Of</hi> the word gun there is no satisfactory etymology.
                    Some have derived it from the French word <hi rend="italic">man gon</hi>
                    (omitting the first syllable), which was the name of a warlike instrument used
                    before the invention of the gun now employed; and the use would seem to justify
                    the derivation, for it was employed in discharging arrows and other missiles,
                    before the invention of gunpowder. Others derive it from <hi rend="italic">gyn,</hi> an engine employed for similar purposes. Selden says, “the word gun
                    was in use in England for an engine to cast a thing from a man, long before
                    there was any gunpowder found out.” The instrument called a gun, used for war or
                    sport, has, in the progress of time, and the changes it has undergone, received
                    various names. We find it called harquebuss, haque-but or hag-but, hand-gun,
                    matchlock, musket, firelock, carabine, fowling-piece, besides several other
                    denominations.</p><p>Fire-arms, under one or other of the above-mentioned names, were introduced into
                    this country about the year 1471; and we find them used at the different sieges
                    which were carried on in Europe about the year 1521. In the time of Henry VIII.,
                    and his successor Elizabeth, the size and shape of fire-arms were regulated by
                    act of parliament. With respect to the mode of firing the guns then in use, this
                    was done either with a match, or by means of a lock which revolved upon a wheel;
                    in the one case, the priming was fired by means of a burning match, and in the
                    other, by means of sparks generated by the revolution of a notched wheel of
                    steel, placed right above the pan containing the priming. Specimens of these
                    guns are to be seen in the cabinets of the curious, or in the national armories.
                    The firing of guns by means of flints is comparatively a modern invention. The
                    balls at first were not, as in modern times, made up along with the powder, but
                    were carried in a separate purse or bag, and the powder by itself in a horn or
                    flask. To ensure certainty of firing, a finer kind of powder was used for
                    priming than for the ordinary charge of the gun, and this priming-powder was
                    carried by itself in what was called a touch-box. Most of the guns, when first
                    used as warlike instruments, were so heavy that they could not be held out and
                    fired from the shoulder, as in modern times. The soldier, therefore, was
                    provided with a rest, which he stuck into the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193639563" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9563-0036"/>ground, and
                    upon which he laid his gun, and took a deliberate and steady aim. The rests were
                    shod with iron, to preserve them from decay, and that they might the more easily
                    penetrate the ground; and were of different lengths, according to the height of
                    the man using them. The addition of the bayonet to the gun was not made earlier
                    than 1671, being first used by the French about that time. It derives its name
                    of bayonet from Bayonne, a town in the south of France, where that instrument
                    was first made. Few practical arts have made more rapid advancement than that of
                    gun-making. The competition amongst the gun-makers has been very great, and they
                    have arrived at a degree of perfection which it is almost impossible to surpass.
                    Almost every great town in England, Scotland, and Ireland, as well as on the
                    Continent, has large establishments for carrying on this beautiful and ingenious
                    branch of manufacture. Judging of the perfection of the art by the expense of
                    the article, we would think that gun-making had reached the very acme of
                    perfection. It was no uncommon thing to pay fifty, sixty, seventy, or eighty
                    guineas for the best London-made gun. The Continent has even gone before us in
                    this respect. When Napoleon was in the plenitude of his grandeur, he established
                    a gun manufactory at Versailles; and we are informed that pistols were there
                    made at ten thousand livres, L.400 sterling, each, and guns at fifty thousand
                    livres, L.2000 sterling. Of these, the first consul often made presents to
                    foreign princes or general officers. The Marquis of Rockingham presented Colonel
                    Thornton with a fowling-piece which cost L.400; and Messrs Robert and John
                    Wheeler, gun-makers, Birmingham, presented George IV. with a gun of the most
                    exquisite workmanship, which cost 300 guineas.</p><p>i The principal part of a gun, whether we consider the safety or the execution,
                    is the barrel. Spain long maintained its superiority over the other nations of
                    Europe for gun barrels. This arose from the supposed excellence of the iron made
                    use of in that country in the manufacture of gun barrels, which were almost
                    exclusively forged from the old shoes of the horses and mules, and stub nails
                    gathered from the highways of that country. Not satisfied with the superior
                    toughness which the old shoes and stubs thus acquired, the Spanish gun-makers,
                    it is said, often reduced, by laborious plyings on the anvil, a mass of iron
                    weighing from forty to fifty pounds, to the weight of an ordinary fowling-piece.
                    From the great excellence of these barrels, many of them were counterfeited by
                    artists of other countries, and the public, thus deceived by fictitious names,
                    were charged exorbitant prices. Some of these Spanish barrels used to sell at
                    very high prices, bringing from L.40 to L.50 each. Even the modern barrels made
                    at Madrid are still much esteemed, and bring high prices. Making every allowance
                    for the prejudice in favour of distant times and places, there can be little
                    doubt of the excellence of the Spanish barrels, when got from the first makers,
                    and bearing the highest price. But however excellent the Spanish barrels may
                    have been, and still are, it is perhaps not too much to say, that they are now
                    rivalled by those of British manufacture. The best British barrels, like the
                    Spanish, are made of iron that has been much worn, and thus toughened by the
                    loss of its fiery particles. Old horse stub nails constitute the best iron for
                    the formation of gun barrels; and accordingly there are people who collect the
                    stubs, and even gather them from the highways, and sell them at a high price to
                    the barrel forgers. Hardly any thing can be imagined better than our best
                    stub-nail twisted barrel.</p><p>Next in excellence to the stub-nail twisted barrel, is the Damascus barrel. It is
                    called Damascus from its resemblance to the beautiful arms made of Damascus
                    steel, and to be met with in Syria, Persia, Hindustan, and other countries of
                    the East. The Damascus barrels, when of the first quality, finished with care,
                    and browned in the best manner, are the most beautiful of all barrels; but
                    although more beautiful, they are much inferior in strength and safety to the
                    twisted stub-barrels. The Damascus barrels are composed of iron and steel in
                    certain proportions, laid crossways or zig-zag, and heated and hammered together
                    the whole length of the barrel. This is easily perceptible when the browning is
                    either taken off by art or worn off by use, and thus the size, position, and
                    variety of the pieces of metal composing the barrel made to appear. According to
                    the opinion of the best judges, the object sought for in the Damascus is beauty;
                    but though beauty is gained, strength is sacrificed. Not but that a Damascus
                    barrel, when of the first quality, may be perfectly safe, but <hi rend="italic">superiority</hi> of safety is on^the side of the twisted stub-barrel.</p><p>The two other kinds of barrels in ordinary use are the stub-iron barrels
                    mentioned, and those made* of the common iron, though of the best quality.
                    Soldiers’ muskets are made of this last, and also the plainest guns, that they
                    may be sold at the lowest prices. Barrels have been formed of other materials,
                    such as old scythes, wire, needles, some with the outer coat of iron, and a
                    lining of steel, and others with layers of iron and steel alternately; but it is
                    needless to do more than mention these, as they seem to have been tried merely
                    as matter of experiment, and to have utterly failed. (See Daniel’s <hi rend="italic">Pural Sports,</hi> p. 479.)</p><p>Having said thus much of the materials of which gun barrels are made, we must now
                    say a few words of the mode of making them. Having fixed in the first place on
                    the size of the gun, and ascertained as near as may be the width of the bore,
                    and the length and thickness of the barrel, the next thing the forger of the
                    barrel does, is to take a portion of the metal of which he is to make the
                    barrel, and to form it into the shape of a thin flexible bar, something like a
                    cooper’s hoop; this bar or hoop must not be all of the same thickness, but that
                    part of it which is to be towards and form the muzzle of the piece, must be
                    thinner than that which is intended to form the breech. An instrument called a
                    mandril is then chosen, according to the size of the intended bore of the gun.
                    The flexible bar or hoop is then heated so as to make it ply easily, and turned
                    round the mandril, much in the same way as a ribbon of leather is turned round
                    the handle of a whip. The edges of the hoop of iron overlap one another a
                    little, so that, when welded, all their joinings may be compact and solid, and
                    no slackness appear where the lips of the bar or hoop touch one another. When
                    the metal has acquired its proper heat, and the weldings are properly executed,
                    the places where the bars overlapped one another are quite imperceptible, and
                    the barrel appears as made out of one piece, and finished at one heat. The mode
                    of making the twisted barrel does not differ materially from that of the common
                    gun now described. The welding of both is the same, the hammering the same, the
                    horizontal stroke called <hi rend="italic">Ú\e jumping</hi> is the same, and
                    they are both wrought on a mandril in the same manner. They differ in this,
                    however, that in the common gun the hoops are broad, overlapping one another
                    considerably, having their edges welded down upon one another, and when finished
                    have the appearance of one continuous piece of plain iron. The bars of the
                    stub-twisted barrel, on the other hand, do not in general exceed half an inch in
                    breadth, and their edges do not overlap, but are just laid close together, and
                    when thus welded, the barrel receives horizontal strokes on the anvil, which
                    make their joints swell up or protuberate, and are then hammered down, and thus
                    made to form a compact and solid union. When the bars are very fine and small,
                    it is called a wire-twist.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193639576" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9576-0037"/><p>The instrument with which barrels are bored is called a bit, introduced into the
                    barrel, and turned round so as to cut or grind off all its inequalities, and
                    render the inside a smooth and perfect cylinder. Of course, the size of the bore
                    is regulated by the diameter of that portion of the bit which grinds the barrel.
                    The bit is worked either by water, by steam, or by the hand. To finish the
                    inside of a barrel perfectly, bits of various sizes are used, the last or
                    finishing one doing little more than merely polishing the bore, so that when it
                    receives the last touch of the finishing bit, it appears as bright and smooth as
                    a mirror of polished steel, or the finest glass. We are now speaking of the
                    finest barrels, as plain or common guns are not bored with such care, nor
                    receive so high a polish.</p><p>The inside of the barrel being finished, the next thing to be done is to polish
                    its exterior. This is done in the first place by the grindstone, and next by the
                    file. The most approved method, however, of smoothing the exterior of a barrel,
                    is by turning it on a lathe, which secures mathematical accuracy, and adds
                    greatly both to its beauty and its strength.</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> ř</hi> Formerly deplorable accidents were continually
                    happening from barrels being sent abroad imperfectly made, of faulty materials,
                    and which never had been subjected to any proper proof. These evils have now in
                    some measure been remedied by act of parliament. By this act every barrel must
                    be tried by a certain quantity of powder and weight of shot, according to the
                    size of the piece; which proof if it stand, it is stamped accordingly with
                    certain marks and letters, bearing that it has stood the ordeal, and been
                    declared sound and safe accordingly. To counterfeit the government mark or
                    letter, or to expose to sale any gun-barrel without its having been subjected to
                    the government proof, subjects the offending party to certain penalties. Some of
                    the best gun-makers, after the <hi rend="italic">powder,</hi> subject their
                    barrels to a <hi rend="italic">water</hi> proof, which is more searching, and
                    brings out the flaws or imperfections of the barrel even more decisively than
                    the powder proof established by government.</p><p>Notwithstanding the act of parliament obtained in the year 1813, by the company
                    of London gun-makers, for establishing a proof-house in London, and another at
                    Birmingham, deplorable accidents are still happening by the bursting of
                    gun-barrels. Various methods are practised to evade the effect of this act,
                    arising from the temptations to elude its sanctions, the difficulty of bringing
                    delinquents to justice, and the smallness of the penalty incurred. It therefore
                    often happens, in direct violation of the act, that gun-barrels are made of the
                    most faulty materials, and sent abroad to the public stamped with the
                    proof-house mark, that never underwent the ordeal of any proof whatever. The
                    best gun-makers are so much aware of this, that they do not trust the barrels
                    whose sufficiency is verified merely by the legal stamp, but subject them in
                    their own premises to the severest test, both by powder and water proof.
                    Complete security can be had by no other means. In verification of this, take
                    the following quotation: “The forging of the proof-marks of the London and
                    Birmingham proof-houses is very common; and the forging is executed with such
                    skill, and the imitation so exact, that the proofmasters are unable to swear to
                    the forging of their own marks. The penalty is so trifling, and the trouble and
                    difficulty of conviction so great, that those guilty of the forgery are rarely
                    brought to punishment. There are persons in Birmingham that would make you up a
                    gun for nothing but the price of the proof as profit.” See an admirable essay on
                    the gun, by Mr William Greener, gunmaker, Newcastle, in which, by a series of
                    admirably conducted experiments, and the most conclusive arguments, he appears
                    to have completely established the danger of trusting to the mode of trial
                    adopted by the proof-houses of London and Birmingham, and laid down rules,
                    which, if universally adopted, would go far to prevent the melancholy
                    catastrophes frequently arising from the bursting of gun-barrels. We recommend
                    this essay, in all the departments of practical gun-making, as one of the best
                    that has fallen in our way, and well worthy the attention of every one who
                    wishes solid information on the beautiful and interesting art of gun-making. We
                    subjoin a scale of proof, as established by act of parliament, obtained in 1813
                    by the company of gun-makers in London, and amended in 1815, and which is still
                    in force.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Proof Scale.</hi></p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. of Balls to the pound avoird.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of Powder for proof.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. of</p><p>Balls to the pound.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of Powder for!</p><p>proof.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. of</p><p>Balls to the pound.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of</p><p>Powder for proof.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. of</p><p>Balls to the pound.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of</p><p>Powder for proof.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. of ļ Balls to the pound.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of</p><p>Powder for proof.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>oz. drs.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>oz∙ drs.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>oz. drs.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>oz. drs.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>oz. drs∙</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. 1</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>11 0</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. 11</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 0</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. 21</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 10</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. 31</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7⅛</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>No. 41</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>5 5</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>12</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> 1 0</hi></p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>22</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 9</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>32</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>42</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 8</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>13</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 15</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>23</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 9</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>33</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>43</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>4</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2 11</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>14</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 14</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>24</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 8⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>34</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>44</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>5</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2 2</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>15</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 14</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>25</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 8⅛</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>35</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>45</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>θ 5⅜</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>6</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 12</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>16</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 13∣</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>26</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 8⅛</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>36</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>46</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 5į</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>7</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 8</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>17</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>o 13⅛</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>27</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 8⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>37</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>47</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 5ļ</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>8</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 6</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>18</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 12⅛</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>28</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 8⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>38</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 6⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>48</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 5ï</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>9</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 2</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>19</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 11 ļ</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>29</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 7⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>39</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 6⅜</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>49</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 5⅛</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>10</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 1</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>20</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 10</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>ļ 30</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>ο ·?ί</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>40</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 θ⅛</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>50</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0 5-∣</p></cell></row></table><p>The powder used is the best round granulated government powder.</p><p>Rifles differ from other guns in their internal construction, and a little in
                    their exterior appearance, although they are composed of the same materials, and
                    are forged in a similar way. After the barrel intended for a rifle is bored
                    nearly to a perfect cylinder, the next thing is to draw in it parallel grooves
                    of a certain depth, running the whole length of the barrel. The grooves in the
                    rifle are not formed all at once, but successively, one after another, till the
                    whole is finished. The grooves are then all polished out in the most careful
                    manner, and rendered of equal depth and fineness. The grooves of some rifles
                    have a slight twist something like a screw, which gives the ball a rotatory
                    motion when it escapes from the muzzle, supposed favourable to its
                    straightforward horizontal flight. A variety of opinion has prevailed as to the
                    depth or shallowness of the grooves in a rifle, some maintaining that they
                    should be pretty deep, and others that they should be very shallow. Robins in
                    his learned and scientific <pb break="no" facs="nls:193639589" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9589-0038"/>treatise on fire-arms, pleads for the latter; and
                    his reasons appear very satisfactory.</p><p>“’ Tis sufficiently obvious,” says he, “that whatever tends to diminish the
                    friction of rifles, renders them more complete; and consequently, the less the
                    rifles are indented, provided they are sufficiently so to keep the bullet from
                    turning round in the barrel, the better they are.” To secure accuracy of flight,
                    he continues, “it is necessary that the sweeps of the rifles should be exactly
                    parallel to each other; for then, after the bullet is put in motion, it will
                    slide out of the barrel without any shake, and with a much smaller friction,
                    than if the threads of the rifles had not the same degree of incurvation.
                    Foreigners are so exact in this, that they try their pieces by pouring melted
                    lead into the barrel; and letting it cool, they thus procure a leaden cylinder
                    of perhaps two or three diameters in length, exactly fitted; if this, being
                    gently pushed by the rammer, will pass from one end of the barrel to the other
                    without any sensible strain, they pronounce the rifle regularly finished; but if
                    it anywhere sticks or moves hard, the piece is esteemed defective.”</p><p>There are three kinds of breeching; namely, what is called the common plug
                    breeching, the chamber plug or mortar breeching, see Plate CCLXXΠI. fig. 1, and
                    the patent breeching. The first used to be put to the plainest kind of
                    fire-arms, as soldiers' muskets, blunderbusses, and the common plain guns used
                    for ordinary purposes. The second kind of breeching is a slight improvement and
                    alteration on the first, which consists in opening the motion-hole running at
                    right angles through both the male and the female screws, and meeting a small
                    antechamber, which comes from the middle of the main chamber, and thus ignites
                    the charge, not, like the common plug, laterally, but from behind and in the
                    centre. The next is the patent breeching, see fig 3, which, indeed, after all
                    that has been said about it, is but a slight alteration on the one last
                    mentioned, and differs from it almost in nothing, except, perhaps, in superior
                    neatness, in having the screws not affected by the touch-holes, in bringing it
                    nearer the <hi rend="italic">ante,</hi> and thus securing more rapid ignition in
                    the <hi rend="italic">main</hi> chamber. However, for a fine gun, the patent
                    breeching ought certainly to be preferred, as much handsomer, and altogether in
                    better keeping with a highly finished fowling-piece.</p><p>The shooting of barrels depends upon three things; their boring, their length,
                    and their weight.</p><p>In boring their barrels, the most approved makers in general observe the
                    following rules: A little tightness for a few inches at the breech end; then a
                    perfect cylinder; and then ease the bore a few inches at the mouth. The
                    tightness at the breech end, the cylinder in the middle, and the widening at the
                    mouth of the barrel, must be in proportion to its length. For a <hi rend="italic">percussion</hi> gun a perfect cylinder the whole length of the
                    barrel, except a few inches of ease at the mouth, is adopted by most of the
                    makers as the best. The next thing affecting the shooting of a gun is the length
                    of the barrels. Here opinions vary, one maintaining that fowling-pieces of
                    twenty-eight or even twenty-four inches in length in the barrels will shoot as
                    well as those of thirty, forty, and forty-five inches long. Robins, who
                    instituted a set of experiments to settle this point, says, that he found this
                    to be the case; and the conclusion he drew from his experiments was, that the
                    sportsman might please himself as to the length of his barrels, varying from
                    twenty-eight up to forty inches; but that either below or above this the barrels
                    began to fall off. The writer of this article suspects there must have been
                    something faulty and imperfect in Mr Robins’ experiments; for after the most
                    careful consideration of the subject, he is satisfied that short barrels are
                    inferior to the long, both in the closeness and the strength with which they
                    throw their shot; the only advantage they have is in snap shooting, but in
                    ordinary sport they are not to be compared to the long barrel. For a barrel of
                    ordinary calibre, its length should not be less than thirty-two inches. In
                    support of this opinion we might refer to the authority of the late Joe Manton
                    of London, no incompetent judge in this matter; and for the verification of the
                    soundness of the opinion in favour of long barrels, we refer to Colonel Hawker,
                    who, after a course of seemingly accurately-conducted experiments, has
                    triumphantly established the superiority of long over short barrels. As to the
                    weight of barrels, it is not common sense that light should do equal execution
                    with heavy barrels. Besides the danger attending the use of light barrels, from
                    their violent vibration when fired, they never can send the shot so strongly and
                    so steadily as those of more metal; and from the necessity of giving them less
                    both of powder and shot, it is evident, even to demonstration, that they never
                    can be so deadly. A double gun, to be safe and to do good execution, should not
                    be below seven pounds or seven pounds and a half, or even eight pounds, if the
                    sportsman does not grudge to carry it.</p><p>Whatever may be said of the Spanish or other continental barrels as rivalling the
                    British, no one will dispute the superiority of our locks. It is allowed by all
                    competent judges, that the beauty and excellence of our finest locks are quite
                    unrivalled. The ancient gun-lock was a very simple and clumsy contrivance. We
                    gave a short description of them in the first part of this article. Here it is
                    necessary only to name them. These were the matchlock, the wheel-lock, and the
                    snaplance. The last was a great improvement on the two others, and indeed is the
                    foundation of our present flint-lock, with such alterations and improvements as
                    the genius of modern times has suggested. Any description of the present
                    flint-lock is unnecessary, as it is known to every one.</p><p>Forsyth’s lock, fig. 2, differs from the ordinary percussion-lock in a few
                    particulars. It has a magazine, <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> for containing the
                    percussion powder; and this magazine revolves round a roller, <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> the end of which is screwed into the breech of the barrel. A small hole
                    is opened in the roller, through which the priming powder passes. This hole
                    communicates with a channel which leads to the chamber of the gun. Right above
                    the little hole in the roller, is the pan for containing the priming. The
                    magazine is provided with a steel punch, c, the under end of which is right
                    above the pan, ready to ignite the priming when struck on the upper end by the
                    cock <hi rend="italic">d</hi> in firing the gun. When the under end of the punch
                    is struck down into the pan, it is raised up again to its former position by a
                    spiral spring Every time the gun is fired, the magazine is turned round so far
                    as to drop a priming of percussion powder into the pan. It is then turned back
                    again, and the steel punch is found in the position ready to fire the gun when
                    the trigger is drawn.</p><p>The merit of inventing this lock, see fig. 2, and the application of percussion
                    powder as a substitute for flint in the discharge of fire-arms, belongs
                    exclusively to the Reverend Mr Forsyth, minister of Belhelvie, a parish in
                    Aberdeenshire. Mr Forsyth’s invention is a very ingenious one, and his
                    principle, though no doubt very much altered and improved in its application,
                    has already almost completely supplanted the use of the flint gun.
                    Notwithstanding the great superiority of the percussion over the flint gun it
                    had to struggle for many years with the most violenl prejudices; but the
                    principle being sound, it has now gained a most complete triumph, so much so,
                    that there is not perhaps at this moment a high-priced flint fowl ing-piece
                    making, either in Great Britain or on the Continent; so complete a revolution in
                    fire-arms has the per cussion principle achieved. Although now and then aι <pb break="no" facs="nls:193639602" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9602-0039"/> old
                    sportsman may be met with whose prejudices are too obstinate to be subdued, and
                    who may still hold out, yet even these are gradually falling into the opposite
                    opinion; so that the percussion gun may now be considered as nearly universal.
                    This is certainly a great triumph to the principle first thought of and applied
                    by Mr Forsyth; but had the application of this principle not been simplified by
                    subsequent alterations and improvements, it is impossible that the percussion
                    gun would ever have gained so sure and universal a triumph. Accordingly, till
                    the invention of the copper cap, the percussion advanced very slowly. This arose
                    from two causes, the expense of Mr Forsyth’s locks, and the complication of
                    their structure. Although Mr Forsyth’s locks are the same internally (we are
                    speaking of his original patent locks), yet externally they differ materially
                    both in appearance and complication from the ordinary lock; and these
                    circumstances increased both their expense and their liability to derangement.
                    This will be obvious from the inspection of the lock, which will give a far
                    better idea of it than any description. To the inventor of the copper cap, then,
                    whoever he was, for there is a dispute about it, must be attributed the rapid
                    and extraordinary spread of the percussion gun. The copper cap, indeed, is so
                    simple, and so easy in its application, both to new guns and those already in
                    existence, that we do not think it will ever be generally superseded. A great
                    variety of contrivances have been fallen upon as substitutes for the copper cap,
                    but it still keeps its ground, and is likely to do so against all
                    competition.</p><p>The superiority of the percussion, and the preference given it by the public,
                    over the flint gun, we conceive, consists in the following circumstances: Its
                    handsome appearance, the comfort in the use of it, the certainty and the
                    rapidity of its discharge, its near approach to a water proof, and the facility
                    with which it at all times obeys the eye of the sportsman. Looking at all these
                    advantages of the detonating gun, we think it a great acquisition to sportsmen,
                    and not likely soon to be supplanted by any other.</p><p>This lock internally is the same as the flint-lock, but externally is a little
                    different both in construction and appearance. See fig. 4. We think it much
                    handsomer than the flint-lock, as it gets entirely clear of three projecting and
                    unseemly encumbrances, the hammer, the hammer spring, and the pan; nothing
                    appears externally on the lock-plate but the cock or striker, which gives the
                    blow to the copper cap when the gun is fired, and which is hollow or concave,
                    provided also with a small ring of projecting metal, called a shield or fence,
                    running round the cock at the bottom of the concave head, to defend the eye from
                    the splinters of the copper cap, and the small stream of fire that issues
                    upwards from the hole in the nipple when the gun is discharged. Serious
                    accidents happened at first from the use of detonators, by not adopting such
                    precautions. At first the heads of the cocks or strikers of copper-cap guns were
                    nnt made hollow or concave, and without any shield or fence round them to
                    protect the eye, but were made plain or smooth, like the head of an ordinary
                    carpenter’s hammer: the consequence was, that when the copper cap flew into
                    pieces when struck, the eye of the sportsman was frequently injured, and
                    sometimes totally destroyed, by such accidents. The next peculiarity of the
                    ordinary detonating lock is the pivot or nipple, and is that part of it which
                    supplies the place of the pan, hammer, and hammer spring of the flint-lock. It
                    is screwed into the patent breèch, and is perforated by a small hole upon which
                    the copper cap is put. It is made two ways, either plain or with small circular
                    rings running round it, intended to prevent the cap from falling or being rubbed
                    off. If properly made, the small rings round it are unnecessary.</p><p>As Barthold Schwartz, a clerical person, a native of Germany, is considered as
                    the inventor of gunpowder in Europe, and as the Reverend Mr Forsyth, minister of
                    Belhelvie, Aberdeenshire, is the inventor of the detonating gun, so it also
                    happens that the Reverend Dr Somerville, minister of the parish of Currie,
                    Edinburghshire, is the inventor of the safety-gun.</p><p>This is effected by means of a stop, slide, or catch, situate under the
                    trigger-plate A. It is pulled forward into a nick in the trigger by means of a
                    spring B on the front of the guard, worked by means of a key C, which presses
                    upon the spring when the gun is discharged. The second method of safety is
                    accomplished by means of a small bit of moveable iron A, of a circular form,
                    rising through a small opening B in the lock-plate C, which prevents the cock
                    from reaching the nipple, as represented in fig. 4, until it is drawn back
                    within the lock-plate when the gun is fired. Fig. 7 is method second discharged.
                    The third method is accomplished by meansofa small bit of iron like a little
                    flap or wing A, folded down in front of the breast of the cock B when the gun is
                    put in the position of safety, and which flap or wing is again raised when the
                    gun is to be fired. This little wing turns on the front of the lock-plate by
                    means of a hinge C. Both these methods are worked by means of a slide or lever,
                    and key, similar to what is described in method first. Fig. 9 is method third
                    discharged.</p><p>There is no man who knows any thing about fire-arms but must be satisfied of the
                    danger attending the use of the ordinary gun. The many advices given about
                    caution by every writer on field-sports; the reiterated paragraphs of newspapers
                    on this subject; the earnest and solicitous admonitions of parents, relations,
                    guardians, and friends; the anxiety felt at the departure, and the joy at the
                    return, of the young sportsman unscathed; the distressing and tragical tales of
                    death and mutilation told in almost every newspaper, announce but too
                    emphatically that the danger is neither imaginary, nor the mischief attending
                    the use of fire-arms of rare occurrence. But if fears about their use, and the
                    admonitions prompted by such fears, could remove the danger, it would be well;
                    experience, however, proves that such admonitions are often in vain. The fact
                    is, shooting is an amusement of that kind which, especially with young
                    sportsmen, so suspends attention, absorbs thought, lays reason and reflection so
                    completely asleep, and excites such ardent and headlong feelings, as to leav« no
                    room for any thing but the occupation of the moment and to talk of preventing
                    entirely accidents from fire-arms by admonition is perfectly hopeless, as it is
                    calling upon young men to exercise thought and caution where thought and
                    caution, we do not say are impossible, but frequently so difficult as to render
                    them very nearly so. It is not without reason, then, that writers have cautioned
                    sportsmen to be careful in the use of fire-arms, and that parents have felt
                    anxiety about their sons when engaged in field-sports with weapons in their
                    hands so precarious in their use, and so fatal in their effects. Too frequently
                    the sprightly and spirited youth, in pursuit of pleasure, finds death. Advice
                    may be given, and caution may be exerted at all times, but still there will be
                    ample room for the employment of means more easy in their application, and more
                    certain in their effects, than either the one or the other. These means are
                    completely furnished by Dr Somerville’s safety-gun.</p><p>Dr Somerville, a few years ago, published an essay on' his safety-gun, and what
                    follows is little more than an abridgment of it. The difficulty, he informs us,
                    was to get a proper principle; but this gained, every thing was gained. Now a
                    proper principle must accomplish four points: 1st, It must allow the right hand
                    to carry the gun in the natural position, without touching or coming in contact,
                    so as to disturb<pb break="no" facs="nls:193639615" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9615-0040"/> or undo the spring or safety apparatus; 2dly, the
                    safety must work mechanically; 3dly, there must be no loss of time in working
                    it; and, lastly, the gun must always be locked except when levelled by the eye
                    and pressed to the shoulder; in other words, it must be locked in its approach
                    to the shoulder, and locked in its descent from it. These four points Dr
                    Somerville has completely gained. This will be obvious from the following mode
                    of applying his principle. Morally speaking, accidental discharge with this gun
                    is completely out of the question, at least the probability is so small, that
                    perhaps philosophy could not calculate when this gun would be discharged in any
                    other way than by design. To fire this gun, two specific points must be touched
                    at one specific time. If accidental pressure shall touch the key which works the
                    safety, no evil happens, because the trigger is untouched; and if it touch the
                    trigger, no evil happens, because it is locked. The pressure must be against the
                    trigger and on the key at the same instant of time, otherwise the lock will not
                    work. If the trigger is touched the twinkling of an eye before the key, or the
                    key before the trigger, no evil can ensue; for unless touched at the same
                    moment, they mutually counteract and support one another, and thus prevent the
                    gun going oft'. Accident may touch the key and the trigger of this gun as well
                    as any other; but then accident cannot touch both key and trigger at the same
                    instant. Design only can touch two specific points at one specific time. If
                    accident do touch the key and trigger, it must be in succession; but successive
                    touching will not fire the gun.' It must be simultaneous to do it; but this
                    supposes thought, and thought supposes design. A short statement of some of the
                    advantages of this gun will conclude our article.</p><p>The first advantage, then, which this gun has over the one in common use, is the
                    <hi rend="italic">preservation of human life.</hi> This is the first and great
                    object of the present contrivance; and in this point of view it was first
                    thought of by the inventor. The other advantages which it possesses are all
                    subordinate to this, and come in merely as subsidiary to the main design. The
                    second advantage of this gun over the ordinary fowling-piece, is <hi rend="italic">superior dispatch.</hi> This is evident at first sight, as this
                    invention enables the sportsman to go with his gun full cocked, and thus, when
                    game rises unexpectedly, saves all the time lost, as well as distraction of
                    thought occasioned, by cocking the ordinary gun; and consequently he has only to
                    present and discharge his piece, which he is enabled to do before the gun in
                    ordinary use can be cocked and brought to the shoulder. So sensible are
                    sportsmen of the advantage of having their fowling-pieces full cocked, that many
                    of them go with them thus prepared, though at the risk both of their own and
                    their friends’ lives. Colonel Hawker, in his instructions to young sportsmen,
                    when speaking of the danger arising from firearms in the field, even when the
                    sportsman goes up to his game with the ordinary gun on half cock, says, “Suppose
                    an eager young man, who is unaccustomed to shooting, walks up to his dog with
                    his gun half eocked; the moment the birds rise, he is in such a state of
                    agitation, that in attempting to draw back the eock of his gun, with a trembling
                    hand, he lets it slip before the scear has caught the tumbler. Oft' goes the
                    gun, and the best fortune that can be expected is the happy escape of a
                    favourite dog, or the life of his fellow shooter.” From this statement we argue
                    thus: If snch is the danger with the ordinary gun carried on half, what must be
                    the danger when carried on full cock? The fact is, with the ordinary gun there
                    is great danger both ways. The present invention, however, removes danger from
                    every way of carrying the gun, as it is always completely locked till it is
                    raised and pressed to &lt; the shoulder, and levelled by the eye of the
                    sportsman.!</p><p>The third advantage of this gun over others is, the ease and tranquillity of mind
                    which it necessarily imparts, not only to the sportsman himself, but to his
                    friends, parents, and relations at home, from the perfect security which it
                    affords him. No man of ordinary feeling can be perfectly at ease,when surrounded
                    by his friends, with a loaded gun in his hand, leaping walls, crossing ditches,
                    brushing through thickets, underwood, and hedges, whilst all the time the life
                    of his friends is within the reach of a mortal weapon, and the danger of that
                    weapon guarded against only by the fallaciousness of memory, and the risk
                    increased tenfold by the eagerness of pursuit, and the suspension of thought
                    necessarily occasioned by a species of amusement which, more than any other,
                    lays caution asleep, and occasions that flutter and hurry of spirits from which
                    such fatal accidents generally spring. It is certainly no very pleasant thing,
                    in the present state of fowling-pieces, to walk all day with two tubes opposite
                    one’s heart, which any neglect or incautionsness on the part of one’s self or
                    friend might render fatal in a moment. What may be called, then, the moral
                    advantage arising from a sense of safety and the removal of anxiety, is not the
                    least advantage in the use of this gun. A man, to be sure, with the ordinary
                    fowling-piece does not always shoot himself or friend; but there is always <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> îí</hi><hi rend="italic">possibility</hi> of doing
                    both, and the accumulated uneasiness and anxiety arising from the very <hi rend="italic">possibility,</hi> is no small deduction from the full enjoyment of
                    his amusement. The hair that suspends the sword over his head does not always
                    snap, to be sure, but there is always a <hi rend="italic">chance of</hi> its
                    doing so. The present safety removes all such anxiety, and prevents all such
                    chances; for it is completely locked, except when levelled at the object, and in
                    the very act of pulling the trigger; for, the moment it ceases to be levelled at
                    the game, the returning action of the safety-spring locks in the gun, not only
                    without the consent, but even contrary to the will, of the sportsman, and thus
                    protects both himself and friends. It must not be supposed from this that the
                    trigger must be drawn the moment the safety-spring is pressed; all that is
                    necessary is, that when the gnn is levelled and pressed to the shoulder, which,
                    as a matter of course, undoes the safety-spring, and allows the locks to work,
                    the right hand shall then draw the trigger, at whatever time the sportsman
                    thinks he has covered his game, or feels inclined to fire, so that he may keep
                    the safety apparatus undone, or worked, any length of time he pleases, before he
                    draws the trigger.</p><p>A fourth advantage is, that one of the modes of shooting with this gun saves the
                    left hand in case of the barrel bursting, by forcing the sportsman to place his
                    left hand on the front of the guard. Colonel Hawker, in his <hi rend="italic">Instructions to Young Sportsmen,</hi> and Daniel, in his <hi rend="italic">Rural Sports,</hi> both most competent judges, recommend this mode of holding
                    the gun. Daniel’s words are, “Always hold the gun with the left hand close to
                    the guard, and not forward on the barrel to grasp it near the entrance of the
                    ramrod, notwithstanding it has been so strenuously recommended; all the
                    requisite steadiness in taking aim, and even of motion, in traversing the flight
                    of a bird, can be obtained by thus holding the heaviest pieces; and in the case
                    of a barrel’s bursting, the certainty of having a hand or arm shattered by
                    grasping the barrel, is reduced to the chance of escaping the effects of such an
                    accident by placing the hand close to the guard beneath it.”</p><p>The fifth advantage of this gun which we mention is, that it completely avoids
                    the necessity of perpetually cocking and uncocking, a very fertile source of
                    danger attending the use of the ordinary gun in the field. With the ordinary
                    gun, the moment the dogs point, or seem to point, both locks are eocked; and if
                    there happen to be no game, or it rise beyond reach, the gun must be uncocked
                    again; so that with the ordinary gun the sportsman during the whole day is
                    perpetually cocking and uncocking his gun. To his friend in company with him,
                    who sees him perpetually<pb break="no" facs="nls:193639628" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9628-0041"/> thumbing his locks, and hears them clicking all
                    day, it is a source not only of great annoyance, but also of great danger.
                    Accidents often happen from this cause.</p><p>The sixth advantage of this gun is, against the danger incurred from the breaking
                    of the point of the scear. This is a very common source of danger, from which
                    the sportsman cannot protect himself or friends, for he is not aware of it. The
                    danger from this cause happens in the following manner: When the sportsman is in
                    search of game with his gun on half cock, up springs the game, and the gun is
                    instantly levelled without being cocked; the trigger remains immoveable; a
                    violent pull is then given; the scear is strained, probably cracked; ignorant
                    that the scear has been injured by the violent pull, the sportsman proceeds in
                    search of his game as usual. The scear may break the next hour, the next day, or
                    the next week; but at whatever time it gives way, the sportsman and his friends
                    are all this time in danger, without having the least idea they are so. This is
                    a very common source of mischief, against which the safety is a completo
                    protection; for although any part or every part of the inside of the lock were
                    to give way, the cock or striker cannot reach the nipple to fire the gun till
                    the safety-spring is drawn back.</p><p>Another common source of danger with the ordinary gun is, that sportsmen often go
                    with the cock or striker resting on the nipple; the consequence of which is,
                    that any thing drawing back the striker by accident, a certain distance, and
                    then losing its hold, off goes the gun. Against accidents of this kind the
                    safety is a complete protection, as the striker cannot be pulled back but by the
                    <hi rend="italic">design</hi> of the person using the gun.</p><p>The last advantage of this gun we mention, is the security it gives to loaded
                    guns, when lying in houses, or exposed to the curiosity of thoughtless or
                    ignorant persons. Many a life has been lost by guns having been presented and
                    fired off in a wanton and incautious manner. Such accidents cannot happen with
                    the present gun; for, to render it perfectly safe, it is only necessary to stop
                    the action of the safety-spring, which is done by a very simple contrivance, and
                    restored again to action by the same simple means.</p><p>Looking at all these advantages of Dr Somerville’s safety-gun, we anticipate that
                    in a short time no gun will be considered complete without having a safety
                    attached to it.</p><p>We shall conclude this article by the insertion of a few tables abridged from a
                    work published in Birmingham, by the authority of the Proof Company,
                    illustrating the different proportions of the British and French muskets. The
                    serjeants of the British light-infan try regiments carry a small musket or fusil
                    of the following dimensions :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches 37</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the bore, in inches ∙65</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the firelock with bayonet, in pounds</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>avoirdupois 9</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Several regiments of British cavalry are armed with
                            rifle</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>guns of the following dimensions :—</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches 30</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the bore, in inches ∙623</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the ball for service, in ounces ∙761</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the piece with sword, in pounds</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>avoirdupois 10∙75</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>The carbine and pistol borne by the regiments of heavy</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>cavalry are of the following dimensions :—</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>CARBINE.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches 28</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the bore ∙645</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the ball, for service ’ 623</p></cell></row></table><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the ball for service, in ounces ∙8</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the piece with the bayonet, in pounds, 8∙25</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">pistol.</hi></p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches 9</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the bore ∙645</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the ball .’. ∙623</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the ball ∙8</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the pistol 3∙2</p></cell></row></table><p>The carbine carried by the regiments of light cavalry is in length only sixteen
                    inches, and in weight six pounds. The pistol is in length, diameter, and weight,
                    the same as that used by the heavy cavalry. The greater liability of the ramrod
                    to shake out of the shorter carbine has led to the adoption of an indention of
                    Lord Anglesey’s, by which the rod is connected to the piece by a swivel. The
                    same invention is also applied to the pistol.</p><p>The barrel of the French musket is longer than that of the British, and the
                    bayonet is shorter, though not so much so as to make the barrel and bayonet of
                    the British musket equal in length to that of the barrel and bayonet of the
                    French. The following are the proportions :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>FRENCH MUSKET.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches</p><p>Length of the bayonet, in
                            inches</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.44∙72</p><p>.15∙</p><p>59∙72</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>BRITISH MUSKET.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches</p><p>Length of the bayonet, in
                            inches</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.39</p><p>.16</p><p>55</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Difference of length in favour of the</p><p>French
                            musket</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>4∙72 inches.</p></cell></row></table><p>In the comparison just drawn between the respective lengths of the British and
                    the French muskets, that of the British is of the India pattern musket, which
                    was used by our forces during the late war; the musket now carried by our
                    infantry is longer, the barrel being forty-two inches and the bayonet seventeen
                    inches, being very nearly equal in length to the French musket.</p><p>The locks of the French muskets have brass pans, and they are altogether heavier,
                    and have a more clumsy appearance, than the British. The calibre of the barrel
                    is likewise narrower than that of our muskets. This will be more distinctly seen
                    by the following statement of the dimensions of the French musket, and of the
                    new pattern musket now carried by the British forces.</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>FRENCH MUSKET.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel, in inches</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>44∙72</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the bore</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>•69</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the ball for service</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>•65</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the ball for service, in ounces avoirdupois</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>•958</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the firelock with bayonet, in pounds
                            avoirdupois</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>10∙98</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel and bayonet, in inches....</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>59∙72</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">new</hi> LAND PATTERN BRITISH
                            MUSKET.</p><p>Length of the barrel, in inches</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>42</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the bore</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>•75</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Diameter of the ball for service</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>•676</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the ball for service, in ounces avoirdupois</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙06</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Weight of the firelock with bayonet, in pounds
                            avoirdupois</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>12∙25</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Length of the barrel and bayonet, in inches</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>59</p></cell></row></table><pb break="no" facs="nls:193639641" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9641-0042"/></div></body></text></TEI>