<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0252-0089-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUYTON DE MORVEAU, Baron Louis Bernard</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 89</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:919014">Extracts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:892595">Diamonds</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1132472">Steel</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d9z">Extracts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hd4m">Diamonds</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xj9j">Steel</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48w38662">Fluids</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640252" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUYTON DE MORVEAU, <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron Louis
                    Bernard</hi></label>, a celebrated chemist, known also as an advocate of
                    eminence, and less advantageously, in his political character, as a regicide,
                    was the son of Antony Guyton de Morveau and Margaret de Saulle his wife, and
                    born at Dijon, on the 4th of January 1737.</p>
                <p>His father was of a respectable family, and filled the situation. of professor of
                    the civil law in the university of Dijon. He was fond of building; and, from the
                    artificers who were frequently employed about his house, young Guyton appears to
                    have derived, almost in his infancy, a taste for mechanical pursuits, which led
                    to an astonishing development of premature talent. For when he was only seven
                    years old, he prevailed on his father to purchase, for his amusement, a clock
                    which was greatly out of repair, and, as is said, he actually put it together
                    and remedied its defects, without any assistance, so effectually, that it
                    continued to go extremely well for fifty or sixty years afterwards. The next
                    year he was equally successful in cleaning and repairing a watch belonging to
                    his mother. But, notwithstanding these remarkable exertions of ingenuity, it
                    does not appear that they depended on any particular bent of the genius to the
                    cultivation of the mechanical arts; at least no such bias was ever exhibited in
                    any of his subsequent pursuits. His education was conducted in the ordinary
                    manner at a provincial school or college, which he left at sixteen. Upon his
                    return home he applied, for a short time, to botany, and he was soon afterwards
                    admitted as a student of law in the university of Dijon, where he remained for
                    three years, and then removed to Paris, in order to continue his studies at the
                    bar. In 1756, he paid a visit to Voltaire at Ferney; and he seems to have
                    imbibed from this personage a taste for satirical poetry, which he soon
                    afterwards displayed, upon the occurrence of a trifling accident, in a ceremony
                    relating to a popular Jesuit of the day. Amongst his posthumous papers, he also
                    left some unfinished sketches of tragedies, which are said not to have been
                    deficient in poetical merit.</p>
                <p>At the age of twenty-four, when he made some progress <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193640265" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0265-0090"/>in the practice of his
                    profession as an advocate, his father procured for him, at the price of 40,000
                    francs, the appointment of advocate-general ôf the parliament at Dijon, so that
                    he had no farther solicitude for the acquisition of an income adequate to his
                    competent subsistence. His health was then considered as delicate; but the fears
                    which were entertained for it proved to be completely groundless.</p>
                <p>In January 1764, he was made an honorary member of the Academy of Sciences at
                    Dijon, then lately established under the patronage of the Prince of Condé. This
                    occurrence seems to have had considerable influence on the pursuits which
                    occupied his leisure hours; and he soon became by far the most distinguished
                    ornament of the academy which had paid him this compliment. His particular
                    application to chemistry arose in a great measure out of an accidental emulation
                    with Dr Chardenon, who afterwards very liberally undertook to assist him in the
                    cultivation of this branch of science. He studied the works of Macquer and of
                    Beaumé, and he was furnished by the latter with the materials necessary for the
                    establishment of a small laboratory for his own use.</p>
                <p>With regard to the more general cultivation of literature and science, he
                    displayed considerable talent in a memoir on public instruction, together with a
                    plan for a college, which he presented to the parliament of Burgundy, insisting,
                    with great force and success, in opposition to Diderot, on the importance of
                    early education in modelling the character of the human mind. About the same
                    time he also wrote a prize essay, an Encomium on Charles V. of France, surnamed
                    the Wise, which was afterwards inserted in the collection of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Discourses,</hi> published in three volumes.</p>
                <p>In July 1767, he visited Paris with a view to the advancement of his scientific
                    pursuits, and excited the admiration of the most celebrated chemists of the day,
                    by the facility which he had acquired in the manipulation of his experiments. He
                    entered, after his return, into the investigation of the great question
                    respecting the oxidation of metals, though he did not succeed in removing the
                    difficulties which then embarrassed it. In 1769, he pronounced, at the opening
                    of the parliament, an elegant oration upon morals. He was soon afterwards
                    engaged in some experiments respecting the communication of heat to different
                    substances, the results of which, though not published, were of some importance
                    to the theory of temperature. At the request of his friend Dr Durande, he
                    undertook to inquire into the nature of biliary calculi, which he found to be
                    readily soluble in ether; and it appears that a combination of ether and oil of
                    turpentine proved of advantage to several of Dr Durande’s patients, who were
                    suffering from these concretions.</p>
                <p>In the year 1773 he was employed in an interesting investigation of the mutual
                    adhesion of the surfaces of solids and fluids, a class of phenomena of which the
                    mathematical theory was never at all understood, until the publication of an
                    essay on the Cohesion of Fluids in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Transactions,</hi> soon after the beginning of this cen- tury, in which the laws
                    of capillary action are extended to a complete analogy with all the experiments
                    of Μ. de Morvcau, as well as those of Taylor and Achard of a similar nature. He
                    succeeded, about the same time, in discovering a mode of destroying the
                    contagious vapours of pestilential diseases, by fumigation with the muriatic
                    acid gas; he afterwards found the oxymuriatic acid, or pure chlorine, still more
                    effectual; and it does not appear that the nitric acid, since proposed in
                    England, has any advantages over either of these substances.</p>
                <p>Μ. de Morveau’s anxious desire to co-operate in the promotion of chemical
                    knowledge induced him to make a new exertion in its favour, by undertaking, in
                    1776, to deliver a public and gratuitous course of lectures as a regular
                    professor of the science, authorized by the approbation and encouragement of his
                    brother magistrates at Dijon. He soon afterwards wrote some essays on the
                    peculiar characters of the carbonic acid; and he strenuously combated the
                    popular prejudice which prevailed, against the introduction of conductors, for
                    preserving buildings from lightning. He established a large manufactory of
                    nitre, which was afterwards conducted by Μ. Courtois, the father of the Μ.
                    Courtois who discovered iodine. From chemistry he naturally diverged into the
                    study of mineralogy; in 1777 he made a tour through the province of Burgundy,
                    with a view to the examination of all its productions; and he actually
                    discovered a rich lead mine, though, for want of coal, it was impossible to
                    derive much benefit from it. He also found a white variety of the emerald in the
                    same province, as well as some combinations of barita, and he invented a new
                    method of obtaining the pure barita from its sulphate.</p>
                <p>He had long been intimately acquainted with the Count de Buffon and with
                    Malesherbes, both persons distinguished by elegance of taste, the one in
                    science, the other in general literature. In 1779 and 1780 he enlarged his
                    connections among the men of letters resident at Paris; and he was induced by
                    Panckoucke, the bookseller, to undertake the chemical department of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Encyclopédie Méthodique;</hi> but it was six years before the <hi
                    rend="italic">Dictionary of Chemistry</hi> appeared; the articles relating to
                    pharmacy and metallurgy were supplied by Maret and Duhamel. In the progress of
                    this work he found himself compelled to disbelieve the existence of phlogiston
                    as a distinct principle of inflammability, though at the beginning he had
                    defended the doctrines of the old school. But he soon became one of the most
                    zealous advocates of the new theory; and he contributed very much to its general
                    introduction by the active part which he took in the arrangement of a new
                    nomenclature. His proposals were at first thought objectionable by many of the
                    members of the Academy of Sciences; but they soon became generally adopted
                    throughout Europe; and the system was without doubt of great use for a time, as
                    far as it assisted the memory and the imagination in retaining the discoveries
                    and comprehending the theories which had so much of novelty to make them
                    interesting. Among the original matter contained in the Dictionary, were some
                    researches on the nature of steel, which coincided in their results with those
                    of Monge, Vandermonde, and Berthollet, made about the same time, but published
                    somewhat earlier. The. whole volume was received in the most flattering manner
                    by all the lovers of chemistry; but it was not till 1791 that the author’s
                    ambition was gratified by the award of the Academy of Sciences, adjudging him a
                    prize of two thousand francs, which had been allotted to the most useful work
                    which should appear in the course of the year. The prize, however, he begged to
                    offer to the exigencies of the state, which were then very urgent. The
                    Dictionary was afterwards ably continued by Μ. de Fourcroy.</p>
                <p>In the mean time he condescended to appear as the translator of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opuscula</hi> of Bergman, which he illustrated by notes. The
                    example was followed by Madame Picařdet, and by others of his friends, who were
                    zealous for the promotion of science; so that the French chemists were by these
                    means speedily made acquainted with the labours of al] their contemporaries in
                    different parts of the world. In the year 1787, Μ. de Morveau applied his
                    speculations to a practical purpose, in establishing a manufactory of sods from
                    common salt, exposed to the atmosphere, with a large proportion of lime, the
                    soda slowly efflorescing as a carbonate. It was in the same year that, having
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Collection of Pleadings,</hi> he finally
                    resigned his office at the bar, in order that the whole of his time might be
                    devoted to the pursuit of science.</p>
                <p>• His next undertaking was of a more adventurous nature<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193640278" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0278-0091"/>; for, in April 1784, he
                    ascended with the President de Virly in a balloon; and he repeated the
                    experiment in the month of June, hoping to be able to direct his aerial course
                    at pleasure. The balloon appears to have been about thirty feet in diameter;
                    and, when we consider the action of the wind upon a surface of such extent, we
                    must be aware that every attempt to oppose or modify it must have been perfectly
                    futile. He was visited soon afterwards by the ingenious and lamented Mr Tennant,
                    who went to Dijon purposely to become acquainted with him, and who had an
                    opportunity of performing some original experiments in his laboratory. He was
                    made a member of the Royal Academy of Medicine at Paris in 1786, as a compliment
                    to the merits of his labours for the preservation of the public health. He
                    received a visit, in the succeeding year, at once from Lavoisier, Berthollet,
                    and Fourcroy, together with Monge and Vandermonde; and our countryman, Dr
                    Beddoes, who was then travelling in France, had the good fortune to join this
                    interesting party, all of them deeply engaged in the discussion of the great
                    chemical questions which were then undecided. In April 1788, Μ. de Morveau was
                    placed on the list of the foreign members of the Royal Society of London; and
                    the same mark of respect was also paid him at different times by almost all the
                    scientific societies of Europe.</p>
                <p>In September 1791 he was unfortunately elected a member of the Legislative Body;
                    and having also been made solicitor-general of his department, he could no
                    longer continue the chemical lectures which he had delivered without
                    intermission for fifteen years, and he resigned his chair to Dr Chausier. It
                    must not be omitted by an impartial biographer, that, on the 16th of January
                    1793, he thought himself compelled to vote with the majority, for the death of
                    the king; and it is a poor compensation for this fatal error that, in the same
                    year, he resigned a pension of two thousand francs a year, in favour of that
                    republic to which he had already sacrificed the best feelings of humanity. He
                    afterwards became a commissary of the assembly attached to the army of the
                    Netherlands. In this capacity, besides many other instances of personal courage,
                    he is said to have rendered essential service to his countrymen, by the
                    construction of a balloon, in which he ascended, together with some of the staff
                    of General Jourdan, in order to observe the motions of the enemy during the
                    battle of Fleurus. After his return to Paris he was appointed professor of
                    chemistry in the <hi rend="italic">Ecole Polytechnique,</hi> and he was an
                    effective co-operator in the first establishment of that useful institution. In
                    1795 he was again chosen a member of the Council of Five Hundred; and he was
                    appointed by the government one of the forty-eight members of the National
                    Institute, then recently embodied. He had for some time been a correspondent,
                    but was never a member, of the Academy of Sciences. His political engagements
                    terminated in 1797, when he resolved once more to devote himself exclusively to
                    science. In 1798, he fulfilled the duties of director of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ecole Polytechnique</hi> during the absence of Monge, w ho was in Egypt, and
                    for whom he insisted that the salary should be reserved. The following year,
                    Bonaparte, then first consul, made him a general administrator of the mint. He
                    received the cross of the Legion of Honour in 1803, and obtained, two years
                    afterwards, still higher rank in the order, particularly as an acknowledgment
                    for the public benefits which had been derived from his methods of fumigation.
                    In 1811, he was elevated to the dignity of a baron of the French empire.</p>
                <p>From 1798 to 1813, he continued his labours as professor of chemistry in the
                    Polytechnic School; he then obtained leave to retire, but he survived only a few
                    years, and died of a paralytic affection, or rather of a total decay of
                    strength, the 21st of December 1815, at a period when he would shortly have had
                    to encounter the effects of a retribution, which would have been very severely
                    felt at so advanced an age. In stature he was rather below than above the middle
                    size; his conversation was animated and copious, his manners courteous and
                    obliging; he was full of anecdote, and always ready to communicate whatever
                    information he possessed. He married, late in life, Madame Picardet, the widow
                    of an academician of Dijon, whose tastes and pursuits were congenial with his
                    own, and who had distinguished herself by translating several works of science
                    and of literature from the different languages of the north of Europe. As to his
                    numerous publications, a bare catalogue of these will be amply sufficient to
                    show the extent of his researches and the variety of his pursuits. It is the
                    more necessary to do justice to his diligence and perseverance, as we cannot
                    easily point out any one important discovery or invention that can be considered
                    as commensurate to the high promise of his early infancy. The article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Acid</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Dictionary,</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Methodical Nomenclature,</hi> must be ranged as the best of his
                    productions: but the character of both these is rather useful than splendid.</p>
                <p>1. Le Rat Iconoclaste, poëme heroi-comique, 12. Dijon, 1763. 2. Mémoire sur
                    l’instruction publique, 12. Dijon, 1764. 3. Eloge du Président Jeanin, Paris,
                    1766. 4. On the effect of air in combustion; Mém. Acad. Dij. i. 1769, p. 416. 5.
                    Manière d’éprouver les charbons de pierre, Dijon, 1769. 6. Réflexions sur la
                    boussole è</p>
                <p>double aiguille, Dijon, 1771. 7. Hauteurs barométriques. Dijon, 1771. 8.
                    Consultation juridicochimique sur le charbon fossile, Dijon, 1771. 9. Plaidoyer
                    sur l’époque de démence d’un testateur, Dijon, 1772. 10. Digressions
                    Académiques, 12. Dijon, 1772. 11. On a cold effervescence; Mem. Ac. Dij. ii.
                    1771, p. 183. 12. On the displacement of a wood, and on a cavern, p. 225. 13.
                    Défense de la volatilité du phlogistique, 12. Paris, 1772. 14. Reflections sur
                    le parallèle du phlogistique et du causticum. Dijon, 1773. 15. On the coal of
                    Monteenis in Burgundy Journ. Phys. ii. p. 445. 16. On platina, and its alloy
                    with steel, vi. p. 193. 17. Discours Publics, 3 vols. Dijon and Paris, 1775. 18.
                    On a fossil tooth; Journ. Phys. vii. p. 414; Mem. Ac. Dij. 1785, i. p. 102. 19.
                    On the crystallization of iron; Journ. Phys, viii. p. 348, ix. p. 303; Mém, Sav.
                    Etr. ix. p. 513. 20. Elémens de Chimie théorique et pratique, 4 vols. 12. Dijon,
                    1777; a clear and elegant compendium. 21. On metallic crystallizations; Journ.
                    Phys, xiii. p. 90. 22. On a singular petrifaction, xv. p. 89. 23. On some
                    properties of manganese, xvi. p. 156. 24. On the red selenite of Montolier, xvi.
                    p. 443. 25. Opuscules de Bergman, 2 vols. 8. Dijon, 1780, translated, with
                    notes. 26. On simple earths, especially absorbents; Journ. Phys, xvii. p. 216,
                    xviii. p. 68. 27. On the improvement of colours used in painting; Mem. Ac. Dij.
                    1782, p. 1, 28. On the congelation of sulphuric acid, p. 68. 29. On some ores of
                    copper, p. 100. 30. On barita, p. 159; Journ, Phys, xviii. p. 299. 31. On
                    biliary concretions, in Durande’s Memoir; Mem. Ac. Dij. 1782, i. p. 199, p. 26.
                    32. On the manufacture of nitre, p. 1, 16. 33. On an ore o: lead, p. 41. 34.
                    Lettre à Μ. J. Z. sur l’influence de l’éducation publique, Dijon, 1782. 35. On a
                    sulphuret ol zinc; Μ. Ac. Dij. 1783, i. p. 37. 36. On an incombustible coal, p.
                    76. 37. On a spirit lamp for experiments, p. 159. 38. On the acetate of bismuth,
                    p. 187. 39. On the karabic or succinic acid, ii. p. 1. 40. On an areometer foi
                    sugar boilers, p. 52. 4L On a meagre limestone of Brion, p. 90, fit for terras.
                    42. On the mephitic gas contained in water, 1784, i. p. 85. 43. On the
                    alteration of gold boiled in nitric acid, ii. p. 133. 44. On the natural
                    dissolution of quartz; Swed. Trans. 1784; Mem. Ac.Dij∏785. i. p. 46, 6Ô. ’ 45.
                    On sugar and its acid, p. 90. 45. Description de l’aërostat de l’Acadĕmie,
                    Dijon, 1784. 46. Plaidoyers sur plusieurs questions importantes, 4. Dijon <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193640291"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-0291-0092"/>1785. 47. On the conversion of iron into steel,
                    and on plumbago; Journ. Phys. 1786, 308. 48. Encyclopédie Méthodique, chimie,
                    vol. i. 4, Paris, 1786, with Maret and Duhamel, noticed Ann. Chim. vii. p. 24.
                    49. Methode de Nomenclature chimique, 8. Paris, 1787, by de Morveau, Lavoisier,
                    Berthollet, and De Fourcroy. 50. On the reduction of an oxyd; Ann. Chim. i. p.
                    106. 51. On adamantine spar, p. 188. 52. On the expansion of gases, p. 256. 53.
                    On adhesion, vii. p. 32. 54. On the affinity of mercury with metals, p. 42. 55.
                    On some pneumatic apparatus, p. 50. 56. On the alteration of solutions heated in
                    glass vessels, ix. p. 3. 57. On saturation and supersaturation, X. p. 38. 58. On
                    a gravimeter, xxi. p. 3. 59. On a French hyacinth, p. 72, containing zirconia.
                    60. Notice of a scientific institution at Erfurt, xxii. p. 81. 61. Extract of a
                    work on the agriculture and arts of Spain, p. 310. 62. Report of the labours of
                    the society at Rouen, p. 320. 63. Notice of Nicholson’s Journal, xxxiii. p. 173.
                    64. On a native sulphate of strontia, p. 216. 65. On the saltpetre of commerce,
                    p. 225, xxv. 231. 66. On the acid and ores of tin, xxiv. p. 127. 67. Extract
                    from Nicholson, p. 156. 68. On basaltic prisms, p. 160. 69. On a micaceous ore
                    of iron, p. 161. 70. Notes on Nicholson, p. 175. 71. On the manufactory of soap,
                    p. 199. 72. On pumice stone, p. 200. 73. On obtaining fire and water for
                    chemical experiments, p. 310. 74. On platina, xxv. p. 3. 75. On sugar, p. 37.
                    76. Note from Nicholson, p.</p>
                <p>69. 77. On the combustion of the diamond, p. 76. 78. On alcarrazas, or cooling
                    jars, p. 167. 79. On the water of Caldas, p. 180. 80. On nomenclature, p. 205.
                    81. On the composition of salts, from Kirwan, with tables, p. 282, 292, 296. 82.
                    On the conducting power of charcoal for heat, xxvi. p. 225. 83. On the action of
                    fused nitre on gold, silver, and platina, xxvii. p. 42. 84. On tempering steel,
                    p. 186. 85. On odorous emanations, p. 218.</p>
                <p>86. On the precipitation of silica by lime, xxvii. p. 320.</p>
                <p>87. On iron and cast steel, from Clouet’s experiments, xxviii. p. 19. 88. On the
                    natural productions of Spain, from Fernandes, p. 311. 89. On the succinic acid,
                    xxix. p. 161. 90. On the destruction of contagious matter, p. 209. 91. On
                    artificial coolings, p. 291. 92. On the application of gas to wounds, p. 305.
                    93. On the fusibility of mixed earths, and on their mutual action, p. 320. 94.
                    On a peculiar crystallization of quartz, xxx. p. 117. 95. On the action of
                    metallic substances on vegetable colours, and on lacs, p. 180. 96. On the
                    combustion of a diamond, xxxi. p. 72. 97. Notice of Reuss’s mineralogical
                    dictionary, p. 177. 98. On the affinities of the earths, p. 246.</p>
                <p>99. Note on the silica found by Davy in the epidermis of vegetables, p. 276. 100.
                    On the conversion of iron into cast steel by a diamond, p. 328; the diamond
                    weighed thirteen grains. 101. On the conversion of diamond into charcoal, and on
                    the disoxigenization of sulphur, xxxii. p. 62. 102. Comparison of the French and
                    German weights, p. 225. 103. Extract of Thenard’s memoir on antimony, p. 257.
                    104. Chemical news, p. 328. 105. Account of Libes’s theory of elasticity,
                    xxxiii. p. 110. 106. On the colouring principle of the lapis lazuli, xxxiv. p.
                    54, supposed to be a sulphuret of iron combined with earth. 107. Note on
                    adhesion, p. 199. 108. On the theory of crystallization, Journal de l’Ec. Polyt.
                    i. p. 278. 109. Analysis of a chalcedony, p. 287. 110. On the composition and
                    proportions of salts, Μ. Inst. Sc. ii. p. 326. 111. On anomalies in affinities,
                    p. 460, v. p. 55. 112. On the composition of the alcalis, iii. p. 321; supposing
                    them to contain lime. 113. On a metal proper for small coins, vii. ii. p. 80.
                    114. On the measurement of high temperature, and on expansion, ix. ii. p. i.; a
                    thermometer of platina. 115. On the tenacity of ductile metals, and on the
                    different densities of lead, x. p. 267; Extract Ann. Chim. lxxi. p. 189. To
                    return to the <hi rend="italic">Annales de Chimie,</hi> in which he continued to
                    be an active co-operator to the close of his life, we find a multiplicity of his
                    essays and abstracts in the latter volumes. 116. On lime and mortar, xxxvii. p.
                    253. 117. Report on the tartaric acid, xxxviii. p. 30. 118. On a lamp, p. 135.
                    119. On Woodhouse’s opinion of phlogiston, p. 272. 120. On a cold combustion of
                    the carbonic oxyd, xxxix. p. 18. 121. Traité des moyens de désinfecter l’air;
                    Extr. Annales Chimie, xxxix. p. 74. Dutch, by Luitschius, noticed Ann. Chim.
                    xlvi, p. 105. 122. On the analysis and synthesis of earths, p. 171. 123. On a
                    stove, xli. p. 79. 124. On bell-metal, p. 167. 125. On an instrument for
                    examining gold coin, xlii. p. 23. 126. On Burkitt’s apparatus for distillation,
                    p. 191. 127. Note on propolis, p. 195. 128. Extract from Nicholson, p. 205. 129.
                    On Davy’s eudiometer, p. 301. 130. On some alloys of iron, xliii. p. 47. 131. On
                    the dilatation of gases, p. 153, 154, 156. 132. On prussic precipitates, p. 185.
                    133. On colcothar for polishing, p. 331. 134. Extract from Nicholson, xliv. p.
                    21. 135. On Mitchell’s nomenclature, p. 305. 136. On fumigation, p. 286; xlvi.
                    p. 113; li. p. 311; lii. p. 347; lvi. p. 103, 114; ]χii. p. 113; lxiv. p. 183.
                    137. On a pyrometer of platina, xlvi. p. 276. 138. On a native carbonate of
                    magnesia, xlvii. p. 85. 139. Extract of a vocabulary, p. 93. 140. Italian
                    novelties, p. 203, xlviii. p. 98, 186. 141. On a ve-rificator for louis d’ors,
                    xlvii. p. 291. 142. On an alloy of gold and platina, p. 300. 143. Extract from
                    Winter!, p. 312. 144. From Chenevix on the eye, xlviii. p. 74. 145. On a
                    sulphate of magnesia, p. 79. 146. On a proposal for washing with sea water, p.
                    108. 147. Note of Hatchett’s memoir on alloys, 1. p. 113. 148. Extract from
                    Christobal’s chemistry of the arts, liii. p. 115. 149. Report on the effect of
                    disagreeable odours on the health, liv. p. 86; not necessarily noxious. 150.
                    Report on chimnies, lv. p. 5. 151. On a sculptured flint, lviii. p. 75. 152. On
                    filtering stones, and on specific gravities, lx. p. 121. 153. Extract on
                    Galvanism, lxi. p. 70. 154. On a supposed antique emerald, p. 260. 155. On
                    nitrous ether, p. 282. 156. On the qualities of glass, lxii. p. 5. 157. Extract
                    on pottery, p. 213. 158. On Galvanism, as affecting minerals, lxiii. p. 113.
                    159. On chimnies, lxiv. p. 113. 160. Extract on diamond, lxv. p. 84. 161. On a
                    hygrometer for gases, lxviii. p. 5. 162. On oxydation in a vacuum, lxix. p. 261.
                    163. On carbonate of potass as a medicine, lxx. p. 32. 164. On a crystallization
                    of the diamond, p. 60. 165. Oh Curaudau’s pyrotechny, lxxi. p.</p>
                <p>70. 166. On glass making, lxxiii. p. 113. 167. On an ore of platina from St
                    Domingo, p. 334. 168. On pyrometry, lxxiv. p. 18, 129. 169. On potass and
                    magnesia as medicines, lxxv. p. 204. 170. On laminated platina, lxxvii. p. 297.
                    171. On oxymuriatic acid as a medicine, p. 305. 172. On the effects of continued
                    heat on pyrometrical bricks, lxxviii. p. 73. 173. On the pseudacorus as a
                    substitute for coffee, p. 95; lxxxvi. p. 63. 174. On coffee as a substitute for
                    bark, lxxviii. p. 203. 175. Official instructions for preventing contagion,
                    lxxxii. p. 205. 176. On a lime wash for walls, lxxxiii. p. 285. 177. On the
                    diamond, lxxiv. p. 20, 233. 178. On the non-existence of sugar in diabetes, p.
                    225. 179. On an indigenous tea, p. 333. 180. On Reid’s pendulum, lxxxv. p. 183.
                    181. On sugar boiling, p. 192. 182. On the diamond, lxxxvi. p. 22. 183. On
                    chemical police, p. 105; xc. p. 101. 184. On measures of zinc, lxxxvi. p. 113.
                    185. On a meagre lime, lxxxviii. p. 19. 186. On biliary calculi, p. 84. 187. On
                    the solution of calculi in the bladder, lxxxix. p. 92. 188. On phosphorescent
                    urine, p. 182. 189. On album graecum, p. 325. 190. On pyrometry, xc. p. 113,
                    225. 191. On magnesia as a medicine, xci. p. 224, 285. 192. On tempering steel,
                    xcii. p. 85. 193. On putrefaction, p. 160. 194. On poisons, from Brodie, xciii.
                    p. 5. 195. On the oxalic acid as a poison, p. 199. 196. On the effect <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193640304" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0304-0093"/> of the phosphoric
                    acid upon turmeric, xciv. p. 223; like that of other acids. 197. On fumigations,
                    xcv. p. 321; xcvi. p. 5. 198. On a solvent for biliary calculi, p. 103; from
                    Durande’s paper. (Life by Dr Granville, Journ. R. Inst. 1817.) (L. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
