<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0380-0367-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOOTBALL (9th edition, volume 9, page 367)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882917">Cricket</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882967">Crickets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884187">Crosses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19t22">Crickets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xf9q">Cricket</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m034">Annuals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb3h">Calendar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n380/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOOTBALL</label> is a game which consists, as the name
                    implies, in giving motion to a ball with the feet alone. It has been aptly
                    designated the “winter game” of Great Britain, and justly takes the place of
                    cricket from Michaelmas to Lady Day. The ball requires to be larger than in all
                    handball pastimes, in order that it may be easily kicked. This was accomplished
                    in ancient times by inflating a bladder or skin termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >follis.</hi> In Greece the ∈7riσκυpoς seems to have borne a resemblance to the
                    modern game. Of this we read in Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of
                    Antiquities—</hi> “It was the game at football, played in much the same way as
                    with us, by a great number of persons divided into two parties opposed to one
                    another.” Amongst the Romans the <hi rend="italic">harpastum,</hi> derived from
                    Greek verb <hi rend="italic">apπdζω,</hi> to seize, thus showing that carrying
                    the ball was permissible, bore a certain resemblance. Basil Kennett, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Romae Antiques</hi><hi rend="italic">Notitia,</hi> terms this
                    missile a “larger kind of ball, which they played with, dividing into two
                    companies and striving to throw it into one another’s goals, which was the
                    conquering cast,”—a description which, if correct, certainly bears a strong
                    resemblance to the modern game of football. The antiquity of football in Great
                    Britain (introduced, there can be little doubt, by the Romans) goes some
                    centuries farther back than cricket, probably because the requisites—only an
                    inflated ball and rude goals—were fewer and simpler than in the summer game. The
                    birthplace of the latter was in the southern counties, that of football in the
                    north. In early times the great football festival of the year was Shrove
                    Tuesday, though the connexion of the game with this particular date is lost in
                    obscurity. William Fitzstephen, in his <hi rend="italic">History of London</hi>
                    (about 1175), speaks of the young men of the city annually going into the fields
                    after dinner to play at the well-known game of ball on the day <hi rend="italic"
                    >quae</hi><hi rend="italic">dicitur</hi><hi rend="italic">Camile-varia.</hi> As
                    far as is known this is the first distinct mention of football in England. A
                    clear reference is made “ad pilam .... pedinam” in the Rotuli Clausarum, 39
                    Edward III. (1365), memb. 23, as one of the pastimes to be prohibited on account
                    of the decadence of archery, and the same thing occurs in 12 Richard II. c. 6
                    (1388). Down to the end of the first quarter of the present century Shrove
                    Tuesday continued to be the high ' festival of football, but it had never taken
                    root, like cricket, amongst the aristocracy and gentry. It was confined to the
                    middle and lower classes. No clubs or code of rules had been formed, and the
                    sole aim seems to have been to drive the ball through the opposing side’s goal
                    by fair means or foul. So rough did the game become that James I. forbade the
                    heir apparent to play it, and describes the exercise in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Basilikon</hi><hi rend="italic">Doron</hi> as “meeter for laming than making
                    able the users thereof.” Both sexes and all ages seem to have taken part in it
                    on Shrove Tuesday; shutters had to be put up and houses closed in order to
                    prevent damage; and it is not to be wondered that the game fell into bad repute
                    under such violent horse-play and eccentric usages. Accidents, sometimes fatal,
                    occurred; and Shrove Tuesday “football-day” gradually died out about 1830. For
                    some thirty years football was only practised at the great public schools, at
                    which there were, as still, two distinct forms of play. The Rugby game, so aptly
                    described in <hi rend="italic">Tom Brown’s School Days,</hi> resembles the Roman
                    <hi rend="italic">harpastum</hi> and the rough Shrove-tide play, since seizing
                    and carrying the ball, charging, and one player’s holding another are freely
                    allowed, and actual hacking was abolished at Rugby only as lately as 1877.
                    Harrow and Winchester are the chief exponents of the game wherein kicking alone
                    is allowed as a means of propulsion. Eton plays a hybrid game in two different
                    ways, viz., “At the Wall” and “In the Field,” the latter being a sort of mixture
                    of both kinds of play. All other schools have arrayed themselves under one or
                    other of these banners, with slight modifications in their rules. About the year
                    1860 when the great volunteer movement and the institution of amateur athletic
                    sports gave a zest to many kinds of exercises, there came a revival of football
                    amongst old public school and university men. It was soon found that a universal
                    code of rules and a society to legislate on matters of dispute were necessary.
                    Followers of the strict foot game were the first to recognize these wants, and
                    the “Football Association” was accordingly formed in 1863, the exponents of the
                    other method not banding themselves together till the “Rugby Football Union” was
                    instituted in 1871.</p>
                <p>Football has extended most rapidly throughout the United Kingdom during the past
                    few years, as is evinced by the fact of all large towns, villages, and schools
                    now possessing football clubs, and has regularly taken the place of cricket
                    during the winter months. It is a game more adapted to youths than to
                    middle-aged persons, and should not be indulged in after the frame is full-grown
                    and set, when the tumbles and scrimmages incidental to the Rugby code are apt to
                    be baneful. The balls are now made of inflated india-rubber bladders, covered
                    with strong leather laced together, the Rugby balls being elliptical or
                    egg-shaped, and the Association ones a perfect sphere.</p>
                <p>The two games may be briefly described thus :—</p>
                <p>Under the Rugby code a level piece of turf is the scene of action, and fifteen a
                    side the usual number of players—ten “forwards,” two “half backs,” one
                    “three-quarters back,” and two “backs.” Each goal is composed of two upright
                    posts, exceeding 11 feet in height, and placed 18⅛ feet apart, with a cross-bar
                    10 feet clear from the ground. The choice of goals is decided by lot, the side
                    which wins the choice either availing themselves of any favourable breeze or
                    gradients which may prevail, or electing to play at a disadvantage for the first
                    period of the game till “half time” is called. The game is commenced by the
                    opposite side to that which has choice of goals kicking off' the ball (placed on
                    the ground) from midway between the two goals. The object of both sides then is
                    to drive the ball over the cross-bar, and between the line of the two upright
                    posts of their opponents’ goal, which achievement constitutes “obtaining a
                    goal.” This can be accomplished either by a player’s touching the ball down
                    behind his adversaries’ goal line, then carrying it out, and thus obtaining a
                    “try” or place kick at goal, or by kicking a goal with a direct drop-kick
                    instantly the ball rebounds from the ground. A match is decided by a majority of
                    goals; if their number be equal, by a majority of ties; and if none of either be
                    obtained, the match is drawn. The other minutiae are <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n381/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0381-0368"/> so numerous that no less than sixty rules are
                    required for their regulation.</p>
                <p>The intricacies of the Association game are far fewer, and only require a very
                    plain set of thirteen rules. No handling or touching the ball, except by the
                    goal-keeper, is permissible, “dribbling” or kicking with the feet being the sole
                    mode of propulsion. The goal posts are 24 feet apart, and the cross-bar only 8
                    feet from the ground, the ball in this case having to be driven <hi
                    rend="italic">under</hi> the latter in order to obtain a goal. “Tries” are
                    unknown, and the gaining of goals are the sole points whereby the game is
                    decided.</p>
                <p>The rules of both games will be found in most football works, the chief of which
                    are Routledge’s <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Football,</hi> 1867; C. W.
                    Alcock’s <hi rend="italic">Football Annual,</hi> annually from 1868; Alcock’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Football, Our Winter Game,</hi> 1874; G. H. West’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Football Calendar,</hi> annually from 1874. (H. F. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
