<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0757-0722-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANKS, The (9th edition, volume 9, page 722)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ht2gd1x">Chatti</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n757/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANKS, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label>. When, in the
                    year 241 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> the soldiers of Aurelian, who just
                    before had been on the north German frontier, marched out of Rome on their way
                    to the Persian war, they sang (Vopiscus <hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Aureliano,</hi> c. 7) a rough barrack song—</p>
                <p>“Mille Sarmatas, mille <hi rend="italic">Francos,</hi> semel et semel occidimus;
                    Mille mille mille mille mille Persas quaerimus;”</p>
                <p>and the words, caught up by the admiring mob, became a street boys’ ballad in
                    those days of debased imperialism. Unless we give to Peutinger’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Itinerary</hi> an earlier date than is probable, this street song
                    marks the first appearance in history of the Frankish name. Caesar, Tacitus,
                    Ptolemy, are alike silent as to it, although they often speak of other tribes
                    which occupied the very districts in which we afterwards find the Franks. It is
                    therefore probable, though Jacob Grimm <hi rend="italic">(Geschichte der
                    Deutschen Sprache,</hi> p. 518) says that the view has “only a moderate value,”
                    that Frank is the newest of all German names, and represents, somewhat vaguely,
                    a group of tribes who dwelt about the lower and middle Rhine. The Frank lived in
                    districts previously occupied by tribes bearing other names; nor have we proof
                    of any incursion of a strange tribe called Franks from north or east. The old
                    Frankish legend that they came from the Danube to the Rhine probably arose from
                    the fact that a colony of the Sicambrian cohort was planted by the Romans on the
                    spot where Buda-Pesth now stands; nor need we seriously consider the usual
                    annalist statement that they were “reliquiae Troianorum.” The meaning and origin
                    of the term also lends itself to the view above stated,—the words “frank and
                    free,” usually grouped together, are in fact the same in origin and meaning <hi
                    rend="italic">(ſri,ſrech,</hi> M.H.G.; <hi rend="italic">ſrekkar,</hi> Scand½
                    <hi rend="italic">ſríks,</hi> Goth. <hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >audax, avidus</hi>; then, by insertion of <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> cp. <hi
                    rend="italic">linquo</hi> from root of <hi rend="italic">liqui,</hi> we get <hi
                    rend="italic">frank).</hi> The two words thus grouped together form an epithet
                    rather than a proper name: the “free Franks” are those tribes whose freedom
                    suffered most attack; the name probably came into being in the 3d century<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n758/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0758-0723"/> A.r&gt;. as a part of the resistance 01 northern
                    and northwestern Germany to the ceaseless attempts of Rome. “Francus habet nomen
                    a feritate sua,” says Ermoldus Nigellus (i. 344); and the word carries the sense
                    of boldness, defiance, freedom. As it did not lend itself well to Latin
                    verse-endings, and as its origin was late, we find the silver and leaden poets
                    delighting to call the Franks Sicambri, as in the famous speech of St Remi to
                    Hlodowig, “Depone mitis colla, Sicamber,” &lt;fcc.</p>
                <p>When their history begins, the Franks are in three groups, mostly on the left
                    bank of the Rhine, from Mainz to the sea. It is, however, quite clear that in
                    earlier days they dwelt also on the right or German bank; for if at first the
                    Romans pressed on them, ere long they began to press on the Romans in return.
                    The oldest Frankish land was then on the Rhine; some of it lay to the north of
                    the Betuwe (the island between Meuse and Rhine), having the river Yssel as its
                    eastern limit, and a line drawn through Durstede, Utrecht, and Muy den as its
                    western boundary. The Franks of this district, afterwards called Salians (a name
                    derived either from Sala, an inheritance, or from the river Saal, or Yssel),
                    filled the parts called the Veluwe and the territory of the Sicambri; south-east
                    of these was a second group, the Chamavi, Bructeri, Attuarii, also at first on
                    the right bank of the Rhine; beyond these, a group of Chatti and Suevi, from a
                    little above Cologne to the Main, filling up all the country between the Taunus
                    hills and the Rhine. It is to this group of tribes, says Watterich <hi
                    rend="italic">(Germanen</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Rheins,</hi> p. 166), that the title Frank was first given. This view of their
                    geographical distribution is supported by the evidence of Peutinger’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Itinerary,xn.</hi> which Francia stands on the right bank of the
                    Rhine from just above Nimwegen to a little below Coblentz; and though this
                    famous map is a road-chart rather than a record of ethnology and tribal
                    distribution, still it may fairly be urged that its author would not have placed
                    the Franks on the very outside of his map had their home been on the left bank
                    of the Rhine.</p>
                <p>In the middle of the 3d century these Franks began to press into the First and
                    Second Germany, two tracts of land on the left bank of the Rhine from Alsace to
                    the sea. In 240 the Chatti crossed at Mainz; in 258 Franks are in the army of
                    Postumus as well as opposed to him; with them he drove their brethren across the
                    Rhine and made Cologne his capital. By degrees they filled the whole district
                    from the Moselle to the Betuwe, occupying the lands of the Ubii and Tungri, that
                    is, from the Ardennes to the Rhine and Meuse. These Franks are known to history
                    as the Ripuarians, receiving, as was not unnatural, a partly Latin name
                    (Ripuarii, Riparii, bank-men <hi rend="italic">; or</hi> possibly Rip-wehr-ii,
                    bank-defenders). About the same time the Salian Franks also moved southward,
                    crossing the Rhine, which in those days was slow and shallow in its lower
                    course, the main waters having been diverted into the Meuse. They occupied the
                    whole Betuwe, and spread down to the sea, inhabiting the marshy delta of the
                    rivers (“paludicolae Sigambri,” or “Franci inviis strati paludibus,” <hi
                    rend="italic">circa</hi> 280 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.);</hi> and presently
                    (287) they took part in naval expeditions down the coast of Gaul. Then, passing
                    the Meuse also, they seized on Toxandria, which was given over to them in 358 by
                    the emperor Julian, who defeated them, and admired their bravery and independent
                    spirit. Henceforth we find plenty of Franks taking service under the empire:
                    Frankish chiefs, like Bald, Mellobald, Arbogast, rise to high places in court
                    and army; their names appear even in the Consular Fasti; they make or unmake
                    emperors. By the end of the 4th century the frontiers of the -empire to the
                    north had permanently receded: Andernach was the outmost Rhine station held by
                    the Romans; Tournay was still theirs; they had a fleet on the Sambre; all beyond
                    was Frankish land. Before long the Franks advanced again: in 429 we hear (in
                    Gregory of Tours) that the Salians, coming “from Dispargum (Disiburg, the city
                    of the goddesses), in Toringia,” won a great battle at Cambrai under Chlodion
                    their king, and penetrated even as far as the Loire. This Toringia is probably a
                    confusion with Tongria, a little district on the Meuse; the Franks were never in
                    Thuringia, With their two capitals, the Salians at Dispargum, the Ripuarians at
                    Cologne, the Franks now became the bulwark of the Romans: they resisted the
                    barbarians who crossed the Rhine at Mainz in 406; and in 451 again joined the
                    legions to repel at Chalons the hideous invasion of Attila. Thus feeling their
                    strength, it was not long before, under their young king Hlodowig, or Clovis,
                    the Salian Franks became masters of northern Gaul, while their brethren the
                    Ripuarians remained for the time near the Rhine. And “as the son of Childerich,
                    following in the steps of his kinsfolk, pressed southwards, in mid career of
                    victory he met the Christians’ God. The Disi, the wild goddesses, abandoned him;
                    he trusted in the god of Hlotehild, and conquered all his foes” (Watterich, <hi
                    rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Germanen des Rheins,</hi> p. 238). These
                    Christianized Salians, under the Merwing house, became in time lords of all
                    Gaul, and gave it a new name, Francia Occidentalis, or Interior, or Latina, to
                    distinguish it from the older Francia Orientalis, the Germany of the middle
                    Rhine; the latter name drifted off towards the east, and has found a home in
                    that central district of Franconia, which lies far away from the true Frankish
                    land.</p>
                <p>Henceforth the history of the Franks falls under that of France; while their
                    institutions were mainly those of all Germans. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >France</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Germany.)</hi> Their physical features
                    were also those of the race in general: the fierceness of their looks; the
                    wrinkled scowl about their brows, “torvi Sicambri ;” their wild blue eyes; their
                    large limbs, which contrasted with the little stature of the Romans; their long
                    fair hair, which was a choice commodity at Rome, being bought eagerly by the
                    ladies of fashion in those late imperialist days,—all these things had little in
                    them that was specially Frankish. Their weapons were more characteristic, being
                    their own and connected closely with their name. They fought either with the
                    “framea” (a word which <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n759/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0759-0724"/> is almost certainly a copyist’s error for
                    “franca”), which was a light javelin, tipped with iron sharpened on either side,
                    a weapon fit for casting or smiting, and sometimes spoken of as a little axe; or
                    with the francisca, which was a heavy battle-axe. It is to the Franks that the
                    great Siegfried Saga properly belongs; and their early history is hopelessly
                    mixed up with legend. It is not till the days of Hlodowig that any light is
                    thrown on their institutions,—the <hi rend="italic">Lex</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Salica,t</hi> ∖ <hi rend="italic">iQ</hi> law of the Salian Franks, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Lex Ripuaria,</hi> of which the origin was a little later,
                    belonging probably to the end of the 5th and the early part of the 6th
                    centuries. The <hi rend="italic">Lex Salica</hi> was afterwards enlarged and
                    altered; in its earliest form it presents to us the Franks in their Toxandrian
                    or Tongrian time, before Christianity had touched them. This law shows no trace
                    of a feudal nobility or a “feudal system” of any kind; as Waitz <hi
                    rend="italic">{Deutsche</hi><hi rend="italic">Verfassungsgeschichte: Das alte
                    Recht der</hi><hi rend="italic">Salischen</hi><hi rend="italic">Franken,</hi> p.
                    103) says, “Das Salische Gesetz kennt keinen Adel; auch nicht die leiseste Spur
                    desselben findet sich.” The tribes had chiefs or kings, elected by the whole
                    body of free men from one family (as Hlodowig from among the Merwings); there
                    were also sundry officers of justice and administration, rachimburgs or grafs,
                    but these are no more noble than the rest of the free Franks, who formed a
                    republic of fighting men, each man’s voice being as potent in the mall as his
                    arm was in the battle. The “laeti,” or the “pueri regis,” the king’s “damsels,”
                    and the antrustions belong to the later editions of the law. King, free Frank,
                    and slave of war,—these are the only grades. The code endeavours, always by
                    imposition of carefully graduated fines, to protect the sanctity of the Frank’s
                    family, to determine his duties towards the king, the graf, and the tribal
                    council or mall, to provide for the security of his property, whether personal
                    or landed. It is in this last part of the code that we find the famous clause
                    <hi rend="italic">{Lex Salica,</hi> lix., De Alodis, § 5; Waitz, p. 266) on
                    which the so-called Salic law of France was afterwards based: “De terra vero
                    nulla in muliere hereditas est, sed ad virilem sexum qui fratres fuerint tota
                    terra perteneat.” This special limitation as to the inheriting of Salic land
                    (the Stamm-land as the Germans call it, the Odal of the Icelanders) is but a
                    scanty basis on which to build a great law of royal succession, which lasted in
                    France as long as the monarchy continued, and might still reappear, were the
                    present republic to prove untrue to itself. Up to the time of the Revolution,
                    the French noblesse prided themselves on being the “proud descendants of the
                    conquerors;” but though it is possible, in earlier times, to trace or to fancy
                    distinctions of feature and character, marking off the noble from the <hi
                    rend="italic">roturier</hi> or the peasant, still in the later days of the
                    monarchy the “noble race of conquerors” was so much changed, so many old houses
                    had become extinct, so many had been diluted with foreign blood, so many new
                    patents of nobility had been issued, that it would require no small ingenuity
                    and imagination to see in the courtiers of Louis XVI. the representatives of the
                    Franks of Hlodowig or Charles the Great.</p>
                <p>The chief authorities for the Franks are Jakob Grimm, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte der deutschen Sprache,</hi> Leip., 1848; Waitz, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Das alte Recht der Salischen Franken: Beilage zur deutschen
                    Verfassungsgeschichte,</hi> Kiel, 1846; Gohm, <hi rend="italic">Fränkische
                    Reichs-und Gerichts-Verfassimg,</hi> Weimar, 1871; Watterich, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die Germanen des Rheins,</hi> Leip., 1872. There is also an ingenious lecture
                    by Giesebrccht. In modern days not much has been written on the Franks, except
                    in connexion with the history of institutions. (G. W. K. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
