<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0362-0349-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLUOR SPAR, Fluorite, or Calcium Fluoride (9th edition,
                    volume 9, page 349)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:879476">Cornish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884667">Crystals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884644">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998476">Light</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3989t">Sparring</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s42j">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FLUOR SPAR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Fluorite</hi>, or <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Calcium Fluoride</hi></label>, CaF <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>, (Germ. <hi rend="italic">Fluss-spatlι),</hi> the “blue John” of
                    Derbyshire, and “cann” or “kann” of Cornish miners, occurs crystallized in <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n363/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0363-0350"/> simple or modified cubes and octahedrons; also
                    nodular, compact and granular, and more rarely fibrous, or soft and earthy. Some
                    octahedral crystals from the mines of St Agnes, in Cornwall, are made up of
                    minute cubes, which may themselves show faces of other forms of the monometric
                    system of crystallography. Fluor spar is a brittle, transparent to
                    sub-translucent mineral, with a perfect octahedral cleavage, a vitreous,
                    sometimes splendent lustre, a hardness of 4, and a specific gravity of 3Ol-3 ’
                    25. Before the blowpipe it decrepitates, tinges the flame dull red, and fuses
                    into an enamel. Heated with concentrated sulphuric acid it yields hydrofluoric
                    acid (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. p. 491). In colour fluor
                    spar varies much, being blue, purple, green, yellow, pink, or brown; it is
                    sometimes dichroic. The colours are attributed by Wyrouboff to the presence of
                    minute quantities of hydrocarbons, taken up from solutions from which the
                    mineral has crystallized; by others they are considered to be due to
                    peculiarities of molecular structure. In the Weardale fluors small cavities
                    containing liquid have occasionally been found. Fluor spar, in common with some
                    other substances, when exposed to light, or when raised to a temperature
                    somewhat under redness, usually phosphoresces, emitting a bright light, the
                    colour of which is not dependent on that of the mineral. A variety of fluor spar
                    has received its name chlorophane from its fine green phosphorescence. Like the
                    colour, the phosphorescence of fluor-spar is destroyed by exposure to a high
                    temperature; it may be partly restored by means of an electric discharge, or, it
                    is said, by moistening with dilute hydrofluoric acid. From the name of the
                    mineral Professor Stokes borrowed the term ‘' fluorescence,” applied by him to
                    the quality which certain bodies, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> sulphate of
                    quinine, possess of rendering the ultra-violet rays of the spectrum visible. W.
                    Hankel <hi rend="italic">{Ann. Phys. Chem.</hi> [2], ii. 66-83), experimenting
                    on crystals of fluor spar from Weardale, found that when exposed to light they
                    exhibited not only phosphorescence but electrical phenomena; the rays of the
                    sun, however, concentrated by a lens, deprived the crystals of their
                    photoelectrical property, which they did not regain. Fluor spar is slightly
                    soluble in water containing hydrated calcium carbonate. Pseudomorphs of
                    hornstone, hematite, calamine, and other minerals after fluor spar are not
                    unfrequent. Fluor spar is commonly used for the production of hydrofluoric acid
                    in etching on seals and glass, and in the smelting of lead and copper and in
                    other metallurgical operations as a flux, whence its name, from the Latin <hi
                    rend="italic">fiuo,</hi> to flow. The manufacture of vases and other ornamental
                    articles from fluor spar, especially the variegated varieties, has long been
                    carried on in Derbyshire. The stone, which is sometimes first heated to change
                    its blue to an amethystine tint, is shaped by means of the lathe and a fine
                    steel tool, and is finished off with coarse stone, and after that with pumice
                    and emery. Fluor spar is of frequent occurrence in metalliferous veins, being
                    most commonly associated with ores of lead, as in the mines of Derbyshire,
                    Cumberland, Cornwall, Saxony, and Bohemia. It is met with also in granite,
                    gneiss, slates, various limestones and sandstones, and some volcanic products,
                    and has occasionally been detected in beds of coal.</p>
                <p>On the phosphorescence of fluor spar see Prof. C. Bohn’s paper on “Negative
                    Fluorescence and Phosphorescence,” <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.</hi> [4J, vol.
                    xxxiv. p. 109, 1867.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
