<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0013-0004-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FALCONER, William (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    4)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1116638">Shipwrecks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090554">Readers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006755">Mallets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134142">Storms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821361">Auroras</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tf38">Shipwrecks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz3256r">Storms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2t88q">Auroras</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n13/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FALCONER, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>, our
                    greatest naval poet,—Charles Dibdin taking rank as second,—was born in
                    Edinburgh, February 11, 1732. His father was a wig-maker, and carried on
                    business in one of the small shops with wooden fronts at the Netherbow Port, an
                    antique castellated structure which remained till 1764, dividing High Street
                    from the Canongate. The old man, who is described as a sort of humorist, was
                    unfortunate. Of his three children two were deaf and dumb; he became bankrupt,
                    then tried business as a grocer, and finally died in extreme poverty. William,
                    the son, having received a scanty education, -was put to sea. He served on board
                    a Leith merchant vessel, and in his eighteenth year was fortunate enough to
                    obtain the appointment of second mate of the “Britannia,” a vessel employed in
                    the Levant trade, and sailed from Alexandria for Venice. The “Britannia” was
                    overtaken by a dreadful storm off Cape Colonna and was wrecked, only three of
                    the crew being saved. Falconer was happily one of the three, and the incidents
                    of the voyage and its disastrous termination formed the subject of his poem of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Shipwreck.</hi> “In all Attica,” says Byron, “if we except
                    Athens itself and Marathon, there is no scene more interesting than Cape
                    Colonna. To the antiquary and artist, sixteen columns are an inexhaustible
                    source of observation and design; to the philosopher the supposed scene of
                    Plato’s conversations will not be unwelcome; and the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n14/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0014-0005"/> traveller will be struck with the beauty of the
                    prospect over ‘ isles that crown the Aegean deep.’ But for an Englishman Colonna
                    has yet an additional interest, as the actual spot of Falconer’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Shipwreck.</hi> Pallas and Plato are forgotten in the recollection
                    of Falconer and Campbell—</p>
                <p>“ ‘ Here in the dead of night, hy Lonna ’ s steep, The seaman’s cry was heard
                    along the deep.’”</p>
                <p>After the wreck of the “Britannia” and his return to England, Falconer, in his
                    nineteenth year, appeared as a poet. He printed at Edinburgh an elegy on
                    Frederick, prince of Wales,—a puerile inflated performance,—and afterwards
                    contributed short pieces to the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine.</hi>
                    Some of these descriptive and lyrical effusions possess merit. The fine naval
                    song of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic">Storm</hi> (“Cease, rude
                    Boreas”), reputed to be by George Alexander Stevens, the dramatic writer and
                    lecturer, has been ascribed to Falconer, but apparently. on no authority. It is
                    foreign to his usual style. Had he been the author he would assuredly have
                    claimed it. Falconer continued in the merchant service until the spring of 1762,
                    when he gained the patronage of Edward, duke of York, by dedicating to him his
                    poem of <hi rend="italic">The Shipwreck,</hi> which appeared in l·NIay of that
                    year, “printed for the author.” The duke advised him to enter the royal navy,
                    and before the end of summer the poet-sailor was rated as a midshipmau on board
                    the “Royal George.” But as this ship was paid off at the peace of 1763, and as
                    Falconer’s period of service had been too short to enable him to obtain the
                    commission of lieutenant, he was advised to exchange the military for the civil
                    department of the navy, and in the course of the same year, he received an
                    appointment a3 purser of the “Glory” frigate, a situation which he held until
                    that vessel was laid up on ordinary at Chatham. In 1764 he published a new
                    edition of <hi rend="italic">The Shipιvreck,</hi> corrected and enlarged, and
                    printed, not for the author, as in the former instance, but for Andrew Millar,
                    the publisher of Hume and Robertson, and whom Johnson called the Maecenas of the
                    age. About nine hundred lines were added to this new edition of the poem,
                    including what may be termed its character-painting and elaborated description
                    and episodes. In the same year, 1764, Falconer published a political satire, a
                    virulent rhyming tirade against Wilkes and Churchill, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >The</hi><hi rend="italic">'Demagogue</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and in 1769
                    appeared his <hi rend="italic">Universal Marine</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionary,</hi> an elaborate and valuable work. "While engaged on this
                    dictionary, Mr Murray, a bookseller in Fleet Street, father of Byron’s
                    munificent publisher and correspondent, wished him to join him as a partner in
                    business. The poet declined the offer, probably because his dictionary was then
                    near completion, and he might reasonably anticipate from its publication some
                    favourable naval appointment. He did receive this reward; he was appointed
                    purser of the “Aurora” frigate, which had been commissioned to carry out to
                    India certain supervisors or superintendents of the East India Company. Besides
                    his nomination as purser, Falconer was promised the post of private secretary to
                    the commissioners. Before sailing he published a third edition of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Shipwreck,</hi> which had again undergone “correction,” but not
                    improvement. Mr Stanier Clarke conceived that the poet, in his agitation and joy
                    on being appointed to the “Aurora,” had neglected this edition, and left the
                    last alterations to his friend Mallet; but NIallet had then been more than four
                    years in his grave, and Falconer, in the “advertisement” which he prefixed to
                    the volume, and which is dated from Somerset House, October 1, 1769, said he had
                    been encouraged by the favourable reception the poem had met with to give it “a
                    strict and thorough revision.” The day after this announcement the poet sailed
                    in the “Aurora” from Spithead. The vessel arrived safely at the Cape of Good
                    Hope, and having passed a fortnight there, left on the 27th of December. She was
                    never more heard of, having, as is supposed, foundered at sea. The captain was a
                    stranger to the navigation, and had obstinately persisted in proceeding by the
                    Mozambique Channel instead of stretching as usual into the Indian Ocean south of
                    Madagascar. Every commander of a vessel, as Fielding has remarked, claims
                    absolute dominion in his little wooden world, and in too many instances shows
                    the dangerous consequences of absolute power.</p>
                <p>Thus miserably perished William Falconer in the thirtyseventh year of his age.
                    His fame rests on his poem of <hi rend="italic">The Shipwreck,</hi> and rests
                    securely. In that work he did not aspire to produce a great effect by a few bold
                    touches, or the rapid and masterly grouping of appalling or horrible
                    circumstances. He labours in detail, bringing before us the events as they
                    arise, and conducting us with an interest constantly increasing towards the
                    catastrophe. Such a tremendous picture of shipwreck as that which Byron has, in
                    wild sportiveness, thrown out in Don Juan, immeasurably transcends the powers of
                    Falconer, and, indeed, stands alone in its terrible sublimity; but, on the other
                    hand, the naval poet, by the truth and reality of his descriptions, ultimately
                    impresses the mind of the reader, if not with such vivid force, perhaps with
                    even more enduring effect. Some of the classic invocations to the shores of
                    Greece, and some descriptive passages, are a little tawdry, but the grand
                    incidents of the poem are never forgotten. The personification of the ship in
                    its last struggles is sublime as well as affecting, and the reader’s anxiety and
                    sympathy with the principal characters and the hapless crew never slumber, Nor
                    are the technical expressions and directions a drawback to the general reader.
                    They are explained in footnotes, and give a truth and reality to the narrative;
                    and they do not occur in the more impassioned scenes. <hi rend="subscript">
                    r</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(r. ca.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
