<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0122-0113-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FESTIVALS (9th edition, volume 9, page 113)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t2w">Feasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb3h">Calendar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0330j">Calendars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202945">Dominica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844160">Calendar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844227">Calendars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n122/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FESTIVALS</label>. A festival or feast<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“To feast” is simply to keep a festum or
                    festival. The etymology of the word is uncertain; but probably it has no
                    connexion with &lt;&lt;rτjSμ.</p></note> is a day or series of days specially
                    and publicly set apart for religious observances. Whether its occurrence be
                    casual or periodic, whether its ritual be grave or gay, carnal as the orgies of
                    Baal and Astarte or spiritual as the worship of a Puritan Sabbath, it is to be
                    regarded as a festival or “holy day” as long as it is professedly held in the
                    name of religion.</p>
                <p>To trace the festivals of the world through all their variations would be to
                    trace the entire history of human religion and human civilization. Where no
                    religion is, there can of course be no feasts; and without civilization any
                    attempt at festival-keeping must necessarily be fitful and comparatively futile.
                    But as religion develops, festivals develop with it, and assume their
                    distinctive character; and an advancing civilization, at least in its earlier
                    stages, will generally be found to increase their number, enrich their ritual,
                    fix more precisely the time and order of their recurrence, and widen the area of
                    their observance.</p>
                <p>Some uncivilized tribes, such as the Juângs of Bengal, the Fuegians, and the
                    Andamanese, have been described as having no word for God, no idea of a future
                    state, and consequently no religious ceremonies of any kind whatever. But such
                    cases, doubtful at the best, are confessedly exceptional. In the vast majority
                    of instances observed and recorded, the religiosity of the savage is
                    conspicuous. Even when incapable of higher manifestations, it can at least take
                    the form of reverence for the dead; the grave-heap can become an altar on which
                    offerings of food for the departed may be placed, and where in acts of public
                    and private worship the gifts of survivors may be accompanied with praises and
                    with prayers. That the custom of ghost-propitiation by some sort of sacrifice is
                    even now very widely diffused among the lower races at least, and that there are
                    also many curious “survivals” of such a habit to be traced among highly
                    civilized modern nations, has been abundantly shown of late by numerous
                    collectors of folk-lore and students of sociology; and indications of the same
                    phenomena can be readily pointed out in the Rig-Veda, the Zend-Avesta, and the
                    Pentateuch, as well as in the known usageβ of the ancient Egyptians, Greeks, and
                    Romans.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Spencer, <hi
                    rend="italic">Principles of Sociology,</hi> i. 170, 280, 306.</p></note> In many
                    cases the ceremonial observed is of the simplest; but it ever tends to become
                    more elaborate; and above all it calls for repetition, and repetition, too, at
                    regular intervals. Whenever thiβ last demand has made itself felt, a calendar
                    begins to take shape. The simplest calendar is obviously the lunar. “The Naga
                    tribes of Assam celebrate their funeral feasts month by month, laying food and
                    drink on the graves of the departed.” But it soon comes to be combined with the
                    solar. Thus the Karens, “while habitually making oblations, have also annual
                    feasts for the dead, at which they ask the spirits to eat and drink.” The
                    natives of the Mexican valley in November lay animals, edibles, and flowers on
                    the graves of their dead relatives and friends. The common people in China have
                    a similar custom on the arrival of the winter solstice. The ancient Peruvians
                    had the custom of periodically assembling the embalmed bodies of their dead
                    emperors in the great square of the capital to be feasted in company with the
                    people. The Athenians had their annual Neκ√σια or Ne/*«r«a and the Romans their
                    <hi rend="italic">Feralia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lemuralia.</hi> The
                    Egyptians observed their three “festivals of the seasons,” twelve “festivals of
                    the month,” and twelve “festivals of the half month,” in honour of their dead.
                    The Parsees, too, were required to render their afringans (blessings which were
                    to be recited over a meal to which an angel or the spirit of a deceased person
                    was invited) at each of the six seasons of the year, and also on certain other
                    days.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Haug, <hi
                    rend="italic">Pαrsis,</hi> 224, 225.</p></note></p>
                <p>In the majority of recorded instances, the religious feeling of the savage has
                    been found to express itself in other forms besides that of reverence towards
                    the dead. The oldest literatures of the world, at all events, whether Aryan or
                    Semitic, embody a religion of a much higher type than ancestor worship. The
                    hymns of the Rig-Veda, for example, while not without traces of the other, yet
                    indicate chiefly a worship of the powers of nature, connected with the regular
                    recurrence of the seasons. Thus in iv. 57 we have <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n123/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0123-0114"/> a hymn designed for use at the commencement of
                    the ploughing time;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“May
                    the heavens, the waters, the firmament, be kind to us; may the lord of the field
                    be gracious to us May the oxen (draw)</p><p>happily, the men labour happily; may
                    the traces bind happily, wield the goad happily” (Wilson’s translation, iii.
                    224).</p></note> and in the <hi rend="italic">Aitareya-Brahmana,cb⅛</hi>
                    earliest treatise on Hindu ceremonial, we already find a complete series of
                    sattras or sacrificial sessions exactly following the course of the solar year.
                    They are divided into two distinct sections, each consisting of six months of
                    thirty days each. The sacrifices are allowed to commence only at certain lucky
                    constellations and in certain months. So, for instance, as a rule, no great
                    sacrifice can commence during the sun’s southern progress. The great sacrifices
                    generally take place in spring, in the months of April and May.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Haug’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aitαreyα-brAhmαnαm of the Rig-Veda;</hi> Max Müller’s <hi rend="italic">Chips
                    from a German Workshop,</hi> i. 115.</p></note> In the Parsee Scriptures<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Visperad. See Haug, <hi
                    rend="italic">Parsis,</hi> 192; Richardson’s <hi rend="italic">Dissertation on
                    the Language, &lt;kc., of Eastern Nations,</hi> p. 184; Morier’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Journey through Persia.</hi></p></note> the year is divided into
                    six seasons or gahanbârs of two months each, concluding with February, the
                    season at which “great expiatory sacrifices were offered for the growth of the
                    whole creation in the last two months of the year.” We have no means of knowing
                    precisely what were the arrangements of the Phoenician calendar, but it is
                    generally admitted that the worship was solar, the principal festivals taking
                    place in spring and in autumn. Among the most characteristic celebrations of the
                    Egyptians were those which took place at the αφαι/ισ-μός or disappearance of
                    Osiris in October or November, at the search for his remains, and their
                    discovery about the winter solstice, and at the date of his supposed entrance
                    into the moon at the beginning of spring. The Phrygian festivals were also
                    arranged on the theory that the deity was asleep during the winter and awake
                    during the summer; in the autumn they celebrated his retiring to rest, and in
                    spring with mirth and revelry they roused him from his slumbers.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plutarch, <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Iside</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Osiride;</hi> Macrobius, <hi rend="italic">Saturnalia,</hi> i. 21.</p></note>
                    The seasonal character of the Teutonic Ostern, the Celtic Beltein, and the
                    Scandinavian Yule is obvious. Nor was the habit of observing such festivals
                    peculiar to the Aryan or the Semitic race. The Mexicans, who were remarkable for
                    the perfection of their calendar (see vol i. 695), had also an elaborate system
                    of movable and immovable feasts distributed over the entire year; the principal
                    festivals, however, in honour of their chiefs gods, Tezcatlipoca,
                    Huitzilopochtli, and Tlaloc, were held in May, June, and December. Still more
                    plainly connected with the revolutions of the seasons was the public worship of
                    the ancient Peruvians, who, besides the ordinary feast at each new moon,
                    observed four solar festivals annually. Of these the most important was the
                    Yntip-Raymi(Sun-feast), which,preceded byathree days’ fast, began with the
                    summer solstice, and lasted for nine days. Its ceremonies have been often
                    described. A similar but less important festival was held at the winter
                    solstice. The Çusqui-Raymi, held after seed-time, as the maize began to appear,
                    was celebrated with sacrifices and banquets, music and dancing. A fourth great
                    festival, called Citua, held on the first new moon after the autumnal equinox,
                    was preceded by a strict fast and special observances intended for purposes of
                    purification and expiation, after which the festivities lasted until the moon
                    entered her second quarter.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Greek Festivals.—</hi> Perhaps the annual Attic festival in
                    honour of Erechtheus alluded to in the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> (ii. 550)
                    ought to be regarded as an instance of ancestor-worship; but the seasonal
                    character of the <hi rend="italic">eopτη</hi> or new-moon feast in <hi
                    rend="italic">Od., XX. 156,</hi> and of the 0αλυσια or harvest-festival in <hi
                    rend="italic">H.,</hi> ix. 533, is generally acknowledged. The older Homeric
                    poems, however, give no such express indications of a fully-developed system of
                    festivals as are to be met with in the so-called “Homeric” hymns, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Works and Hays</hi> of Hesiod, in the pages of Herodotus, and so
                    abundantly in most authors of the subsequent period; and it is manifest that the
                    calendar of Homer or even of Herodotus must have been a much simpler matter than
                    that of the Tarentines, for example, came to be, of whom we are told by Strabo
                    that their holidays were in excess of their working days. Each demos of ancient
                    Greece during the historical period had its own local festivals (∈opται <hi
                    rend="italic">δημοτικοί),</hi> often largely attended and splendidly solemnized,
                    the usages of which, though essentially alike, differed very considerably in
                    details. These details have in many cases been wholly lost, and in others have
                    reached us only in a very fragmentary state. But with regard to the Athenian
                    calendar, the most interesting of all, our means of information are fortunately
                    very copious. It included some 50 or 60 days on which all business, and
                    especially the administration of justice, was by order of the magistrates
                    suspended. Among these <hi rend="italic">lcpομηνiαι</hi> were included—in
                    Gamelion (January), the <hi rend="italic">Lenoea</hi> or wine-press feast in
                    honour of Dionysus; in Anthesterion (February), the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anthesteria,</hi> also in honour of Dionysus, lasting three days (Pithoigia,
                    Choes, and Chutroi); the <hi rend="italic">Diasia</hi> in honour of Zeus, and
                    the lesser <hi rend="italic">Eleusinia;</hi> in Elaphebolion (March), the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pandia</hi> of Zeus, the <hi rend="italic">Elaphe-bolia</hi> of
                    Artemis, and the greater <hi rend="italic">Dionysia</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    in Munychion, the <hi rend="italic">Munychia</hi> of Artemis as the moon goddess
                    (Mowυχiα) and the <hi rend="italic">Delphinia</hi> of Apollo; in Thargelion
                    (May), the <hi rend="italic">Thargelia</hi> of Apollo and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Plynteria</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Callynteria</hi> of Athene; in
                    Skirophorion (June), the <hi rend="italic">Diipolia</hi> of Zeus and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Skirophοria</hi> of Athene; in Hekatombaion hecatombs were offered
                    to Apollo the summer-god, and the <hi rend="italic">Crania</hi> of Cronus and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Panothenoea</hi> of Athene were held; in Metageitnion, the
                    <hi rend="italic">Metageitnia</hi> of Apollo; in Boedromion, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Boedromia·</hi> of .Apollo the helper,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In this month the anniversaries of the battle
                    of Marathon, and of the downfall of the thirty tyrants, were also publicly
                    celebrated.</p></note> the <hi rend="italic">Nekusia</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nemeseia</hi> (the festival of the dead), and the greater <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eleusinia</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> in Pyanepsion, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pyanepsia</hi> of Apollo, the <hi rend="italic">Qscho-phoria</hi> of Dionysus
                    (probably), the <hi rend="italic">Chalkeia</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Athenaea</hi> of Athene, the <hi rend="italic">Thesmophoria</hi> of Demeter,
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Apaturia;</hi> in Maimakterion, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Maimakteria</hi> of Zeus; and in Poseideon (December), the lesser <hi
                    rend="italic">Hiσnysia.</hi></p>
                <p>Of these (for the more important of which reference is made to the separate
                    articles) some are commemorative of historical events, and one at least may
                    perhaps be regarded as a relic of ancestor-worship; but the great majority are
                    nature-festivals, associating themselves in the manner that has already been
                    indicated with the phenomena of the seasons, the equinoxes and the
                    solstices.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Schoemann, <hi rend="italic">Griechische</hi><hi rend="italic">Alterthümer,</hi>
                    ii. 439 sq.; Mommsen. <hi rend="italic">Ueortologie.</hi></p></note> In addition
                    to their numerous public festivals, the Greeks held various family celebrations,
                    also called <hi rend="italic">eορταl,</hi> in connexion with weddings, births,
                    and similar domestic occurrences. The great national <hi rend="italic"
                    >τravηγυpeις—</hi> Olympian, Pythian, Nemean, and Isthmian—will be found under
                    separate headings.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Boman Festivals.—</hi> For the purpose of holding comitia and
                    administering justice, the days of the Roman year were regarded as being either
                    dies fasti or dies nefasti—the dies fasti being the days on which it was lawful
                    for the praetors to administer justice in the public courts, while on the dies
                    nefasti neither courts of justice nor meetings of comitia were allowed to be
                    held. Some days were fasti during one portion and nefasti during another; these
                    were called dies intercisi For the purposes of religion a different division of
                    the year was made; the days were treated as festi or as profesti,—the former
                    being consecrated to acts of public worship, such as sacrifices, banquets, and
                    games, while the latter (whether fasti or nefasti) were not specially claimed
                    for religious purposes. The dies festi or feriae <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n124/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0124-0115"/> publicae<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Feriae private, such as anniversaries of births, deaths, and
                    the like, were observed by separate clans, families, or individuals.</p></note>
                    were either stativae, conceptivae, or imperativae. The stativae were such as
                    were observed regularly, each on a definite day; the conceptivae were observed
                    annually on days fixed by the authorities for the time being; the imperativae
                    were publicly appointed as occasion called for them. In the Augustan age the
                    feriae stativae were very numerous, as may be seen from what we possess of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Fasti</hi> of Ovid. The number was somewhat fluctuating.
                    Festivals frequently fell into desuetude or were revived, were increased or
                    diminished, were shortened or prolonged at the will of the emperor, or under the
                    caprice of the popular taste. Thus Augustus restored the Compitalia and
                    Lupercalia; while Marcus Antoninus in his turn found it expedient to diminish
                    the number of holidays.</p>
                <p>The following is an enumeration of the stated festivals as given by Ovid and
                    contemporary writers. The first day of January was observed somewhat as is the
                    modem New Year’s Day: clients sent presents to their patrons, slaves to their
                    masters, friends and relations to one another. On the 9th the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Agonalia</hi> were held, apparently in honour of Janus. On the 11th the <hi
                    rend="italic">Carmentalia</hi> were kept as a halfholiday, but principally by
                    women; so also on the 15th. On the 13th of February were the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Faunalia,</hi> on the 15th the <hi rend="italic">Lupercalia,</hi> on the 17 th
                    the <hi rend="italic">Quirinalia,</hi> on the 18th the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Feralia,</hi> on the 23d (at one time the last day of the Roman year) the <hi
                    rend="italic">Terminalia,</hi> on the 24th the <hi rend="italic">Regifugium</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">Fugalia,</hi> and on the 27th the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Equiria</hi> (of Mars). On the 1st of March were the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Matronalia,</hi> on the 14th a repetition of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Equiria,</hi> on the 15th the festival of Anna Perenna, on the 17th the <hi
                    rend="italic">Liberalia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Agonalia,</hi> and from the
                    19th to the 23d the <hi rend="italic">Quinquatria</hi> (of Minerva). On the 4th
                    of April were the <hi rend="italic">Megalesia</hi> (of Cybele), on the 12th the
                    <hi rend="italic">Cerecdia,</hi> on the 21st the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Palilia·,</hi> on the 23d the <hi rend="italic">Vinalia,</hi> on the 25th the
                    <hi rend="italic">Robigalia,</hi> and on the 28th the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Floralia.</hi> The 1st of May was the festival of the Lares Praestites; on the
                    9th, llth, and 13th the <hi rend="italic">Lemuria</hi> were celebrated; on the
                    12th the <hi rend="italic">Ludi</hi><hi rend="italic">Martiales,</hi> and on the
                    15th those of Mercury. June 5 was sacred to Semo Sancus; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vestalia</hi> occurred on the 9th, the <hi rend="italic">Matralia</hi> on the
                    llth, and the <hi rend="italic">Quinquatrus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Minusculoe</hi> on the 13th. The <hi rend="italic">Ludi Apollinares</hi> were
                    on the 5th, and the <hi rend="italic">Neptunalia</hi> on the 23d of July. On the
                    13th of August were the <hi rend="italic">Nemoralia,</hi> in honour of Diana; on
                    the 18th the <hi rend="italic">Consualia,</hi> on the 19th the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vinalia Rustica,</hi> and on the 23d the <hi rend="italic">Vulcanalia.</hi> The
                    <hi rend="italic">Ludi Magni,</hi> in honour of Jupiter, Juno, and Minerva,
                    began on September 4. The <hi rend="italic">Meditrinalia</hi> (new wine) were on
                    the 1 lth of October, the <hi rend="italic">Faunalia</hi> on the 13th, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Equina</hi> on the 15th. The <hi rend="italic">Epulum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Jovis</hi> was on 13th November. The December festivals were—on
                    the 5th <hi rend="italic">Faunalia,</hi> and towards the close <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opalia,</hi><hi rend="italic">Saturnalia,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Larentalia.</hi></p>
                <p>The calendar as it stood at the Augustan age was known to contain many
                    comparatively recent accessions, brought in under the influence of two “closely
                    allied powers, the foreign priest and the foreign cook” (Mommsen). The
                    Megalesia, for example, had been introduced 204 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    The Ludi Apollinares could not be traced further back than 208 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The Floralia and Cerealia had not come in much
                    earlier. Among the oldest feasts were undoubtedly the Lupercalia, in honour of
                    Lupercus, the god of fertility; the Equiria, in honour of Mars; the Palilia; the
                    great September festival; and the Saturnalia.</p>
                <p>Among the feriae conceptivae were the very ancient feriae Latinae, held in honour
                    of Jupiter on the Alban Mount, and attended by all the higher magistrates and
                    the whole body of the senate. The time of their celebration greatly depended on
                    the state of affairs at Rome, as the consuls were not allowed to take the field
                    until they had held the Latinae, which were regarded as days of a sacred truce.
                    The feriae sementivae were held in the spring, and the Ambarvalia in autumn,
                    both in honour of Ceres. The Paganalia of each pagus, and the Compitalia of each
                    vicus were also conceptivae. Of feriae imperativae,—that is to say, festivals
                    appointed by the senate, or magistrates, or higher priests to commemorate some
                    great event or avert some threatened disaster,—the best known is the Novendiale,
                    which used to be celebrated as often as stones fell from heaven (Livy, xxi. 62,
                    XXV. 7, &amp;c.). In addition to all those already mentioned, there occasionally
                    occurred ludi votivi, which were celebrated in fulfilment of a vow; ludi
                    funebres, sometimes given by private persons; and ludi seculares, to celebrate
                    certain periods marked off in the Etrusco-Roman religion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Feasts of the Jews.—</hi> By Old Testament writers a festival
                    or feast is generally called either J∏ (compare the Arabic Hadj), from 3J¾ to
                    rejoice, or ΙJ∏D, from "∣PJ, to appoint. The words and B∖fp K∏pD are also
                    occasionally used. In the Talmud the three principal feasts are called Ο'?$Ί,
                    after Exod. xxiii. 14. Of the Jewish feasts which are usually traced to a
                    pre-Mosaic origin the most important and characteristic was the weekly Sabbath,
                    but special importance was also attached from a very early date to the lunar
                    periods. It is probable that other festivals also, of a seasonal character, were
                    observed (see Exod. v. 1). In common with most others, the Mosaic system of
                    annual feasts groups itself readily around the vernal and autumnal equinoxes. In
                    Lev. xxiii., where the list is most fully given, they seem to be arranged with a
                    conscious reference to the sacred number seven (compare Numb. xxviii. ). Those
                    belonging to the vernal equinox are three in number; a preparatory day, that of
                    the Passover, leads up to the principal festival, that of unleavened bread,
                    which again is followed by an after-feast, that of Pentecost (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Passover, Pentecost).</hi> Those of the autumnal equinox are
                    four; a preparatory day on the new moon of the seventh month (the Feast of
                    Trumpets) is followed by a great day of rest, the day of Atonement (which,
                    however, was hardly a <hi rend="italic">festival</hi> in the stricter sense of
                    the word), by the Feast of Tabernacles, and by a great concluding day (Lev.
                    xxiii. 36; John vii. 37). If the feast of the Passover be excepted, it will be
                    seen that all these celebrations or commemorations associate themselves more
                    readily with natural than w ith historical events.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In the “parallel” passages, there is
                    considerable variety in the designation and arrangement of these feasts. While
                    Ex. xii. approximates most closely to Lev. xxiii. and Num. xxviii., Ex. xxiii.
                    has stronger affinities with Dent. xvi. The relations of these passages are
                    largely discussed by Graf, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichtlichen Bücher</hi><hi rend="italic">des A. Τ.,</hi> pp. 34-41, and by
                    other recent critics.</p></note> There was also a considerable number of
                    post-Mosaic festivals, of which the principal were that of the Dedication
                    (described in 1 Macc. iv. 52-59; comp. John X. 22) and that of Purim, the origin
                    of which is given in the book of Esther (ix. 20 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi> It
                    has probably no connexion with the Persian festival Furdigân (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Esther).</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>On the whole subject of Jewish festivals see Reland, <hi
                    rend="italic">Antig. Hebr.;</hi> Knobel, <hi rend="italic">Leviticus</hi> (c.
                    23); George, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Jüdischen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Festi;</hi> Hupfeld, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >primitiva</hi><hi rend="italic">fest. ap. Hebr.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ratione;</hi> Ewald, <hi rend="italic">Alterthümer des Volkes Israel;</hi>
                    Dillmann in Schenkel⅛ <hi rend="italic">Βibel-lexicon,</hi> art.
                    “Feste.”</p></note><hi rend="italic">Earlier Christian Festivals.—</hi> While
                    making it abundantly manifest that Christ and His disciples observed the
                    appointed Jewish feasts, the New Testament nowhere records the formal
                    institution of any distinctively Christian festival. But we have unambiguous
                    evidence of the actual observance, from a very early period, of the first day of
                    the week as a holy day (John xx. 19, 26; 1 Cor. xvi. 2; Acts XX. 7; Rev. i. 10).
                    Pliny in his letter to Trajan describes the Christians of Bithynia as meeting
                    for religious purposes on a set day; that this day was Sunday is put beyond all
                    reasonable doubt by such a passage as that in the <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>
                    of Justin Martyr, where he says that “on Sunday (τp τoυ <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n125/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0125-0116"/><hi rend="italic">ηλiov λcγoμwy η</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">Hp&lt;ι)</hi> all the Christians living
                    either in the city or the country met together.” The Jewish element, in some
                    churches at least, and especially in the East, was strong enough to secure that,
                    along with the <hi rend="italic">dies</hi><hi rend="italic">dominica,</hi> the
                    seventh day should continue to be kept holy. Thus in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apostolic Constitutions</hi> (ii. 59) we find the Saturday specially mentioned
                    along with the Sunday as a day for the assembling of the church; in v. 15 it is
                    ordained that there shall be no fasting on Saturday, while in viii. 33 it is
                    added that both on Saturday and Sunday slaves are to have rest from their
                    labours. The 16th canon of the council of Laodicea almost certainly means that
                    solemn public service was to be held on Saturday as well as on Sunday. In other
                    quarters, however, the tendency to regard both days as equally sacred met with
                    considerable resistance. The 36th canon of the council of Illiberis, for
                    example, deciding that Saturday should be observed as a fa3t-day, was doubtless
                    intended to enforce the distinction between Saturday and Sunday. At Milan in
                    Ambrose’s time Saturday was observed as a festival; but Pope Innocent is found
                    writing to the bishop of Eugubium to urge that it should be kept as a fast.
                    Ultimately the Christian church came to recognize but one weekly festival.</p>
                <p>The numerous yearly festivals of the later Christian church, when historically
                    investigated, can be traced to very small beginnings. Indeed, while it appears
                    to be tolerably certain that Jewish Christians for the most part retained all
                    the festivals which had been instituted under the old dispensation, it is not at
                    all probable that either they or their Gentile brethren recognized any yearly
                    feasts as of distinctively Christian origin or obligation. It cannot be doubted,
                    however, that gradually, in the course of the 2d century, the universal church
                    came to observe the anniversaries of the death and resurrection of Christ —the
                    πάσχα <hi rend="italic">σταυρωσιμον</hi> and the πάσχα <hi rend="italic"
                    >άναστάσιμον,</hi> as they were respectively called (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Easter</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Good Friday).</hi> Not long afterwards
                    Whitsunday also came to be fixed in the usage of Christendom as a great annual
                    festival. Even Origen (in the 8th book <hi rend="italic">Against</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Celsus)</hi> enumerates as Christian festivals the Sunday, the
                    7rαpα- <hi rend="italic">σκ,evη,</hi> the Passover with the feast of the
                    Resurrection, and Pentecost; under which latter term, however, he includes the
                    whole period between Easter and Whitsuntide. About Cyprian’s time we find
                    individual Christians commemorating their departed friends, and whole churches
                    commemorating their martyrs; in particular, there are traces of a local and
                    partial observance of the feast of the Innocents. Christmas day and Epiphany
                    were among the later introductions, the feast of the Epiphany being somewhat the
                    earlier of the two. Both are alluded to indeed by Clemens Alexandrinuβ (L 310),
                    but only in a way which indicates that even in his time the precise date of
                    Christ’s birth was unknow-n, that its anniversary was not usually observed, and
                    that the day of his baptism was kept as a festival only by the followers of
                    Basilides (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Epiphany).</hi></p>
                <p>When we come down to the 4th century we find that, among the 50 days between
                    Easter and Pentecost, Ascension day has come into new prominence. .Augustine,
                    for example, enumerates as anniversaries celebrated by the whole church those of
                    Christ’s passion, resurrection, and ascension, along with that of the outpouring
                    of the Holy Ghost, while he is silent with regard ta Christmas and Epiphany. The
                    general tendency of this and the following centuries was largely to increase the
                    festivals of the church, and by legislation to make them more fixed and uniform.
                    Many passages, indeed, could be quoted from Chrysostom, Jerome, and Augustine to
                    show that these fathers had not by any means forgotten that comparative freedom
                    with regard to outward observances was one of the distinctive excellencies of
                    Christianity as contrasted with Judaism and the various heathen systems (compare
                    Socrates, <hi rend="italic">H. E.,</hi> v. 22). But there were many special
                    circumstances which seemed to the leaders of the Church at that time to
                    necessitate the permission and even legislative sanction of a large number of
                    new feasts. The innovations of heretice sometimes seemed to call for
                    rectification by the institution of more orthodox observances; in other
                    instances the propensity of rude and uneducated converts from paganism to cling
                    to the festal rites of their forefathers proved to be invincible, so that it was
                    seen to be necessary to seek to adapt the old usages to the new worship rather
                    than to abolish them altogether;<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>As, at a later period (601), Gregory the Great instructed
                    his Anglo-Saxon missionaries so to Christianize the temples, festivals, &amp;c.,
                    of the heathen “ut durae mentes gradibus vel passibus, non autem saltibus,
                    eleventur.”</p></note> moreover, although the empire had become Christian, it
                    was manifestly expedient that the old holidays should be recognized as much as
                    possible in the new arrangements of the calendar. Constantine soon after his
                    conversion enacted that on the <hi rend="italic">dies</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dominica</hi> there should be no suits or trials in law; Theodosius the Great
                    added a prohibition of all public shows on that day, and Theodosius the younger
                    extended the prohibition to Epiphany and the anniversaries of martyrdoms, which
                    at that time included the festivals of St Stephen, and of St Peter and St Paul,
                    as also that of the Maccabees. In the 21st canon of the council of Agde (506),
                    besides Easter, Christmas, Epiphany, Ascension, and Pentecost, we find the
                    Nativity of John the Baptist already mentioned as one of the more important
                    festivals on which attendance at church was regarded as obligatory. To these
                    were added, in the centuries immediately following, the feasts of the
                    Annunciation, the Purification, and the Assumption of the Virgin; as well as
                    those of the Circumcision, of St Michael, and of All Saints.</p>
                <p>Festivals were in practice distinguished from ordinary days in the following
                    ways:—all public and judicial business was suspended,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Manumission, however, was lawful on any
                    day.</p></note> as well as every kind of game or amusement which might interfere
                    with devotion; the churches were specially decorated; Christians were expected
                    to attend public worship, attired in their best dress; love feasts were
                    celebrated, and the rich were accustomed to show special kindness to the poor;
                    fasting was strictly forbidden, and public prayers were said in a standing
                    posture.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Later Practice.—</hi> In the present calendar of the Roman
                    Catholic Church the number of feast days is very large. Each is celebrated by an
                    appropriate office, which, according to its character, is either duplex,
                    semi-duplex, or simplex. A duplex again may be either of the first class or of
                    the second, or a major or a minor. The distinctions of ritual for each of these
                    are given with great minuteness in the general rubrics of the breviary; they
                    turn chiefly on the number of Psalms to be sung and of lessons to be read, on
                    the manner in which the antiphons are to be given, and on similar details. The
                    duplicia of the first class are the Nativity, the Epiphany, Easter with the
                    three preceding and two following days, the Ascension, Whitsunday and the two
                    following days, Corpus Christi, the Nativity of John Baptist, Saints Peter and
                    Paul, the Assumption of the Virgin, All Saints, and, for each church, the feast
                    proper to its patron or title and the feast of its dedication. The duplicia of
                    the second class are the Circumcision, the feast of the Holy Name of Jesus, of
                    the Holy Trinity, and of the Most Precious Blood of Christ, the feasts of the
                    Purification, Annunciation, Visitation, Nativity, and Conception of the Virgin,
                    the Natalitia of the Twelve Apostles, the feasts of the Evangelists, of St
                    Stephen, of the Holy Innocents, of St Joseph and of the Patrocinium of Joseph,
                    of St Lawrence, of the Invention of the Cross, and of the Dedication of <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n126/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0126-0117"/> St Michael. The Dominicae majores of the first
                    class are the first Sunday in Advent, the first in Lent, Passion Sunday, Palm
                    Sunday, Easter Sunday, Dominica in Albis, Whitsunday, and Trinity Sunday; the
                    Dominicae majores of the second class are the second, third, and fourth in
                    Advent, Septuagesima, Sexagesima, and Quinquagesima Sundays, and the second,
                    third, and fourth Sundays in Lent.</p>
                <p>In the canons and decrees of the council of Trent repeated allusions are made to
                    the feast days, and their fitness, when properly observed, to promote piety.
                    Those entrusted with the cure of soule are urged to see that the feasts of the
                    church be devoutly and religiously observed, the faithful are enjoined to attend
                    public worship on Sundays and on the greater festivals at least, and parish
                    priests are bidden expound to the people on such days some of the things which
                    have been read in the office for the day. Since the council of Trent, the
                    practice of the church with respect to the prohibition of servile work on
                    holidays has varied considerably in different Catholic countries, and even in
                    the same country at different times. Thus in 1577, in the diocese of Lyons,
                    there were almost 40 annual festivals of a compulsory character. By the
                    concordat of 1802 the number of such festivals was for France reduced to four,
                    namely, Christmas day, Ascension day, the Assumption of the Virgin, and All
                    Saints day.</p>
                <p>The calendar of the Greek Church is even fuller than that of the Latin,
                    especially a3 regards the copταl <hi rend="italic">τωv</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >άγιων.</hi> Thu3 on the last Sunday in Advent the feast of All Saints of the
                    Old Covenant is celebrated; while Adam and Eve, Job, Elijah, Isaiah, &amp;c.,
                    have separate days. The distinctions of ritual are analogous to those in the
                    Western Church. In the Coptic Church there are seven great festivals, Christmas,
                    Epiphany, the Annunciation, Palm Sunday, Easter Sunday, Ascension, and
                    Whitsunday, on all of which the Copts “wear now clothes (or the best they have),
                    feast, and give alms” (Lane). They also observe, as minor festivals, Maundy
                    Thursday, Holy Saturday, the feast of the Apostles (11th July), and that of the
                    Discovery of the Cros3,</p>
                <p>In common with most of the churches of the Reformation, the Church of England
                    retained a certain number of fea3t3 beside3 all Sundays in the year. They are,
                    besides Monday anl Tuesday both in Easter-week and Whitsunweek, as follows :—the
                    Circumcision, the Epiphany, the Conversion of St Paul, the Purification of the
                    Blessed Virgin, St Matthias the Apostle, the Annunciation of the Blessed Virgin,
                    St Mark the Evangelist, St Philip and St James (Apostles), the Ascension, St
                    Barnabas, the Nativity of St John Baptist, St Peter the Apostle, St James the
                    Apostle, St Bartholomew, St Matthew, St Michael and all Angels, St Luke the
                    Evangelist, St Simon and St Jude, All Saints, St Andrew, St Thomas, Christmas,
                    St Stephen, St John the Evangelist, the Holy Innocents. The 13th canon enjoins
                    that all manner of persons within the Church of England shall from henceforth
                    celebrate and keep the Lord’s day, commonly called Sunday, and other holy days,
                    according to God’s holy will and pleasure, and the orders of the Church of
                    England prescribed in that behalf, that is, in hearing the Word of God read and
                    taught, in private and public prayers, in acknowledging their offences to God
                    and amendment of the same, in reconciling themselves charitably to their
                    neighbours where displeasure hath been, in oftentimes receiving the communion of
                    the body and blood of Christ, in visiting of the poor and sick, using all godly
                    and sober conversation. (Compare Hooker, <hi rend="italic">E. P.,</hi> v. 70. )
                    In the <hi rend="italic">Directory for the Public Worship of God</hi> which was
                    drawn up by the Westminster Assembly, and accepted by the Church of Scotland in
                    1645, there is an appendix which declares that there is no day commanded in
                    Scripture to be kept holy under the gospel but the Lord’s day, which is the
                    Christian Sabbath; festival days, vulgarly called holy-days, having no warrant
                    in the Word of God, are not to be continued; nevertheless it is lawful and
                    necessary, upon special emergent occasions, to separate a day or days for public
                    fasting or thanksgiving, as the several eminent and extraordinary dispensations
                    of God’s providence shall administer cause and opportunity to his people.</p>
                <p>Several attempts have been made at various times in western Europe to reorganize
                    the festival system on some other scheme than the Christian. Thus at the time of
                    the French Revolution, during the period of Robespierre’s ascendency, it was
                    proposed to substitute a tenth day (Décadi) for the weekly rest, and to
                    introduce the following new festivals :—that of the Supreme Being and of Nature,
                    of the Human Race, of the French People, of the Benefactors of Mankind, of
                    Freedom and Equality, of the Martyrs of Freedom, of the Republic, of the Freedom
                    of the World, of Patriotism, of Hatred of Tyrants and Traitors, of Truth, of
                    Justice, of Modesty, of Fame and Immortality, of Friendship, of Temperance, of
                    Heroism, of Fidelity, of Unselfishness, of Stoicism, of Love, of Conjugal
                    Fidelity, of Filial Affection, of Childhood, of Youth, of Manhood, of Old Age,
                    of Misfortune, of Agriculture, of Industry, of our Forefathers, of Posterity and
                    Felicity. The proposal, however, was never fully carried out, and soon fell into
                    oblivion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mahometan Festivals.—</hi> These are chiefly two—the ’Eed
                    es-Sagheer (or minor festival) and the’Eed el-Kebeer(or great festival),
                    sometimes called ’Eed el-Kurban. The former, which lasts for three day3,
                    immediately follows the month Ramadan, and is generally the more joyful of the
                    two; the latter begins on the tenth of Zu-l-Heggeh (the last month of the
                    Mahometan year), and lasts for three or four days. Besides these festivals they
                    usually keep holy the first ten days of Moharram (the first month of the year),
                    especially the tenth day, called Yom Ashoora; the birthday of the prophet, on
                    the twelfth day of the third month; the birthday of El-Hoseyn, in the fourth
                    month; the anniversary of the prophet’s miraculous ascension into heaven, in the
                    seventh month; and one or two other anniversaries (see vol. vii. p. 727).
                    Friday, called the day of El-Gumah (the assembly), is a day of public worship;
                    but it is not usual to abstain from public business on that day except during
                    the time of prayer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hindu and Buddhist Festivals.—</hi> In modern India the leading
                    popular festivals are the Holi, which is held in March or April and lasts for
                    five days, and the Dasahara, which occurs in October (see Hunter’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Statistical Account of Bengali).</hi> Although in its origin
                    Buddhism was a deliberate reaction against all ceremonial, it does not now
                    refuse to observe festivals. By Buddhists in China, for example, three days in
                    the year are especially observed in honour of the Buddha,—the eighth day of the
                    second month, when he left his home; the eighth day of the fourth month, the
                    anniversary of his birthday; and the eighth of the twelfth, when he attained to
                    perfection and entered Nirvana. In Siam the eighth and fifteenth days of every
                    month are considered holy, and are observed as days for rest and worship. At
                    Trut, the festival of the close of the year, visiting and play-going are
                    universal. The new year (January) is celebrated for three days; in February is
                    another holiday; in April is a sort of Lent, ushering in the rainy season; on
                    the last day of J une presents are made of cakes of the new rice; in August is
                    the festival of the angel of the river, “whθ3θ forgiveness is then asked for
                    every act by which the waters of the Meinam have been rendered impure.” See
                    Bowring’s <hi rend="italic">Siam</hi> and Carné’s <hi rend="italic">Travels in
                    Indo-China and the Chinese Empire.</hi> Copious details of the elaborate
                    festival-system of the Chinese may be found in Doolittle's <hi rend="italic"
                    >Social Life of the Chinese.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> s. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">bl.)</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n127/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0127-0118"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
