<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0202-0193-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FINE (9th edition, volume 9, page 193)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1007857">Manors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137633">Suites</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cr5nn2t">Tenants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n202/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FINE</label>, in law, is a pecuniary penalty inflicted for
                    the less serious offences. Fines are necessarily discretionary as to amount; but
                    a maximum is generally fixed when the penalty is imposed by statute. And it is
                    an old constitutional maxim that fines must not be unreasonable. In Magna
                    Charta, c. Ill, it is ordained “<hi rend="italic">Liber homo non amercietur
                    pro</hi><hi rend="italic">parvo</hi><hi rend="italic">delicto nisi
                    secundum</hi><hi rend="italic">modum ipsius</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >delicti,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">pro magno delicto
                    secundum</hi><hi rend="italic">magnitudinem</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >delicti”</hi></p>
                <p>The term is also applied to payments made to the lord of a manor on the
                    alienation of land held according to the custom of the manor, to payments made
                    on the renewal of leases granted by ecclesiastical and other corporations, and
                    to other similar payments.</p>
                <p>Fine also denotes a fictitious suit at law, which played the part of a conveyance
                    of landed property. “A fine,” says Blackstone, “may be described to be an
                    amicable composition or agreement of a suit, either actual or fictitious, by
                    leave of the king or his justices, whereby the lands in question become or are
                    acknowledged to be the right of one of the parties. In its original it was
                    founded on an actual suit commenced at law for the recovery of the possession of
                    land or other hereditaments; and the possession thus gained by such composition
                    was found to be so sure and effectual that fictitious actions were and continue
                    to bo every day commenced for the sake of obtaining the same security.” Freehold
                    estates could thus be transferred from one person to another without the formal
                    delivery of possession which was generally necessary to a feoffment. This is one
                    of the oldest devices of the law. A statute of 18 Edward I. describes it as the
                    most solemn and satisfactory of securities, and gives a reason for its name—“Qui
                    quidem finis sic vocatur, eo quod finis et consummatio omnium placitorum esse
                    debet, et hac de causa providebatur.” The action was supposed to be founded on a
                    breach of covenant: the defendant, owning himself in the wrong,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hence called <hi
                    rend="italic">cognizor;</hi> the other party, the purchaser, is the <hi
                    rend="italic">cognizee.</hi></p></note> makes overtures of compromise, which are
                    authorized<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n203/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0203-0194"/> by the <hi rend="italic">licentia
                    concordandi;</hi> then followed the concord, or the compromise itself. These,
                    then, were the essential parts of the performance, which became efficient as
                    soon as they were complete; the formal parts were the <hi rend="italic"
                    >nots,</hi> or abstract of the proceedings, and the <hi rend="italic">foot</hi>
                    of the fine, which recited the final agreement. Fines were said to be of four
                    kinds, according to the purpose they had in view, as for instance, to convey
                    lands in pursuance of a covenant, to grant reversionary interest only, &amp;c.
                    In addition to the formal record of the proceedings, various statutes required
                    other solemnities to be observed, the great object of which was to give
                    publicity to the transaction. Thus by statutes of Richard III. and Henry VII.
                    the fine had to be openly read and proclaimed in court no less than sixteen
                    times. A statute of Elizabeth required a list of fines to be exposed in the
                    Court of Common Pleas and at assizes. The reason ſor these formalities was the
                    high and important nature of the conveyance, which, according to the Act of
                    Edward I. above mentioned, “precludes not only those which are parties and
                    privies to the fine and their heirs, but all other persons in the world who are
                    of full age, out of prison, of sound memory, and within the four seas, the day
                    of the fine levied, unless they put in their claim on the foot of the fine
                    within a year and a day.” This barring by <hi rend="italic">non-claim</hi> was
                    abolished in the reign of Edward III., but restored with an extension of the
                    time to five years in the reign of Henry VII. The effect of this statute,
                    intentional according to Blackstone, unintended and brought about by judicial
                    construction according to others, was that a tenantin-tail could bar his issue
                    by a fine. A statute of Henry VIII. expressly declares this to be the law.
                    Fines, along with the kindred fiction of recoveries, were abolished by statute 3
                    and 4 Will. IV. c. 74, which substituted a deed enrolled in the Court of
                    Chancery.</p>
                <p>Fines are so generally associated in legal phraseology with recoveries that it
                    may not be inconvenient to describe the latter in the present place. A recovery
                    was employed as a means for evading the strict law of entail. The purchaser or
                    alienee brought an action against the tenant in-tail, alleging that he had no
                    legal title to the land. The tenant-in-tail brought a third person into court,
                    declaring that be had warranted his title, and praying that he might be ordered
                    to defend the action. This person was called the <hi rend="italic">vouchee,</hi>
                    and he, after having appeared to defend the action, takes himself out of the
                    way. Judgment for the lands is given in favour of the plaintiff; and judgment to
                    recover lands of equal value from the vouchee was given to the defendant, the
                    tenant-in-tail. In a real action, such lands when recovered would have fallen
                    under the settlement of entail; but in the fictitious recovery the vouchee was a
                    man of straw, and nothing was really recovered from him, while the lands of the
                    tenant-in-tail were effectually conveyed to the successful plaintiff. A recovery
                    differed from a fine, as to <hi rend="italic">form,</hi> in being an action
                    carried through to the end, while a fine was settled by compromise, and as to
                    effect, by barring all reversions and remainders in estates tail, while a fine
                    barred the issue only of the tenant. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. e.)</hi></p>
                <p>THE FINE ARTS</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
