<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0768-0733-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FREDERICK WILLIAM (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    733)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n768/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FREDERICK WILLIAM</label> (1620-1688), elector of
                    Brandenburg, was born in Berlin in 1620. He is usually called “The Great
                    Elector,” and next to Frederick the Great he was the chief founder of the power
                    of Prussia. A man of immense energy and determination, he devoted himself to his
                    country, missing no opportunity, whether by intrigue or by force of arms, of
                    adding to its extent and its influence. When at the age of twenty (1640) he
                    succeeded to the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n769/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0769-0734"/> electorate, he found it almost ruined. His
                    father, George William, being of feeble and vacillating character, had been
                    unable to prevent the inroads of the contending armies during the Thirty Years’
                    War; and they had laid waste nearly the whole land, and treated the inhabitants
                    with horrible cruelty. Frederick William, by skilful management, succeeded in
                    getting rid of these barbarous hordes, and by slow degrees collected an army of
                    about 30,000 men, which very effectually secured for him the respect of his
                    neighbours. It was universally admitted that he was the true heir of the dukes
                    of Pomerania, whose line died out in 1637; but at the Peace of Westphalia the
                    lion’s share of their territory was ceded to Sweden, Frederick William receiving
                    only the eastern half of the country, shorn of Stettin. But he also obtained the
                    bishoprics of Halberstadt, Minden, and Camin, with a promise of the
                    archbishopric of Magdeburg. In 1655 war broke out between Sweden and Poland.
                    Charles Gustavus, king of Sweden, compelled Frederick William to join him, and
                    to do homage for Prussia, which had formerly been held in fief of Poland. After
                    a battle of three days at Warsaw, the Poles were defeated (1656). In the
                    following year the elector turned round and concluded an alliance with the
                    Poles, receiving, by the treaty of Wehlau, in return for the promise of his aid
                    an acknowledgment of the complete independence of Prussia. Charles Gustavus
                    uttered fierce threats of vengeance, but was prevented by sudden death from
                    attempting to execute them. Frederick William had much trouble in inducing the
                    states of Prussia to do homage to him as their sole lawful sovereign; but by a
                    happy mingling of severity and kindness, he overcame in the end all opposition.
                    As duke of Prussia he was now an absolutely independent sovereign, although
                    still owing allegiance to the emperor for his other dominions. In 1666 he
                    received, by the settlement of the Jülich-Cleve dispute, the duchy of Cleve
                    proper, and the counties of Mark and Ravenstein; while Jülich and Berg were to
                    fall to Brandenburg in the event of the Pfalz-Neuburg line dying out. When Louis
                    XIV. invaded the Netherlands in 1674, Frederick William saw the danger which
                    threatened Germany, and his own territories in particular; he therefore
                    persuaded the emperor, various German princes, and the king of Denmark to form
                    an alliance against the French. He soon withdrew from this contest, but in the
                    war which began with the second French invasion of the Netherlands in 1674 he
                    took a leading part. The Swedes sided with France, and were persuaded by Louis
                    XIV. to invade Brandenburg, which they easily overran and devastated. The
                    elector was unable to leave the seat of war for some time, but at last, in the
                    summer of 1675, set out from Franconia, hastening forward with his cavalry,
                    directing the infantry to follow as speedily as possible. Halting at Magdeburg,
                    he heard that the Swedes were divided into three parties, and that the middle
                    party was not more than forty miles off. Although overtaken only by a small body
                    of his infantry, he rapidly advanced on this middle party, and on June 18, at
                    Fehrbellin, after a severe struggle, decisively defeated it. The rest of the
                    Swedes were then easily disposed of. He drove them not only from Brandenburg but
                    from Pomerania, of which he became complete master. Between three and four years
                    afterwards (about Christmas, 1678) they invaded Prussia, threatening Königsberg.
                    In the dead of winter Frederick started from Berlin with a powerful force, and
                    in the middle of January 1679 finally beat them, crossing the Frische Haff with
                    4000 men on sledges. After all, however, he did not obtain Pomerania, for when
                    the peace of St Germain en-Laye was concluded in 1679,Louis XIV. insisted on its
                    being restored to his ally,the king of Sweden. Frederick William, indignant at
                    Austria for allowing this, maintained for a time an alliance with</p>
                <p>France; but he had ultimately to cultivate the friendship of the emperor, from
                    whom he hoped to obtain the Silesian principalities of Liegnitz, Brieg, and
                    Wohlau, which, after 1675, he claimed as his by inheritance. He received the
                    circle of Schwiebus, in Silesia (1686), on condition that he should withdraw his
                    claim and send 8000 men to the help of the emperor in his war with the Turks.
                    Two years afterwards he died. Although famous as a soldier, he was even greater
                    as an administrator. He w as the most economical ruler of his age, yet did no
                    injustice to any branch of the state service. Among the most important of his
                    public works may be named the canal between the Oder and the Spree, which still
                    bears his name. After the revocation of the edict of Nantes, he welcomed large
                    numbers of French refugees to his dominions; and long before that time he had
                    offered every encouragement to Flemish settlers, thus giving a powerful impulse
                    to industry and commerce. He was twice married,—his first wife, Louise
                    Henrietta, being a pious and energetic lady, endowed with so clear and
                    penetrating an understanding that her husband took no important step without
                    consulting her.</p>
                <p>See Puffendorf, <hi rend="italic">De rebus</hi><hi rend="italic">gestis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Fridcrici Wilhclmi Magni</hi> (Berlin, 1695); Förster, <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">Friedrich Wilhelms</hi> (4th ed.,
                    Berlin 1855); W. Pierson, <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Grosse</hi><hi rend="italic">Kurfürst</hi> (Berlin, 1873); Carlyle, <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Friedrich II. of Prussia.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
