<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0799-0764-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FREIBURG, or Freyburg (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    764)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819857">Asylums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025892">Monuments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6270k">Asylums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39364">Monuments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n799/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FREIBURG, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Freyburg</hi></label>,
                    usually distinguished as Freiburg in the Breisgau, is a city formerly of the
                    Austrian dominions but now in the grand-duchy of Baden, about 12 miles E. of the
                    Rhine, at the foot of the Schlossberg, one of the heights of the Black Forest
                    range. It is one, of the stations on the railway between Basel and Mannheim, and
                    lies about 40 miles northwards from the former city. The town is for the most
                    part well built, having several wide and handsome streets and a number of
                    spacious squares. It is kept clean and cool by the waters of the Dreisam, which
                    flow through the streets in open channels; and its old fortifications have been
                    replaced by public walks, and, what is more unusual, by vineyards. Since 1827
                    Freiburg has been the seat of an archbishop who has authority over the bishops
                    of Mainz, Fulda, Rottenberg, and Limberg; and it possesses a famous Catholic
                    university, the <hi rend="italic">Ludovico Albertina,</hi> which owes its origin
                    to Albert VI., archduke of Austria, and dates from 1454, 1456, or 1457. This was
                    at one time a very wealthy institution, having been endowed by its founder with
                    extensive lands in the Breisgau, Upper Alsatia, and Wurtemberg; but since the
                    French Revolution it has lost nearly all its estates, and the revenue derived
                    from those still held in Baden is not sufficient for its expenses. In 1876 it
                    had 41 professors, ordinary and extraordinary, and 9 privat-docenten, and the
                    students numbered 290, of whom 141 were foreigners. The library contains upwards
                    of 250,000 volumes; and among the other <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n800/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0800-0765"/> auxiliary establishments are an anatomical hall
                    and museum and bo anical gardens. The Freiburg minster is considered one of the
                    finest of all the Gothic churches of Germany, being remarkable alike for the
                    symmetry of its proportions, for the taste of its decorations, and for the fact
                    that it may mor <hi rend="smallcaps">j</hi> correctly be said to be finished
                    than almost any other building of the kind. The period of its erection probably
                    lies for the most part between 1122 and 1252; bat the choir was not built till
                    1513. The tower, which rises above the western entrance, is 386 feet in height,
                    and it presents a skilful transition from a square base into an octagonal
                    superstructure, which in its turn is surmounted by a pyramidal spire of the most
                    exquisite open work in stone. In the interior of the church are some beautiful
                    stained glass windows, both ancient and modern, the tombstones of several of the
                    dukes of Zähringen, statues of archbishops of Freiburg, and paintings by Holbein
                    and by Hans Balding, surnamed Grün. Among the other noteworthy buildings of
                    Freiburg are the palaces of the grand duke and the arch bishop, the town hall,
                    the theatre, the <hi rend="italic">Kaufhaus</hi> or merchants’ hall, a
                    16th-century building with the front painted red, the Protestant church,
                    formerly the church of the abbey of Thennenbach, removed thither in 1839, the
                    hall of art and harmony, and the barracks, erected by the Austrian Government in
                    1776, and capable of containing 5000 men. The charitable institutions include a
                    foundling hospital, an orphan asylum, a blind asylum, and a military hospital.
                    In the centre of the fishmarket square is a fountain surmounted by a statue of
                    Duke Berthold III. of Zähringen, the founder of the city; in the Franciskaner
                    Platz there is a monument to Schwarz, the traditional discoverer of gunpowder;
                    the Rotteck Platz takes its name from the monument of Rotteck, the historian,
                    which formerly stood on the site of the Schwarz statue; and in Kaiser Wilhelm
                    Strasse a bronze statue was erected in 1876 to the memory of Herder, who in the
                    early part of the 19th century founded in Freiburg an institute for draughtsmen,
                    engravers, and lithographers, and carried on a famous bookselling business. On
                    the Schlossberg above the town there are massive ruins of two castles which were
                    destroyed by the French in 1744; and about two miles to the N.E. stands the
                    castle of Zähringen. the original seat of the famous family of counts. Situated
                    on the ancient road which runs by the Höllenpass between the valleys of the
                    Danube and the Rhine, Freiburg early acquired commercial importance, and it is
                    still the principal centre of the trade of the Black Forest. It manufactures
                    chicory, chemicals, starch, leather, tobacco, silk thread, paper, and hempen
                    goods, as well as beer and wine. The population is rapidly increasing. In 1864
                    it numbered 19,085, inclusive of the suburbs of Herdern and Wiehre, and in 1875
                    no less than 30,531. About a sixth of the whole are Protestants.</p>
                <p>Freiburg was founded, as has been already stated, by Count Berthold 111. of
                    Zähringen. In 1120 it became a free town, with privileges similar to those of
                    Cologne; but in 1219 it fell into the hands of a branch of the family of Urach.
                    After it had vainly attempted to throw off the yoke by force of arms, it
                    obtained its freedom in 1366 for a sum of 20,000 silver marks; but as it was
                    unable to reimburse the creditors who had advanced the money, it was, in 1368,
                    obliged to recognize the supremacy of the house of Haρsburg. In the 17th and
                    18th centuries it played a considerable part as a fortified town. It was
                    captured by the Swedes in 1632, 1634, and 1638; and in 1644 it was seized by the
                    Bavarians, who shortly after, under General Marcey, defeated in the
                    neighbourhood the French forces under Enghien and Turcnne. The French were in
                    possession from 1677 to 1697, and again in 1713-14 and 1744 , and when they left
                    the place in 1748, at the peace of Aix-la∙ Chapelle, they dismantled the
                    fortifications. The Baden insurgents gained a victory at Freiburg in 1848, and
                    the revolutionary Government took refuge in the town in June 1849, but in the
                    following July the Prussian forces took possession, and did not leave till
                    1851.</p>
                <p>Sec Schreiber, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte und Beschreibung des Münster zu
                    Freiburg,</hi> 1820 and 1825; <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Stadt und
                    Universität Freiburgs,</hi> 1857-59; <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Schlossberg</hi><hi rend="italic">bei Freiburg,</hi> 1860.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
