<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0726-0691-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCIS II (9th edition, volume 9, page 691)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n726/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCIS II</label>. (1768-1835), the last Holy Roman Emperor,
                    and, as Francis I., first emperor of Austria, was born in Florence on the 12th
                    Feburary 1768. He was the son of the emperor Leopold II., after whose death, in
                    1792, he succeeded to the hereditary dominions of the house of Austria, being
                    crowned emperor in the same year. Before this time he had gained some experience
                    of war during the conflict of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n727/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0727-0692"/> the emperor Joseph II. with the Turks, ∏e was
                    immediately involved in the first of his famous wars with France, in which, till
                    1795, he had the support of the king of Prussia. In 1794 he himself was with the
                    Austrian army which defeated the French at Tournay; but when fortune turned on
                    the side of France he went back to Vienna. He was compelled, mainly in
                    consequence of the victories of Napoleon, who pressed northward from Italy into
                    Carinthia, to conclude, on the 17th October 1797, the treaty of Campo Formio,
                    whereby the empire lost the greater part of the left bank of the Rhine, and
                    Austria had to give up the Netherlands and Lombardy. Austria received in return
                    Venetia, Friuli, Istria, and Dalmatia. In 1799 war broke out afresh, the emperor
                    having on this occasion England and Russia as allies. During the first campaign
                    the French were everywhere defeated; but in the following year Napoleon gained
                    the brilliant victory of Marengo, while Moreau was equally successful at
                    Hohenlinden. The shock of these two battles made it impossible for Austria to
                    continue the war, and on the 9th February 1801 she concluded t’.ie treaty of
                    Lunéville, which confirmed that of Campo Formio, besides exacting fresh
                    sacrifices. France now obtained the whole of the left bank of the Rhine. Once
                    more in association with Russia and England, the emperor began another war with
                    France in 1805. The capitulation of tſlm and the battle of Austerlitz, great as
                    were these disasters, did not make the case of Austria hopeless, for she still
                    had large forces, Russia was willing to continue the war, and the power of
                    France had been seriously crippled at Trafalgar. But Francis was dispirited, and
                    craved peace. On December 25, 1805, was concluded the treaty of Presburg, which
                    deprived Austria of Venetia and Tyrol. In 1806, after the formation of the
                    Confederation of the Rhine, he formally resigned the imperial crown, thus
                    bringing to an end the ∣Holy Roman Empire and the kingdom of Germany.
                    'Forgetting the true meaning of the word emperor, he had in 1804 proclaimed
                    himself, as Francis I., hereditary emperor of Austria; and this title has been
                    retained by his successors. He took no part in the war of Prussia with France in
                    1806, but after some time began to make preparations for a determined struggle,
                    by which he should regain all the advantages lost in previous wars. The new
                    conflict broke out in 1809, and the whole of Germany awaited the result with
                    intense anxiety. Austria was unfortunate at first; but the highest hopes were
                    excited by her thorough victory of Aspern. It was followed by the battle of
                    Wagram, which enabled Napoleon to dictate peace from the palace of Schönbrunn,
                    where he had once before taken up his quarters. By the treaty of Schönbrunn
                    (October 14, 1809) he transferred the allegiance of about four millions of
                    Austrian subjects to other rulers; but as in the following year he married Maria
                    Louisa, the eldest daughter of Francis, it seemed probable that the two
                    sovereigns would in future be on friendly terms. Francis was the ally of
                    Napoleon in his war with Russia in 1812; and when, after the retreat from
                    Moscow, France found herself confronted by Russia and Prussia, Austria at first
                    remained neutral, and in the summer of 1813 acted as mediator. In August of the
                    same year she joined the allies; and, like the sovereigns of Prussia and Russia,
                    Francis accompanied his troops in the war which followed. The settlement of
                    Europe which resulted from the final defeat ’of Napoleon made Francis a more
                    powerful sovereign than he had been at the beginning of his reign; and from this
                    time forward he lived at peace, except that he had to put down a rising in
                    Lombardy in 1821. He was a well-meaning ruler, but had been so alarmed by the
                    successes of the French Revolution that he detested modern ideas of government.
                    The aspirations of his various states for some measure of independence he
                    regarded as criminal, and in Prince Metternich he found a willing agent for his
                    policy of stern repression. Thus a large amount of discontent was excited, which
                    prepared serious, troubles for the emperors who came after him. Francis was
                    married four times, having by his second wife, Maria Theresa, princess of
                    Sicily, thirteen children. He died on the 2d March 1835, and was succeeded by
                    his son Ferdinand.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
