<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0826-0791-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FROBISHER, Sir Martin (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    791)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xr3k">Ores</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dx0q">Armada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n826/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FROBISHER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Martin</hi></label> (c.
                    1535-1594), English navigator and explorer, was the fourth child of Bernard
                    Frobisher, and was born, it is usually stated, at Doncaster, but more probably
                    at Al tofts in the parish of Norman ton, Yorkshire, some time between 1530 and
                    1540. The family came originally from North Wales. Martin was sent to London to
                    his mother’s brother, Sir John York, and in 1554 went with a small fleet of
                    merchant ships to Guinea under Admiral John Lock. We next hear of him in 1565 as
                    Captain Martin Frobisher, and again iu 1571 as superintending at Plymouth the
                    building of a ship to be employed against the Irish. As early as 1560 or 1561
                    Frobisher had conceived the idea of discovering a north-west passage to Cathay,
                    a short route to which was the motive of most of the Arctic voyages undertaken
                    at that period and for long after. For years he schemed and plotted, and
                    solicited in all quarters, from the court downwards, to obtain means to carry
                    his favourite project into execution; and it was only in 1576 that, mainly by
                    help of the earl of Warwick, he was put iu command of two tiny barks, the
                    “Gabriel” and “Michael,” mere cockle shells of about 20 tons each, and a pinnace
                    of 10 tons, with an aggregate crew of 35. On June 7 Frobisher left Blackwall,
                    and having received a good word from Queen Elizabeth at Greenwich, the
                    expedition, if we may apply to it so considerable a term, sailed northwards to
                    the Shetland Islands. Stormy weather had been met with, in which the pinnace was
                    lost, and sometime after the “Michael” deserted. After passing Greenland and
                    being nearly wrecked, the “Gabriel” reached the coast of Labrador on July 28.
                    Some days later Hall’s Island, at the mouth of Frobisher Bay, was reached, and a
                    landing effected. Among the things hastily brought away by the men was some
                    “black earth,” which played an important part in connexion with Frobisher’s
                    further career. Sailing up Frobisher Bay, then thought to be a strait, they
                    reached Butcher’s Island on August 18. Here some natives were met with, and
                    intercourse carried on with them for some days, the result being that five of
                    Frobisher’s men were decoyed and captured, and never more seen. After vainly
                    trying to get back his men, Frobisher turned homewards, and reached London on
                    October 9. It seemed as if nothing more was to come of this expedition, when it
                    was noised abroad that the apparently valueless “black earth” was really a lump
                    of gold ore. It is difficult to say how this rumour arose, and whether there was
                    any truth in it, or whether Frobisher was a party to a deception, in order to
                    obtain means to carry out the great idea of his life. The story, at any rate,
                    was so far successful; the greatest enthusiasm was manifested by the court and
                    the commercial and speculating world of the time; and next year a much more
                    important expedition than the former was fitted out, the queen lending Frobisher
                    from the royal navy a ship of 200 tons. A Cathay company was established, with a
                    charter from the crown, giving the company the sole right of sailing in every
                    direction but the east; Frobisher was appointed high admiral of all lands and
                    waters that might be discovered by him. The queen herself subscribed £1000, and
                    the rest required was soon forthcoming. On May 26, 1577, the expedition, which,
                    besides the royal ship, the “Aid” of 200 tons, consisted of the “Gabriel” and
                    “Michael” of the previous year, with boats and pinnaces and an aggregate
                    complement of 120 men, including miners, refiners, &amp;c., left Blackwall, and
                    sailing by the north of Scotland, arrived at Greenland early in July. Hall’s
                    Island was reached on the 18th, and though no more “black earth” was found
                    there, abundance of it was found on other islands, and the ships well loaded
                    with it. The country around, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Meta
                    Incognita,</hi> was solemnly taken possession of in the queen’s name. Several
                    weeks were spent in Frobisher Bay collecting ore, but very little was done in
                    the way of discovery. There was much parleying and some skirmishing with the
                    natives, and earnest but futile attempts made on the part of Frobisher to
                    recover the men captured the previous year. The return was begun on August 22,
                    and the “Aid” reached Milford Haven on September 20; the “Gabriel” and
                    “Michael,” having separated, arrived later at Bristol and Yarmouth. Frobisher
                    was received and thanked by the queen at Windsor. Great preparations were made
                    and considerable expense incurred for the assaying of the great quantity of
                    “ore” brought home, in the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n827/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0827-0792"/> testing of which the queen manifested a strong
                    personal interest. This took up much time, and led to considerable dispute among
                    the various parties interested. Meantime the faith of the queen and others
                    remained strong in the productiveness of Meta Incognita, and it was resolved to
                    send out a larger expedition than ever, with all necessaries for the
                    establishment of a colony of 100 men. The queen herself contributed two ships of
                    400 and 200 tons, manned with 150 men, and carrying 120 pioneers. Besides these
                    the fleet contained other 13 vessels of various sizes, carrying other 250 men,
                    and the most elaborate and minute instructions were drawn up for the conduct of
                    the expedition. Frobisher was again received by the queen at Greenwich, and her
                    Majesty threw a fine chain of gold around his neck. On May 31 the expedition
                    left Harwich, and sailing by the English Channel, reached Greenland on June 19.
                    This time Frobisher and some of his men managed to land, “being the first known
                    Christians that we have true notice of that ever set foot upon that ground.” In
                    the first days of July Frobisher Bay was reached, but stormy weather and
                    dangerous ice drove the fleet southwards, and unwittingly Frobisher entered what
                    was afterwards known as Hudson Strait, up which he sailed about 60 miles. When
                    he found that he was sailing away from his destination, he, with apparent
                    reluctance, turned back, and after many buffetings part of the fleet managed to
                    come to anchor in Frobisher Bay. Some attempt was made at founding a settlement,
                    and immense quantities of ore were shipped. But, as might be expected, there was
                    much dissension and not a little discontent among so heterogeneous a company,
                    and on the last day of August the fleet set out on its return to England, which
                    was reached in the beginning of October. Thus ended what was little better than
                    a fiasco, though Frobisher himself cannot be held to blame for the result; the
                    scheme was altogether chimerical, and the “ore” seems to have been not worth
                    smelting. Between 1578 and 1585 we hear little of Frobisher, though he seems to
                    have been doing service at various places, and steadily advancing in the good
                    opinion of those in power. In 1580 he obtained the reversion of the clerkship of
                    the royal navy, of no immediate value. In 1585 he commanded in the “Primrose” in
                    Sir F. Drake’s expedition to the West Indies, in the large booty brought home
                    from which he no doubt had a good share. For the next year or two he was
                    employed in various responsible services against the designs of Spain, and in
                    1588 he did such excellent work in the “Triumph” against the Spanish Armada that
                    he was rewarded with the honour of knighthood. He continued to cruise about in
                    the Channel until 1589, when he was sent in command of a small fleet to the
                    coast of Spain. In 1591 he visited his native Altofts, and there married a
                    daughter of Lord Wentworth. He had prospered during recent years and was able to
                    become a landed proprieter in Yorkshire and Notts. But he found little leisure
                    for a country life, and was soon on the seas again watching and cutting off the
                    richly laden ships of Spain. In November 1594 he took part in the siege of
                    Crozan, near Brest, and received a wound from which he died at Plymouth on
                    November 22. His body was taken to London and buried at St Giles’s, Cripplegate.
                    Frobisher was brave and skilful as a naval leader, and had the enthusiasm of the
                    true explorer, but was characterized by much of the coarseness, and probably
                    some of the unscrupulousness, of his time, and appears to have been somewhat
                    rough in his bearing, and too strict a disciplinarian to be much loved. He
                    justly takes rank among England’s great naval heroes.</p>
                <p>See Hakluyt’s <hi rend="italic">Voyages;</hi> the Hakluyt Society’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Three Voyages of</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> c,</hi> Λ ⅛ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> alls</hi> JV <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> * <hi
                    rend="superscript"> n</hi> &lt;AiAe-⅛wmαwΛ5 Campbell’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lives</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> lιev</hi><hi rend="italic">'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> F</hi><hi rend="italic">· of Frobisher,</hi> aní
                    authorities mentioned therein. ¢j_ <hi rend="subscript"> g κ</hi> j</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
