<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0738-0703-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCONIA (9th edition, volume 9, page 703)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863204">Claims</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1746469">Grandsons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n738/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCONIA</label>, in German <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Franken,</hi> a name of very different application in different historical
                    periods. It properly signifies the land of the Franks, and is consequently
                    identical in original meaning with the word Francia or France. In the beginning
                    of the 4th century the Frankish territory stretched from the Loire eastward to
                    the basin of the Rhine and the Main; but it was shortly afterwards broken up
                    into two divisions—Austrasia, Francia Orientalis, or the kingdom of the East
                    Franks,and Neustria, Francia Occidentalis, or the kingdom of the West Franks. As
                    time went on both kingdoms extended their boundaries; and when the treaty of
                    Verdun in 845 settled the claims of the grandsons of Charles the Great, there
                    was a kingdom of Western France with Latin tendencies, and a kingdom of Eastern
                    France with Teutonic tendencies, each possessing a central district or duchy of
                    its own name. These districts were separated from each other by the district of
                    Lotharingia or Lorraine. The western was soon after lost sight of; but the
                    eastern continued for a long period to be considered the very core and kernel of
                    the German kingdom, and a theory became prevalent that it was the original seat
                    of the Franks in Germany. Under the Saxon and Franconian emperors it was
                    subdivided into Ost-Franken, Francia Orientalis, or Eastern Franconia <hi
                    rend="italic">par excellence,</hi> and Rhein-Franken, Francia Rhenensis, or
                    Rhenish Franconia. The former, which was also distinguished as Saal-Frunken,
                    stretched from the Fichtelgebirge and the Rhone to the Danube, and from the
                    Upper Palatinate to the Spessart and the lands of the Neckar; while the latter
                    was the country between the Spessart and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n739/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0739-0704"/> the Rhine, and included the present district of
                    Frankfort-onthe-Main. Though the name frequently occurs in our histories, there
                    was probably no proper “duchy” of Franconia, in the same sense at least as there
                    was a duchy of Saxony or a duchy of Bavaria. Conrad I. and Conrad II., for
                    example, do not style themselves dukes “of” Franconia but dukes “in” Franconia.
                    Both Eastern Franconia and Rhenish Franconia were broken up into a number of
                    distinct territories—countships, lordships, &amp;c. When Maximilian divided
                    Germany into circles in 1501, he gave the name of Franconia to the circle
                    whichincluded the bishoprics of Würzburg, Bamberg, and Eichstädt, the district
                    of Mergentheim belonging to the grand master of the Teutonic Order, the
                    territory of the abbey of Schönthal, the principalities of Baireuth and Ansbach,
                    the countships of Henneberg and Schwarzenberg, the territories of the curia of
                    Franconian counts, the imperial towns of Nuremberg, Rothenburg, Schweinfurt,
                    Weissenburg, and Windsheim. Altogether the circle comprised 69 territories and
                    had an area of about 10,430 square miles, and in 1792 its population amounted to
                    1,547,000. The name of Franconia ceased to be officially used after the
                    dissolution of the German empire in 1806; but in 1837 King Louis I. of Bavaria
                    gave the names of Upper, Middle, and Lower Franconia to what had previously been
                    known as the circles of the Upper Main, the Rezat, and the LowerMain. Upper
                    Franconia forms the north-east portion of Bavaria, and is partly conterminous
                    with the frontiers of Bohemia, Saxony, and Prussia. Its mountains are the
                    Fichtelgebirge, the Frankenwald, the Böhmerwald, and the Steigerwald; and the
                    Main, the Naab, the Saale, and the Eger take their rise within its territory.
                    The seat of the administration is at Baireuth, and the court of appeal at
                    Bamberg. Lower Franconia lies to the west, and forms the north-west province of
                    the kingdom,—conterminous with Prussia, Weimar, Meiningen, Würtemberg, Baden,
                    and Hesse. Its rivers arc the Main, the Saale, the Itz, and the Baunach. The
                    principal town is Würzburg. Middle Franconia lies to the south of the other two,
                    conterminous with the Upper Palatinate, Swabia, and Würtemberg. It is watered by
                    the Regnitz and the Altmühl. The principal town is Nuremberg, the seat of the
                    administration is at Ausbach, and the court of appeal at Eichstädt.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
