<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0520-0489-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOURIER, François Charles Marie (9th edition, volume 9,
                    page 489)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n520/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOURIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">François Charles
                    Marie</hi></label> (1772-1837), one of the most celebrated socialist writers,
                    was born at Besançon in Franche-Comté, on the 7th April 1772. His father was a
                    draper in good circumstances, and Fourier received an excellent education at the
                    college in his native town. After completing his studies there he travelled for
                    some time in France, Germany, and Holland. On the death of his father he
                    inherited a considerable amount of property, which, however, was lost when Lyons
                    was besieged by the troops of the Convention. Being thus deprived of his means
                    of livelihood, Fourier entered the army, but after two years’ service as a
                    chasseur was discharged on account of ill-health. In 1803 he published a
                    remarkable article on European politics which attracted the notice of Napoleon,
                    some of whose ideas were foreshadowed in it. Inquiries were made after the
                    author, but nothing seems to have come of them. After leaving the army Fourier
                    entered a merchant’s office in Lyons, and some years later undertook on his own
                    account a small business as broker. He obtained in this way just sufficient to
                    supply his wants, and devoted all his leisure time to the elaboration of his
                    first work on the organization of society.</p>
                <p>During the early part of his life, and while engaged in commerce, he had become
                    deeply impressed with the conviction that social arrangements resulting from the
                    principles of individualism and competition were essentially imperfect and
                    immoral. He proposed to substitute for these principles co-operation or united
                    effort, by means of which full and harmonious development might be given to
                    human nature. The scheme, worked out in detail in his first work, <hi
                    rend="italic">Théorie des Quatre Mouvements</hi> (2 vols., Lyons, 1808,
                    published anonymously), has for foundation a particular psychological
                    proposition and a special economical doctrine. Psychologically Fourier held what
                    may with some laxity of language be called natural optimism,—the view that the
                    full, free development of human nature or the unrestrained indulgence of human
                    passion is the only possible way to happiness and virtue, and that misery and
                    vice spring from the unnatural restraints imposed by society on the
                    gratification of desire. This principle of harmony among the passions he
                    regarded as his grandest discovery—a discovery which did more than set him on a
                    level with Newton, the discoverer of the principle of attraction or harmony
                    among material bodies. Throughout his works, in uncouth, obscure, and often
                    unintelligible language, he endeavours to show that the same fundamental fact of
                    harmony is to be found in the four great departments,— society, animal life,
                    organic life, and the material universe. In order to give effect to this
                    principle and obtain the resulting social harmony, it was needful that society
                    should be reconstructed; for, as the social organism is at present constituted,
                    innumerable restrictions are imposed upon the free development of human desire.
                    As practical principle for such a reconstruction Fourier advocated co-operative
                    or united industry. In many respects what he says of co-operation, in particular
                    as to the enormous waste cf economic force which the actual arrangements of
                    society entail, still deserves attention, and some of the most recent efforts
                    towards extension of the co-operative method, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> to
                    house-keeping, were in essentials anticipated by him. But the full realization
                    of his scheme demanded much more than the mere admission that co-operation is
                    economically more efficacious than individualism. Society as a whole must be
                    organized on the lines requisite to give full scope to co-operation and to the
                    harmonious evolution of human nature. The details of this reorganization of the
                    social structure cannot be given briefly, but the broad outlines may be thus
                    sketched. Society, on his scheme, is to be divided into departments or <hi
                    rend="italic">phalanges,</hi> each <hi rend="italic">phalange</hi> numbering
                    about 1600 persons. Each <hi rend="italic">phalange</hi> inhabits <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n521/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0521-0490"/> a <hi rend="italic">phalanstère</hi> or common
                    building, and has a certain portion of soil allotted to it for cultivation. The
                    <hi rend="italic">phalanstères</hi> are built after a uniform plan, and the
                    domestic arrangements are laid down very elaborately. The staple industry of the
                    <hi rend="italic">phalanges</hi> is, of course, agriculture, but the various <hi
                    rend="italic">series</hi> and <hi rend="italic">groupes</hi> into which the
                    members are divided may deVote themselves to such occupations as are most to
                    their taste; nor need any occupation become irksome from constant devotion to
                    it. Any member of a group may vary his employment at pleasure, may pass from one
                    task to another. The tasks regarded as menial or degrading in ordinary society
                    can be rendered attractive if advantage is taken of the proper principles of
                    human nature: thus children, who have a natural affinity for dirt, and a
                    fondness for “cleaning up,” may easily be induced to accept with eagerness the
                    functions of public scavengers. It is not, on Fourier’s scheme, necessary that
                    private property should be abolished, nor is the privacy of family life
                    impossible within the phalanstère. Each family may have separate apartments, and
                    there may be richer and poorer members. But the rich and poor are to be locally
                    intermingled, in order that the broad distinction between them, which is so
                    painful a feature in actual society, may become almost imperceptible. Out of the
                    common gain of the phalange a certain portion is deducted to furnish to each
                    member the minimum of subsistence; the remainder is distributed in shares to
                    labour, capital, and talent,—five-twelfths going to the first, four-twelfths to
                    the second, and three-twelfths to the third. Upon the changes requisite in the
                    private life of the members Fourier was in his first work more explicit than in
                    his later writings. The institution of marriage, which imposes unnatural bonds
                    on human passion, is of necessity abolished; a new and ingeniously constructed
                    system of licence is substituted for it. Considerable offence seems to have been
                    given by Fourier’s utterances with regard to marriage, and generally the later
                    advocates of his views are content to pass the matter over in silence, or to
                    veil their teaching under obscure and metaphorical language.</p>
                <p>The scheme thus sketched attracted no attention when the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Théorie</hi> first appeared, and for some years Fourier remained in his obscure
                    position at Lyons. In 1812 the death of his mother put him in possession of a
                    small sum of money, with which he retired to Bellay in order to perfect his
                    second work. The <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">de If
                    Association</hi><hi rend="italic">Agricole Domestique</hi> was published in 2
                    vols, at Paris in 1822, and a summary appeared in the following year. After its
                    publication the author proceeded to Paris in the hope that some wealthy
                    capitalist might be induced to attempt the realization of the projected scheme.
                    Disappointed in this expectation, he returned to Lyons. In 1826 he again visited
                    Paris, and as a considerable portion of his means had been expended in the
                    publication of his book, he accepted a clerkship in an American firm. In 1829
                    and 1830 appeared what is probably the most finished exposition of his views,
                    <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Nouveau Monde</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Industriel.</hi> In 1831 he attacked the rival socialist doctrines of St Simon
                    and Owen in the small work <hi rend="italic">Pièges et Charlatanisme de deux
                    Sectes, St Simon et</hi><hi rend="italic">Owen.</hi> His writings now began to
                    attract some attention. A small body of adherents gathered round him, and the
                    most ardent of them, Victor Considérant, published in 1834 his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Destinée Sociale,</hi> undoubtedly the most able and most important work of the
                    Fourierist school. In 1832 a newspaper, <hi rend="italic">Le Phalanstère ou la
                    Réforme Industrielle</hi> was started to propagate the views of the school, but
                    its success was not great. In 1833 it declined from a weekly to a monthly, and
                    in 1834 it died of inanition. It was revived in 1836 as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Phalange,</hi> and in 1843 became a daily paper, <hi
                    rend="italic">La Democratic</hi><hi rend="italic">Pacifique.</hi> In 1850 it was
                    suppressed.</p>
                <p>Fourier did not live to see the success of his newspaper, and the only practical
                    attempt during his lifetime to establish a phalanstère was a complete failure.
                    In 1832 Μ. Baudet Dulary, deputy for Seine-et-Oise, who had become a convert,
                    purchased an estate at Condé sur Vesgre, near the forest of Rambouillet, and
                    proceeded to establish a socialist community. The capital supplied was, however,
                    inadequate, and the community broke up in disgust. Fourier was in no way
                    discouraged by this failure, and till his death, in October 1837, lived in daily
                    expectation that wealthy capitalists would see the merits of his scheme, and be
                    induced to devote their fortunes to its realization. It may be added that
                    subsequent attempts to establish the phalanstère have been uniformly
                    unsuccessful.</p>
                <p>For an examination of the principles on which Fourier’s socialist scheme is
                    based, reference must be made to the general articles <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Communism</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Socialism,</hi> but a word must be
                    added as to the character of the man and his works. Fourier seems to have been
                    of extremely retiring and sensitive disposition. He mixed little in society, and
                    appeared, indeed, as if he were the denizen of some other planet. Of the true
                    nature of social arrangements, and of the manner iu which they naturally grow
                    and become organized, he must be pronounced extremely ignorant. The faults of
                    existing institutions presented themselves to him in an altogether distorted
                    manner, and he never appears to have recognized that the evils of actual society
                    are immeasurably less serious than the consequences of his arbitrary scheme. Out
                    of the chaos of human passion he supposed harmony was to be evolved by the
                    adoption of a few theoretically disputable principles, which themselves impose
                    restraints even more irksome than those due to actual social facts. With regard
                    to the economic aspects of his proposed new method, it is of course to be
                    granted that co-operation is more effective than individual effort, but he has
                    nowhere faced the question as to the probable consequences of organizing society
                    on the abolition of those great institutions which have grown with its growth.
                    His temperament was too ardent, his imagination too strong, and his acquaintance
                    with the realities of life too slight to enable him justly to estimate the
                    merits of his fantastic views. That this description of him is not expressed in
                    over-strong language must be clear to any one who not only considers what is
                    true in his works,—and the portion of truth is by no means a peculiar discovery
                    of Fourier’s,— but who takes into account the whole body of his speculations,
                    the cosmological and historical as well as the economical and social. No words
                    can adequately describe the fantastic nonsense which he pours forth, partly in
                    the form of general speculation on the universe, partly in the form of prophetic
                    utterances with regard to the future changes in humanity and its material
                    environment. From these extraordinary writings it is no extreme conclusion that
                    there was much of insanity in Fourier’s mental constitution.</p>
                <p>Ch. Pellarin, <hi rend="italic">Fourier,</hi><hi rend="italic">sa</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">et sa Théorie,</hi> 5th ed., 1872;
                    Sargant, <hi rend="italic">Social Innovators,</hi> 1859; Reybaud, <hi
                    rend="italic">Réformateurs Modernes,</hi> 7th ed., 1864; Stein, <hi
                    rend="italic">Socialismus ïind Commuìiismus</hi><hi rend="italic">des heutigen
                    Frankreichs,</hi> 2d ed., 1848; Booth, <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly
                    Review,</hi> N. S., vol. xii. (R∙ AD.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
