<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0821-0786-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRIGATE-BIRD (9th edition, volume 9, page 786)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c355">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10s8q">Sternum</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f6h">Albatrosses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804176">Albatrosses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174597">White</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174816">Whites</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812191">Aquila</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927291">Flight</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n821/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRIGATE-BIRD</label>, the name commonly given by our sailors,
                    on account of the swiftness of its flight, its habit of cruising about near
                    other species and of daringly pursuing them, to a large Sea-bird<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“Man-of-war-Bird” is also
                    sometimes applied to it, and is perhaps the older name; but it is less
                    distinctive, some of the larger Albatrosses being so called, and, in books at
                    least, has generally passed out of use.</p></note> —the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fregata</hi><hi rend="italic">aquila</hi> of most ornithologists—the <hi
                    rend="italic">Fregatte</hi> of French and the <hi rend="italic">Rabihorcado</hi>
                    of Spanish mariners. It was placed by Linnaeus in the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pelecanus,</hi> and until lately its assignment to the family <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pelecaniclae</hi> has hardly ever been doubted. Professor Mivart has, however,
                    now declared <hi rend="italic">{Trans. Zool.</hi><hi rend="italic">Soc.,</hi> x.
                    p. 364) that, as regards the postcranial part of its axial skeleton, he cannot
                    detect sufficiently good characters to unite it with that family in the group
                    named by Professor Brandt <hi rend="italic">Steganopodes.</hi> There seems to be
                    no ground for disputing this decision so far as separating the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Fregata</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">Pelecanidae</hi> goes, but
                    systematists will probably pause before they proceed to abolish the <hi
                    rend="italic">Steganopodes,</hi> and the result will most likely be that the
                    Frigate-Birds will be considered to form a distinct family <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Fregatidcf)</hi> in that group. In one very remarkable way the osteology of
                    <hi rend="italic">Fregata</hi> differs from that of all other birds known. The
                    furcula coalesces firmly at its symphysis with the carina of the sternum, and
                    also with the coracoids at the upper extremity of each of its rami, the anterior
                    end of each coracoid coalescing also with the proximal end of the scapula. Thus
                    the only articulations in the whole sternal apparatus are where the coracoids
                    meet the sternum, and the consequence is a bony framework which would be
                    perfectly rigid did not the flexibility of the rami of the furcula permit a
                    limited amount of motion. That this mechanism is closely related to the faculty
                    which the bird possesses of soaring for a considerable time in the air with
                    scarcely a perceptible movement of the wings can hardly be doubted, but the
                    particular way in which it works has yet to be explained.</p>
                <p>Two species of <hi rend="italic">Fregata</hi> are considered to exist, though
                    they differ in little but size and geographical distribution. The larger, <hi
                    rend="italic">F. aquila,</hi> has a wide range all round the world within the
                    tropics, and at times passes their limits. The smaller, <hi rend="italic">F.
                    minor,</hi> appears to be confined to the eastern seas, from Madagascar to the
                    Moluccas, and southward to Australia, being particularly abundant in Torres
                    Strait,—the other species, however, being found there as well. Having a spread
                    of wing equal to a Swan’s and a comparatively small body, the buoyancy of these
                    birds is very great. It is a beautiful sight to watch one or more of them
                    floating overhead against the deep blue sky, the long forked tail alternately
                    opening and shutting like a pair of scissors, and the head, which is of course
                    kept to windward, inclined from side to side, while the wings are to all
                    appearance fixedly extended, though the breeze may be constantly varying in
                    strength and direction. Equally fine is the contrast afforded by these birds
                    when engaged in fishing, or, as seems more often to happen, in robbing other
                    birds, especially Boobies, as they are fishing. Then the speed of their flight
                    is indeed seen to advantage, as well as the marvellous suddenness with which
                    they can change their rapid course as their victim tries to escape from their
                    attack. Before gales Frigate-Birds are said often to fly low, and their
                    appearance near or over land, except at their breeding-time, is supposed to
                    portend a hurricane.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Hence another of the names—“Hurricane-Bird”—by which this species is
                    occasionally known</p></note> Gene rally seen singly or in pairs,’except when
                    the prospect of prey induces them to congregate, they breed in large companies,
                    and MrSalvinhas graphically described <hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi> 1864, p.
                    375) one of their settlements off the coast of British Honduras, which he
                    visited in May 1862. Here they chose the highest mangrove-trees<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Capt. Taylor, however, found
                    their nests as well on low bushes of the same tree in the Bay of Fonseca <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ibis,</hi> 1859, pp. 150-152).</p></note> on which to build their
                    frail nests, and seemed to prefer the leeward side. The single egg laid in each
                    nest has a white and chalky shell very like that of a Cormorant’s. The nestlings
                    are clothed iu pure white down, and so thickly as to resemble puff-balls. When
                    fledged, the beak, head, neck, and belly are white, the legs and feet
                    bluish-white, but the body is dark above. The adult females retain the white
                    beneath, but the adult males lose it, and in both sexes at maturity the upper
                    plumage is of a very dark chocolate brown, nearly black, with a bright metallic
                    gloss, while the feet iu the females are pink, and black in the males—the last
                    also acquiring a bright scarlet pouch, capable of inflation, and being
                    perceptible when on the wing. The habits of <hi rend="italic">F. minor</hi> seem
                    wholly to resemble those of <hi rend="italic">F. aquila.</hi> According to
                    Bechstein, an example of this last species was obtained at the mouth of the
                    Weser in January 1792, and it has hence been included by some ornithologists
                    among European birds! <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
