<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0244-0234-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RICE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:991153">Lampoon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946112">Graining</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945891">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp2r">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=244" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">RICE</label>. “Rice <hi rend="italic">bras,"</hi>
                    says Mr Marsden, “whilst in the husk, is in Indian called <hi rend="italic"
                        >paddee,</hi> and assumes a different name in each of its other various
                    states. We observe no distinction of this kind in Europe, where our grain
                    retains through all its stages, till it becomes flour, its original name of
                    barley, wheat, or oats. The following, besides many others, are names applied to
                    rice in its different stages of growth and preparation: <hi rend="italic"
                        >paddee,</hi> original name of the seed; <hi rend="italic">oossαy,</hi>
                    grain of last season; <hi rend="italic">bunnee,</hi> the plants before removed
                    to the sawoors; <hi rend="italic">bras,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">bray,</hi>
                    rice, the husk of the paddee being taken off; <hi rend="italic">charroop,</hi>
                    rice cleaned for boiling; <hi rend="italic">ηassee,</hi> boiled rice; <hi
                        rend="italic">peerang,</hi> yellow rice; <hi rend="italic">jambar,</hi> a
                    service of rice, &amp;c.</p>
                <p part="N">“Among people whose general objects of contemplation are few, those
                    which do of necessity engage their attention are often more nicely discriminated
                    than the same objects among more enlightened people, whose ideas, ranging over
                    the extensive field of art and science, disdain to fix long on obvious and
                    common matters. <hi rend="italic">Paddee,</hi> in Sumatra and the Malay Islands,
                    is distinguished into two sorts; <hi rend="italic">laddang</hi> or upland
                    paddee, and <hi rend="italic">sawoor</hi> or lowland, which are always kept
                    separate, and will not grow reciprocally. Of these, the former bears the higher
                    price, being a whiter, heartier, and better-flavoured grain, and having the
                    advantage in point of keeping. The latter is much more prolific from the seed,
                    and liable to less risk in the culture, but is of a watery substance, produces
                    less increase in boiling, and is subject to a swifter decay. It is, however, in
                    more common use than the former. Besides this general distinction, the paddee of
                    each sort, particularly the laddang, presents a variety of species, which, as
                    far as my information extends, I shall enumerate and endeavour to describe. The
                    common kind of dry ground paddee; colour light brown; the size rather large, and
                    very little crooked at the extremity. Paddee <hi rend="italic">undal-long;</hi>
                    dry ground; short round grain; grows in whorls or bunches round the stock.
                    Paddee <hi rend="italic">Mass;</hi> dry ground; large grain; common. Paddee <hi
                        rend="italic">gαlloo;</hi> dry ground; light coloured; scarce. Paddee <hi
                        rend="italic">sennee;</hi> dry ground; deep coloured; small grain; scarce.
                    Paddee <hi rend="italic">ejoo;</hi> dry ground; light coloured. Paddee <hi
                        rend="italic">kooning;</hi> dry ground; deep yellow; fine rice; crooked and
                    pointed. Paddee <hi rend="italic">coocoor badium;</hi> dry ground; much
                    esteemed; light coloured: small, and very much crooked, resembling a dove’s
                    nail, from whence its name. <hi rend="italic">Paddee pesang;</hi> dry ground;
                    outer coat light brown; inner red; longer, smaller, and less crooked than the
                        <hi rend="italic">coocoor bαllum,</hi> Paddee <hi rend="italic"
                        >santong;</hi> the finest sort that is planted in wet ground; small,
                    straight, and light coloured. In general it may be observed that the larger
                    grained rice is the least esteemed, and the smaller and whiter the most prized.
                    In the Lampoon country they make a distinction of paddee <hi rend="italic"
                        >crawrang</hi> and paddee <hi rend="italic">jerroo;</hi> the former of which
                    is a month earlier in growth than the latter.”</p>
                <p part="N">The following is the Chinese method of cultivating rice, as it is stated
                    by Sir George Staunton: “Much of the low grounds in the middle and southern
                    provinces of the empire are appropriated to the culture of that grain. It
                    constitutes, in fact, the principal part of the food of all those inhabitants
                    who are not so indigent as to be forced to subsist on other and cheaper kinds of
                    grain. A great proportion of the surface of the country is well adapted for the
                    production of rice, which, from the time the seed is committed to the soil till
                    the plant approaches to maturity, requires to be immersed in a sheet of water.
                    Many and great rivers run through the principal provinces of China, the low
                    grounds bordering on those rivers are annually inundated, by which means is
                    brought upon their surface a rich mud or mucilage that fertilizes the soil, in
                    the same manner as Egypt receives its fecundative quality from the overflowing
                    of the Nile. The periodical rains which fall near the sources of the Yellow and
                    the Kiang rivers, not very far distant from those of the Ganges and the
                    Burumpooter, among <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=245"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0245-0235"/>the mountains bounding India to the north and
                    China to the west, often swell those rivers to a prodigious height, though not a
                    drop should have fallen on the plains through which they afterwards flow.</p>
                <p part="N">“After the mud has lain some days upon the plains in China, preparations
                    are made for planting them with rice. For this purpose a small piece of ground
                    is enclosed by a bank of clay; the earth is ploughed up; and an upright harrow,
                    with a row of wooden pins in the lower end, is drawn lightly over it by a
                    buffalo. The grain, which had previously been steeped in dung diluted with
                    animal water, is then sown very thickly upon it. A thin sheet of water is
                    immediately brought over it, either by channels leading to the spot from a
                    source above it, or, when below it, by means of a chain-pump, of which the use
                    is as familiar as that of a hoe to every Chinese husbandman. In a few days the
                    remainder of the ground intended for cultivation, if stiff, is ploughed, the
                    lumps broken by hoes, and the surface levelled by the harrow. As soon as the
                    shoots have attained the height of six or seven inches, they are plucked up by
                    the roots, the tops of the blades cut off, and each root is planted separately,
                    sometimes in small furrows turned with the plough, and sometimes in holes made
                    in rows by a drilling stick for that purpose. The roots are about half a foot
                    asunder. Water is brought over them a second time. For the convenience of
                    irrigation, and to regulate its proportion, the rice-fields are subdivided by
                    narrow ridges of clay into small enclosures. Through a channel in each ridge the
                    water is conveyed at will to every subdivision of the field. As the rice
                    approaches to maturity, the water, by evaporation and absorption, disappears
                    entirely; and the crop, when ripe, covers dry ground. The first crop or harvest,
                    in the southern provinces particularly, happens towards the end of May or
                    beginning of June. The instrument for reaping is a small sickle, dentated like a
                    saw, and crooked. Neither carts nor cattle are used to carry the sheaves off
                    from the spot where they were reaped; but they are placed regularly in frames,
                    two of which, suspended at the extremities of a bamboo pole, are carried across
                    the shoulders of a man, to the place intended for disengaging the grain from the
                    stems which had supported it. This operation is performed, not only by a flail,
                    as is customary in Europe, or by cattle treading the com in the manner of other
                    orientalists, but sometimes also by striking it against a plank set upon its
                    edge, or beating it against the side of a large tub scolloped for that purpose;
                    the back and sides being much higher than the front, to prevent the grain from
                    being dispersed. After being winnowed, it is carried to the granary.</p>
                <p part="N">“To remove the skin or husk of rice, a large strong earthen vessel, or
                    hollow stone, in form somewhat like that which is used elsewhere for filtering
                    water, is fixed firmly in the ground; and the grain, placed in it, is struck
                    with a conical stone fixed to the extremity of a lever, and cleared, sometimes
                    indeed imperfectly, from the husk. The stone is worked frequently by a person
                    treading upon the end of the lever. The same object is attained also by passing
                    the grain between two flat stones of a circular form, the upper of which turns
                    round upon the other, but at such a distance from it as not to break the
                    intermediate grain. The operation is performed on a large scale in mills turned
                    by water; the axis of the wheel carrying several arms, which by striking upon
                    the ends of levers, raise them in the same manner as is done by treading on
                    them. Sometimes twenty of these levers are worked at once. The straw from which
                    the grain has been disengaged is cut chiefly into chaff, to serve as provender
                    for the very few cattle employed in the Chinese husbandry.</p>
                <p part="N">“The labour of the first crop being finished, the ground is immediately
                    prepared for the reception of fresh seeds. The first operation undertaken is
                    that of pulling up the stubble, collecting it into small heaps, which are burnt,
                    and the ashes scattered upon the field. The former processes are afterwards
                    renewed. The second crop is generally ripe late in October or early in November.
                    The grain is treated as before; but the stubble is no longer burnt. It is turned
                    under with the plough, and left to putrefy in the earth. This, with the slime
                    brought upon the ground by inundation, are the only manures usually employed in
                    the culture of rice.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
