<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0205-0195-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REYNOLDS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222r689">Boys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:837358">Boys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1072324">Portraits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=205" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">REYNOLDS</label> Sir Joshua, the celebrated painter,
                    was born at Plympton, a small town in Devonshire, on the 16th July 1723. His
                    father was minister of the parish, and also master of the grammar school; and
                    being a man of learning and philanthropy, he was beloved and respected by all to
                    whom he was known. Such a man, it will naturally be supposed, was assiduous in
                    the cultivation of the minds of his children, amongst whom his son Joshua shone
                    conspicuous, by displaying at a very early period a superiority of genius and
                    the rudiments of a correct taste. Unlike other boys, who generally content
                    themselves with giving a literal explanation of their author, regardless of his
                    beauties or his faults, young Reynolds attended to both these, displaying a
                    happy knowledge of what he read, and entering with ardour into the spirit of his
                    author. He discovered likewise talents for composition, and a natural propensity
                    for drawing, in which his friends and intimates thought him qualified to excel.
                    Emulation was a distinguishing feature in his mind, which his father perceived
                    with the delight natural to a parent; and designing him for the church, in which
                    he hoped that his talents might raise him to eminence, he sent him to one of the
                    universities.</p>
                <p part="N">Soon after this period he grew passionately fond of painting; and, by
                    the perusal of Richardson’s theory of that art was determined to make it his
                    profession through'life. At his own earnest request therefore, he was removed to
                    London; and about the year 1742 became a pupil to Mr Hudson, who, though not
                    himself an eminent painter, was preceptor to several who afterwards excelled in
                    the art. One of the first advices which he gave to Mr Reynolds was to copy
                    carefully Guercino’s drawings. This was done with such skill, that many of the
                    copies are said to be now preserved in the cabinets of the curious as the
                    originals of that very great master.</p>
                <p part="N">About the year 1749, Mr Reynolds went to Italy under the auspices and in
                    the company of Lord, then Commodore, Keppel, who was appointed to the command of
                    the British squadron in the Mediterranean. In this garden of the world, this
                    magical seat of the arts, he failed not to visit the schools of the great
                    masters, to study the productions of different ages, and to contemplate with
                    unwearied attention the various beauties which are characteristic of each. His
                    labour here, as has been observed of another painter, was “the labour of love,
                    not the task of the hireling ;” and how much he profited by it is known to all
                    Europe.</p>
                <p part="N">Having remained about two years in Italy, and studied the language as
                    well as the arts of the country with great success, he returned to England,
                    improved by travel and refined by education. On the road to London from the port
                    where he landed, he accidentally found in the inn where he lodged Johnson’s life
                    of Savage; and was so taken with the charms of composition and the masterly
                    delineation of character displayed in that performance, that having begun to
                    read it whilst leaning with his arm on the chimney-piece, he continued in that
                    attitude insensible of pain till he was hardly able to raise his hand to his
                    head. The admiration <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=206"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0206-0196"/>of the work naturally led him to seek the
                    acquaintance of its author, who continued one of his most sincere admirers and
                    warmest friends till 1784, when they were separated by the stroke of death.</p>
                <p part="N">The first thing that distinguished him after his return to his native
                    country, was a full-length portrait of Commodore Keppel; which in the polite
                    circles was spoken of in terms of the highest encomium, and testified to what a
                    degree of eminence he had arrived in his profession. This was followed by a
                    portrait of Lord Edgecumbe, and a few others, which at once introduced him to
                    the first business in portrait-painting; and that branch of the art he
                    cultivated with such success as will for ever establish his fame with all
                    descriptions of refined society. Having painted some of the first-rate beauties
                    of the age, the polite world flocked to see the graces and the charms of his
                    pencil; and he soon became the most fashionable painter, not only in England,
                    but in all Europe. He has indeed preserved the resemblance of so many
                    illustrious characters, that we feel the less regret for his having left behind
                    him so few historical paintings; though what he has done in that way shows him
                    to have been qualified to excel in both departments. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">As the lovers of painting may
                            wish to have a catalogue of this great master’s historical pieces, we
                            subjoin the following :—Hope nursing Love; Venus chastising Cupid for
                            having learned to cast accounts; Count Ugolino in the Dungeon; the
                            Calling of Samuel; Ariadne; a Captain of Banditti; Beggar Boy; a Lady in
                            the character of St Agnes; Thais; Dionysius the Areopagite; an infant
                            Jupiter; Master Crewe in the character of Henry VIII.; the Death of
                            Dido; a Child asleep; Cupid sleeping; Covent Garden Cupid; Cupid in the
                            Clouds; Cupids painting; Boy laughing; Master Herbert in the character
                            of Bacchus; Hebe; Miss Meyer In the character of Hebe; Madona, a head;
                            the Blackguard Mercury; a little Boy (Samuel) praying; an old Man
                            reading; Love loosing the zone of Beauty; the Children in the Wood;
                            Cleopatra dissolving the Pearl; Garrick in the character of Kitely;
                            Garrick between Tragedy and Comedy; Mrs Abingdon in the character of
                            Comedy; a Child surrounded by Guardian Angels; Miss Beau-clerc in the
                            character of Spenser’s Una; Resignation; the Duchess of Manchester in
                            the character of Diana; Lady Blake in the character of Juno; Mrs
                            Sheridan in the character of St Cecilia; Edwin, from Beattie's Minstrel;
                            the Nativity, Four Cardinal Virtues, and Faitli, Hope, and Charity,for
                            the window of New College Chapel, Oxford; the Studious Boy; a Bacchante;
                            a daughter of Lord W. Gordon as an Angel; the Holy Family; the
                            Cottagers, from Thomson; the Vestal; the Careful Shepherdess; a Gipsy
                            telling Fortunes; the infant Hercules strangling the Serpent; the
                            Mouse-trap Girl; Venus; Cornelia and her Children; the Bird; Melancholy;
                            Mrs Siddons in Tragedy; Head of Lear; Mrs Talmash in the character of
                            Miranda, with Prospero and Caliban; Robin Goodfellow; Death of Cardinal
                            Beaufort; Macbeth, with the CaIdron of the Witches. </p></note> The only
                    landscape, perhaps, which he ever painted, except those beautiful and chaste
                    ones which compose the back grounds of many of his portraits, is a View on the
                    Thames from Richmond, which in 1784 was exhibited by the Society for Promoting
                    Painting and Design in Liverpool.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1764 Mr Reynolds had the merit of being the first promoter of that
                    club which, having long existed without a name, became at last distinguished by
                    the appellation of the <hi rend="italic">Literary Club.</hi> Upon the foundation
                    of the Royal Academy of Painting, Sculpture, and Architecture, he was appointed
                    president; and his acknowledged excellence in his profession made the
                    appointment acceptable to all the lovers of art. To add to the dignity of this
                    new institution, his majesty conferred on the president the honour of
                    knighthood; and Sir Joshua delivered his first discourse at the opening of the
                    academy on the 2d of January 1769. The merit of that discourse has been
                    universally admitted among painters; but it contains some directions respecting
                    the proper mode of prosecuting their studies, to which every student of every
                    art would do well to pay attention. “I would chiefly recommend,” says he, “that
                    an implicit obedience to the rules of art, as established by the practice of the
                    great masters, should be exacted from the young students. That those models
                    which have passed through the approbation of ages should be considered by them
                    as perfect and infallible guides; as subjects for their imitation, not their
                    criticism. I am confident, that this is the only efficacious method of making a
                    progress in the arts; and that he who sets out with doubting, will find life
                    finished before he becomes master of the rudiments. For it may be laid down as a
                    maxim, that he who begins by presuming on his own sense, has ended his studies
                    as soon as he has commenced them. Every opportunity, therefore, should be taken
                    to discountenance that false and vulgar opinion, that rules are the fetters of
                    genius. They are fetters only to men of no genius; as that armour which, upon
                    the strong, becomes an ornament and a defence, upon the weak and mishapen turns
                    into a load, and cripples the body which it was made to protect.”</p>
                <p part="N">Each succeeding year, on the distribution of the prizes, Sir Joshua
                    delivered to the students a discourse of equal merit with this: and perhaps we
                    do not hazard too much when we say, that, from the whole collected, the lover of
                    belles lettres and the fine arts will acquire juster notions of what is meant by
                    taste in general, and better rules for acquiring a correct taste, than from
                    multitudes of those volumes which have been professedly written on the
                    subject.</p>
                <p part="N">In the autumn of 1785 he went to Brussels, where he expended about
                    L.1000 on the purchase of paintings, which, having been taken from the different
                    monasteries and religious houses in Flanders and Germany, were then exposed to
                    sale by the command of the Emperor Joseph. Gainsborough and he had engaged to
                    paint each other’s portrait; and the canvass for both being actually stretched,
                    Sir Joshua gave one sitting to his distinguished rival; but, to the regret of
                    every admirer of the art, the unexpected death of the latter prevented all
                    further progress.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1790 he was anxiously desirous to procure the vacant professorship of
                    perspective in the academy for Mr Bononi, an Italian architect; but that artist
                    no* having been yet elected an associate, was of course no academician, and it
                    became necessary to raise him to these situations, in order to qualify him for
                    being a professor. Mr Gilpin being his competitor for the associateship, the
                    numbers on the ballot proved equal, when the president by his casting vote
                    decided the election in favour of his friend, who was thereby advanced so far
                    towards the professorship. Soon after this, an academic seat being vacant, Sir
                    Joshua exerted all his influence to obtain it for Mr Bononi; but finding himself
                    outvoted by a majority of two to one, he quitted the chair with great
                    dissatisfaction, and next day sent to the secretary of the academy a formal
                    resignation of the office, which for twenty-one years he had filled with honour
                    to himself and his country. His indignation, however, subsiding, he suffered
                    himself to be prevailed upon to return to the chair, which within a year and a
                    half he was again desirous to quit for a better reason.</p>
                <p part="N">Finding a disease of languor, occasioned by an enlargement of the liver,
                    to which he had for some time been subject, increase upon him, and daily
                    expecting the total loss of sight, he wrote a letter to the academy, intimating
                    his intention to resign the office of president on account of bodily
                    infirmities, which disabled him from executing the duties of it to his own
                    satisfaction. The academicians received this intelligence with the respectful
                    concern due to the talents and virtues of their president; and either then did
                    enter, or designed to enter, into a resolution, honourable to all parties,
                    namely, that a deputation from the whole body of the academy should wait upon
                    him, and inform him <hi rend="italic">of</hi> their wish, that the authority and
                    privileges of the office of president might be his during his life; declaring
                    their wil<pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=207"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0207-0197"/>lingness to permit the performance of any of
                    its duties which might be irksome to him by a deputy.</p>
                <p part="N">From this period Sir Joshua never painted more. The last effort of his
                    pencil was the portrait of Charles James Fox, which was executed in his best
                    style, and shows that his fancy, his imagination, and his other great powers in
                    the art which he professed, remained unabated to the end of his life. When the
                    last touches were given to this picture,</p>
                <p part="N">The hand of Reynolds fell, to rise no more.</p>
                <p part="N">On Thursday the 23d of February 1792, the world was deprived of this
                    amiable man and excellent artist, at the age of sixty-eight years; a man than
                    whom no one, according to Johnson, had passed through life with more observation
                    of men and manners. The following character of him is said to be the production
                    of Mr Burke.</p>
                <p part="N">“His illness was long, but borne with a mild and cheerful fortitude,
                    without the least mixture of anything irritable or querulous, agreeably to the
                    placid and even tenor of his whole life. He had from the beginning of his malady
                    a distinct view of his dissolution, which he contemplated with that entire
                    cotnposure which nothing but the innocence, integrity, and usefulness of his
                    life, and an unaffected submission to the will of Providence, could bestow. In
                    this situation he had every consolation from family tenderness, which his
                    tenderness to his family had always merited.</p>
                <p part="N">“Sir Joshua Reynolds was, on very many accounts, one of the most
                    memorable men of his time; he was the first Englishman who added the praise of
                    the elegant arts to the other glories of his country. In taste, in grace, in
                    facility, in happy invention, and in the richness and harmony of colouring, he
                    was equal to the great masters of the renowned ages. In portrait he went beyond
                    them; for he communicated to that description of the art in which English
                    artists are the most engaged, a variety, a fancy, and a dignity, derived from
                    the higher branches, which even those who professed them in a superior manner
                    did not always preserve when they delineated individual nature. His portraits
                    remind the spectator of the invention of history and the amenity of landscape.
                    In painting portraits he appears not to be raised upon that platform, but to
                    descend to it from a higher sphere. His paintings illustrate his lessons, and
                    his lessons seem to be derived from his paintings.</p>
                <p part="N">“He possessed the theory as perfectly as the practice of his art. To be
                    such a painter, he was a profound and penetrating philosopher.</p>
                <p part="N">“In full happiness of foreign and domestic fame, admired by the expert
                    in art, and by the learned in science, courted by the great, caressed by
                    sovereign powers, and celebrated by distinguished poets, his native humility,
                    modesty, and candour never forsook him, even on surprise or provocation; nor was
                    the least degree of arrogance or assumption visible to the scrutinizing eye in
                    any part of his conduct or discourse.</p>
                <p part="N">“His talents of every kind, powerful from nature, and not meanly
                    cultivated in letters, his social virtues in all the relations and all the
                    habitudes of life, rendered him the centre of a very great and unparalleled
                    variety of agreeable societies, which will be dissipated by his death. He had
                    too much merit not to excite some jealousy, too much innocence to provoke any
                    enmity. The loss of no man of his time can be felt with more sincere, general,
                    and unmixed sorrow.” See Painting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
