<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0249-0239-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RIDLEY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:852224">Chaplains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954948">Heme</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=249" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">RIDLEY</label> Nicholas, bishop of London, and a
                    martyr to the Reformation, was descended of an ancient family, and born in the
                    beginning of the sixteenth century, at Wil<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=250"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0250-0240"/>montswick in Northumberland. From the
                    grammar-school of Newcastle-upon-Tyne he was sent to Pembroke Hall in Cambridge,
                    in the year 1518, and was there supported by his uncle Dr Robert Ridley, fellow
                    of Queen’s College. In 1522 he took his first degree in arts; two years after,
                    was elected fellow; and, in 1525, he commenced master of arts. In 1527, having
                    taken orders, he was sent by his uncle, for further improvement, to the Sorbonne
                    at Paris; from thence he went to Louvain, and continued abroad till the year
                    1529. On his return to Cambridge, he was chosen under-treasurer of the
                    university; and, in 1533, was elected senior proctor. He afterwards proceeded
                    bachelor of divinity, and was chosen orator and a chaplain of the university. At
                    this time he was much admired as a preacher and disputant. He lost his kind
                    uncle in 1536; but was soon after patronised by Dr Cranmer, archbishop of
                    Canterbury, who made him his domestic chaplain, and presented him to the
                    vicarage of Heme in East Kent, where, we are told, he preached the doctrine of
                    the Reformation. In 1540, having commenced doctor of divinity, he was made
                    king’s chaplain; and in the same year was elected master of his college in
                    Cambridge. Soon after, Ridley was collated to a prebend in the church of
                    Canterbury; and it was not long before he was accused in the bishop’s court, at
                    the instigation of Bishop Gardiner, of preaching against the doctrine of the Six
                    Articles. The matter being referred to Cran-mer, Ridley was acquitted. In 1545,
                    he was made a prebendary of Westminster; in 1547 was presented, by the fellows
                    of Pembroke Hall, to the living of Soham, in the diocese of Norwich; and the
                    same year was consecrated bishop of Rochester. In 1550 he was translated to the
                    see of London. During the same year he was one of the commissioners for
                    examining Bishop Gardiner, and concurred in his deprivation. In 1552, returning
                    from Cambridge, he, unfortunately for himself, paid a visit to the Princess,
                    afterwards Queen Mary; to whom, prompted by his zeal for reformation, he
                    expressed himself with too much freedom; for she was scarcely seated on the
                    throne when Ridley was doomed a victim to her revenge. With Cranmer and Latimer
                    he was burnt alive at Oxford, on the l6th of October 1555. Among other works, he
                    wrote, 1. A Treatise concerning Images in Churches; 2. A brief Declaration of
                    the Lord’s Supper; 3. Certain godly and comfortable Conferences between Bishop
                    Ridley and Mr Hugh Latimer, during their imprisonment; 4. A Comparison between
                    the comfortable Doctrine of the Gospel and the Traditions of the Popish
                    religion.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ridlev,</hi><hi rend="italic">Gloster,</hi> was of
                    the same family with the preceding. He was born at sea, in the year 1702, on
                    board the Gloucester East Indiaman, from which circumstance he obtained his
                    Christian name. He was educated at Winchester school, and afterwards obtained a
                    fellowship of New College, Oxford, where he took the degree of LL. B. in 1729.
                    He paid his court to the Muses at an early period, and laid the foundation of
                    those solid and elegant acquisitions which afterwards distinguished him as a
                    divine, historian, and poct. During a vacation in 1728, he joined with four
                    friends in composing a tragedy called “The Fruitless Redress,” each undertaking
                    an act, agreeably to a plan which they had previously concerted. It was offered
                    to Mr Wilkes, but never acted, and is still in manuscript. Dr Ridley in his
                    youth was extremely attached to theatrical performances. The Redress, and
                    another tragedy called Jugurtha, were exhibited at Midhurst in Sussex; and the
                    actors were chiefly the gentlemen who assisted him in their composition. We are
                    informed that he played Marc Antony, Jaflier, Horatio, and Moneses, with very
                    great applause, which may be readily inferred from his graceful manner of
                    speaking in the pulpit.</p>
                <p part="N">During a great part of his life he had only the small college living of
                    Westow in Norfolk, and that of Poplar in</p>
                <p part="N">Middlesex, which was the place of his residence. After an interval of
                    some years, his college added to these the donative of Romford in Essex, which
                    left him little or no time for what he considered as the necessary studies of
                    his profession. Yet in this situation he remained in the possession of, and
                    satisfied with domestic felicity, and enjoyed the intimate friendship of some
                    who were equally distinguished for worth and learning.</p>
                <p part="N">The eight Sermons which he preached at Lady Moyer’s lecture it 1740 and
                    1741 were given to the public in 1742. In the year 1756 he was invited to go to
                    Ireland as first chaplain to the duke of Bedford, but declined to accept the
                    offer. In the year 1763 he published the Life of Bishop Ridley, in 4to, by
                    subscription, from the profits of which he was enabled to purchase L.800 in the
                    public funds. In the year 1765 he published his Review of Philips’s Life of
                    Cardinal Pole. In 1767 the university of Oxford conferred upon him by diploma
                    the degree of D. D. In 1768 he was presented by Archbishop Secker with a rich
                    prebend in the cathedral church of Salisbury; the only reward he received from
                    the great during a long and useful life. He was at last worn out with
                    infirmities, and died in 1774, leaving behind him a wife and four daughters. Dr
                    Ridley survived both his sons, who were young men of considerable abilities. The
                    elder, called James, was author of Tales of the Genii, and some other literary
                    performances; and his brother Thomas was sent as a writer to Madras by the East
                    India Company, but he suddenly died of the smallpox.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
