<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0198-0188-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RETICULATION</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k055">Twine</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b75c">Rowing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cf8t">Nets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87332f">Netting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1159845">Twine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100781">Rowing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036191">Nets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036214">Netting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=198" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">RETICULATION</label>. Of all the devices which man
                    has invented wherewithal to secure to himself the “dominion over the fish of the
                    sea and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle,” few can plead greater
                    antiquity than reticulation; none has retained its place as an essential item in
                    the catalogue of useful engines so permanently, through all ages and changes, as
                    the net. Other weapons and instruments have either fallen into total disuse
                    before the gigantic strides of improvement, or now only minister to our
                    recreation; but the net, to this hour, forms an indispensable part of the
                    apparatus used by many of the industrious classes of society. As a means of
                    supplying us with a variety of wholesome food, and of enabling us to carry on an
                    extensive commerce with other nations, net-making becomes an art of some
                    importance; and, as an agreeable occupation to the amateur, it may be reckoned
                    among the chief in point of domestic utility; and therefore is not in either
                    case to be placed “next to mere idleness in the scale of insignificance.”
                    Fishing-net making is decidedly now the most extensive branch of reticulation,
                    how serviceable soever it may be for other purposes. To say nothing of the
                    shapes of the various engines of this kind used in our fisheries, their texture
                    is the best that human ingenuity has been able to conceive; for, when wet, they
                    are easily dried, when torn, easily mended; they offer little resistance when
                    drawn out of the water, whereby the labour of hauling them is greatly
                    diminished; the risk of their being overthrown or carried away by tides,
                    currents, or storms, is lessened; and the more shy fish are not so easily scared
                    away as they otherwise would be by toils more densely wrought; the sand, the
                    mud, the young fry and spawn, the small insects and other animals inhabiting the
                    waters, find a free passage through the meshes, and thus much wanton destruction
                    of animal life is prevented, whilst a larger abundance and a more regular supply
                    of fish is obtained than by any other mode. Such are some of the advantages
                    which principally <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=199"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0199-0189"/>result from the delicacy of texture and rarity
                    which, comparatively speaking, all nets exhibit, when fairly used, and no
                    contrivances adopted for abusively increasing the take. The forms of nets vary
                    according to the manner in which they are intended to act, and this is either by
                    entangling the fish in their complicated folds, as in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >trammel,</hi> receiving them into pockets, as in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >trawl,</hi> suspending them by the body in the meshes, as in the <hi
                        rend="italic">mackerel-net,</hi> imprisoning them within their
                    labyrinth-like <hi rend="italic">chambers,</hi> as in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >stake-net,</hi> or drawing them to shore, as in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >seine.</hi> It is somewhat extraordinary that it was not until the year
                    1685 that nets were introduced into Norway, by one Claus Niels Sti-ningen. The
                    fishermen set up a general outcry against so <hi rend="italic">pernicious an
                        innovation,</hi> and, after much disputing, the question was decided by an
                    appeal to the law, and experience has confirmed the verdict, that nets are not
                    only not prejudicial, but highly conducive to the prosperity of the fishing
                    trade. Of the antiquity of the art of net-making it will not be necessary to
                    enter into any detail; that nets were invented at a very early period, and have
                    been universally adopted all over the world, and were, and have been ever since,
                    put to an infinite variety of uses, requires no farther proof than can be
                    afforded by a reference to the works of the most ancient authors, both sacred
                    and profane, by whom constant allusion is made to network; and modern travellers
                    have found it to be in vogue amongst the most rude as well as the most polished
                    nations. For much curious information on this head we must refer the reader to
                        <hi rend="italic">Beckmann.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">Beckmann’s History of Inventions, art. <hi
                                rend="italic">Netting.</hi> See also Adams's Roman Antiquities,
                            “Retiarius.” </p></note> One use of the net, however, though known to
                    the ancients, and long since adopted in Italy and other hot climates, has only
                    quite recently, and hitherto but partially, been recognised in this country. It
                    deserves notice, not solely on account of its exhibiting a curious phenomenon in
                    the habits of certain insects highly interesting to the naturalist, but, for the
                    sake of humanity, it is worthy also of the attention of the philanthropist. It
                    has been found by careful experiments that a net made of the finest thread, of
                    any colour, and with meshes of one inch and a quarter square, effectually keeps
                    out the house-fly from the apartments across the open windows of which it is
                    spread. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">See
                            the Transactions of the Entomological Society of London, vol. ii.
                        </p></note> We must leave it to others to speculate upon the causes which
                    operate on the imagination of the gnat and house-fly, so as to prevent them
                    venturing through the “capacious breadth of these divisions.” It has been
                    suggested with much probability, that an optical delusion in the eyes of these
                    insects produces this w <hi rend="superscript">,</hi> onderful effect. The fact
                    having been so well ascertained, what is there, except prejudice, to prevent our
                    taking advantage of it, as affording, at a very trifling expense, and with very
                    little trouble, a material comfort, not only to “the whole,” but to “the sick ?”
                    How refreshing will it prove to many a poor helpless sufferer to feel that he
                    can enjoy in hot weather the luxury of fresh air, free from the irksome attacks
                    of these persevering, buzzing, biting disturbers of his peace, at a time when he
                    most needs repose, and every palliative that art can suggest! But our limits
                    warn us to commence our practical directions relating to our subject. 1. <hi
                        rend="italic">Tools and terms used by net-makers ;— Accrues, false
                        meshes,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">quarterings,</hi> are loops inserted in
                    any given row, by which the number of meshes is increased. To <hi rend="italic"
                        >bread</hi> or <hi rend="italic">breathe</hi> a net, is to make a net. <hi
                        rend="italic">Dead</hi> netting is a piece without either <hi rend="italic"
                        >accrues,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> (stolen) meshes, which last
                    means that a mesh is taken away by netting into two meshes of the preceding row
                    at once, thereby diminishing the net at any part. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >head</hi> of a net is the upper margin, along which the corks are strung
                    upon a rope called the <hi rend="italic">head-rope.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                        >foot</hi> of a net is the opposite or lower margin, which carries the <hi
                        rend="italic">foot-rope,</hi> on which, in many cases, leaden plummets are
                    made fast. <hi rend="italic">Over</hi> means wide, as a <hi rend="italic"
                        >day-net</hi> is three fathoms long, and one <hi rend="italic">over</hi> or
                    wide. The <hi rend="italic">lever</hi> is the first row of a net. <hi
                        rend="italic">Meslws</hi> are the squares composing the net. A <hi
                        rend="italic">needle</hi> is the instrument used for holding and netting the
                    material to be netted; it is made with an <hi rend="italic">eye</hi> E, a <hi
                        rend="italic">tongue</hi> T, and <hi rend="italic">a. fork</hi> F, fig. 1,
                    Plate CCCCXXXV. The twine is wound on it by being passed alternately between the
                        <hi rend="italic">fork</hi> and round the <hi rend="italic">tongue,</hi> so
                    that the turns of the string lie parallel to the length of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >needle,</hi> and are kept on by the <hi rend="italic">tongue</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">fork.</hi> A short <hi rend="italic">needle,</hi> about four
                    inches long, should be set apart for <hi rend="italic">mending.</hi> A <hi
                        rend="italic">spool</hi> or <hi rend="italic">rnesh-pin</hi> is a round
                    (fig. 2) or a flat (fig. 3) piece of wood, on which the <hi rend="italic"
                        >loops</hi> are formed; the circumference of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >spool</hi> determining the size of the <hi rend="italic">loops.</hi> Each
                        <hi rend="italic">loop</hi> contains two sides of the square mesh;
                    therefore, supposing that it be required to make a mesh one inch square, that
                    is, measuring one inch from knot to knot, a <hi rend="italic">spool</hi> two
                    inches circumference must he used. Large meshes may be formed by giving the
                    twine two or more turns round the <hi rend="italic">spool,</hi> as occasion may
                    require, or the <hi rend="italic">spool</hi> may be made flat, and of a
                    sufficient width, having a portion cut away to admit the finger and thumb to
                    grasp it conveniently (fig. 3). A pair of <hi rend="italic">round-pointed
                        scissors,</hi> so as to be carried conveniently in the pocket, and a <hi
                        rend="italic">knife,</hi> are likewise indispensable. To <hi rend="italic"
                        >return on your work</hi> is, when, in <hi rend="italic">breading</hi> a
                    cylindrical net, you stop at any given point, turn your work and net back again,
                    instead of going on round and round, as in forming the <hi rend="italic"
                        >regard</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">hoop</hi> net; which is a slit made in
                    that engine, through which the fisherman introduces his hand to extract the fish
                    caught therein, when he goes to <hi rend="italic">look (regarder,</hi> French)
                    what success he has had. <hi rend="italic">Taught,</hi> tight; the twine is
                    pulled <hi rend="italic">taught</hi> when a knot is made. 2. <hi rend="italic"
                        >How to make the loop or stitch in netting.</hi> Being so generally
                    understood that any neighbour can in a few minutes teach the uninitiated, we
                    shall not describe the process; a little careful observation will show more than
                    any written description can, however minute. 3. The same may be said <hi
                        rend="italic">of making accrues.</hi> It will be easily understood how a
                    very simple manoeuvre, when put in practice, becomes apparently complicated when
                    described in words. It would be idle were we, under the plea of rendering this
                    article complete, to encumber it with laboured explanations, if they can be
                    called such, which leave the reader more in the dark than he was before. 4. The
                        <hi rend="italic">bend-knot</hi> is constantly required for uniting two ends
                    of twine together, &amp;c., and is thus performed. See fig. 4, in which A and B
                    are to be joined. 5. <hi rend="italic">The art of mending</hi> is of great
                    importance; for, if the fisherman cannot mend an occasional rent, he will soon
                    be obliged to have a new net. Two or three damaged meshes will, if neglected,
                    speedily become a yawning hole; whereas the engine will last a long time by
                    taking care to replace injured parts properly, and without delay. By amateur
                    netters and gamekeepers this part of the art of reticulation is generally
                    unheeded, and a bungling confusion of threads, drawn together any how, serving
                    rather to increase the mischief, is substituted for a neat and efficient repair.
                    In order to explain, as clearly as may be, the method to be pursued, we must
                    request the reader to suppose that a net (fig. 5) has an injury in the middle of
                    the space indicated hy the dotted lines. We must begin by <hi rend="italic"
                        >cutting</hi> the net, that is, the hole must be enlarged, not only by
                    removing that portion which is actually torn, but by cutting into the sound
                    parts. This operation is represented in fig. 5. The parts to be cut away are
                    marked by the transverse lines <hi rend="italic">baa a, cba a ad,</hi> below the
                    knots of the original net. It will be observed that, whereas at <hi
                        rend="italic">a a a c, α a a d,</hi> two sides of the meshes are cut,</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=200"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0200-0190"/>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">one</hi> only is removed at <hi rend="italic">b
                        b.</hi> In performing this manoeuvre the workman must be careful to have his
                    net hung before him in its proper position, viz. in the order in which the rows
                    were netted, as in fig. 5. This requires attention, because, if either of the
                    sides <hi rend="italic">c</hi> or <hi rend="italic">d</hi> were uppermost, the
                    mischief would be increased when he came to cut away according to the above
                    instructions. The next thing to be done is to unpick the knots of the old
                    meshes, α, a, a, <hi rend="italic">a, a, a;</hi> but the lateral knots <hi
                        rend="italic">c, d,</hi> must <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be unpicked, for
                    that would destroy the adjoining sound meshes; for the same reason, only <hi
                        rend="italic">one</hi> side of the meshes ό, <hi rend="italic">b</hi> is
                    cut. We must Suppose, then, that the meshes represented by the dotted fines are
                    entirely removed; the next thing to be done is to replace them. It is evident
                    that this cannot be properly accomplished unless the inserted meshes resemble as
                    accurately as possible those that have been removed. A practised hand will
                    effect this without a spool, but some skilful workmen think that it is
                    infinitely less troublesome, and that the required regularity of the meshes is
                    better insured, if a spool be used suitable to the meshes of the old net. Having
                    filled a <hi rend="italic">small</hi> needle with twine, make fast the end above
                    the knot at K (fig. S), hold the spool and needle in the usual way, and take up
                    the loops L, M, N, as in common netting; when at N, lay aside the spool, and
                    make the side NO. This is done by means of the <hi rend="italic">bend-knob</hi>
                    the angle P being the <hi rend="italic">bend</hi> or loop of the knot. The
                    second row is now to be netted in the same way as the first, and so on with the
                    rest, the single side at the end of each row being managed as at NO, and leading
                    down to the row beneath. We have supposed the workman to have begun and ended
                    this first row, netting from left to right; to work back the second row, he has
                    simply to get on the other side of his net, or to turn the latter over, as may
                    be most convenient, and thus to net on as usual from left to right, changing at
                    the end of each row either the position of his net or of his own person. We
                    shall next suppose that the required number of rows, save one, is completed; we
                    must insert a <hi rend="italic">junction</hi> row between the row QRST, and that
                    of the old net VWXY. This is done without a spool, by making the side TV fast at
                    V with a <hi rend="italic">bend-knot</hi> round the loop of the <hi
                        rend="italic">old</hi> net at V; then the side VS with a <hi rend="italic"
                        >bend-knot</hi> at S, round the loop of the <hi rend="italic">new</hi> piece
                    at S; then the sides SW, WR, RX, XQ, QY, in the same manner. Care must be taken
                    that these sides be of the same length as the sides of the other meshes. At the
                    beginning K and the end Y of your work, leave ends <hi rend="italic">e e,</hi>
                    to prevent the knot slipping. In fig. 5 three rows have been removed, and it
                    will be seen that those loops which have only <hi rend="italic">one</hi> side
                    removed, are diagonally opposite to each other, and thus it is when an <hi
                        rend="italic">uneven</hi> number of rows is to be cut away; but when an <hi
                        rend="italic">even</hi> number is removed, those loops of which only one
                    side is cut are at opposite angles of the orifice, but on the same side of the
                    square. 6. <hi rend="italic">Oblong and square netting.</hi> If it be required
                    to have the net with meshes setting in squares with their sides, accurately at
                    right angles with each other, like the squares in a sash-window-frame, the
                    following method is to be pursued. Net one loop for the first row, draw the
                    spool out and net two loops for the second row, the additional loop being
                    obtained by taking up that one loop which formed your first row twice, or, as it
                    is technically termed, <hi rend="italic">by setting in a false mesh.</hi> Your
                    second row will thus consist of two loops. Remove the spool, begin the third
                    row, which is to consist of three loops, the additional one being gained as
                    before. Continue thus adding a loop at the <hi rend="italic">end of</hi> each
                    row until you have made your half square as large as you require; the two <hi
                        rend="italic">selvages</hi> on each side of your netting forming two sides
                    of your square; then, before you begin to form the other two sides of your
                    square, net one row of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting, i. e. do not
                    increase or diminish anywhere; but at the <hi rend="italic">end</hi> of the
                    following rows set in a <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> mesh, i. e. take up the two
                    last loops of the row together. Your net will at last be reduced to one loop
                    again, and will, when stretched out, form a complete square, and all the meshes
                    will stand square with each other. But, supposing you want your net to be longer
                    than it is wide, and yet the meshes composing it to be square, as in the other,
                    you are to proceed as follows: Form half a square as before, the length of one
                    side of which will determine the width of the oblong to be made. When this is
                    done, you must set in a <hi rend="italic">false mesh</hi> at the <hi
                        rend="italic">end</hi> of one row, and a <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> mesh
                    at the <hi rend="italic">end</hi> of the other row. Continue thus adding and
                    diminishing <hi rend="italic">alternately,</hi> until your oblong is of the
                    required length, aad this is ascertained by measuring the long side of the
                    netting from α to <hi rend="italic">b</hi> (fig. 6), from the corner at <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi> to the last knot at <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Finish
                    off so as to net the part expressed by dotted lines in fig. 6, as you did in the
                    case of the square net, viz. by taking two loops up at once at the <hi
                        rend="italic">end of each</hi> row. In the <hi rend="italic">oblong</hi> you
                    need not net a row of plain loops before you begin to finish off, as was done in
                    the <hi rend="italic">square net.</hi> Oblong and square nets, when worked as
                    now directed, will, when finished, appear in the shape of a lozenge, and so will
                    all the meshes of which they are composed; but when stretched out with the sides
                    at right angles, each to the other, the whole net will assume its proper shape.
                    It adds to the finished appearance of the net, if, in making the last single
                    loop of the net, the spool be withdrawn before the knot is <hi rend="italic"
                        >taught,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">then</hi> draw the twine up; the last
                    loop is thus, as it were, <hi rend="italic">absorbed,</hi> instead of remaining
                    there to spoil the neatness of the work. The single loop, too, with which the
                    net was begun, may have its knot sufficiently loosened to enable the workman to
                    tighten up the loop and make it <hi rend="italic">vanish,</hi> as he did at the
                    other end. A little practice will demonstrate this clearly.</p>
                <p part="N">Many net-makers consider it a great saving both of time and twine to
                    make their <hi rend="italic">hay-nets,</hi> and the like, after this manner;
                    besides which, the <hi rend="italic">selvage</hi> thus formed along each side of
                    the net affords sufficient strength without any additional cord to border it. 7.
                        <hi rend="italic">How to net a round or cylindrical net without having to
                        join.</hi> Net any given number of loops, and, when you come to the end of
                    the row, instead of turning the net over to net a second, keep the spool in the
                    last loop, and with the needle pick up the <hi rend="italic">first</hi> loop of
                    the row just finished, and net into it in the usual manner; thus the row will be
                    united. Continue to take up each loop on your right hand in succession, as in
                    ordinary netting, and thus go on netting round and round until you have obtained
                    the required length. The rows will resemble the turns of a spiral spring
                    descending from the top to the bottom. 8. <hi rend="italic">How to make a
                        bag-net from a square.</hi> Net a piece of <hi rend="italic">dead
                        netting</hi> containing any given number of loops in the row, observing
                    always an <hi rend="italic">odd</hi> number, as 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, according to the
                    proposed size of the bag; net double the number of rows that there are loops in
                    the row save one, as 5, 9, 13, 17, 21. This done, draw the foundation string,
                    viz. the string on which you netted the <hi rend="italic">lever,</hi> and fix it
                    in the middle of your square, then net round and round it. The corner loops must
                    be carefully worked for the first few rounds, to make them set even. It is
                    always in the workman’s power to increase the circumference of his bag as he
                    proceeds from the bottom to the mouth, by setting in <hi rend="italic">false
                        meshes.</hi> In doing this, however, he must observe regularity, and take
                    care to insert his <hi rend="italic">quarterings</hi> at equal distances, else
                    the net will be lop-sided, and distorted. 9. <hi rend="italic">Of joining two
                        nets together.</hi> Apply one net on the other, supposing each to contain
                    the same number of meshes in the rows to be united, and that the meshes are of
                    the same size; then, with a spool a full quarter less in size than that on which
                    the nets were <hi rend="italic">breaded,</hi> net one row along the margins to
                    be joined, taking up two loops on the needle, i. <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> one
                    mesh of each net together; or, if the object be to join the first with the last
                    row of the same net,</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=201"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0201-0191"/>
                <p part="N">the two rows must be accurately placed one upon the other, by folding
                    the net over on itself; then proceed as before. Sea-nets, such as those for
                    herrings and mackerel, which are made in <hi rend="italic">rands</hi> or
                    breadths, are joined rand to rand lengthways, or along the <hi rend="italic"
                        >selvages.</hi> The former are composed of three breadths, each thirty-two
                    yards long by fifty loops deep, on a spool three inches in circumference. At the
                    close of each year the lowest rand, which goes deepest into the sea, is removed,
                    and a new one joined on at the top of the net; so that the rand which was
                    uppermost now becomes second, and that which was second is now the lowest. This
                    latter is removed at the end of the next season, when the same rule is observed
                    in replacing it, and so on every year; thus the whole of the original net is
                    renewed every three years. This operation is called by net-makers, giving the
                    net a <hi rend="italic">new jacket.</hi> Another mode of joining, and when
                    performed carefully it is the neatest, is by uniting the two nets, or the two
                    margins of one net, in the same way as the last row of the new piece is joined
                    to the meshes of the old net in <hi rend="italic">mending.</hi> The first-made
                    side of the <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi> or <hi rend="italic">joining
                        work</hi> must be twice as long as the rest, as also the last side of the
                    suture; for they, in fact, are equivalent to <hi rend="italic">two</hi> sides of
                    a mesh. The following description of specific nets will serve to furnish
                    examples of the foregoing rules, and of the mode of <hi rend="italic"
                        >mounting</hi> nets, which yet remains to be noticed.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">The casting-net</hi> (fig. 7) is netted round and
                    round (see No. 7 in this article); the number of the loops for the <hi
                        rend="italic">lever</hi> vary, as well as their size, according as it is
                    intended for <hi rend="italic">gudgeons,</hi> &amp;c. or <hi rend="italic"
                        >minnows;</hi> in either case, it would be a great loss of labour if the
                    whole net were made on one spool so small as it is necessary the lower part of
                    this engine should be. Spools therefore of different circumferences are used,
                    diminishing gradually from the largest for the top, to the smallest for the <hi
                        rend="italic">tuck.</hi> The following will form a good-sized net for <hi
                        rend="italic">gudgeons</hi> and larger fish. Fill the needle with double
                    twine, net four rounds with a spool two inches and a half circumference, on a
                        <hi rend="italic">lever</hi> of thirty-six loops; then use single twine, and
                    in the fifth row set in twelve <hi rend="italic">false meshes;</hi> net two
                    rounds dead netting, and then set i <hi rend="italic">n false meshes</hi> in the
                    same line with the others, having taken care to set in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >quarterings</hi> of the fifth row so as to divide the circle into equal
                    parts. Net two feet down on the first spool, then one foot down on each of seven
                    other spools, each spool being an eighth of an inch less than the preceding one.
                    Continue to set in <hi rend="italic">quarterings</hi> in their proper places,
                    and at the commencement of the <hi rend="italic">eighth foot</hi> set m four
                    additional <hi rend="italic">false meshes</hi> equidistantly between the <hi
                        rend="italic">original quarterings,</hi> and continue putting in the <hi
                        rend="italic">accrues</hi> until you have netted a foot and a half more,
                    having taken to your <hi rend="italic">eighth spool</hi> at the beginning of the
                        <hi rend="italic">ninth foot;</hi> then net four rows <hi rend="italic"
                        >dead</hi> netting in <hi rend="italic">double</hi> twine; take your <hi
                        rend="italic">ninth spool,</hi> and net two feet six inches of <hi
                        rend="italic">dead</hi> netting for the <hi rend="italic">tuck,</hi> the
                    last two rounds in <hi rend="italic">double</hi> twine. Have a stout line with
                    leaden bullets threaded on it, and sew this line, with running stitches, through
                    each mesh, along the lowest row of the net, the interval between each <hi
                        rend="italic">lead</hi> being two inches. This weighted margin is then
                    turned upwards and inwards, and made fast to the <hi rend="italic">double
                        twine-work above the tuck,</hi> at about every foot of the circumference, by
                    means of ratlines three inches long. The <hi rend="italic">lead-line</hi> should
                    be about a foot less in length than the row of the <hi rend="italic">tuck</hi>
                    to which it is sewn. The leads are made fast to the line by being tied at each
                    end to prevent slipping, and the holes should be bored as near the size of the
                    line as possible. In fig. 7, the lines <hi rend="italic">a, a, a,</hi> show the
                    seams formed by the <hi rend="italic">accrues</hi> running down tile net; <hi
                        rend="italic">d, d, d, d,</hi> are the <hi rend="italic">ratlines</hi> by
                    which the tuck is suspended from the rows of <hi rend="italic">double</hi>
                    meshes, marked by dots; <hi rend="italic">be, be,</hi> indicate the <hi
                        rend="italic">tuck</hi> which forms a series of pockets, or rather one
                    continuous pocket, inside the net, into which the fish fall. Fig. 7* shows a
                    portion of the <hi rend="italic">lead-line l, l,</hi> sewn on to the last row of
                    the <hi rend="italic">tuck;</hi> L is the bullet; <hi rend="italic">s, s, s, s,
                        s, s, s,</hi> the course of the twine, simply run through the meshes and
                    round the lead-line; <hi rend="italic">t, t,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">tie</hi>
                    which holds the mesh on each side the bullet L first; v, v <hi
                        rend="superscript">,</hi> , <hi rend="italic">V,</hi> the twine which sews
                    the line to the meshes, passing over the bullet, being threaded through the
                    loops which extend along the length of the bullet. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >trammel</hi> consists of three separate layers of nettings, and derives its
                    name from its conformation ( <hi rend="italic">trois mailles,</hi> French),
                    because it ensnares by <hi rend="italic">threefold meshes.</hi> The three parts
                    consist Of two <hi rend="italic">out-wallings</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >lint;</hi> this latter is suspended loosely between the two former, it
                    being made twice their length and twice their depth. The two <hi rend="italic"
                        >out-wallings</hi> are to be of the same size.</p>
                <p part="N">The length and depth of this engine varies according to the service it
                    is intended to perform, either in fishing or fowling; the same may be said of
                    the size of the meshes; those of the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings,</hi>
                    however, are generally five times larger from knot to knot than those of the <hi
                        rend="italic">lint.</hi> All the parts should be netted <hi rend="italic"
                        >four square</hi> (as <hi rend="italic">oblong</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >square</hi> netting is sometimes called, see No. 6 in this article), the
                        <hi rend="italic">lint</hi> in twine as fine as may be consistent with the
                    required strength, and the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings</hi> with much stouter
                    material in proportion. These, when finished, are to be <hi rend="italic"
                        >mounted.</hi> Fix each of the four corners of one <hi rend="italic"
                        >out-walling</hi> to four pegs driven into the ground, which should be
                    cleared of rubbish, &amp;c. The <hi rend="italic">out-walling</hi> is to be
                    stretched tight. Pass all round the <hi rend="italic">lint,</hi> through each
                    mesh, a stout line of twine, as thick as that of which the <hi rend="italic"
                        >out-wallings are</hi> made. This line, and likewise the <hi rend="italic"
                        >lint</hi> at its four corners, is made fast to the four pegs; the former is
                    drawn tight from peg to peg, but the latter, being longer and wider, hangs
                    loosely. The meshes of the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi> should be as equally
                    distributed along the line as is possible. Over the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>
                    is applied the other <hi rend="italic">out-walling,</hi> the four corners of
                    which are to be fastened to the four pegs. If the engine is intended for
                    fishing, a stout cord must be threaded with round flat corks two inches
                    diameter, and half an inch thick, more or less. This cord is to be fixed along
                    the <hi rend="italic">head</hi> of the net by means of pieces of twine whipped
                    two or three times round, and embracing the line of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >lint</hi> , the margins of each out <hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">walling,</hi> and tile <hi rend="italic">cord</hi> itself. The
                    twine is tied into a firm knot at those points where the cord meets the angles
                    of the <hi rend="italic">out-walling's</hi> meshes. The floats are placed about
                    six inches apart, and are pierced, so as to embrace the <hi rend="italic"
                        >heud-rope</hi> firmly. This last is made fast down <hi rend="italic">each
                        side of</hi> the net, at the angles of the meshes of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >out-wallings;</hi> but it has here no floats; it is extended along the
                    bottom of the net, where it is called the <hi rend="italic">foot-rope,</hi> and
                    is weighted with small plates of lead rolled and beaten round it with a hammer,
                    as a tag is fixed round a boot-lace, at about every three inches.</p>
                <p part="N">The cord that thus surrounds the net must be bent into a loop at each
                    end of the top of the net, for to these is to be made fast a <hi rend="italic"
                        >draw-rope</hi> when the net is <hi rend="italic">shot.</hi> Some net-makers
                    also tie the three layers of net together at each angle of the meshes of the <hi
                        rend="italic">out-wallings</hi> throughout the area of the net, to give
                    additional strength, and to prevent the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi> getting <hi
                        rend="italic">huddled</hi> together at the bottom when suspended in the
                    water or drawn along the ground. This engine acts thus: The fish or fowl passes
                    through the large mesh <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the out-walling, strikes
                    against the <hi rend="italic">lint,</hi> which, hanging loosely, yields, and
                    protrudes through the corresponding mesh of the other <hi rend="italic"
                        >out-walling,</hi> and thus forms a <hi rend="italic">coecum,</hi> into
                    which the animal falls, and is entangled. The <hi rend="italic">hoop-net</hi>
                    consists of two parts; the <hi rend="italic">body,</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">valve, funnel,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gullet,</hi> which
                    are united in the manner hereafter to be described. Begin with the <hi
                        rend="italic">body</hi> at its lower or pointed end (see fig. 8), and work
                    up to its entrance, thus: Net thirty-seven loops round on a spool four inches
                    circumference, one row. Take a spool two inches circumference and net twenty
                    rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting. In the next row set in five</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=202"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0202-0192"/>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">false meshes</hi> equidistantly, then twenty rows of
                        <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting, then a row with five <hi rend="italic"
                        >false meshes;</hi> repeat this manoeuvre; then net thirty-six rows of <hi
                        rend="italic">dead</hi> netting, and the next row in <hi rend="italic"
                        >double</hi> twine; thus you have an upper and a lower row, as shown in fig.
                    5, the dotted lines representing the lower row. Cut off the thread which has
                    worked the <hi rend="italic">upper</hi> row, leaving an end; empty your needle,
                    and wind on it the thread that proceeds from the <hi rend="italic">lower</hi>
                    row, and work on with the single twine as follows, taking care, however, to pick
                    up only the loops of the <hi rend="italic">lower</hi> row as you go round. Net
                    on the same spool fourteen rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting, then at
                    equal distances in the circumference of the fifteenth row set in eight <hi
                        rend="italic">stole</hi> meshes, then net two rows of <hi rend="italic"
                        >dead</hi> netting, in the next row eight stole meshes in a line with the
                    others; repeat this action three times more. After you have for the fifth time
                    set in your <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> meshes, net a row of plain netting; lay
                    aside the two-inch spool, and take a twelve-inch and net one row. The <hi
                        rend="italic">valve</hi> is now finished, and must be reflected inwards to
                    gain its right position. You now take your needle, charged with single twine,
                    and join on to that end which was left at the upper row where the valve issued
                    from the <hi rend="italic">body</hi> of the engine; with the two-inch spool net
                    eleven rows of dead netting. In the next row set in five <hi rend="italic">false
                        meshes</hi> at equal distances each from the other, and continue to set in
                    these at every third row eleven times in the same line. This done, make seven
                    rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting, then one row on a four-inch spool
                    in <hi rend="italic">double</hi> twine. Through this last row a pliant stick is
                    passed, about six feet long, and bent into a <hi rend="italic">bow</hi> (BBB,
                    fig. S); a piece of cord keeps the extremities in place, answering to the string
                    of the archer’s bow; the lower meshes of the net’s mouth are strung on this
                    cord, see fig. 8. A weight is generally attached to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >bow</hi> at its extremities, somew'here towards BB. Four hoops are lashed
                    round the net at HHHH, to prevent its collapsing; these are larger as they
                    proceed from the point to the mouth, and are made of slighter wood than the bow,
                    the smallest being about one foot three inches diameter, and the largest two
                    feet.</p>
                <p part="N">Some <hi rend="italic">hoop-nets</hi> have more tnan one <hi
                        rend="italic">valve.</hi> In that case the hoops must always be placed at
                    the entrance of the <hi rend="italic">valves,</hi> and many netters make a row
                    of <hi rend="italic">double</hi> twine at those parts, to give additional
                    strength where there is most strain on the netting. The large loops at the
                    bottom of the <hi rend="italic">funnel</hi> are tied together, in <hi
                        rend="italic">fasces</hi> of equal number of loops, to four lines, and these
                    are made fast to another line which is threaded through the last row of meshes
                    belonging to the point of the <hi rend="italic">body,</hi> and which, being
                    drawn tight, closes up the entrance at that part. All the lines are then tied to
                    a support at P, and thus the net is kept extended. The principle of this engine
                    is analogous to that of the common mouse-trap. When there is only one valve (as
                    in fig. 8, V), the fisherman withdraws the fish by loosing the line that closes
                    the body of the engine at P; but when there are more than one valve, he makes a
                        <hi rend="italic">regard</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">body</hi> between
                    each hoop. A <hi rend="italic">regard</hi> is thus made: Net round and round,
                    and when arrived at the part wherein you wish to put a <hi rend="italic">regard,
                        return on your worh;</hi> and when you again come to the place where you
                    altered your mode of netting, return again; and thus continue until you have
                    made the <hi rend="italic">regard</hi> of sufficient length, then work round and
                    round as before.</p>
                <p part="N">A <hi rend="italic">tunnel</hi> for partridges is made like the
                    hoop-net, but without valves.</p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">trawl</hi> is a very large and rapacious net, and
                    much discussion has been held as to whether it should be permitted. It would
                    seem, however, upon a careful examination of evidence, that, under proper
                    restrictions, it is not detrimental to the fisheries. This engine is composed of
                    two separate pieces, called the <hi rend="italic">upper</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">lower leaf;</hi> the meshes are about two inches square. For
                    the <hi rend="italic">under leaf</hi> or <hi rend="italic">blade,</hi> net 160
                    loops in <hi rend="italic">double</hi> twine, two rows, then with single twine
                    net a plain row; in the next, set in a <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> mesh at
                    about the sixth mesh from the beginning, and another at about the sixth mesh
                    from the end of the row; net three rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting,
                    then set in <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> meshes as before; repeat this once
                    again, afterwards go on setting in <hi rend="italic">stole meshes</hi> less
                    frequently, t. <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> leave five rows of dead netting
                    between, until the width of the <hi rend="italic">blade</hi> is reduced to
                    thirty-six meshes, then net about five feet for the <hi rend="italic">hose</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">tail</hi> H, fig. 9. The <hi rend="italic">wings</hi> are
                    now to be set on to this <hi rend="italic">leaf.</hi> For this purpose you must
                    begin working at the other extremity, or top of the <hi rend="italic">leaf,</hi>
                    as at T or <hi rend="italic">t;</hi> net fifty-six loops and stop; return on
                    your work; net again to the end of your row (the third), and here, quite at the
                    extremity, set in a <hi rend="italic">false</hi> mesh; but when, in the course
                    of netting row after row, you come to the <hi rend="italic">false</hi> meshes,
                    do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> take them up, but let them <hi rend="italic"
                        >hang,</hi> as is shown in fig. 9 at B and B of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >wings</hi> W and W. At the <hi rend="italic">commencement</hi> of every row
                    which alternates with those to which you add a <hi rend="italic">false</hi>
                    mesh, at about three loops from the beginning, set in a <hi rend="italic"
                        >stole</hi> mesh; thus <hi rend="italic">the false</hi> meshes will always
                    be on one side, and the <hi rend="italic">stole</hi> meshes on the other side of
                    the <hi rend="italic">wing,</hi> which will thus be diminished at last to
                    eighteen meshes. When this is effected, net two rows in <hi rend="italic"
                        >double</hi> twine, not adding or diminishing. Thus one <hi rend="italic"
                        >wing</hi> is done; net the other in the same way, and take care that the
                    one is exactly the same as the other. The <hi rend="italic">under</hi> leaf
                    being now finished, we pass on to the structure of the <hi rend="italic">upper
                        blade,</hi> fig. 10. Net 180 <hi rend="italic">loops</hi> in <hi
                        rend="italic">double</hi> twine, two rows; then with single twine forty rows
                    of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> netting; diminish evenly and gradually from 180
                    to 160 meshes, taking notice that this reduction must be made before you come to
                    a level with the <hi rend="italic">double</hi> rows whence the <hi rend="italic"
                        >wings</hi> rose in the other <hi rend="italic">blade.</hi> Diminish from
                    160 to thirty-six, as you did when working down the <hi rend="italic">lower
                        leaf,</hi> making the <hi rend="italic">hose</hi> as before. The <hi
                        rend="italic">blades</hi> being now finished, must be joined together down
                    their sides, as the sides of a sack are; and a rope, acting as a binding along
                    the seams, is sewn on, in the same way as the <hi rend="italic">head-rope</hi>
                    of the <hi rend="italic">trammel.</hi> Round the top of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >upper blade</hi> a rope is strung through the meshes, and carried round the
                        <hi rend="italic">bosom</hi> BBB, fig. 9, being sewn to, and not threaded
                    through, the <hi rend="italic">hanging false loops</hi> of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >wings</hi> W, W. The two blades are then sewn together at certain parts to
                    form <hi rend="italic">pockets,</hi> in the direction of A, A, A, A, A, A; <hi
                        rend="italic">oooooo,</hi> being the orifice of the pockets. At L, L, loops
                    of rope are bent, to which lines are hitched for hauling the net out of the sea
                    into the boat. The two <hi rend="italic">blades</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >leaves</hi> must be <hi rend="italic">exactly</hi> of the same length; for,
                    when joined, the top row of the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi> must be even with
                    the top row of the back of the net or <hi rend="italic">upper blade,</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">hose</hi> should meet no less accurately at the bottom.
                    When the <hi rend="italic">trawl</hi> is in the sea, a long beam of about thirty
                    feet in length and seven inches in circumference is lashed to the top of the
                    net, keeping the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi> and back extended from point to
                    point. This beam is let into irons, called <hi rend="italic">trawl-heads,</hi>
                    at each extremity, which serve to sink it. A heavy rope, usually made of old
                    netting, tightly twisted and bound round with strong twine, is lashed along the
                    bosom of the net. Thus <hi rend="italic">mounted,</hi> the engine is lowered
                    into the sea, being <hi rend="italic">trailed</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >trawled</hi> along the bottom by means of a rope attached to the boat’s
                    mast, and communicating with each end of the <hi rend="italic">beam</hi> by a
                        <hi rend="italic">bridle.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">bosom</hi> touches the
                    ground, and the <hi rend="italic">upper blade</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >beam</hi> floats over it; the <hi rend="italic">bosom’s</hi> rope disturbs
                    the fish at the bottom; they are, however, stopped from escaping, by striking
                    against the <hi rend="italic">upper blade,</hi> which extends over the <hi
                        rend="italic">bosom,</hi> so they swim down the <hi rend="italic">trawl</hi>
                    to the hose; but this is tied up, so they next attempt to return towards the
                    mouth of the net; but in their way they fall into the pockets, which only open
                    inwards towards the <hi rend="italic">hose,</hi> and thus are secured. <hi
                        rend="italic">Λ</hi><hi rend="italic">day-net</hi> is used for catching
                    larks from 14th September to 14th November; after that, until 25th February, the
                        <hi rend="italic">trammel.</hi> The reason of this is, that during the
                    latter division of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=203"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0719-0203-0193"/>the season the weather usually is cloudy, and
                    the <hi rend="italic">doring-glass</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">day-net</hi>
                    cannot act. The structure of this net is very simple, and is represented in fig.
                    11. The thread should be very fine, as also that used for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >trammels;</hi> the meshes three quarters of an inch from knot to knot; two
                    pieces of <hi rend="italic">oblong</hi> netting, measuring three fathoms by one,
                    are extended to their full width, by being lashed to light staves of the
                    required length, one at each end (see fig. 11, A, A). These two leaves are to be
                    laid on the ground exactly opposite each other, so accurately, that when they
                    are drawn over, the two margins <hi rend="italic">m, m</hi> shall touch each
                    other. Each leaf is to be staked down with pegs at the lower corners, at G, G,
                    G, G. A line By and By is to be stretched from the top of the stakes B, B, and
                    fastened firmly to the ground by the pegs <hi rend="italic">g, g.</hi> Another
                    line is to be stretched from the head of the stakes <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> in the direction of <hi rend="italic">bC, bC,</hi>
                    and fixed to the ground by a peg C and C. Another line F and F is to proceed
                    from the head of each stake <hi rend="italic">b, b,</hi> and is to be joined at
                    H to the <hi rend="italic">main line,</hi> which draws the leaves over; F, F
                    should each be at least a fathom long. In the centre D is to be placed the
                    doring-glass, whence proceeds a line E. The fowler retires to his ambuscade, and
                    with his left hand he plays the doring-glass with the line E, and holds the <hi
                        rend="italic">main line</hi> H in his right; when the birds are seen playing
                    around the glass, and within reach of the net, he pulls the leaves over with a
                    quick jerk, and thus secures them. The <hi rend="italic">doring-glass</hi> is
                    thus made: Take a piece of wood (AC, fig. 12) nine inches long and one and a
                    half thick, cut out in the shape of an arch, and the edges at the top bevelled
                    off so as to make it a six-sided figure. This bow is to be painted red, and
                    covered with pieces of looking-glass along the sides and at each end; a wooden
                    peg B, six inches long and three fourths of an inch in circumference, a little
                    pointed at the end, with a hole at I, through which the line E (fig. 11) is
                    threaded, must be fixed to the under surface of the arch, at the centre. Take
                    another piece of wood six inches thick and one foot long (fig. 13), sharpened at
                    the end in order to fix it in the ground; cut out a mortise in it two inches
                    high, and one inch and three fourths deep; bore a hole at N and O, large enough
                    to receive the peg B (fig. 12). This device is made to act by winding up the
                    string round the peg several turns, and then pulling it; then letting it wind
                    itself up again, and then jerking it again; thus making the glass revolve
                    briskly, as children do their toy windmills.</p>
                <p part="N">The object we have had in view is that of embodying, in plain and simple
                    language, a few practical hints on the subject of net-making, so that they may
                    be conveniently consulted by all classes requiring that kind of information. The
                    various engines described may be modified, altered, and combined, as occasion
                    requires. It would be endless to enter into these minutiae, or to give a
                    catalogue of the different nets used, with the technical name for each in
                    different parts of the kingdom. We shall therefore conclude with a few <hi
                        rend="italic">general observations.</hi> 1. In all cases use twine as fine
                    as circumstances will permit, and make your meshes as large as is consistent
                    with the object in view; for the nets will be thereby more easily dried,
                    lighter, and more efficient. 2. In filling your needle <hi rend="italic"
                        >double,</hi> draw the twine from separate balls. 3. Take greatcare to dry
                    your nets thoroughly, and hang them up away from walls, where rats and mice
                    cannot get at them. 4. Mend them immediately. 5. Keep them well tanned, or
                    immersed in Kyan’s Patent as often as may be necessary; but never use tar and
                    oil. This mixture has been proved to be inefficient as a preservative, and to be
                    so offensive to the fish as to drive many away from the nets thus prepared, and
                    to impart an unpleasant flavour to those that are caught in them. 6. If you wish
                    to <hi rend="italic">dye</hi> your nets green, russet, yellow, &amp;c. for
                    fowling or other purposes, send them to the nearest dyer or tanner, as the
                    cheapest and best mode of treatment. (b. k.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
