<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0921-0856-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORMSKIRK (9th edition, volume 17, page 856)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897296">Drachma</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104337">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212768">Oman</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n921/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORMSKIRK</label>, a market-town of Lancashire, is situated on
                    the Lancashire and Yorkshire Railway, 11 miles northeast of Liverpool. It
                    consists principally of four streets, diverging at right angles from the
                    market-place. The church of St Peter and St Paul is a spacious edifice in
                    various styles of architecture, with a square embattled tower and steeple, and a
                    Saxon window. To the south-east of the church, and divided from it by a screen,
                    is the Derby chapel, the exclusive property of the earls of Derby, whose vault
                    is contained within. A free grammar school was founded about 1614. Among the
                    other public buildings are the sessions-house and police offices, the
                    working-men’s institute, the public library, the dispensary, and the union
                    workhouse. Rope and twine making, iron-founding, and brewing are carried on, and
                    the town has long been famous for its gingerbread. The population of the town
                    and urban sanitary district (area 573 acres) was 6651 in 1881 (6127 in
                    1871).</p>
                <p>0rmskirk is not found in Domesday; but the parish according to tradition belonged
                    to 0rm, the Saxon proprietor of Halton. The name and church existed in the time
                    of Richard I., when the priory of Burscough was founded. The prior and convent
                    obtained from Edward I. a royal charter for a market at the manor of 0rmskirk.
                    On the dissolution of the monasteries the manor was granted to the earl of
                    Derby.</p>
                <p>0RMUS. This is the European form of the name Hormuz or Hurmûz, applied to a
                    famous city on the shores of the Persian Gulf, which occupied more than one
                    position in the course of history, and which has now long practically ceased to
                    exist. The earliest mention of the name occurs in the voyage of Nearchus (325
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> When that admiral beached his fleet at the
                    mouth of the river Anamis on the shore of Harmozia, a coast district of
                    Karmania, he found the country to be a kindly one, rich in every product except
                    the olive. The Anamis appears to be the river now known as the Minâb,
                    discharging into the Persian Gulf near the entrance of the latter. The name
                    Hormuz is derived by some from that of the Persian god Hormuzd, but it is not
                    unlikely that the original etymology was connected with <hi rend="italic"
                        >khurma,</hi> “a date”; for the meaning of Moghistân, the modern name of the
                    territory Harmozia, is “the region of date-palms.” The foundation of the city of
                    Hormuz in this territory is ascribed by one Persian writer to the Sasanian
                    Ardashir Babegân (c. 230 A.D.). But it must have existed at an earlier date, for
                    Ptolemy takes note of <hi rend="italic">"Aρμovζa</hi> τro'λιs (vi. 8).</p>
                <p>Hormuz is mentioned by Edrisf, who wrote <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1150, under
                    the title of Hormuz-al-sâhilïah, “Hormuz of the shore” (to distinguish it from
                    inland cities of the same name then existing), as a large and well-built city,
                    the chief mart of Kirmân. Sirâf and Kish (Kais), farther up the gulf, had
                    preceded it as ports of trade with India, but in the 13th century Hormuz had
                    become the chief seat of this traffic. It was at this time the seat also of a
                    petty dynasty of kings, of which there is a history by one of their number
                    (Tùrân Shâh); an abstract of it is given by the Jesuit Teixeira. According to
                    this history the founder of the dynasty was Shâh Mohammed Dirhem-Ku (“the
                    Drachma-coiner ”), an Arab chief who crossed the gulf and established himself
                    here. The date is not given, but it must have been before 1100 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> as Ruknuddin Mahmùd, who succeeded in 1246, was
                    the twelfth of the line. These princes appear to have been at times in
                    dependence necessarily on the atâbegs of Fars, and on the princes of Kirmân.</p>
                <p>About the year 1300 Hormuz was so severely and repeatedly harassed by raids of
                    Tartar horsemen that the king and his people abandoned their city on the
                    mainland and transferred themselves to the island of Jerιin (Organa of
                    Nearchus), about 12 miles westward, and 4 miles from the nearest shore.</p>
                <p>The site of the continental or ancient Hormuz was first traced in modern times by
                    Colonel (Sir Lewis) Pelly when resident at Bushire. It stands in the present
                    district of Minâo, several miles from the sea, and on a creek which communicates
                    with the Minâo river,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>∙It is alleged, however, in the <hi rend="italic">Persian Gulf
                                Pilot,</hi> 1864, that this creek, called Khor Minâb, “is in no way
                            connected with” the river flowing past the town and fort of Minâo or
                            Minâb.</p></note> but which is partially silted up and not now
                    accessible for vessels. There remain the traces of a long wharf and of extensive
                    ruins.</p>
                <p>The island adopted for the new site is of a pear-shape, with the stalk to the
                    north, about 13∣ miles in circumference and 4 miles in longest axis. The rounded
                    southern portion is entirely composed of rugged serrated hills rising some 300
                    feet above the sea, and of an extraordinary variety of vivid colours, a few
                    white peaks, like snow-covered hills, rising high above the general mass, one to
                    a height of 690 feet. The hills, with the remarkable exception (according to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Persian Gulf Pilot)</hi> of the white peaks, and also of a
                    range on the south and south-east, are all of salt. There is also sulphur. The
                    island was devoid of fresh water except in one small well which exists, or
                    formerly existed, at Tùrân Bâgh, all the other water in use being collected in
                    cisterns from rainfall; and of vegetation, with the exception of a very little
                    scrub among the hills and of what was produced in the time of the kings by
                    laborious gardening and irrigation at the spot above mentioned. The new city
                    occupied a triangular plain forming the northern part of the island, the
                    southern wall, as its remains still show, being about 2 miles in extent from
                    east to west. A suburb with a wharf or pier, called Tùrân Bâgh (garden of Tùrân)
                    after one of the kings, a name now corrupted to Trumpâk, stood about three miles
                    from the town to the south-east.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Odoric</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.υ.)</hi> gives the earliest
                    notice we have of the new city (c. 1320). He calls it Ormes, a city strongly
                    fortified and abounding in costly wares, situated on an island 5 miles distant
                    from the main, having no trees and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n922/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0922-0857"/> no fresh water, unhealthy, and (as all
                    evidence confirms) incredibly hot. Some years later it was visited more than
                    once by Ibn Batuta, who seems to speak of the old city as likewise still
                    standing. The new Hormuz, called also Jerιin <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> still
                    retaining the original name of the island), was a great and fine city rising out
                    of the sea, and serving as a mart for all the products of India, which were
                    distributed hence over all Persia. The hills on the island were of rock-salt,
                    from which vases and pedestals for lamps were carved. Near the gate of the chief
                    mosque stood an enormous skull, apparently that of a sperm-whale. The king at
                    this time was Kutbuddin Tahamtan, the son of Tùrân Shâh; and the traveller gives
                    a curious description of him, seated on the throne, in patched and dirty
                    raiment, whilst holding a rosary of enormous pearls, procured from the Bahrein
                    fisheries, which at one time or another belonged, with other islands in the gulf
                    and on the Oman shores from Râs-al-hadd (C. Rosalgat of the Portuguese) on the
                    ocean round to Juif ar on the gulf, to the princes of Hormuz. Abdurazzâk, the
                    envoy of Shâh Rukh on his way to the Hindu court of Vijayanagar, was in Hormuz
                    in 1442, and speaks of it as a mart which had no equal, frequented by the
                    merchants of all the countries of Asia, among which he enumerates China, Java,
                    Bengal, Tenasserim, Shahr-i-nao <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> Siam), and the
                    Maldives. Nikitin, the Russian (c. 1470), gives a similar account; he calls it
                    “a vast emporium of all the world.”</p>
                <p>In September 1507 the king of Hormuz, after for some time hearing of the terrible
                    foe who was carrying fire and sword along the shores of Arabia, saw the squadron
                    of Alphonso d’Albuquerque appear before his city, an appearance speedily
                    followed by extravagant demands, by refusal of these from the ministers of the
                    young king, and by deeds of matchless daring and cruelty on the part of the
                    Portuguese, which speedily broke down resistance. The king acknowledged himself
                    tributary to Portugal, and gave leave to the Portuguese to build a castle, which
                    was at once commenced on the northern part of the island, commanding the city
                    and the anchorage on both sides. But the mutinous conduct and desertion of
                    several of Albuquerque’s captains compelled him suddenly to abandon the
                    enterprise; and it was not till 1514, after the great leader had captured Goa
                    and Malacca, and had for five years been viceroy, that he returned to Hormuz (or
                    Ormuz, as the Portuguese called it), and, without encountering resistance to a
                    name now so terrible, laid his grasp again on the island and completed his
                    castle. For more than a century Ormuz remained practically in the dominions of
                    Portugal, though the hereditary prince, paying from his revenues a tribute to
                    Portugal (in lieu of which eventually the latter took the whole of the customs
                    collections), continued to be the instrument of government. The position of
                    things during the Portuguese rule may be underst∞d from the description of
                    Cesare de’ Federici, a Venetian merchant who was at Ormuz about 1565. After
                    speaking of the great trade in spices, drugs, silk and silk stuffs, and pearls
                    of Bahrein, and in horses for export to India, he says the king was a Moor <hi
                        rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> Mohammedan), chosen by and subordinate to the
                    Portuguese. “At the election of the king I was there and saw the ceremonies that
                    they use. . . . The old king being dead, the captain of the Portugals chooseth
                    another of the blood-royal, and makes this election in the castle with great
                    ceremony. And when he is elected the captain sweareth him to be true . . . to
                    the K. of Portugal as his lord and governor, and then he giveth him the sceptre
                    regal. After this . . . with great pomp . . . he is brought into the royal
                    palace in the city. The king keeps a good train and hath sufficient revenues, .
                    . . because the captain of the castle doth maintain and defend his right . . .
                    he is honoured as a king, yet he cannot ride abroad with his train, without the
                    consent of the captain first had” (in Hakluyt).<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In Barros, <hi rend="italic">Dec.</hi>
                            II., book x. c. 7, there is a curious detail of the revenue and
                            expenditure of the kingdom of Ormuz, which would seem to exhibit the
                            former as not more than £100,000.</p></note></p>
                <p>The rise of the English trade and factories in the Indian seas in the beginning
                    of the 17 th century led to constant jealousies and broils with the Portuguese,
                    and the successful efforts of the English company to open traffic with Persia
                    especially embittered their rivals, to whom the possession of Ormuz had long
                    given a monopoly of that trade. The officers of Shâh Abbâs, who looked with a
                    covetous and resentful eye on the Portuguese occupation of such a position, were
                    strongly desirous of the aid of English ships in attacking Ormuz. During 1620
                    and 1621 the ships of Portugal and of the English company had more than once
                    come to action in the Indian seas, and in November of the latter year the
                    council at Surat had resolved on what was practically maritime war with the
                    Portuguese flag. There was hardly a step between this and the decision come to
                    in the following month to join with “the duke of Shirâz” (Imâm Κύΐί Khân, the
                    governor of Fars) in the desired expedition against Ormuz. There was some
                    pretext of being forced into the alliance by a Persian, threat to lay embargo on
                    the English goods at Jashk; but this seems to have been only brought forward by
                    the English agents when, at a later date, their proceedings were called in
                    question. The English crews were at first unwilling to take part in what they
                    justly said was “no merchandizing business, nor were they engaged for the like,”
                    but they were persuaded, and five English vessels aided, first, in the attack of
                    Kishm, where (at the east end of the large island so called) the Portuguese had
                    lately built a fort,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                            attack on Kishm was notable in that one of the two Englishmen killed
                            there was the great navigator Baffin.</p></note> and afterwards in that
                    of Ormuz itself. The latter siege was opened on the 18th February 1622, and
                    continued to 1st May, when the Portuguese, after a gallant defence of ten weeks,
                    surrendered. It is to be recollected that Portugal was at this time subject to
                    the crown of Spain, with which England was at peace; indeed, it was but a year
                    later that the prince of Wales went on his wooing adventure to the Spanish
                    court. The irritation there was naturally great, though it is surprising how
                    little came of it. The company were supposed (apparently without foundation) to
                    have profited largely by the Ormuz booty; and both the duke of Buckingham and
                    the king claimed to be “sweetened./’ as the record phrases it, from this
                    supposed treasure. The former certainly received a large bribe (&lt;£10,000).
                    The conclusion of the transaction with the king was formerly considered
                    doubtful; but entries in the calendar of East India papers lately published seem
                    to show that James received an equal sum.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Colonial Series, E. Indies,</hi> by
                            Sainsbury, vol. iii. <hi rend="italic">passim,</hi> especially see pp.
                            296 and 329.</p></note></p>
                <p>Ormuz never recovered from this blow. The Persians transferred their
                    establishments to Gombroon on the mainland, about 12 miles to the north-west,
                    which the king had lately set up as a royal port under the name of Bandar
                    Abbâsi. The English stipulations for aid had embraced an equal division of the
                    customs duties. This division was apparently recognized by the Persians as
                    applying to the new Bandar, and, though the trade with Persia was constantly
                    decaying and precarious, the company held to their factory at Gombroon for the
                    sake of this claim to revenue, which of course was most irregularly paid. In
                    1683-84 the amount of debt due to the company in Persia, including their
                    proportion of customs duties, was reckoned at a million sterling. As late as
                    1690-91 their right seems to have been admitted, and a payment of 3495 sequins
                    was received by them on this account. The factory at Gom<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n923/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0923-0858"/>broon lingered on till 1759, when it was
                    seized by two French ships of war under Comte d’Estaing. It was re-established,
                    but at the time of Niebuhr’s visit to the gulf a few years later no European
                    remained. Niebuhr mentions that in his time (c. 1765) Mulla ’ Ali Shâh, formerly
                    admiral of Nâdir Shâh, was established on the island of Ormuz and part of Kishm
                    as an independent chief. On Ormuz the solidly-built Portuguese castle still
                    stands, and some of the immense water-tanks, with fresh water in them, in almost
                    perfect integrity. “With their arched and groined roofs, supported on heavy
                    pillars, they appeared like the crypts of some great cathedral” (Colomb, <hi
                        rend="italic">Slave-catching in the Indian Ocean,</hi> 1873, pp. 142-143).
                    Of the city hardly anything stands except a minaret,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Fraser heard that this was erected by
                            Shah Abbas after the capture.</p></note> by some called a lighthouse,
                    but the traces of buildings are numerous and extensive. A small band of
                    fishermen and salt-diggers living in mat huts and a small guard from Muscat in
                    the castle form the sole population. The island is, with Kishm and other places
                    near, rented from Persia by the sultan of Muscat, chiefly for the salt and
                    sulphur.</p>
                <p>Works consulted, besides some of those specifically quoted above, have been
                    Barros, <hi rend="italic">Asia; Commentaries of Albuquerque,</hi> trans, by
                    Birch (Hak. Society); <hi rend="italic">Relationes</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Pedro Teixeira</hi> (Antwerp, 1610); Narratives in Hakluyt’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Collection</hi> (reprint of 1809, vol. iι.) and in Purchas’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Pilgrims,</hi> vol. ii.; Pietro della Valle, <hi
                        rend="italic">Persia,</hi> lett. xii·-xvii.; <hi rend="italic">Calendar
                        of</hi><hi rend="italic">E.</hi><hi rend="italic">I. Papers,</hi> by
                    Sainsbury, vol. iii.; Ritter, <hi rend="italic">Erdkunde,</hi> xii.; <hi
                        rend="italic">Jour. Roy. Geog. Soc.,</hi> Kempthorne in vol. v., Whitelocke
                    in voL viii, Pelly in vol. xxxiv.; Fraser, <hi rend="italic">Narrative of a
                        Journey into Khorasan</hi> (1825); Constable and Stiffe, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Persian Gulf Pilot</hi> (1864); Brace, <hi rend="italic">Annals of
                        the</hi><hi rend="italic">E.</hi><hi rend="italic">I. Company,</hi> &amp;c.
                    (1810). (H. Y.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
