<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0754-0697-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OATES, Titus (9th edition, volume 17, page 697)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7g36p">Rectors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808176">Anabaptists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808921">Anglicans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n754/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OATES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Titus</hi></label> (<hi
                        rend="italic">c.</hi> 1650 to 1705), was, according to one account, the son
                    of an Anabaptist preacher, chaplain to Pride, and, according to another, of
                    Samuel, the rector of All Saints’ Church, Hastings. He was admitted on 11th June
                    1665 to Merchant Taylors’, having, according to one authority, been previously
                    at Oakham. There he remained a year, more or less, “and seems afterwards to have
                    gone to Sedlescombe school in Sussex, from whence he passed to Caius College,
                    Cambridge, on 29th June 1667, and was admitted a sizar of St John’s, 2d February
                    1668/9, aged 18.” Upon very doubtful authority he is stated to have been also at
                    Westminster School before going to the university. On leaving the university he
                    apparently took Anglican orders, and officiated in several parishes, Hastings
                    among them. Having brought malicious charges in which his evidence was rejected,
                    he narrowly escaped prosecution for peιjury. He next obtained a chaplaincy in
                    the navy, from which he appears to have been speedily dismissed for bad conduct
                    and with the reputation of worse. He now, it is said, applied for help to Dr
                    Tonge, rector of St Michael’s in Wood Street, an honest half-crazy man, who even
                    then was exciting people’s minds by giving out quarterly “treatises in print to
                    alarm and awake his majesty’s subjects.” Oates offered his help, and it was
                    arranged that he should pretend to be a Roman Catholic so as the better to
                    unearth the Jesuit plots which possessed Tonge’s brain (Lingard). Accordingly he
                    was received into the church by one Berry, himself an apostate, and entered the
                    Jesuit College of Valladolid as Brother Ambrose. Hence he was soon expelled. In
                    October 1677 he made a second application, and was admitted to St Omer on 10th
                    December. So scandalous, however, was his conduct that he was finally dismissed
                    in 1678. Returning in June 1678 to Tonge, he set himself to forge a plot by
                    piecing together things true and false, or true facts falsely interpreted, and
                    by inventing treasonable letters and accounts of preparations for military
                    action. The whole story was written by Oates in Greek characters, copied into
                    English by Tonge, and finally told to one of Charles II.’s confidential servants
                    named Kirkby (Lingard). Kirkby having given the king his information, Oates was
                    sent for (13th August), and in a private interview gave details, in forty-three
                    articles, of the plot and the persons who had engaged to assassinate Charles.
                    The general improbability of the story was so manifest, and the discrepancies
                    were so glaring, that neither then nor at any subsequent time did Charles
                    express anything but amused incredulity. To bolster up the case a fresh packet
                    of five forged letters was concocted (31st August); but the forgery was
                    transparent, and even Sir William Jones, the attorney-general, though a violent
                    upholder of the plot, dared not produce them as evidence.</p>
                <p>Oates now (6th September) made an affidavit before Sir Edmondbury Godfrey to an
                    improved edition of his story, in eighty-one articles. Among the persons named
                    was Coleman, secretary to the duchess of York, whom Godfrey knew, and to whom he
                    sent word of the charges. Coleman in turn informed the duke, and he, since the
                    immediate exposure of the plot was of the utmost consequence to him, induced
                    Charles to compel Oates to appear (28th September) before the privy council.
                    Here Oates delivered himself of a story the falsehood of which was so obvious
                    that the king was able to expose him by a few simple questions. At this moment
                    an accident most fortunate for Oates took place. Amongst the papers seized at
                    his request were Coleman’s, and in them were found copies of letters written by
                    the latter to Père la Chaise, suggesting that Louis should furnish him with
                    money, which he would use in the French and Catholic interest among members of
                    parliament. Among them, too, were these passages: “Success will give the
                    greatest blow to the Protestant religion that it has received since its birth”;
                    “we have here a mighty work upon our hands, no less than the conversion of three
                    kingdoms, and by that perhaps the utter subduing of a pestilent heresy, which
                    has so long domineered over great part of the northern world.” The credit of
                    Oates was thus, in the eyes of the people, re-established, and Coleman and
                    others named were imprisoned. Charles was anxious for his brother’s sake to
                    bring the matter to a conclusion, but he dared not appear to stifle the plot;
                    so, when starting for Newmarket, he left orders with Danby that he should finish
                    the investigation at once. But Danby purposely delayed; an impeachment was
                    hanging over his head, and anything which took men’s minds off that was welcome.
                    Possibly, too, he was sincerely desirous of frustrating Charles’s Catholic
                    sympathies and secret dealings with France. Shaftesbury, with very different
                    views, was eager in his patronage of the plot and its founder.</p>
                <p>On 12th October occurred the murder of Godfrey, and the excitement was at its
                    highest pitch. That Oates could ever have induced any one to believe in his
                    tales is incredible to one who does not recollect the victories of Catholic
                    France, the relaxing of the penal laws, the activity of the Jesuits, the fear of
                    a standing army and of James, the agitation of the opposition led by
                    Shaftesbury, and the ignorance and apprehension of the designs of the court. On
                    21st October parliament met, and, though Charles in his speech had barely
                    alluded to the plot, all other business was put aside and Oates was called
                    before the House. Here he gave details of a pretended apportioning by Oliva, the
                    general of the Jesuit order, of all the chief posts to leading Roman Catholics
                    in the country. The proceedings which followed are best read in the
                    parliamentary history. A new witness was wanted to support Oates’s story, and in
                    November Bedloe came forward. At first he remembered little; by degrees he
                    remembered everything that was wanted. Not even so, however, did their witness
                    agree together, so, as a bold stroke, Oates, with great circumstantiality,
                    accused the queen before Charles of high treason. Charles both disbelieved and
                    exposed him, whereupon Oates carried his tale before the House of Commons. The
                    Commons voted for the queen’s removal from court, but, the Lords refusing to
                    concur, the matter dropped. It was not, however, until 18th July 1679 that the
                    slaughter of Jesuits and other Roman Catholics upon Oates’s testimony and that
                    of his accomplices was to some extent checked. Sir George Wakeman, the queen’s
                    physician, was accused of purposing to poison the king, and the queen was named
                    as being concerned in the plot. The refusals of Charles to credit or to
                    countenance the attacks on his wife are the most creditable episodes in his
                    life. Scroggs had intimation that he was to be lenient. Sir Philip Lloyd proved
                    Oates to have perjured himself in open court, and Wakeman was acquitted. On 26th
                    June 1680, upon Oates’s testimony, the duke of York was presented as a recusant
                    at Westminster, and in November the informer gave evidence in the trial of
                    Strafford. But the panic had now worn itself out, and the importance .of Oates
                    rapidly declined; so much so that after the dissolution in 1682 he was no more
                    heard of during Charles’s reign, but enjoyed his pension of &lt;£600 or
                    &lt;£900, it is uncertain which, in quiet. Shortly before the death of Charles,
                    James brought, and won, a civil action against Oates, with damages of £100,000;
                    in default of payment Oates was taken to prison; while there he was indicted for
                    perjury, and was tried in May 1685, soon after the accession of James II. He was
                    convicted, and received an awful sentence, the execution of which was expected
                    to kill him, and which was rigorously carried out; but to the astonishment of
                    all he survived.</p>
                <p>Oates was in prison for three and a half years. Upon <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n755/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0755-0698"/> the flight of James, and during the
                    excitement against the Catholics, he partially gained his liberty, and brought
                    an appeal against his sentence before the Lords, who, while admitting the
                    sentence to bè unjust, confirmed it by a majority of thirty-five to
                    twenty-three. The Commons, however, passed a bill annulling the sentence; and a
                    conference was held in which the Lords, while again acknowledging that legally
                    they were wrong, adhered to their former determination. The matter was finally
                    settled by Oates receiving a royal pardon, with a salary of £300 a year. In
                    November 1689 he was again seen in Westminster Hall, when Peterborough,
                    Salisbury, and others were impeached. In 1690, finding that there was no hope of
                    preferment in the English Church, he became a Baptist, but in less than a year
                    was ejected from their body. In 1691 he became acquainted with William Fuller,
                    whom he induced to forge another plot, though not with the success he had
                    himself attained. He appears to have lived after this chiefly in retirement,
                    though we read in Evelyn that in 1696 he dedicated to William a book against
                    James. He died 13th July 1705.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities. —</hi> Oates’s, Dangerfield’s, and Bedloe’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Narratives; State Trials·, Journals of Houses of
                        Parliament·,</hi> North’s <hi rend="italic">Examen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> the various memoirs and diaries of the period; Fuller’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Narrative;</hi> Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Absalom and
                        Achitophel;</hi> Burnet’s <hi rend="italic">History</hi>; Narcissus
                    Luttrell’s <hi rend="italic">Relation.</hi> Lingard gives an exhaustive and
                    trustworthy account of the Popish terror and its victims; and the chief
                    incidents in Oates’s career are graphically described by Macaulay. On the
                    question of the place of his education see <hi rend="italic">Notes and
                        Queries,</hi> 22d December 1883. (0. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
