<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0746-0689-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">O (9th edition, volume 17, page 689)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140749">Symbolism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br5j">Symbolism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04774">Representation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nv0r">Lips</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n746/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">O</label> The history of the symbol O is parallel to that of
                    E. Each represents several sounds which are distinguished habitually in speech
                    without any difficulty, but for which, owing to the imperfection of the English
                    alphabet, there are no separate symbols. Probably the confusion is worst in
                    English; but French and Italian also have more sounds for each of these symbols
                    than can be properly included under them, and so they distinguish these
                    sometimes by diacritical marks, as <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >ô,</hi> and sometimes they do not distinguish at all.</p>
                <p>The different sounds which O is used to denote in English lie, with one
                    exception, on the line between the pure <hi rend="italic">a-</hi> sound and the
                    pure <hi rend="italic">u-</hi> sound. We have already seen that <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> denotes several different sounds on the other line—that
                    between pure α and pure <hi rend="italic">i.</hi> The difference between the
                    sounds on these two lines is this. In the <hi rend="italic">a—i</hi> line only
                    the tongue is employed; it is raised more and more for each successive sound.
                    But in the <hi rend="italic">a—u</hi> line the tongue is not the only agent; the
                    cavity of the mouth is also contracted, so that the passage is narrowed, and the
                    lip-aperture is lessened more and more for each sound; in technical phrase the
                    lips are “rounded,” so that for <hi rend="italic">u</hi> the aperture is the
                    smallest possible to allow of the utterance of a true vowel, hence the great
                    ease with which the Ή-sound passes into a w, in which there is friction caused
                    by the still greater closing of the lips, and therefore we have a consonant not
                    a vowel sound.</p>
                <p>The following different sounds—denoted by 0 in English—are readily discriminated.
                    Beginning from the «-end of the line, we come first to the sounds heard in “not”
                    and in “lord”; for both of these the back of the tongue is much depressed and
                    the lips are only slightly rounded. The difference between the two sounds
                    consists in this—for the first the back of the tongue is more convex than for
                    the second; the passage is therefore somewhat narrowed, and the two
                    corresponding sounds are therefore (here and in all the other similar pairs)
                    known technically as “narrow’’and “wide,” or as “open’’and “close.” The narrow
                    sound is written by <hi rend="italic">o</hi> in English when <hi rend="italic"
                        >r</hi> or <hi rend="italic">I</hi> follows, and the wide is written <hi
                        rend="italic">aw</hi> as in “law,” or <hi rend="italic">au</hi> as in
                    “Paul,” or even <hi rend="italic">a</hi> as in “pall.” The next pair may be
                    exemplified by “pole” and “pour,” narrow and wide respectively; for these the
                    tongue is higher and the rounding greater. Here again several digraphs represent
                    the same sound, as in “foal,” “soul,” “hoe,” “grow.” Next the doubled <hi
                        rend="italic">o</hi> is generally used to represent the last sound in the
                    scale, the close <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> for which the tongue is highest and
                    the “rounding” greatest, as in “pool”; but in “rule” and others the same symbol
                    is used for this sound as would be used in other Europeah languages. Lastly—the
                    exception mentioned above— <hi rend="italic">o</hi> is one of the symbols
                    employed to denote the neutral vowel, as in “son,” as well as <hi rend="italic"
                        >u</hi> in “sun” and <hi rend="italic">a</hi> in “final.”</p>
                <p>The modified German <hi rend="italic">o—</hi> written <hi rend="italic">ö</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">or oe—</hi> is a sound unknown in English. It is produced by
                    putting the tongue into the position for the sound denoted by <hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi> in “fate” or <hi rend="italic">e</hi> in “fête ”—a middle sound in
                    the line between <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i—</hi> and then
                    by rounding the lips. It thus combines the specialities of the two scales of
                    vowelsound— the <hi rend="italic">i-</hi> scale and the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ή</hi>-scale.</p>
                <p>In Italian there are an “open” <hi rend="italic">o</hi> (marked o) and a “close”
                    o (marked <hi rend="italic">o).</hi> The “open” o corresponds to the open or
                    wide sound described above. The “close ”o is not quite the same as the “narrow”
                    o of English, but comes a little nearer to <hi rend="italic">u.</hi></p>
                <p>In the form of the symbol there is no recorded variation, except that in old
                    Latin it was sometimes square, as O. In Greek two symbols were employed—O and
                    Ω—for short and long o respectively. But it is not improbable that the second of
                    these denoted at first not merely long <hi rend="italic">o</hi> but a more open
                    sound, more near to the sound of “law” in English.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
