<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0859-0796-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OPOSSUM (9th edition, volume 17, page 796)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f57c">Opossums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046590">Opossums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152071">Toes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205154">Guatemala</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n859/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OPOSSUM</label>. The animals to which this name is applied
                    are the only non-Australian members of the Marsupials or pouched animals, being
                    found throughout the greater part of the continent of America, from the United
                    States to Patagonia, the number of species being largest in the more tropical
                    parts (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mammalia—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Marsupialia,</hi> vol. xv. p. 380). They form the family <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didelphyidae,</hi> distinguished from the other Marsupial families by their
                    equally developed hind-toes, their nailless but fully opposable hallux, and by
                    their dentition, its formula being t∣ <hi rend="italic">c⅛ pm⅜ m~,</hi> total
                    50, a number only exceeded among heterodont Mammalia by the Australian <hi
                        rend="italic">Myrmecobius</hi><hi rend="italic">fasciatus.</hi> The
                    peculiarity in the mode of succession of these teeth has been explained in the
                    article referred to, where also (p. 378) a figure of the teeth may be seen.
                    Opossums are small animals, varying from the size of a mouse to that of a large
                    cat, with long noses, ears, and tails, the latter being as a rule naked and
                    prehensile, and with their great toes so fully opposable to the other digits as
                    to constitute a functionally perfect posterior pair of “hands.” These opposable
                    great toes are without nail or claw, but their tips are expanded into broad flat
                    pads, which are no doubt of the greatest use to such a climbing animal as an
                    opossum. On the anterior limbs all the five digits are provided with long sharp
                    claws, and the pollex or thumb is but little opposable. Their numerous teeth are
                    covered with minute sharply-pointed cusps, with which to crush the insects on
                    which they feed, for the opossums seem to take in South America the place in the
                    economy of nature filled in other countries by the true <hi rend="italic"
                        >Insectiυora,</hi> the hedgehogs, moles, and shrews.</p>
                <p>The family consists of two well-recognized genera only, viz., <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didelphys,</hi> containing all the members of the family, with the
                    exception of the Yapock, a curious animal which forms by itself the second
                    genus, <hi rend="italic">Chironectes,</hi> and is distinguished from all other
                    opossums by its webbed feet, non-tuberculated soles, and peculiar coloration.
                    Its ground colour is light grey, with four or five sharply-contrasted brown
                    bands passing across its head and back, giving it a very peculiar mottled
                    appearance. It is almost wholly aquatic in its habits, living on small fish,
                    crustaceans, and other water animals; its range extends from Guatemala to
                    southern Brazil.</p>
                <p>The other genus of opossums, <hi rend="italic">Didelphys,</hi> is an extremely
                    heterogeneous one, and has been split up into several groups, some of which
                    perhaps ought also to be recognized as genera. The first of these consists of
                    three or four large dull-coloured long-and coarse-haired species, with perfect
                    marsupial pouches, large leafy ears, and greatly-developed muscular ridges on
                    their skulls. The best known of these, and indeed of all the family, is the
                    Virginian Opossum, <hi rend="italic">Didelphys virginiana,</hi> an animal spread
                    over all temperate North America; it is extremely common, being even found
                    living in the towns, where it acts as a scavenger by night, retiring for shelter
                    by day upon the roofs of the houses or into the sewers. It produces in the
                    spring from six to sixteen young ones, which are placed by the mother in her
                    pouch immediately after birth, and remain there until able to take care of
                    themselves; the period of gestation is from fourteen to seventeen days. Another
                    very similar species is found in central and tropical South America, and is
                    known as the Crab-eating Opossum (Z&gt;. <hi rend="italic">cancrivora)</hi> The
                    second group, or sub-genus, named <hi rend="italic">Metachirus,</hi> contains a
                    considerable number of species found all over the tropical parts of the New
                    World. They are of medium size, with short close fur, very long, scaly, and
                    naked tails, and have less developed ridges on their skulls. They have as a rule
                    no pouches in which to carry their young, and the latter therefore commonly ride
                    on their mother’s back, holding on by winding their prehensile tails round hers.
                    The accompanying woodcut represents Lord Derby’s Opossum (Zλ <hi rend="italic"
                        >derbiand)</hi> carrying its young in this manner.</p>
                <p>The third group is <hi rend="italic">Mic&lt;mreus {Grymxomys</hi> of Burmeister),
                    differing only from <hi rend="italic">Metachirus</hi> by the comparatively
                    smaller size of its members and by certain slight differences in the shape of
                    their teeth. Its best-known species is the Murine Opossum (Z&gt;. <hi
                        rend="italic">murind),</hi> no larger than a house-mouse, of a bright-red
                    colour, which is found as far north as central Mexicq <hi rend="subscript">
                        i</hi> and extends thence right down to the south of Brazil. The last
                    sub-genus contains three or four wonderfully shrew-like species, of very small
                    size, with short, hairy, and non-prehensile tails, not half the length of the
                    trunk, and with wholly unridged skulls. The most striking mem ber of the group
                    is the Three-striped Opossum (Z&gt;. <hi rend="italic">tristriatd),</hi> from
                    Brazil, which is of a reddish-grey colour, with three clearly-defined deep-black
                    bands down its back, very much as in some of the striped mice of Africa. This
                    sub-genus has been named <hi rend="italic">Hemiurus</hi> or “half-tail” by
                    Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire <hi rend="italic">{Microdelphys</hi> of Burmeister), and
                    should perhaps be allowed full generic rank.</p>
                <p>The numerous fossil remains referable to species of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didelphyidae</hi> are of special interest as showing some of the connecting
                    links in geographical distribution between the opossums and the Australian
                    Marsupials, now so widely and absolutely separated. They consist of the bones of
                    a considerable number of species from the Eocene and Early Miocene deposits of
                    central France, one or two Eocene species having also been found in southern
                    England These ancient opossums have been separated generically from <hi
                        rend="italic">Didelphys</hi> on account of certain differences in the
                    relative sizes of the lower premolars, but as nearly the whole of the species
                    have been formed on lower jaws only, of which some hundreds have been found, it
                    is impossible to judge how far these differences are correlated with other
                    dental or osteological characters. In the opinion of Dr Filhol, who has devoted
                    considerable attention to the subject, the fossils themselves represent two
                    genera, <hi rend="italic">Peratherium,</hi> containing <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n860/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0860-0797"/> the greater part of the species, about twenty
                    in number, and <hi rend="italic">Amphi-pcratherium,</hi> with three species
                    only. All are comparatively small animals, few of them exceeding the size of a
                    rat.</p>
                <p>Besides these interesting European fossils, a certain number of Didelphian bones
                    have been found in the caves of Brazil, but these are either closely allied to
                    or identical with the species now living in the same region. (0. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
