<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0861-0798-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">OPTICS, Geometrical</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 798</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:998476">Light</term>
                    <term n="32" ref="fasttopic:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1046845">Optics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:846775">Carbon</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:846943">Carbonization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rk78">Optics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87m7w">Carbon</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25d8h">Carbonates</term>
                    <term n="58" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f7g">Bagging</term>
                    <term n="58" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="32" ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n861/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OPTICS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometrical</hi></label>. The
                    subject of optics is so extensive that some subdivision of it is convenient if
                    not necessary. Under the head of <hi rend="smallcaps">Light</hi> will be found a
                    general sketch accompanied by certain developments. The wave theory and those
                    branches of the subject which are best expounded in connexion with it are
                    reserved for treatment in a later volume. The object of the present paper is to
                    give some account of what is generally called geometrical optics,—a theoretical
                    structure based upon the laws of reflexion and refraction. We shall, however,
                    find it advisable not to exclude altogether the conceptions of the wave theory,
                    for on certain most important and practical questions no conclusions can be
                    drawn without the use of facts which are scarcely otherwise interpretable.
                    Indeed it is not to be denied that the too rigid separation of optics into
                    geometrical and physical has done a good deal of harm, much that is essential to
                    a proper comprehension of the subject having fallen between the two stools.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Systems of Rays in General.—</hi> In the investigation of this
                    subject a few preliminary propositions will be useful.</p>
                <p>If a ray AB (fig. 1) travelling in a homogeneous medium suffer reflexion at a
                    plane or curved surface BD, the total path between any two points A, C on the
                    ray is a minimum, t.e., AB + BC is less along the actual path than it would be
                    if the point B were slightly varied.</p>
                <p>For a variation of B in a direction perpendicular to the plane of reflexion (that
                    of the diagram) the truth of this statement is at once evident. For a small
                    variation BB' in the plane of reflexion we see that the difference AB' - AB is
                    equal to the projection of BB' upon AB, and that the difference CB - CB' is
                    equal to the projection of BB' upon BC. These projections are equal, since by
                    the law of reflexion AB and BC are equally inclined to BB', and thus the
                    variation of the total path, AB'+ B'C - (AB + BC), vanishes.</p>
                <p>A corresponding proposition holds good in the case of refraction. If we multiply
                    the distances travelled in the first and second media respectively by the
                    refractive indices appropriate to the media, the quantity so obtained is a
                    minimum for the actual path of the ray from any point to any other. It is
                    sufficient to consider the case of a variation of the point of passage in the
                    plane of refraction.</p>
                <p>In the first medium (fig. 2) <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> AB' - μ. AB = μBB'cos ABD,
                    and in the second medium μ'OB - μ'OB' = μ'BB' cos CBD. The whole variation of
                    the quantity in question is therefore</p>
                <p>BB' <hi rend="italic">(μ</hi> cos ABD - <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> cos CBD). Now by
                    the law of refraction the sines of the angles of incidence and refraction are in
                    the ratio <hi rend="italic">μ'</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >μ,</hi> and accordingly <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> cos ABD - <hi rend="italic"
                    >μ</hi> cos C’BD = 0.</p>
                <p>In whichever direction, therefore, the point of transition be varied, the
                    variation of the quantity under consideration is zero. It is evident that the
                    second proposition includes the first, since in the case of reflexion the two
                    media are the same.</p>
                <p>The principle of the superposition of variations now allows us to make an
                    important extension. If the quantity, which we may denote by <hi rend="italic"
                    >∑μs,</hi> be a minimum for separate variations of all the points of passage
                    between contiguous media, it is also a minimum even when simultaneous variations
                    are admitted. However many times a ray may be reflected or refracted at the
                    surfaces of various media, the actual path of the ray between any two points of
                    its course makes ∑μs a minimum. Even if the variations of refractive index be
                    gradual instead of sudden, the same principle holds good, and the actual path of
                    the ray makes <hi rend="italic">Jμds,</hi> as it would now be written, a
                    minimum.</p>
                <p>The principle itself, though here deduced from the laws of reflexion and
                    refraction, is an immediate consequence of the fundamental suppositions of the
                    wave-theory of light, and if we are prepared to adopt this point of view we may
                    conversely deduce the laws of reflexion and refraction from the principle. The
                    refractive index <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> is inversely proportional to the
                    velocity of propagation, and the principle simply asserts that in passing from
                    any point to any other the light follows the shortest course, that is, the
                    course of earliest arrival.</p>
                <p>If two points be such that rays issuing from one of them, and ranging through a
                    finite angle, converge to the other after any number of reflexions and
                    refractions, the value of <hi rend="italic">∑μs</hi> from one focus to the other
                    must be the same for all the rays.</p>
                <p>Thus, in order to condense rays issuing from one point S upon a second point H by
                    a single reflexion (fig. 3), the reflecting surface must be such that SP + HP =
                    const., <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> must be an ellipsoid of revolution with 8
                    and H for foci.</p>
                <p>Again, if it be required to effect the same operation by a single refraction at
                    the surface of a medium whose index is <hi rend="italic">μ,</hi> we see that the
                    surface (fig. 4) must be such that</p>
                <p>SP + μ HP=const.</p>
                <p>If S be at an in finite distance, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> if the incident
                    rays be parallel, the surface is an ellipsoid of revolution with H for focus,
                    and of eccentricity <hi rend="italic">μ~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    1</hi> (μ&gt;l).</p>
                <p>Another important proposition, obvious from the point of view of the wave-theory,
                    but here requiring an independent proof, was enunciated by Malus. It asserts
                    that a system of rays, emanating originally from a point, retains always the
                    property of being normal to a surface, whatever reflexions or refractions it may
                    undergo in traversing singly-refracting media.</p>
                <p>Suppose that ABODE, A'B'C'D'E'. . . (fig. 5) are rays originally normal to a
                    surface AA', which undergo reflexions or refractions at BB', CC', &amp;c. On
                    every ray take points E, E', &amp;c., such that <hi rend="italic">~∑μs</hi> is
                    the same along the courses AE, A'E', &amp;c. We shall prove that the rays in the
                    final medium are normal to the surface EE'.</p>
                <p>For by hypothesis ∑μs along ABODE is the same as along A'B'C'D'E', and, by the
                    property proved above to attach to every ray, ∑μs reckoned along the
                    neighbouring hypo<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n862/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0862-0799"/>thetical course A'BCDE' is the same as along
                    A'B'C'D'E'. Hence ∑∕*s along A'BCDE' is the same as along ABODE, or (on
                    subtraction of the common part) the same along A'B, DE' as along AB, DE. But
                    since AB is perpendicular to AA', the value along A'B is the same as along AB,
                    and therefore the value along DE' is the same as along DE; or, since the index
                    is the same, DE = DE', that is, EE' is perpendicular to DE. The same may be
                    proved for every point E' which lies infinitely near E, and thus the surface EE'
                    is perpendicular to the ray DE, and by similar reasoning to every other ray of
                    the system. It follows that reflexions and refractions cannot deprive a system
                    of rays of the property of being normal to a surface, and it is evident that a
                    system issuing from a point enjoys the property initially.</p>
                <p>Consecutive rays do not in general intersect one another; but if we select rays
                    which cut the orthogonal surface along a <hi rend="italic">line of
                    curvature,</hi> we meet with ultimate intersection, the locus of points thus
                    determined being a <hi rend="italic">caustic</hi> curve to which the rays are
                    tangents. Other lines of curvature of the same set give rise to similar caustic
                    curves, and the locus of these curves is a caustic surface to which every ray of
                    the system is a tangent. By considering the other set of lines of curvature we
                    obtain a second caustic surface. Thus every ray of the system touches two
                    caustic surfaces.</p>
                <p>In the important case in which the system of rays is symmetrical about an axis,
                    the orthogonal surface is one of revolution. The first set of lines of curvature
                    coincide with meridians. The rays corresponding to any one meridian meet in a
                    caustic curve, and the surface which would be traced out by causing this to
                    revolve about the axis is the first caustic surface. The second set of lines of
                    curvature are the circles of latitude perpendicular to the meridians. The rays
                    which are normal along one of these circles form a cone of revolution, and meet
                    in a point situated on the axis of symmetry. The second caustic surface of the
                    general theorem is therefore here represented by a portion of the axis.</p>
                <p>The character of a limited symmetrical pencil of rays is illustrated in fig. 6,
                    in which BAG is the orthogonal surface, and HFI the caustic curve having a cusp
                    at F, the so-called geometrical focus. The distance FD between F and the point
                    where the extreme ray BHDG cuts the axis is called the longitudinal aberration.
                    On account of the symmetry FD is an even function of AB. If the pencil be small,
                    we may in general consider FD to be proportional to AB<hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>, although in particular cases the aberration may vanish to this order of
                    approximation. Let us examine the nature of the sections at various points as
                    they may be exhibited by holding a piece of paper in the solar rays converging
                    from a common burning-glass of large aperture. In moving the paper towards the
                    focus nothing special is observed up to the position HI, where the caustic
                    surface is first reached. A bright ring is there formed at the margin of the
                    illuminated area, and this gradually contracts. At D the second caustic surface
                    DF is reached, and a bright spot develops itself at the centre. A little farther
                    back, at EG, the area of the illuminated patch is a minimum, and its boundary is
                    called the least circle of aberration. Farther back still the outer boundary
                    corresponding to the extreme rays begins to enlarge, although the circle of
                    intersection with the caustic surface continues to contract. Beyond F the
                    caustic surfaces are passed, and no part of the area is specially
                    illuminated.</p>
                <p>As a simple example of a symmetrical system let us take the case of parallel rays
                    QR, 0A (fig. 7), incident upon a spherical mirror AR. By the law of reflexion
                    the angle OR 7 = angle ORQ — angle çOR. Hence the triangle R7O is isosceles, and
                    if we denote the radius of the surface OA. by <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> and the
                    angle AOR by α, we have <hi rend="smallcaps">&lt;⅛ = 5~</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> l</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">-</hi></p>
                <p>2 cos <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p>
                <p>If F be the geometrical focus, OF = AF=⅜r. If <hi rend="italic">a</hi> be a small
                    angle, the longitudinal aberration Fg=Og ’- OF = ⅜r (sec α-l) = jα <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> r, in which AR=ra, <hi rend="italic">Focal
                    Lines.—</hi> In the general case of a small pencil of rays there is no one point
                    which can be called the geometrical focus. Consider the corresponding small area
                    of the orthogonal surface and its two sets of lines of curvature. Of all the
                    rays which are contiguous to the central ray there are only two which intersect
                    it, and these will in general intersect it at different points. These points may
                    be regarded as foci, but it is in a less perfect sense than in the case of
                    symmetrical pencils. Even if we limit ourselves to rays in one of the principal
                    planes, the aberration is in general a quantity of the first order in the angle
                    of the pencil, and not, as before, a quantity of the second order. If, however,
                    we neglect this aberration and group the rays in succession according to the two
                    sets of lines of curvature, we see that the pencil of rays passes through two
                    focal lines perpendicular to one another and to the central ray, and situated at
                    the centres of curvature of the orthogonal surface. At some intermediate place
                    the section of the pencil is circular.</p>
                <p>It happens not unfrequently that the pencil under consideration forms part of a
                    symmetrical system, but is limited in such a manner that the central ray of the
                    pencil does not coincide with the axis of the system. The plane of the meridian
                    of the orthogonal surface is called the primary plane, and the corresponding
                    focus, situated on the caustic surface, the primary focus. The secondary focus
                    is on the axis of symmetry through which every ray passes. The distinction of
                    primary and secondary is also employed when the system, though not of
                    revolution, is symmetrical with respect to a plane passing through the central
                    ray, this plane being considered primary.</p>
                <p>The formation of focal lines is well shown experimentally by a plano-convex lens
                    of plate-glass held at an obliquity of 20° or 30° in the path of the nearly
                    parallel rays, which diverge from a small image of the sun formed by a lens of
                    short focus. The convex face of the lens is to be turned towards the parallel
                    rays, and a piece of red glass may be interposed to mitigate the effects of
                    chromatic dispersion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">To find the position of the focal lines of a small pencil
                    incident obliquely upon a plane refracting surface of index</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">μ.</hi></p>
                <p>The complete system of rays issuing from Q (fig. 8).and refracted at the plane
                    surface CA is symmetrical about the line QC drawn through Q perpendicularly to
                    the surface. Hence, if QA be the central ray of the pencil, the secondary focus
                    <hi rend="italic">q</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> lies at the
                    intersection of the refracted ray with the axis. If <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> be
                    the angle of incidence, <hi rend="italic">φ'</hi> of refraction, AQ = w, Ag <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =¾ then</p>
                <p>22, <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi> sinø <hi rend="subscript"> =/i</hi> · (<hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">u</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">φ'</hi></p>
                <p>To find the position of the primary focus g <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, let QA'
                    be a neighbouring ray in the primary plane (that of the paper) with angles of
                    incidence and refraction <hi rend="italic">φ + δφ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">φ'
                    + δφ', Aq</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">— v</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> We have</p>
                <p>AA ' cos <hi rend="italic">φ = uδφ,</hi> AA' cos <hi rend="italic">φ'=v</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">δφ';</hi> moreover, by the law
                    of refraction, cos <hi rend="italic">φ δφ—μ</hi> cos <hi rend="italic"
                    >φ'δφ';</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n863/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0863-0800"/> and thus</p>
                <p>¾ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> _ Μ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> Φ'</hi><hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">).</hi><hi rend="italic">u ~</hi> cos <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">φ</hi></p>
                <p>If the refracting surface be curved, with curvature r <hi rend="superscript">
                    -1</hi>, we get by similar reasoning <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> c os <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &lt;∕&gt;' _ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    &lt;∕&gt; <hi rend="italic">_</hi><hi rend="italic"> μ</hi> cos <hi
                    rend="italic"> φ'</hi> - cos <hi rend="italic"> φ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >.</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u ~ r</hi><hi rend="italic">μ</hi> 1 _ <hi rend="italic"> μ</hi>
                    COS <hi rend="italic"> φ' -</hi> COS <hi rend="italic"> φ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >.</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u ~ r</hi> in which (1) and (2) are of course included as
                    particular cases.</p>
                <p>When the incidence is direct, cos <hi rend="italic">Φ' =</hi> 1, cos <hi
                    rend="italic">φ</hi> = 1, and ¾ = <hi rend="italic">υ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p>In this case (3) and (4) become</p>
                <p>(5).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">To find the positions of the focal lines of a pencil refracted
                    obliquely through a plate of thickness</hi> t <hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">indece</hi><hi rend="italic">μ.</hi></p>
                <p>If <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> be the angle of incidence (and emergence), <hi
                    rend="italic">φ'</hi> the angle of refraction of the ray QAST (fig. 9), S7 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = v <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, Sg <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> =∙υ <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">AQ=m,</hi> we get by successive applications of (1)
                    and (2)</p>
                <p>, ^cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> φ v <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = <hi
                    rend="italic">u +</hi> s∈-,, (6); <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> cos- <hi
                    rend="italic">φ</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    s</hi><hi rend="italic">=u +</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>, (7).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">μ</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">φ</hi></p>
                <p>If the incidence be direct, 0 <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =0 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> a</hi> =u4- A (8).</p>
                <p>Thus, if we interpose a plate between the eye and an object, the effect is to
                    bring the object apparently nearer by the amount <hi rend="subscript">
                    (9)</hi>.</p>
                <p>On this result is founded a method for determining the refractive index of
                    materials in the form of plates. A set of cross wires is observed through a
                    magnifying glass. On interposition of the plate the glass must be drawn back
                    through a distance given by (9) in order to recover the focus. If we measure
                    this distance and the thickness of the plate we are in a position to determine
                    the refractive index.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prism,. —</hi> By a prism is meant in optics a portion of
                    transparent material limited by two plane faces which meet at a finite angle in
                    a straight line called the edge of the prism. A section perpendicular to the
                    edge is called a principal section.</p>
                <p>Parallel rays, refracted successively at the two faces, emerge from the prism as
                    a system of parallel rays. The angle through which the rays are bent is called
                    the deviation.</p>
                <p>The deviation depends upon the angles of incidence and emergence; but, since the
                    course of a ray may always be reversed, the deviation is necessarily a
                    symmetrical function of these angles. The deviation is consequently a maximum or
                    a minimum when a ray within the prism is equally inclined to the two faces, in
                    which case the angles of incidence and emergence are equal. It is in fact a
                    minimum; and this position of the prism is described as the position of minimum
                    deviation, and is usually adopted for the purposes of measurement.</p>
                <p>The relation between the minimum deviation D, the angle of the prism <hi
                    rend="italic">i,</hi> and the refractive index <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> is
                    readily found. In fig. 10 the internal angles &lt;∕&gt;', <hi rend="italic"
                    >ψ</hi> ’ are each equal to ∣ι. The external angles <hi rend="italic">φ, ψ</hi>
                    are also equal, and are connected with <hi rend="italic">φ'</hi> by the law of
                    refrac tion sin <hi rend="italic">φ =</hi><hi rend="italic">μ</hi> sin <hi
                    rend="italic">φ'.</hi> The deviation is 2(≠ - <hi rend="italic">φ').</hi>
                    Hence</p>
                <p>_ sin ø _ sin ⅜(D + <hi rend="italic"> i)</hi><hi rend="superscript"> μ,</hi> ~
                    sin <hi rend="italic">φ' ~</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">⅛i ’</hi> and this is the
                    formula by which the refractive index is usually determined, since both D and
                    <hi rend="italic">i</hi> can be measured with great precision.</p>
                <p>The instrument now usually employed for this purpose is called a goniometer or
                    spectrometer. Parallel rays are provided by a collimator, consisting of an
                    object-glass and telescope-tube, by means of which the subject of examination,
                    either a fine slit or a set of cross wires, is seen as if it were at an infinite
                    distance. The parallel rays from the collimator, after reflexion from a face or
                    refraction through the body of the prism, are received by a telescope also
                    provided with a set of cross wires at its focus. The table upon which the prism
                    is supported, as well as the telescope, are capable of rotation about a vertical
                    axis, and the position of either can be read off at any time by means of
                    graduated circles and verniers.</p>
                <p>As a preliminary to taking an observation it is necessary to focus the collimator
                    and telescope. The first step is to adjust the eye-lens of the telescope until
                    the cross wires are seen distinctly and without effort. The proper position
                    depends, of course, upon the eyesight of the observer, and is variable within
                    certain limits in virtue of the power of accommodation. It is usually best to
                    draw out the lens nearly to the maximum distance consistent with distinct
                    vision. The telescope is now turned to a distant object and focused by a common
                    motion of the cross wires and eye-lens, until both the object and the cross
                    wires are seen distinctly at the same time. The final test of the adjustment is
                    the absence of a relative motion when the eye is moved sideways across the
                    eye-piece. The collimator is now brought opposite to the telescope and adjusted
                    until the cross wires in its focus behave precisely like the distant object.</p>
                <p>To measure the angle of a prism it may be placed with its edge vertical upon the
                    table, in a symmetrical position with respect to the collimator (fig. 11). The
                    telescope is then successively brought into such positions that the cross wires
                    of the telescope coincide with the cross wires of the collimator when seen by
                    reflexion in the two faces. The difference of the readings is twice the angle of
                    the prism.</p>
                <p>Another method is also often employed in which the telescope is held fixed and
                    the prism is rotated. The angle between the two positions of the table found by
                    use in succession of the two faces is the supplement of the angle of the
                    prism.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n864/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0864-0801"/>
                <p>Suppose next that we wish to determine D for the given prism and for sodium
                    light. The slit of the collimator is backed by a sodium flame, the telescope is
                    adjusted for direct vision of the slit, and the reading taken. The prism is now
                    placed upon the table, and rotated until the deviation of the light from its
                    original direction when seen through the prism is a minimum. The difference of
                    the readings for the two positions of the telescope is the value of D. The angle
                    to be observed may be doubled by using the deviation in both directions. In this
                    case no direct reading in the absence of the prism is required.</p>
                <p>The following table of indices of refraction is taken from Watt’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Dictionary of Chemistry,</hi> article “Light.”</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Name of Substance.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Index of Refraction.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Name of Substance.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Index of Refraction.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chromate of lead ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙50 to 2’97</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Phosphoric acid ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙534</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diamond</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙47 to 2∙75</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sulphate of copper ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’531 to 1’552</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Phosphorus</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’224</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Canada balsam</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’532</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Glass of antimony ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’216</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Citric acid</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’527</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sulphur (native) ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’115</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Crown glass</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’525 to 1’534</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Zircon</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙95</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nitre</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’514</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Borate of lead</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’866</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Plate glass</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’514 to 1’542</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Carbonate of lead ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>l∙81to2∙08</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Spermaceti</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’503</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ruby.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’779</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Crown glass</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Felspar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’764</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sulphate of potassium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tourmalin</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’668</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ferrous sulphate ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’494</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Topaz (colourless)....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’610</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tallow; wax</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’492</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Beryl</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’598</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sulphateofmagnesium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’488</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tortoise-shell</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’591</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Iceland spar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’654</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Emerald</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’585</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Obsidian</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’488</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Flint glass</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’57 to 1’58</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Gum</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’476</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>Rock-crystal</p><p>Rock-salt</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’547</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Borax</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙475</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’545</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Alum</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1'457</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Apophyllite</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’543</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fluorspar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙436</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Colophony</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙543</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ice</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’310</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sugar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’535</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tabasheer</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’1115</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>A selection from some results given by Hopkinson,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> June
                    1877.</p></note> relating to Chance’s glasses, may be useful to those engaged in
                    the designing of optical instruments. D is the more refrangible of the pair of
                    sodium lines; <hi rend="italic">b</hi> is the most refrangible of the group of
                    magnesium lines; (G) is the hydrogen line near G.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hard Crown α.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Soft Crown.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Extra Light Flint.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Light Flint.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Dense Flint.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Extra Dense Flint.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Double Extra Dense Flint</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Specific )</p><p>Gravity J</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙48575</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’55035</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2'86636</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’20609</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3∙65865</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’88947</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4’42162</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>B</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*513625</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’510916</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’536450</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’568558</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>l∙615701</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*642874</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*701060</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>C</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’514568</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’511904</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’537673</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’570011</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’617484</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 '644866</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*703478</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>D</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’517114</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙514591</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’541011</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’574015</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’622414</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*650388</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*710201</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>E</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*520331</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’518010</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’545306</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’579223</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’628895</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*657653</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*719114</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ft</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’520967</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 '518686</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’546166</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’580271</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’630204</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*659122</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*720924</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>F</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’523139</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’520996</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙549121</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’583886</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’634748</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*664226</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*727237</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>(G)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 ’527994</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’526207</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’555863</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’592190</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’645267</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*676111</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 *742063</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ä</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 ’528353</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙526595</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1'556372</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’592824</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’646068</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 ’ 677019</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*743204</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’530902</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’529359</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’560010</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’597332</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’651840</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*683577</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*751464</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hi</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’532792</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’531416</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’562760</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’600727</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’656219</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*688569</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1*757785</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>To determine the index of refraction of a liquid it must of course be placed in a
                    hollow prism, whose faces are formed of some transparent material, usually of
                    glass. The following results of Dale and Gladstone show the influence of
                    temperature upon the refracting power of some important liquids. They relate to
                    the soda flame, or the line D in the solar spectrum.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bisulphide of Carbon.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ether.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Alcohol Absolute.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6442</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>l∙3330</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6346</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙3327</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙3592</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙3658</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6261</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>l∙3320</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3545</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3615</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6182</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3309</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3495</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3578</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6103</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3297</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙3536</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>l∙3280</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3491</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’3259</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙3437</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Refractive Indices of Bisulphide of Carbon for the several
                    Fixed, Lincs.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>B</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>D</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>E</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>F</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>G</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6142</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6207</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6333</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6465</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6584</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6836</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>36°’5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’5945</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6004</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6120</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6248</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6362</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6600</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Difference ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’0197</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’0203</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’0213</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’0217</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’0222</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’0236</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The rapid alteration of refractive power with temperature is a serious obstacle
                    to the use of bisulphide of carbon prisms for exact purposes. Not only does the
                    dispersive power vary from day to day, but inequalities of temperature in the
                    various parts of the liquid at any one moment disturb the optical uniformity,
                    and are thus the cause of bad definition. A difference of l <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> Cent, alters the index about as much as a change in
                    the light from one of the two D lines to the other, so that a variation of one
                    degree within the prism may be expected to prevent the satisfactory resolution
                    of this double line.</p>
                <p>Excellent results have recently been obtained by Liveing with prisms containing
                    aqueous solution of iodide of potassium and mercury. This liquid can be brought
                    up to a density as high as three times that of water, and gives a powerful
                    dispersion. Some difficulty has, however, been experienced in finding a suitable
                    cement for the faces. Bisulphide of carbon prisms are usually cemented with a
                    mixture of glue and treacle.</p>
                <p>For many purposes the deviation of the light in passing through an ordinary prism
                    is objectionable. In such cases recourse may be had to <hi rend="italic">direct
                    vision</hi> prisms (fig. 12), in which two materials, usually flint and crown,
                    are so combined that the refractions are equal and opposite for a selected ray,
                    while the dispersions are as unequal as may be. The direct vision prism may be
                    contrasted with the achromatic lens (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Light).</hi> In
                    the first the object is to obtain dispersion without refraction, and in the
                    second to obtain refraction without dispersion.</p>
                <p>Compound prisms, composed of a flint between two crowns, are also made, in which
                    the action of the crown is not carried so far as to destroy the deviation due to
                    the flint. By this construction a larger angle is admissible for the more
                    dispersive material, but it is not clear that any sufficient advantage is
                    gained.</p>
                <p>The principle of the compound prism is carried to its limit by employing media of
                    <hi rend="italic">equal</hi> refracting power for the part of the spectrum under
                    examination. For this purpose bisulphide of carbon and flint glass may be
                    chosen. With Chance’s “dense flint” the refractions are the same, and the
                    difference of dispersions is about as great as for “double-extra-dense flint”
                    and crown. A dozen glass prisms of 90° may be cemented in a row on a strip of
                    glass and immersed in a tube of bisulphide of carbon closed at the ends by glass
                    plates. To vary the ray, which passes without deviation, ether may be mixed with
                    the bisulphide.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    “Investigations in Optics,” <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> January
                    1880.</p></note></p>
                <p>The formation of a pure spectrum, which may be either thrown upon a screen or
                    photographic plate, or received at once by the eye armed with a magnifier, has
                    been explained under <hi rend="smallcaps">Light.</hi> It sometimes happens that
                    the object is not to see the spectrum itself, but to arrange a field of view
                    uniformly illuminated with approximately homogeneous light. For this purpose the
                    pure spectrum is received upon a screen perforated by a narrow slit parallel to
                    the fixed lines. The light which passes this second slit (eyeslit) is
                    approximately homogeneous. Suppose that it corresponds to the red of the
                    spectrum. The eye, placed immediately behind the eye-slit, receives only red
                    light, and, if focused upon the prism, sees a red field of view whose brightness
                    is uniform if the light falling in different directions upon the original slit
                    be uniform. To secure the fulfilment of the last condition we may use the light
                    from an overcast sky, or that of the sun reflected from a large surface of white
                    paper. If it be desired to work by artificial light, an Argand gas flame
                    diffused by an opal globe will be found suitable. When the adjustments are
                    correct the tint should be perfectly uniform. Any difference of colour on the
                    two sides of the field of view is an indication that the screen is not in its
                    proper place.</p>
                <p>The most important application of this arrangement is to the investigation of
                    compound colours, as carried out by Maxwell.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>“Theory of Compound Colours,” <hi rend="italic">Phü.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Trans.,</hi> 1860.</p></note> If light be admitted also through a
                    second slit, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n865/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0865-0802"/> displaced laterally from the position occupied by
                    the first, a second spectrum overlapping the former will be thrown upon the
                    screen, and a second kind of light will be admitted to the eye. In this way we
                    may obtain a field of view lighted with a mixture of two or more spectrum
                    colours, and we may control the relative proportions by varying the widths of
                    the slits. For instance, by mixing almost any kind of red with any kind of green
                    not inclining to blue we may match the brightest yellows, proving λvhat so many
                    find it difficult to believe, that yellow is a compound colour. In Maxwell’s
                    systematic examination of the spectrum, mixtures of three colours were used, and
                    the proportions were adjusted so as to match the original white light incident
                    upon the apparatus.</p>
                <p>A similar arrangement (with one original slit) was employed by Helmholtz in his
                    examination of a fundamental question raised by Brewster. The latter physicist
                    maintained that there was abundant evidence to show that light of definite
                    refrangibility was susceptible of further analysis by absorption, so that the
                    colour of light (even of given brightness) could not be defined in terms of
                    refrangibility or wave-length alone. The appearances which misled Brewster have
                    since been explained as the effect of contrast or of insufficient purity. It is
                    obvious that light, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> from the red end of the
                    spectrum, may be contaminated with light from some other part, say the yellow,
                    in such proportion that though originally entirely preponderant it may fall into
                    the second place under the action of a medium very much more transparent to
                    yellow than to red. To obtain light of sufficient purity for these experiments
                    Helmholtz found it advisable to employ a double prismatic analysis. A spectrum
                    is first thrown upon a screen perforated by a slit in the manner already
                    described. The light which penetrates the second slit, already nearly pure, is
                    caused to pass a second prism by the action of which any stray light is thrown
                    aside. Using such doubly purified light, Helmholtz found the colour preserved,
                    whatever absorbing agents were brought into play. Light of given refrangibility
                    may produce a variety of <hi rend="italic">effects,</hi> visual, thermal, or
                    chemical, but (apart from polarization) it is not itself divisible into parts of
                    different kinds. If yellow light produces the compound sensation of yellow, we
                    are to seek the explanation in the constitution of the retina, and not in the
                    divisibility of the light.</p>
                <p>In all accurate work with the prism the use of a collimating lens to render the
                    incident light parallel is a matter of necessity. If the incident rays diverge
                    from a point at a finite distance, the pencil after emergence will be of a
                    highly complicated character. There are, however, cases in which a collimator is
                    dispensed with, and thus it is a problem of interest to find the foci of a thin
                    pencil originally diverging from a point at a moderate distance. Even when a
                    collimator is employed, the same problem presents itself whenever the focusing
                    is imperfect. For the sake of simplicity the pencil is supposed to pass so near
                    the edge of the prism that the length of path within the glass may be neglected
                    in comparison with the distances of the foci.</p>
                <p>We denote as usual the angles of incidence and emergence by <hi rend="italic">Φ,
                    ψ,</hi> and the corresponding angles within the glass by <hi rend="italic">φ',
                    φ'.</hi> The distance AQ from the edge of the prism to original source is
                    denoted by <hi rend="italic">u</hi>; the corresponding distances for the primary
                    and secondary f°ci ft, g ’ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> by <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> υ <hi rend="italic superscript"> v</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">2∙</hi> By successive applications of the results already proved
                    for a single refraction, we get cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &lt;⅛' cos
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ≠</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">υ.,=u, υ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=—£</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic">ιc</hi> fl); cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    &lt;∕&gt; <hi rend="italic">cos</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ψ</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> v</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">' ’</hi> so that <hi rend="italic"> υ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1</hi> _ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ≠' <hi rend="italic">
                    cos-ψ</hi><hi rend="italic">_</hi> (μ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- 1) tan <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ≠ + μ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >v</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi> cos <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ≠ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ^' ~ (μ-'-l)tan
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ^ + <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi> u <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> '</p>
                <p>In order that the primary and secondary foci may coincide we must have <hi
                    rend="italic">ψ=φ</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> that is to say, the ray must pass
                    with minimum deviation. This is sometimes given as a reason why this arrangement
                    should be adopted in spectroscopes; but in reality, since the slit is parallel
                    to the edge of the prism, a slight elongation in this direction of the image of
                    a point is without detriment to the definition. Hence a good image will be seen
                    when the telescope is adjusted for the <hi rend="italic">primary</hi> focus; and
                    it is not clear that any improvement λvould arise from coincidence of the two
                    foci, the question being in fact one of aberration. The position of minimum
                    deviation is, however, usually adopted for the sake of definiteness, and
                    sometimes it is convenient that the fixed lines and the extremities of the slit
                    (or the markings produced by dust) should be in focus together.</p>
                <p>The deviation is a symmetrical function of <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">φ,</hi> and therefore is not altered by an interchange of these
                    angles. The corresponding values of <hi rend="italic">v</hi> are thus by (1)
                    reciprocals, and their product is equal to w <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.
                    This principle has been ingeniously applied by Schuster<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> February
                    1879.</p></note> to the adjustment for focus of the telescope and collimator of
                    a spectroscope. The telescope is so placed that the deviation necessary to bring
                    the object upon the cross wires is greater than the minimum, and the prism is
                    adjusted in azimuth until the effect is produced, that position being chosen for
                    which the angle of incidence is greater than the angle of emergence, so that r
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> is greater than <hi rend="italic">u.</hi> After
                    focusing the telescope the prism is turned into the other position which gives
                    the same deviation, and the <hi rend="italic">collimator</hi> is focused, the
                    telescope remaining untouched. The prism is next brought back to the first
                    position, and the telescope is again focused. A few repetitions of this
                    operation, always focusing the telescope in the first position of the prism and
                    the collimator in the second, will bring both into perfect adjustment for
                    parallel rays.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lenses.—</hi> The usual formula for the focal length of lenses
                    (vol. xiv. p. 593),</p>
                <p>)-⅛-υ(<hi rend="superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>-i)</p>
                <p>ignores the fact that the various parts of a lens bounded by spherical surfaces
                    have not the same focus, and is applicable in strictness only when the aperture
                    is small. It is not necessary here to repeat the process by which (1) is usually
                    obtained, but before passing on to give the formulae for the aberration of
                    lenses it may be well to exhibit the significance of (1) from the point of view
                    of the wavetheory.</p>
                <p>Taking the case of a convex lens of glass, let us suppose that parallel rays DA,
                    EC, GB (fig. 13) fall upon the lens ACB, and are collected by it to a focus at
                    F. The points D, E, G, equally distant from</p>
                <p>ACB, lie upon a front of the wave before it impinges upon the lens. The focus is
                    a point at which the different parts of the wave arrive at the same time, and
                    that such a point can exist depends upon the fact that the propagation is slower
                    in glass than in air. The ray ECF is retarded from having to pass through the
                    thickness (i) of glass by the amount (μ - l)i. The ray DAF, which traverses only
                    the extreme edge of the lens, is retarded merely on account of the crookedness
                    of its path, and the amount of the retardation is measured by AF - CF. If F is a
                    focus these retardations must be equal, or</p>
                <p>AF-CF=(∕*-l)i,</p>
                <p>Now if <hi rend="italic">y</hi> be the semi-aperture AC of the lens, and ∕ be the
                    focal length CF,</p>
                <p>AF-CF = √{∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +y <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>}
                    -∕=⅜ y-approximately,</p>
                <p>. o∕2</p>
                <p>whence f= —* <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> (2).</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> 2(<hi rend="subscript"> λt</hi>-l)i <hi
                    rend="superscript"> k</hi> '</p>
                <p>In the case of plate-glass <hi rend="italic">μ</hi>- 1 = ∣ nearly, and then the
                    rule (2) may be thus stated: <hi rend="italic">the semi-aperture is a mean
                    proportional between the focal length and the thickness.</hi> The form (2) is in
                    general the more significant, as well as the more practically useful, but we may
                    of course express the thickness in terms of the curvatures and semi-aperture by
                    means of <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n866/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0866-0803"/> In the preceding statement it has been supposed
                    for simplicity that the lens comes to a sharp edge. If this be not the case we
                    must take as the thickness of the lens the <hi rend="italic">difference</hi> of
                    the thicknesses at the centre and at the circumference. In this form the
                    statement is applicable to concave lenses, and we see that the focal length is
                    positive when the lens is thickest at the centre, but negative when the lens is
                    thickest at the edge.</p>
                <p>To determine practically the focal length of a convex lens we may proceed in
                    several ways. A convenient plan is to set up a source of light Q (fig. 14) and a
                    screen <hi rend="italic">q</hi> at a distance exceeding four times the focal
                    length, and to observe the two positions of the lens A, A' at which the source
                    is in focus upon the screen. These positions are symmetrically situated, and the
                    distance between them is observed. Thus</p>
                <p>AQ = ⅜Qg ’ + ⅛AA', A <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =^Q^-⅛AA'.</p>
                <p>Now <hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> a</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">j__i_</hi></p>
                <p>AQ <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic">Aq~f ’</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> so that</hi> AQ. <hi rend="italic">kq</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> =</hi> Q&lt;∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- AA' <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> f</hi> ~ AQ + A? <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -4</hi> Q?</p>
                <p>From the measured values of· Q⅛ and A A',/ can be deduced.</p>
                <p>If A and A' coincide, the conjugate foci Q and <hi rend="italic">q</hi> are as
                    close as possible to one another, and then ∕ = ∣Q&lt;∕.</p>
                <p>The focal length on a concave lens may be found by combining it with a more
                    powerful convex lens of known focus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Aberration of Lenses.—</hi> The formula (1) determines the
                    point at which a ray, originally parallel to the axis and at but a short
                    distance from it, crosses the axis after passage through the lens. When,
                    however, the ray considered is not quite close to the axis, the point thus
                    determined varies with the distance <hi rend="italic">y.</hi> In the case of a
                    convex lens the ray DH (fig. 15), distant HC ( = y) from the axis, crosses it
                    after refraction at a point F' which lies nearer to the lens than the point F
                    determined by (1), and corresponding to an infinitely small value of <hi
                    rend="italic">y.</hi> The distance F'F is called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >longitudinal aberration</hi> of the ray, and may be denoted by <hi
                    rend="italic">8f.</hi></p>
                <p>The calculation of the longitudinal aberration as dependent upon the refractive
                    index (μ) and the anterior and posterior radii of the surfaces (r, <hi
                    rend="italic">s')</hi> is straight forward, but is scarcely of sufficient
                    interest to be given at length in a work like the present. It is found that</p>
                <p>- <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> ∕^=⅛{⅜ <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi>
                    (ψ-l)(l-j∏∕3...(3X</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">r, s,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f</hi> being related as usual
                    by (1).</p>
                <p>The first question which suggests itself is whether it is possible so to
                    proportion <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and s that the aberration may vanish.
                    Writing for brevity R, S, F respectively for r <hi rend="superscript"> -1</hi>.
                    s <hi rend="superscript"> -1</hi>, ∕ <hi rend="superscript"> -1</hi>, and taking
                    ∕∕P ’</p>
                <p>G = so that - S = (G/μ) - R, we get μ- 1</p>
                <p>⅛ + (<hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> y <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- τ)(y - ⅛)
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = <hi rend="superscript"> G</hi> i W+ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) - RG(2μ+l)+μG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>} -r∕
                    <hi rend="italic">H</hi> J-ΟΊ P (2μ + l)G V, μ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> F
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 4μ-1.</p>
                <p>-Gj√(μ + 2).R- <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ^ <hi rend="subscript"> + 2</hi> J +
                    <hi rend="subscript"> (/t</hi> _ <hi rend="subscript"> 1)84(M + 2</hi>)···(<hi
                    rend="superscript"> 4</hi>)·</p>
                <p>Since μ &gt;1, both terms are of the same sign; and thus it appears that the <hi
                    rend="italic">aberration can never vanish,</hi> whatever may be the ratio of <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> to s. Under these circumstances all that we can do is
                    to ascertain for what form of lens the aberration is a minimum, the focal length
                    and aperture being given. For this purpose we must suppose that the first term
                    of (4) vanishes, which gives</p>
                <p>2(μ + 2)(μ-l)</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ~ μ(2μ <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> l)</p>
                <p>The corresponding value of-s is</p>
                <p>2(μ+2)(μ-l) <hi rend="italic superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">--ΓΓμ-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 2μ</hi><hi rend="italic">2 f</hi> (6)&gt; so that <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">-</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> szr</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">-</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"> m(</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"> ^+1)</hi><hi rend="subscript
                    smallcaps"> m</hi></p>
                <p>4+μ-2μ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> '*</p>
                <p>In the case of plate-glass μ=1 · 5 nearly, and then from (5), (6), (7) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> =⅛ ^ <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> =⅛∕&gt; -s:
                    r=6:l.</p>
                <p>Both surfaces are therefore convex, but the curvature of the anterior surface
                    (that directed towards the incident parallel rays) is six times the curvature of
                    the posterior surface. By (3) the outstanding aberration is</p>
                <p>15 y <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="superscript"> δ</hi> ∙^ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 14 ∕ &lt; <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi>) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi></p>
                <p>The use of a plano-convex lens instead of that above determined does not entail
                    much increase of aberration. Putting in (3) s= αo, and therefore by (1) <hi
                    rend="italic">τ=⅛f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> we get</p>
                <p>*∕=4τ <hi rend="superscript"> (9)</hi> ·</p>
                <p>This is on the supposition that the curved side faces the parallel rays. If the
                    lens be turned round so as to present the plane face to the incident light we
                    have <hi rend="italic">r=∞, -s=⅛f,</hi> and then <hi rend="italic superscript">
                    s</hi><hi rend="italic">-f=-lτ—</hi> (10).</p>
                <p>nearly four times as great.</p>
                <p>For a somewhat higher value of μ the plano-convex becomes the form of minimum
                    aberration. If s=∞ in (6), 4+μ-2μ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =0, whence
                    μ=l'69.</p>
                <p>If μ be very great, we see from (5) and (6) that <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and s
                    tend to become identical with <hi rend="italic">f.</hi></p>
                <p>For the general value of μ the minimum aberration corresponding to (7) is by
                    (4)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">_ . f _</hi> X*μ-i) ∏ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic superscript"> δf</hi><hi rend="italic">∙f</hi> 8(μ-l) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (μ + 2)</p>
                <p>The right-hand member of (11) tends to diminish as μ increases, but it remains
                    considerable for all natural substances. If μ=2, <hi rend="italic superscript">
                    f</hi><hi rend="italic">f</hi> 16</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Oblique Pencils.—</hi> Hitherto we have supposed that the axis
                    of the pencil coincides with the axis of the lens. If the axis of the pencil,
                    though incident obliquely, pass through the centre of the lens, it suffers no
                    deviation, the surfaces being parallel at the points of incidence and emergence.
                    In this case the primary and secondary foci are formed at distances from the
                    centre of the lens which can only differ from the distance corresponding to a
                    direct pencil by quantities of the second order in the obliquity. Hence, if the
                    obliquity be moderate, we may use the same formulae for oblique as for direct
                    pencils.</p>
                <p>The consideration of excentrical pencils leads to calculations of great
                    complexity, upon which we do not enter.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Chromatic Aberration.—</hi> The operation of simple lenses is
                    much interfered with by the variation of the refractive index with the colour of
                    the light. The focal length is decidedly less for blue than for red light, and
                    thus in the ordinary case of white light it is impossible to obtain a perfect
                    image, however completely the spherical aberration may be corrected. From the
                    formula for the focal length we see that <hi rend="italic">f-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> μ</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">r s
                    )</hi> μ-l <hi rend="italic">f'</hi> so that</p>
                <p>-v=⅛∕≡</p>
                <p>or the longitudinal chromatic aberration varies as the focal length and as the
                    dispersive power of the material composing<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n867/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0867-0804"/> the lens. The best image will be formed at a
                    position midway between the two foci, and the diameter <hi rend="italic">d</hi>
                    of the circle over which the rays are spread bears the same ratio to the
                    semi-aperture of the lens (y) that δ∕ bears to <hi rend="italic">f.</hi> Hence
                    <hi rend="italic">δμ d=</hi> — <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> y.</p>
                <p>M-l</p>
                <p>The diameter of the circle of chromatic aberration is thus proportional to the
                    aperture and <hi rend="italic">independent of the focal length</hi>; and, since
                    the linear dimensions of the image are proportional to the focal length, the
                    confusion due to chromatic aberration may be considered to be inversely as the
                    focal length. Before the invention of the achromatic object-glass this source of
                    imperfect definition was by far the most important, and, in order to mitigate
                    its influence, telescopes were made of gigantic length. Even at the present day
                    the images of large so-called achromatic glasses are sensibly impaired by
                    secondary chromatic aberration, the effect of which is also directly as the
                    aperture and inversely as the focal length.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Achromatic Object-glasses.—</hi> It has been shown in vol. xiv.
                    p. 595 that the condition of achromatism for two thin lenses placed close
                    together is</p>
                <p>⅛⅛7=&lt;&gt; (1).</p>
                <p>∕* -1 ∕ Μ -1 ∕</p>
                <p>in which <hi rend="italic">f f'</hi> are the focal lengths of the two lenses, and
                    δ∕z∕(∕χ - 1), <hi rend="italic">δμ∕(μ'</hi>- 1) the dispersive powers of the two
                    kinds of glass. In practice crown and flint glass are used, the dispersive power
                    of the flint being greater than that of the crown. Thus <hi rend="italic"
                    >f'</hi> is negative and numerically greater than <hi rend="italic">f,</hi> so
                    that the combination consists of a convex lens of crown and a concave lens of
                    flint, the converging power of the crown overpowering the diverging power of the
                    flint. When the focal length F of the combination is given, the focal lengths of
                    the individual lenses are determined by (1) in conjunction with</p>
                <p>1 1 1</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> f=7</hi><hi rend="italic superscript smallcaps">
                    +</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> 7</hi><hi rend="italic superscript
                    smallcaps"> γ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript smallcaps"> (2)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> ·</hi></p>
                <p>The matter, however, is not quite so simple as the above account of it might lead
                    us to suppose. In consequence of what is called the irrationality of spectra,
                    the ratio of dispersive powers of two media is dependent upon the parts of the
                    spectrum which we take into consideration. Whatever two rays of the spectrum we
                    like to select, we can secure that the compound lens shall have the same focal
                    length for these rays, but we shall then find that for other rays the focal
                    length is slightly different. In the case of a single lens the focal length
                    continually diminishes as we pass up the spectrum from red to violet. By the use
                    of two lenses the spectrum, formed as it were along the axis, is doubled upon
                    itself. The focal length is least for a certain ray, which may be selected at
                    pleasure. Thus in the ordinary achromatic lens, intended for use with the eye,
                    the focal length is a minimum for the green, and increases as we pass away from
                    the green, whether towards red or towards blue. Stokes has shown that the
                    secondary colour gives a sharp test of the success of the achromatizing
                    process.</p>
                <p>“The secondary tints in an objective are readily shown by directing the telescope
                    to a vertical line separating light from dark, such as the edge of a chimney
                    seen in the shade against the sky, and covering half the object-glass with a
                    screen having a vertical edge. So delicate is this test that, on testing
                    different telescopes by well-known opticians, a difference in the mode of
                    achromatism may be detected. The best results are said to be obtained when the
                    secondary green is intermediate between green and yellow. This corresponds to
                    making the focal length a minimum for the brightest part of the spectrum.</p>
                <p>“To enable me to form a judgment as to the sharpness of the test furnished by the
                    tint of the secondary green, as compared with the .performance of an
                    object-glass, I tried the following experiment. A set of parallel lines of
                    increasing fineness was ruled with ink on a sheet of white paper, and a broader
                    black object was laid upon it as well, parallel to the lines. The paper was
                    placed, with the black lines vertical, at a considerable distance on a lawn, and
                    was viewed through two opposed prisms, one of crown glass and the other of
                    flint, of such angles as nearly to achromatize each other in the positions of
                    minimum deviation, and then through a small telescope The achromatism is now
                    effected, and varied in character, by moving one of the prisms slightly in
                    azimuth, and after each alteration the telescope was focused afresh to get the
                    sharpest vision that could be had. I found that the azimuth of the prism was
                    fixed within decidedly narrower limits by the condition that the secondary green
                    should be of such or such a tint, even though no attempt was made to determine
                    the tint otherwise than by memory, than by the condition that the vision of the
                    fine lines should be as sharp as possible. Now a small element of a double
                    object-glass may be regarded, so far as chromatic compensation is concerned, as
                    a pair of opposed prisms; and therefore we may infer that the tint of the
                    secondary green ought to be at the very least as sharp a test of the goodness of
                    the chromatic compensation as the actual performance of the telescope.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy.
                    Soc.,</hi> June 1878.</p></note></p>
                <p>In the case of photographic lenses the conditions of the problem are materially
                    different. It is usually considered to be important to secure “coincidence of
                    the visual and chemical foci,” so that the sensitive plate may occupy the exact
                    position previously found by the eye for the ground glass screen. For this
                    purpose the ray of minimum focus must be chosen further up in the spectrum. If,
                    however, the object be to obtain the sharpest possible photographs, coincidence
                    of visual and chemical foci must be sacrificed, the proper position for the
                    sensitive plate being found by trial. The middle of the chemically-acting part
                    of the spectrum, which will vary somewhat according to the photographic process
                    employed, should then be chosen for minimum focus.</p>
                <p>When the focal lengths of the component lenses have been chosen, it still remains
                    to decide upon the curvatures of the individual faces. Between the four
                    curvatures we have at present only two relations, and thus two more can be
                    satisfied. One of these is given by the condition that the first term in the
                    expression for the aberration—that proportional to the square of the
                    aperture—shall vanish for parallel rays. As to the fourth condition, various
                    proposals have been made. If equal and opposite curvatures are given to the
                    second and third surfaces, the glasses may be cemented together, by which some
                    saving of light is effected. Herschel proposed to make the aberration vanish for
                    nearly parallel, as well as for absolutely parallel, rays. This leads to a
                    construction nearly agreeing with that adopted by Fraunhofer.</p>
                <p>The following results are given by Herschel<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1821.</p></note> for
                    the radii of the four surfaces, corresponding to various dispersive powers, and
                    to mean refractive indices l <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 524 (crown) and 1 ’
                    585 (flint). The focal length of the combination is taken equal to 10, and, as
                    well as the radii, is measured in arbitrary units; so that all the numbers in
                    the table (with the exception of the first column) may be changed in any
                    proportion.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ratio of Dispersive
                            Powers.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 Radius of First
                            Surface.</p><p>+</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 Radius of
                            Second</p><p>Surface.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Radius of Third Surface.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Radius of Fourth Surface.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Focal Length of Crown
                            Lens.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Focal</p><p>Length of Flint
                            Lens.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•50</p><p>•55</p><p>•60</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>6∙7485</p><p>6’7184</p><p>6’7069</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>4’2827</p><p>3’6332</p><p>3’0488</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4Ί575 3’6006 3Ό640</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>14∙3697</p><p>14’5353</p><p>14’2937</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5’0 4∙5</p><p>4Ό</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10’0000 8’1818 6’6667</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•65</p><p>•70</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6∙7316</p><p>6’8279</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’5208</p><p>2Ό422</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’5566</p><p>2Ό831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13’5709</p><p>12’3154</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’5</p><p>3’0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5’3846</p><p>4’2858</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•75</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7’0816</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6073</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1’6450</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10’5186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3’3333</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The general character of the combination is shown in fig. 16.</p>
                <p>The radii of the first and fourth surfaces within practical limits are so nearly
                    constant that Herschel lays down <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n868/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0868-0805"/> the following rule as in all probability
                    sufficiently exact for use. A double object-glass will be free from aberration,
                    provided the radius of the exterior surface of the crown lens be 6’720 and of
                    the flint 14’20, the focal length of the combin ation being 10’000, and the
                    radii of the interior surface being computed from these data, by the formulae
                    given in all elementary works on optics, so as to make the focal lengths of the
                    two glasses in the direct ratio of their dispersive powers.</p>
                <p>Numerous experiments have been made with the view of abolishing the secondary
                    spectrum. Theoretically, if three different kinds of glasses are combined it
                    will generally be possible to make the focal lengths of the combination equal
                    for any <hi rend="italic">three</hi> selected rays of the spectrum. Or the
                    ingredients of one of the glasses may be mixed in such proportions as to suit
                    the requirements of the problem when combined with crown. In this way Stokes has
                    succeeded in constructing a small object-glass free from secondary colour, but
                    it is doubtful whether the practical difficulties could be overcome in the
                    construction of a large object-glass, where alone the outstanding chromatic
                    aberration is important.</p>
                <p>The practical optician is not limited to spherical surfaces, and the final
                    adjustment of the aberration of large objectglasses is controlled by the action
                    of the polishing tool. It is understood that some of the best makers apply a
                    local correction, according to the methods developed by Foucault for mirrors.
                    The light from a natural or artificial star is allowed to fall upon the lens. At
                    the focus is placed a small screen, which is gradually advanced so as to cut off
                    the light. The eye is immediately behind the screen and is focused upon the
                    lens. If there are no imperfections the illumination falls off very suddenly,
                    the surface of the mirror passing from light to dark through a nearly uniform
                    grey tint. If, however, from uniform aberration, or from local defects, any of
                    the light goes a little astray, the corresponding parts of the surface will show
                    irregularities of illumination during the passage of the screen, and in this
                    manner a guide is afforded for the completion of the figuring.</p>
                <p>Töppler<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pogg. Ann.,</hi> cxxxi.. 1867.</p></note> has developed the idea of Foucault
                    into a general method for rendering visible very small optical differences.
                    Instead of a mere point of light, it is advisable to use as source an aperture
                    (backed by a bright flame) of sensible size, and bounded on one side by a
                    straight edge. An image of this source is formed at a considerable distance by a
                    lens of large aperture and free from imperfections, and in the plane of the
                    image is arranged a screen whose edge is parallel to the straight edge of the
                    image, and can be advanced gradually so as to coincide with it. Behind this
                    screen comes a small telescope through which the observer examines the object
                    placed near the lens. When the light is just cut off by the advancing screen,
                    the apparatus is in the most sensitive state, and the slightest disturbance of
                    the course of the rays is rendered evident. To show the delicacy of the
                    arrangement Töppler introduced into the cone of light a small trough with
                    parallel glass sides containing distilled water. A syphon dipped under the
                    surface and discharged distilled water from another vessel, and it was found
                    almost impossible so to control the temperatures that the issuing jet should
                    remain invisible. Not only were sound-waves in air, generated by electric
                    sparks, rendered visible, but their behaviour when reflected from neighbouring
                    obstacles was beautifully exhibited.</p>
                <p>An apparatus on this principle may often be employed with advantage in physical
                    demonstrations,—for instance, for the exhibition of the changes of density in
                    the neighbourhood of the electrodes of a metallic solution undergoing
                    electrolysis. The smallest irregularity that could be rendered visible would be
                    such as would retard transmitted light by a moderate fraction of the
                    wave-length.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Even when
                    the optical differences are not small it is well to remember that transparent
                    bodies are only visible in virtue of a variable illumination. If the light falls
                    equally in all directions, as it might approximately do for an observer on a
                    high monument during* a thick fog, the edge of (for example) a perfectly
                    transparent prism would be absolutely invisible. If a spherical cloud, composed
                    of absolutely transparent material, surround symmetrically a source of light,
                    the illumination at a distance would not be diminished by its
                    presence.</p></note></p>
                <p>In objectives for photographic use the requirements are in many respects
                    different from those most important in the case of telescopes. A flat field, a
                    wide angle of view— in some cases as much as 90° —freedom from distortion, and a
                    great concentration of light are more important than a high degree of
                    definition. As a rule, photographs are not subjected to the ordeal of a high
                    magnifying power. Usually the picture includes objects at various distances from
                    the camera, which cannot all be in focus at once. That the objects at one
                    particular distance should be depicted with especial sharpness would often be
                    rather a disadvantage than otherwise. A moderate amount of “diffusion of focus”
                    is thus desirable, and implies residual aberration. In some lenses an adjustment
                    is provided by means of which the diffusion of focus may be varied according to
                    the circumstances of the case.</p>
                <p>For landscapes and general purposes a so-called single lens is usually employed.
                    This, however, for the sake of achromatism, is compounded of a flint and a crown
                    cemented together; or sometimes three component lenses are used, the flint being
                    encased in two crowns, one on each side. To get tolerable definition and
                    flatness of field a stop must be added, whose proper place is some little
                    distance in front of the lens.</p>
                <p>For portraiture, especially before the introduction of the modern rapid dry
                    plates, a brilliant image was a necessity. This implies a high ratio of aperture
                    to focal length, which cannot be attained satisfactorily with any ft&gt;rm of
                    single lens. To meet the demand, Petzval designed the “portrait-lens,” in which
                    two achromatic lenses, placed at a certain distance apart, combine to form the
                    image. This construction is so successful that the focal length is often no more
                    than three times the available aperture. When stops are employed to increase the
                    sharpness and depth of focus they are placed <hi rend="italic">between</hi> the
                    lenses.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vision through a Single Lens.—</hi> A single lens may be used
                    to improve the vision of a defective eye, or as a magnifying glass. A normal eye
                    is capable of focusing upon objects at any distance greater than about 8 inches.
                    The eyes of a short-sighted person are optically too powerful, and cannot be
                    focused upon an object at a moderate distance. The remedy is of course to be
                    found in concave glasses. On the other hand, persons beyond middle life usually
                    lose the power of seeing near objects distinctly, and require convex
                    glasses.</p>
                <p>A not uncommon defect, distinct from mere short or weak sight, is that known as
                    astigmatism. In such cases the focal length varies in different planes, and at
                    no distance is the definition perfect. Many people, whose sight would not
                    usually be considered inferior, are affected by astigmatism to a certain extent.
                    If a set of parallel black lines ruled upon white paper be turned gradually
                    round in its own plane, it will often be seen more distinctly and with greater
                    contrast of the white and black parts in one azimuth than in another. When the
                    focal line on the retina is parallel to the length of the bar, the definition
                    (as in the case of the spectroscope) is not much prejudiced, but it is <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n869/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0869-0806"/> otherwise when the bars are turned through a
                    right angle so as to be perpendicular to the focal line.</p>
                <p>In extreme cases a remedy may be applied in the form of glasses of different
                    curvatures in perpendicular planes, so adjusted both in form and position as to
                    compensate the corresponding differences in the lens of the eye.</p>
                <p>The use of a lens as a magnifier has been explained under <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Microscope.</hi> The simplest view of the matter is that the lens, consistently
                    with good focusing, allows of a nearer approach, and therefore of a higher
                    visual angle, than would otherwise be possible.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Telescope, &lt;L</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">c.—</hi> In a large
                    class of optical instruments an <hi rend="italic">image</hi> of the original
                    object is first formed, and this image is examined through a magnifier. If we
                    use a single lens merely for the latter purpose, the field of view is very
                    restricted. A great improvement in this respect may be effected by the
                    introduction of a <hi rend="italic">field-∖ens.</hi> The ideal position for the
                    field-lens is at the focal plane of the object-glass. The image is then entirely
                    uninfluenced, and the only effect is to bend round the rays from the margin of
                    the field which would otherwise escape, and to make them reach the eye-lens, and
                    ultimately the eye. If the field-lens and the eye-lens have nearly the same
                    focal length an image of the object-glass will be formed upon the eye-lens, and
                    through this small image will pass every ray admitted by the object-glass and
                    field-lens.</p>
                <p>However, to obtain a sufficient augmentation of the field of view it is not
                    necessary to give the field-lens the exact position above mentioned, and other
                    considerations favour a certain displacement. For example, it is not desirable
                    that dust and flaws on the field-lens should be seen in focus. In Huygens’s
                    eye-piece the field-lens is displaced from its ideal position <hi rend="italic"
                    >towards</hi> the object-glass. In Ramsden’s eye-piece, on the other hand, the
                    focal plane of the object-glass is outside the system. This eye-piece has the
                    important advantage that cross wires can be placed so as to coincide with the
                    image as formed by the object-glass. The component lenses of a Ramsden’s
                    eye-piece are sometimes achromatic. For further particulars, with diagrams, on
                    the subject of eye-pieces, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Microscope.</hi></p>
                <p>In large telescopes the object-glass is often replaced by a mirror, which may be
                    of speculum metal, or of glass coated chemically with a very thin layer of
                    polished silver. The mirror presents the advantage (especially important for
                    photographic applications) of absolute achromatism. On the other hand, more
                    light is lost in the reflexion than in thé passage through a good object-glass,
                    and the surface of the mirror needs occasional re-polishing or re-coating. For
                    fuller information see <hi rend="smallcaps">Telescope.</hi></p>
                <p>The function of a telescope is to increase the “apparent magnitude” of distant
                    objects; it does not increase the ‘apparent brightness.” If we put out of
                    account the loss of light by reflexion at glass surfaces (or by imperfect
                    reflexion at metallic surfaces) and by absorption, and suppose that the
                    magnifying power does not exceed the ratio of the aperture of the object-glass
                    to that of the pupil, under which condition the pupil will be filled with light,
                    we may say that the “apparent brightness” is absolutely unchanged by the use of
                    a telescope. In this statement, however, two reservations must be admitted. If
                    the object under examination, like a fixed star, have no sensible apparent
                    magnitude, the conception of “apparent brightness” is altogether inapplicable,
                    and we are concerned only with the total quantity of light reaching the eye.
                    Again, it is found that the visibility of an object seen against a black
                    background depends not only upon the “apparent brightness” but also upon the
                    apparent magnitude. If two or three crosses of different sizes be cut out of the
                    same piece of white paper, and be erected against a black background on the
                    further side of a nearly dark room, the smaller ones become invisible in a light
                    still sufficient to show the larger. Under these circumstances a suitable
                    telescope may of course bring also the smaller objects into view. The
                    explanation is probably to be sought in imperfect action of the lens of the eye
                    when the pupil is dilated to the utmost. The author of this article has found
                    that in a nearly dark room he becomes distinctly short-sighted, a defect of
                    which there is no trace whatever in a moderate light.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Camb. Phil. Proc.,</hi>
                    vol. iv.</p></note> If this view be correct, the brightness of the image on the
                    retina is really less in the case of a small than in the case of a large object,
                    although the so-called apparent brightnesses may be the same. However this may
                    be, the utility of a night-glass is beyond dispute.</p>
                <p>The general law that (apart from the accidental losses mentioned above) the
                    “apparent brightness” depends only upon the area of the pupil filled with light,
                    though often ill understood, has been established for a long time, as the
                    following quotation from Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Optics</hi> (Cambridge,
                    1738), p. 113, will show.</p>
                <p>“Since the magnitude of the pupil is subject to be varied by various degrees of
                    light, let NO be its semi-diameter when the object PL is viewed by the naked eye
                    from the distance OP; and upon a plane that touches the eye at 0, let OK be the
                    semi-diameter of the greatest area, visible through all the glasses to another
                    eye at P, to be found as PL was; or, which is the same thing, let OK be the
                    semi-diameter of the greatest area inlightened by a pencil of rays flowing from
                    P through all the glasses; and when this area is not less than the area of the
                    pupil, the point P will appear just as bright through all the glasses as it
                    would do if they were removed; but if the inlightened area be less than the area
                    of the pupil, the point P will appear less bright through the glasses than if
                    they were removed in the same proportion as the inlightened area is less than
                    the pupil. And these proportions of apparent brightness would be accurate if all
                    the incident rays were transmitted through the glasses to the eye, or if only an
                    insensible part of them were stopt.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Resolving Power of Optical Instruments.—</hi> According to the
                    principles of common optics, there is no limit to the resolving power of an
                    instrument. If the aberrations of a microscope were perfectly compensated it
                    might reveal to us worlds within a space of a millionth of an inch. In like
                    manner a telescope might resolve double stars of any degree of closeness. The
                    magnifying power may be exalted at pleasure by increase of focal length and of
                    the power of eye-pieces; and there are at any rate some objects, such as the
                    sun, in dealing with which the accompanying loss of light would be an advantage
                    rather than the contrary. How is it, then, that the power of the microscope is
                    subject to an absolute limit, and that if we wish to observe minute detail on
                    the over-lighted disk of the sun we must employ a telescope of large aperture?
                    The answer requires us to go behind the approximate doctrine of rays, on which
                    common optics is built, and to take into consideration the finite character of
                    the wave-length of light.</p>
                <p>A calculation based upon the principles of the wavetheory shows that, no matter
                    how perfect an object-glass may be, the image of a star is represented, not by a
                    mathematical point, but by a disk of finite size surrounded by a system of
                    alternately dark and bright rings. Airy found that if the angular radius of the
                    central disk (as seen from the centre of the object-glass) be <hi rend="italic"
                    >θ,</hi> 2R the aperture, λ the wave-length, then i = l∙21W⅛, showing that the
                    definition, as thus limited by the finiteness of λ, increases with the
                    aperture.</p>
                <p>In estimating theoretically the resolving power of a telescope on a double star
                    we have to consider the illumination of the field due to the superposition of
                    the two independent images. If the angular interval between the components of
                    the double star were equal to <hi rend="italic">2θ,</hi> the central <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n870/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0870-0807"/> disks would be just in contact. Under these
                    conditions there can be no doubt that the star would appear to be fairly
                    resolved, since the brightness of the external ring systems is too small to
                    produce any material confusion, unless indeed the components are of very unequal
                    magnitude. The diminution of star disks with increasing aperture was observed by
                    W. Herschel; and in 1823 Fraunhofer formulated the law of inverse
                    proportionality. In investigations extending over a long series of years, the
                    advantage of a large aperture in separating the components of close double stars
                    was fully examined by Dawes.</p>
                <p>The resolving power of telescopes was investigated also by Foucault, who employed
                    a scale of equal bright and dark alternate parts; it was found to be
                    proportional to the aperture and independent of the focal length. In telescopes
                    of the best construction the performance is not sensibly prejudiced by
                    outstanding aberration, and the limit imposed by the finiteness of the waves of
                    light is practically reached. Verdet has compared Foucault’s results with
                    theory, and has drawn the conclusion that the radius of the visible part of the
                    image of a luminous point was nearly equal to half the radius of the first dark
                    ring.</p>
                <p>The theory of resolving power is rather simpler when the aperture is rectangular
                    instead of circular, and when the subject of examination consists of two or more
                    light or dark lines parallel to one of the sides of the aperture. Supposing this
                    side to be vertical, we may say that the definition, or resolving power, is <hi
                    rend="italic">independent of the vertical aperture,</hi> and that a double line
                    will be about on the point of resolution when its components subtend an angle
                    equal to that subtended by the wave-length of light at a distance equal to the
                    <hi rend="italic">horizontal aperture.</hi></p>
                <p>The resolving power of a telescope with a circular or rectangular aperture is
                    easily investigated experimentally. The best object is a grating of fine wires,
                    about fifty to the inch, backed by a soda-flame. The object-glass is provided
                    with diaphragms pierced with round holes or slits. One of these, of width equal,
                    say, to one-tenth of an inch, is inserted in front of the object-glass, and the
                    telescope, carefully focused all the while, is drawn gradually back from the
                    grating until the lines are no longer seen. From a measurement of the maximum
                    distance the least angle between consecutive lines consistent with resolution
                    may be deduced, and a comparison made with the rule stated above.</p>
                <p>Merely to show the dependence of resolving power on aperture it is not necessary
                    to use a telescope at all. It is sufficient to look at wire-gauze backed by the
                    sky, or by a flame, through a piece of blackened cardboard pierced by a needle
                    and held close to the eye. By varying the distance the point is easily found at
                    which resolution ceases; and the observation is as sharp as with a telescope.
                    The function of the telescope is in fact to allow the use of a wider, and
                    therefore more easily measurable, aperture. An interesting modification of the
                    experiment may be made by using light of various wave-lengths.</p>
                <p>In the case of the microscope the wave-theory shows that there must be an
                    absolute limit to resolving power independent of the construction of the
                    instrument. No optical contrivances can decide whether light comes from one
                    point or from another if the distance between them do not exceed a small
                    fraction of the wave-length. This idea, which appears to have been familiar to
                    Fraunhofer, has recently been expanded by Abbe and Helmholtz into a systematic
                    theory of the microscopic limit. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Microscope.</hi></p>
                <p>Similar principles may be applied to investigate the resolving power of
                    spectroscopes, whether dispersing or diffracting. Consider for simplicity any
                    combination of prisms, anyhow disposed, but consisting of one kind of glass. Let
                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi> be the final width and <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> the
                    index of a parallel beam passing through, and let the thicknesses of glass
                    traversed by the extreme rays on either side be <hi rend="italic">t</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> It is not difficult to see that, if
                    the index be changed to <hi rend="italic">μ</hi><hi rend="italic">+ δμ,</hi> the
                    rays will be turned through an angle <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> given by <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi></p>
                <p>Now, if the two kinds of light correspond to a double line which the instrument
                    can just resolve, we have <hi rend="italic">θ=</hi><hi rend="italic">∖∣</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">a,</hi> and thus i <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>-i <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =λ∕δμ, a formula of capital importance in the theory of
                    the dispersing spectroscope. In a well-constructed instrument, <hi rend="italic"
                    >t</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> v</hi> the smaller
                    thickness traversed, may be small or negligible, and then we may state the law
                    in the following form :—the smallest thickness of prisms necessary for the
                    resolution of a double line whose indices are <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">μ</hi><hi rend="italic">+ δμ</hi> is found by dividing the
                    wave-length by <hi rend="italic">δμ.</hi></p>
                <p>As an example, let it be required to find the smallest thickness of a prism of
                    Chance’s “extra dense flint,” necessary for resolution of the soda-lines.</p>
                <p>By Cauchy’s formula for the relation between <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> and λ we
                    have μ=A+Bλ~ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, <hi rend="italic">δμ=-</hi> 2Bλ"
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> δλ,</p>
                <p>From the results given by Hopkinson for this kind of glass we find</p>
                <p>B=∙984×10- <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> °, the unit of length being the
                    centimetre. For the two soda-lines λ=5∙889 × 10~ <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi>,
                    δλ= ∙006 × 10~ <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi>; ajrd thus the thickness <hi
                    rend="italic">t</hi> necessary to resolve the lines is λ <hi rend="superscript">
                    4</hi> 10 <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> λ <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> =2Ba=Fs∞X= <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ' <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 02 ce</hi> " <hi rend="superscript"> tlmetra</hi> ∙</p>
                <p>the meaning of which is that the soda-lines.will be resolved if, and will not be
                    resolved unless, the difference of thicknesses of glass traversed by the two
                    sides of the beam amount to one centimetre. In the most favourable arrangement
                    the centimetre is the length of the base of the prism. It is to be understood,
                    of course, that the magnifying power applied is sufficient to narrow the beam
                    ultimately to the diameter of the pupil of the eye; otherwise the full width
                    would not be utilized.</p>
                <p>The theory of the resolving power of a diffracting spectroscope, or grating, is
                    even simpler. Whatever may be the position of the grating, a double line of
                    wave-lengths λ and λ-t-δλ will be just resolved provided</p>
                <p>δλ <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi> J_</p>
                <p>Λ <hi rend="italic">mn</hi> where <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is the total number of
                    lines in the grating, and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is the order of the spectrum
                    under examination.</p>
                <p>If a grating giving a spectrum of the first order and a prism of extra dense
                    glass have equal power in the region of the soda-lines, the former must have
                    about as many thousand lines as the latter has centimetres of available
                    thickness.</p>
                <p>The dispersion produced by a grating situated in a given manner is readily
                    inferred from the resolving power. If <hi rend="italic">a</hi> be the width of
                    the beam after leaving the grating, the angle <hi rend="italic">δθ,</hi>
                    corresponding to the limit of resolution, is λ∕α, and thus <hi rend="italic">δθ
                    _mn</hi></p>
                <p>δλ <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi><hi rend="italic">a *</hi></p>
                <p>Thus the dispersion depends only upon the order of the spectrum, the total number
                    of lines, and the width of the emergent beam.</p>
                <p>An obvious inference from the necessary imperfection of optical images is the
                    uselessness of attempting anything like an absolute destruction of aberration.
                    In an instrument free from aberration the waves arrive at the focal point in the
                    same phase. It will suffice for practical purposes if the error of phase nowhere
                    exceeds ⅛λ. This corresponds to an error of ∣λ in a reflecting and ⅜λ in a
                    (glass) refracting surface, the incidence in both cases being perpendicular.</p>
                <p>If we inquire what is the greatest admissible longitudinal aberration in an
                    object-glass according to the above rule, we find δ∕=λα^ <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>,</p>
                <p>α being the angular semi-aperture.</p>
                <p>In the case of a single lens of glass with the most favourable curvatures, <hi
                    rend="italic">δf</hi> is about equal to ∕α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; so
                    that α <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> must not exceed λ∕∕. For a lens of 3-feet
                    focus this condition is satisfied if the aperture do not exceed 2 inches.</p>
                <p>When parallel rays fall directly upon a spherical mirror the longitudinal
                    aberration is only about one-eighth as great as for the most favourable-shaped
                    single lens of equal focal length and aperture. Hence a spherical mirror of
                    3-feet focus might have an aperture of 2⅜ inches, and the image would not suffer
                    materially from aberration.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>For fuller information on the subject of the preceding paragraphs see Lord
                    Rayleigh’s papers entitled “Investigations in Optics,” <hi rend="italic">Phil.
                    Mag.,</hi> 1879, 1880.</p></note></p>
                <p>On general optics the treatises most accessible to the English reader are
                    Parkinson’s <hi rend="italic">Optics</hi> (3d ed., 1870) and Glazebrook’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Physical Optics</hi> (1883). Verdet’s Leçons <hi rend="italic"
                    >d’optique</hi><hi rend="italic">physique</hi> is an excellent work. Every
                    student should read the earlier parts of Newton’s <hi rend="italic">Optics,</hi>
                    in which are described the fundamental experiments upon the decomposition of
                    white light ( <hi rend="smallcaps">r.</hi>)</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n871/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0871-0808"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
