<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0879-0816-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORCHIDS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 816</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1070009">Pollen</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1131414">Stamen</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:810099">Anther</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:999431">Lips</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1047313">Orchids</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32b9f">Orchids</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b46m33b2g">Pollen</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nv0r">Lips</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORCHIDS</label>. The word <hi rend="italic">Orchis</hi> is
                    used in a special sense to denote a particular genus of the Orchid family <hi
                    rend="italic">(Orchidaceae)</hi>; very frequently, also, it is employed in a
                    more general way to indicate any member of that large and very interesting
                    group. It will be convenient here to use the word <hi rend="italic">Orchis</hi>
                    as applying to that particular genus which gives its name to the order or
                    family, and to employ the term “orchid” in the less precise sense.</p>
                <p>The flowers of all orchids, though extremely diverse within certain limits, and
                    although superficially very different from those of other monocotyledons, are
                    all formed upon one common plan, which is only a modification of that observable
                    in such flowers as those of the narcissus or snowdrop <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Galanthus).</hi> The conformation of those flowers consists essentially in the
                    presence of a six-parted perianth, the three outer segments of which correspond
                    to a calyx, the three inner ones to a corolla. These segments spring apparently
                    from the top of the ovary,—the real explanation, however, being that the end of
                    the flower-stalk or “thalamus,” as it grows, becomes dilated into a sort of cup
                    or tube enclosing and indeed closely adhering to the ovary, so that the latter
                    organ appears to be beneath the perianth instead of above it as in a lily, an
                    appearance which has given origin to the term “inferior ovary.” Within the
                    perianth, and springing from its sides, or apparently from the top of the ovary,
                    are six stamens whose anthers contain pulverulent pollen-grains. These stamens
                    encircle a style which is the upward continuation of the ovary, and which shows
                    at its free end traces of the three originally separate but now blended carpels
                    of which the ovary consists. An orchid flower (disregarding for the moment a
                    very small number of exceptions) has an inferior ovary like that just described,
                    but with the ovules-on the walls of the cavity (not in its axis or centre), a
                    six-parted perianth, a stamen or stamens, and a style or styles. The main
                    distinguishing features consist in the fact that one of the inner pieces of the
                    perianth become⅛ in course of its growth much larger than the rest, and usually
                    different in colour, texture, and form. So different is it that it receives a
                    distinct name, that of the “lip” or “labellum.” In place of the six stamens we
                    commonly find but one (two in <hi rend="italic">Cypripediitm),</hi> and that one
                    is inseparably blended with the style to form the “column,” bringing about
                    the-condition technically called “gynandrous.” Moreover, the pollen, instead of
                    consisting of separate cells or grains, consists of cells aggregated into
                    “pollenmasses,” the number varying in different genera, but very generally two,
                    four, or eight, and in many of the genera provided at the base with a
                    strap-shaped stalk or “caudicle” ending in a flattish gland or “viscid disk”
                    like a boy’s sucker. The style has very generally at its upper part a peculiar
                    pouch-like process called the “rostellum,” in which the viscid disk of the
                    pollen-masses is concealed till released in the manner presently to be
                    mentioned. It would appear, then, that the orchid flower differs from the type
                    in the irregularity of the perianth, in the suppression of five out of six
                    stamens and of two out of three styles, and in the union into one column of the
                    one stamen and the one style which remain in the adult flower. In addition to
                    these modifications, which are common to nearly all orchids, there are others
                    generally but not so universally met with; among them is the displacement of the
                    flower arising from the twisting of the inferior ovary, in consequence of which
                    the flower is so completely turned round that the “lip,” which originates in
                    that part of the flower, conventionally called the posterior or superior part,
                    or that nearest to the supporting stem, becomes in course of growth turned to
                    the anterior or lower part of the flower nearest to the bract, from whose axil
                    it arises. Other common modifications arise from the union of certain parts of
                    the perianth to each other, and from the inordinate outgrowths from the lip.</p>
                <p>These statements are borne out by evidence derived from a variety of sources,
                    such as that afforded by the progressive development of the parts of the flower
                    from their earliest to their most complete condition, by the anatomy or internal
                    organization of the parts of the flower, by the number and distribution of the
                    vascular bundles which run through the cellular tissue, by the comparative
                    morphology of the floral organs of the different genera of the order, and by
                    teratology, or the study of unusual or monstrous formations<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n880/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0880-0817"/>, which reveals the existence of a complete series
                    of intermediate forms constituting a regular gradation from the ordinary
                    irregular gynandrous flower to regular flowers with six separate stamens such as
                    we have taken as the type.</p>
                <p>What brings about—what has brought about—this extraordinary series of changes, by
                    virtue of which a flower typically as regular as a snowdrop becomes transmuted
                    into the forms often more grotesque and extraordinary than can be found in any
                    other group of plants? To the first part of the question the reply is that the
                    present form has been inherited from generation to generation of orchids; to the
                    second part the answer most in accordance with the present state of knowledge is
                    that these modifications are associated with the structure and habits of insects
                    and their visits to the flowers. Cross fertilization, or the impregnation of any
                    given flower by pollen from another flower of the same species on the same or on
                    another plant, has been proved to be of great advantage to the plant by securing
                    a more numerous or a more robust offspring, or one better able to adapt itself
                    to the varying conditions under which it has to live. This cross fertilization
                    is effected by the agency of insects. They are attracted to the flower by its
                    colour or its perfume; they seek, collect, or feed on its honey, and while so
                    doing they remove the pollen from the anther and convey it to another flower,
                    there to germinate on the stigma when its tubes travel down the style and their
                    contents ultimately come in near apposition, perhaps in actual confluence, with
                    the “oosphere” or immature egg, which becomes in consequence fertilized, and
                    thereafter gradually develops into a new plant. To facilitate the operations of
                    such insects, by compelling them to move in certain lines so as to secure the
                    due removal of the pollen and its subsequent deposit on the right .place, the
                    form of the flower and the conformation of its several parts are modified in
                    ways as varied as they are wonderful. Other insects visit the flower with more
                    questionable result. For them the pollen is an attraction as food, or some other
                    part of the flower offers an inducement to them for a like object. Such visitors
                    are clearly prejudicial to the flower, and so we meet with arrangements which
                    are calculated to repel the intruders, or at least to force them to enter the
                    flower in such a way as not to effect mischief. It would be quite impossible
                    within the limits of this article to go into detail on this subject. All we can
                    do is to give one or two illustrations, referring the reader desirous of fuller
                    information to Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Fertilization of Orchids.</hi></p>
                <p>In the common orchids of British meadows, <hi rend="italic">Orchis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Morio, mascula</hi> (Shakespeare’s long purples), &lt;tc., the
                    general structure of the flower is as we have described it. In addition there is
                    in this particular genus, as indeed in many others, a long tubular spur or horn
                    projecting downwards from the back of the lip, whose office it is to secrete and
                    store a honeyed juice; the forepart of the lip forms an expanded plate, usually
                    larger and more brightly coloured than the other parts of the flower, and with
                    hairs or ridges and spots of various kinds according to the species. The
                    remaining parts of the perianth are very much smaller, and commonly are so
                    arranged as to form a hood overarching the “column.” This column stands up from
                    the base of the flower, almost at right angles to the lip, and it bears at the
                    top an anther, in the two hollow lobes of which are concealed the two
                    pollen-masses, each with its caudicle terminating below in a roundish gland,
                    concealed at first in the pouch-like rostellum at the front of the column. Below
                    the anther the surface of the column in front is hollowed out into a greenish
                    depression filled with viscid fluid,—this is the stigma. The other parts of the
                    flower need not detain us. Such being in general terms the mechanism of the
                    flower of a common orchis, let us now see he w it acts. A bee, we will assume,
                    attracted by the colour and perfume of the flower, alights on that part of it
                    which is the first to attract its attention,—the lip. There, guided by the hairs
                    or ridges before-mentioned, it is led to the orifice of the spur with its store
                    of honeyed juice. The position of this orifice, as we have seen, is at the base
                    of the lip and of the column, so that the insect, if of sufficient size, while
                    bending his head to insert his proboscis into the spur, almost of necessity
                    displaces the pollenmasses. Liberated from the anthers, these adhere to the head
                    or back of the insect by means of the sticky gland at the bottom of the
                    caudicle. Having attained his object the insect withdraws, taking with him the
                    pollen-masses, and visits another flower. And now occurs another device or
                    adaptation no less marvellous than those of which mention has been made. The two
                    anther-cases in an orchis are erect and nearly parallel the one to the other;
                    the pollen-masses within them are of course in like case, as may be thus
                    represented ∣∣, but immediately the pollenmasses are removed movements take
                    place in the caudicle so as to effect the bending of this stalk and the placing
                    the pollen-mass in a more or less horizontal position, thus =, or, as in the
                    case of <hi rend="italic">0.</hi><hi rend="italic">pyramidalis,</hi> the two
                    pollenmasses originally placed parallel ∣∣ diverge from the base like the letter
                    V. The movements of the pollen-masses may readily be seen with the naked eye by
                    thrusting the point of a needle into the base of the anther, when the disks
                    adhere to the needle as they would do to the antenna of an insect, and may be
                    withdrawn. Sometimes the lip is mobile and even sensitive to impressions, as are
                    also certain processes of the column. In such cases the contact of an insect or
                    other body with those processes is sufficient to liberate the pollen often with
                    elastic force, even when the anther itself is not touched. In other orchids
                    movements take place in different ways and in other directions. The object of
                    these movements will be appreciated when it is remembered that, if the
                    pollen-masses retained the original direction they had in the anther in which
                    they were formed, they would, when transported by the insect to another flower,
                    merely come in contact with the anther of that flower, where of course they
                    would be of no use; but, owing to the divergences and flexions above alluded to,
                    the pollenmasses come to be so placed that, when transplanted to another flower
                    of the same species, they come in contact with the stigma and so effect the
                    fertilization of that flower. These illustrations are comparatively simple; it
                    would have been easy to select others of a more complicated nature, but all
                    evidently connected with the visits of insects and the cross fertilization of
                    the flower. In some cases the form of the male flowers is so different from that
                    of the female that before the different flowers had been found on the same
                    spike, and before the facts of the case were fully known, they were taken to be
                    representatives of distinct genera.</p>
                <p>The floral structure is so curious that perhaps less attention has been paid to
                    the vegetative organs than the peculiarities of their organization demand. We
                    can only allude to some of these points. The orchids of British fields are all
                    of terrestrial habit, and their roots are mostly tuberous (fig. 5), the tubers
                    being partly radical partly budlike in their character. There is often a marked
                    alternation in the production of vegetative and flowering shoots respectively;
                    and, sometimes, from various circumstances, the flowering shoots are not
                    produced for several years in succession . This fact will account for the
                    profusion with which <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n881/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0881-0818"/> some orchids, like the common bee orchis for
                    instance, are found in some seasons and their scarcity in others. Tropical
                    orchids are mostly epiphytal,—that is, they grow upon trees without deriving
                    nourishment from them. They are frequently provided with “pseudo-bulbs,” large
                    solid swellings of the stem, in the tissues of which water and nutritive
                    materials are stored. Very generally, too, such plants have aerial roots, of
                    thick or thin wire-like form, covered with a spongy white investment, the
                    constituent cells of which are found under the microscope to contain spiral
                    fibres tightly coiled up within them. By these “air-roots” the plants are able
                    to absorb watery vapour and perhaps actual water.</p>
                <p>The number of species of orchids is greater than that of any other
                    monocotyledonous order—not even excepting grasses—amounting to between 4000 and
                    5000 at least. This large number is partly accounted for by the diligent search
                    in all countries that has been made for these plants for purposes of
                    cultivation,—they being held at present in the greatest esteem by plant-lovers,
                    and prices being paid for new or rare varieties which recall the days of the
                    tulipo-mania. It must be admitted, however, that orchid-lovers have better
                    reasons to support their fancy than had the speculative growers and barterers of
                    tulips.</p>
                <p>The economic uses of orchids are not remarkable. When we have mentioned vanilla,
                    which consists of the pods of an orchid, we have mentioned about the only
                    economic product that now comes into market Salep, still used in the Levant,
                    consists of the dried tubers of some terrestrial orchid, and contains a
                    relatively large amount of nutritious matter.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cypripedium</hi> demands notice, inasmuch as it, with one or
                    two other genera, constitutes a tribe of the order in which two stamens are
                    present, one on each side of the column instead of one only at the top. What may
                    be considered the normal number of stamens is, as has been said, six, arranged
                    in two rows. In most orchids the only stamen developed to maturity is the
                    posterior one of the three opposite to the lip (anterior before the twisting of
                    the ovary), the other two, as well as all three inner ones, being entirely
                    absent, or present only in the form of rudiments. In <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cypripedium</hi> all three of the outer stamens are wanting, but the two
                    lateral ones of the inner series are present, the third being undeveloped. This
                    aιτangement may be understood by reference to the following diagram,
                    representing the relative position of the stamens in orchids generally and in
                    <hi rend="italic">Cypripedium.</hi> The letter L indicates the position of the
                    labellum; the large figures indicate the developed stamens; the italic figures
                    show the position of the suppressed stamens.</p>
                <p>1 <hi rend="italic">1</hi><hi rend="italic">4 5</hi> 4 5</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">6 6</hi><hi rend="italic">2 3 2 3</hi></p>
                <p>L L</p>
                <p>Arrangement of stamens Arrangement of stamens in <hi rend="italic">Orchis.</hi>
                    in <hi rend="italic">Cypripedium.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
