<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0781-0724-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ODER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 724</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x193">Moravians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1026120">Moravians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1118567">Silesians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n781/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ODER</label> (Latin, <hi rend="italic">Viadrus</hi>;
                    Slavonic, <hi rend="italic">Vjodr),</hi> one of the principal rivers of Germany,
                    rises on the Odergebirge in the Moravian tableland, in 49° 43' N. lat. and 17°
                    35' E. long., at a height of 1950 feet above the sea, and 14 miles to the east
                    of Olmiitz. It is 550 miles long from its source to its mouth in the Baltic Sea,
                    and drains an area of about 50,000 square miles. The first 45 miles of its
                    course lie within Moravia; for the next 15 it forms the frontier between
                    Prussian and Austrian Silesia; while the remaining 490 miles belong to Prussia,
                    where it traverses the provinces of Silesia, Brandenburg, and Pomerania. It
                    flows at first towards the south-east, but on quitting Austria turns towards the
                    north-west, maintaining this direction as far as Frankfort, beyond which its
                    general course is nearly due north. As far as the frontier the Oder flows
                    through a well-defined valley, but, after passing through the gap between the
                    Moravian mountains and the Carpathians and entering the Silesian plain, its
                    valley is wide and shallow and its banks generally low. In its lower course it
                    is divided into numerous branches, forming a large quantity of islands. The main
                    channel follows the left side of the valley and finally expands into the
                    Pommersche or Stettiner Haff, which is connected with the sea by three arms, the
                    Peene, the Swine, and the Dievenow, forming the islands of Usedom and Wollin.
                    The Swine, in the middle, is the main channel for navigation. The chief
                    tributaries of the Oder on the left bank are the Oppa, Glatz Neisse, Katzbach,
                    Bober, and Lausitz Neisse; on the right bank the Malapane, Bartsch, Faule Obra,
                    and Warthe. Of these the only one of importance for navigation is the Warthe,
                    which through the Netze is brought into communication with the Vistula. The Oder
                    is also connected by canals with the Havel and the Spree. The most important
                    towns on its banks are Ratibor, Oppeln, Brieg, Breslau, Glogau, Frankfort,
                    Cüstrin, and Stettin, with the seaport of Swinemünde at its mouth. Glogau and
                    Cüstrin are strongly fortified, and Swinemünde is also defended by a few
                    forts.</p>
                <p>The navigation of the Oder is rendered somewhat difficult by the rapid fall of
                    its upper course, amounting above Brieg to 2 feet per mile, and by the enormous
                    quantities of débris brought into it by its numerous mountain tributaries. The
                    German authorities, however, have been unwearied in their efforts to improve the
                    channel, and have now succeeded in securing a minimum depth of 3 feet at low
                    water throughout almost the whole of the Prussian part of the river. Their most
                    important undertaking was the diversion of the river into a new and straight
                    channel in the Oderbruch below Frankfort, by which an extensive detour was cut
                    off and a large tract of swampy country brought under cultivation. The Oder at
                    present begins to be navigable for barges at Ratibor, where it is about 100 feet
                    wide, but the navigable channel will probably soon extend upwards to Oderberg.
                    Sea-going vessels cannot go beyond Stettin. A second Oder-Spree canal, leaving
                    the Oder opposite the mouth of the Warthe and joining the Spree near Berlin, has
                    been determined on; and a canal connecting the Oder and the Danube has also been
                    planned. The traffic on the Oder, which is steadily increasing, is mainly
                    concerned with agricultural produce and timber. Some idea of its extent may be
                    gathered from the fact that 280 riversteamers and 2800 other vessels passed
                    through the Oderbruch (up and down) in 1881 with cargoes amounting in all to
                    166,500 tons. The river is here about 750 feet wide and 8 feet deep. The fishing
                    is important, particularly in the neighbourhood of Stettin.</p>
                <p>Those interested in river navigation or engineering may be referred to the
                    following works: Becker, <hi rend="italic">Zur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Kenntniss</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">Oder</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">und ihres Flächengeöiets</hi> (1868); “Die Deutschen
                    Wasserstrassen” in the <hi rend="italic">Statistik des Deutschen Reiches</hi>
                    for 1874; Haase, <hi rend="italic">Regulation der deutschen Hauptströme</hi>
                    (Breslau, 1880).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
