<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0790-0733-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">OGLETHORPE, James Edward</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 733</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40g3h15m">Floods</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:927573">Floods</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1113393">Serval</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205150">Florida</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n790/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OGLETHORPE, <hi rend="smallcaps">James Edward</hi></label>
                    (1696-1785), general, the founder of the State of Georgia, was born in London
                    21st December 1696, the son of Sir Theophilus Oglethorpe of Godaiming, Surrey.
                    He entered Corpus Christi College, Oxford, in 1714, but in the same year joined
                    the army of Prince Eugène. Through the recommendation of the duke of Marlborough
                    he became aide-de-camp to the prince, and he served with distinction in the
                    campaign against the Turks, 1716-17, more especially at the siege and capture of
                    Belgrade. After his return to England he was in 1722 chosen member of parliament
                    for Hazlemere. He devoted much attention to the improvement of the circumstances
                    of poor debtors in London prisons; and for the purpose of providing an asylum
                    for persons who had become insolvent, and for oppressed Protestants on the
                    Continent, he projected the settlement of a colony in America between Carolina
                    and Florida. A full account of the enterprise and the subsequent relation of
                    Oglethorpe to the colony will be found in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Georgia,</hi> vol. x. p. 437. In 1745 Oglethorpe was promoted to the rank of
                    major-general. His conduct in connexion with the Scottish rebellion of that year
                    was the subject of inquiry by court-martial, but he was acquitted. In 1765 he
                    was raised to the rank of general. He died at Cranham Hall, Essex, 1st July
                    1785.</p>
                <p>0G0WAY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Ogowe</hi><hi rend="italic">(0gooauai,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">O gobai),</hi> a river of West Africa which falls into the
                    Atlantic in the neighbourhood of 1° S. lat., or 400 miles north of the mouth of
                    the Congo. The extent of its delta (70 to 80 miles from north to south), and the
                    immense volume of water which it brings down when in flood, gave origin to the
                    belief that it must either be a bifurcation of the Congo or one of the leading
                    arteries of the continent. The former view was set aside by the fact that the
                    two rivers did not rise at the same season of the year; but so recently as 1876
                    Czerny advocated the identity of the Ogoway with Schweinfurth’s famous Uelle
                    (Welle), with Nachtigal’s Bahr-Kuta, and with Barth’s river of Kubanda, thus
                    taking it right across to the neighbourhood of the Nile basin. It appears,
                    however, that the head-streams of the Ogoway rise in the hilly country about 200
                    or 300 miles from the coast of the Atlantic (though the actual course of the
                    river is 500 to 600 miles), and its extraordinary volume is to be explained by
                    their draining an extensive tract on both sides of the equator which is deluged
                    with tropical rains. Savorgnan de Brazza claims to have reached (1882) the
                    sources of the river in a rugged, sandy, and almost treeless plateau, which
                    forms the watershed between its basin and that of the Congo, whose main stream
                    is only 140 miles distant. Cutting its way athwart the gneiss and schists of the
                    various ranges of the Sierra Complida, the main stream of the Ogoway (often
                    called the Okanda from one of the tribes on its banks) is interrupted with
                    cataracts and rapids (at Fare, 26 feet, and Dume, for example) till within a
                    comparatively short distance from the confluence with its principal left-hand
                    affluent, the Ngunie, in 0° 35' S. lat. and 10° 25' E. long. Even in the upper
                    part of its course, however, it often attains a great width, and below this
                    confluence it spreads out into an average of 8000 feet, at the same time showing
                    a tendency to split into a number of secondary channels, some of which connect
                    it on the north with the great Ajingo Lake, and on the south with the still
                    larger Jonanga Lake. The northmost branch of the delta—the Nazareth river, which
                    falls into Nazareth" Bay to the north of Cape Lopez—has in the driest period of
                    the year a depth of from 20 to 30 feet, and its water is drinkable even at
                    flood-tide. The southern arms discharge into the extensive Cama or Nkomi Lagoon
                    and the Rio Fernäo Vaz. With the exception of the Ngunie, which has been
                    ascended 40 miles as far as the Samba falls, the affluents of the Ogoway—the
                    Passa, Lolo, Shebe, Ivindo, Ofue, &lt;fcc.—are but very partially known; and
                    some of those from the north may prove to have a longer course than is at
                    present supposed. The Ogoway rises in March and April, and again in October and
                    November; it is navigable for steamers in its low-water condition as far as the
                    junction of the Ngunie.</p>
                <p>Though Bowditch called attention in 1817 to the existence of the river, it was
                    not till 1857-59 that its exploration was begun by Du Chaillu. It has since been
                    made known by the labours of Serval and Griffon du Ballay, R. B. N. Walker,
                    Aymés, the marquis de Compiègne, A. Marche, Oskar Lenz, and Savorgnan de Brazza.
                    English and German factories were founded about 1868 at Adelina Longa
                    (Adaûlinaûlonga), and at Franceville, a station of the International African
                    Association, in 1880.</p>
                <p>See Petermann’s <hi rend="italic">Mittheil.</hi>, 1872, pp. 5-10; 1875, pp.
                    121-130; 1879, pp. 103-108; and 1883, pp. 177-184, with map; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proc.</hi><hi rend="italic">R.</hi><hi rend="italic">G. Soc.,</hi> 1873
                    (Walker’s narrative); <hi rend="italic">Bull,</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Soc.
                    de Géogr.,</hi> Paris, 1877; <hi rend="italic">Zeitsch.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >der</hi><hi rend="italic">Ges. f. Erdk.,</hi> Berlin, 1875 and 1876 (the former
                    Lenz’s narrative, the latter a résumé of the course of discovery by Czerny).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
