<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0890-0825-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OREL, or Orloff (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    825)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:955129">Hemp</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010360">Marl</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1000435">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880643">Cossacks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f27h">Hemp</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c4k">Marl</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4697039w">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n890/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OREL, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Orloff</hi></label>, a
                    government of central Russia, bounded by Smolensk, Kaluga, and Tula on the N.,
                    and by Voronezh, Kursk, and Tchernigoff on the S., with an area of 18,040 square
                    miles. The surface is an undulating plateau gently sloping towards the west; the
                    highest hills do not reach 900 feet, and none of the valleys are less than 450
                    feet above the sea. Geologically Orel consists principally of Lower Devonian
                    limestones, marls, and sandstones, covered with Jurassic clays, the last
                    appearing at the surface, however, only as isolated islands, or in the valleys,
                    being concealed for the most part under thick beds of cretaceous chalk, marls,
                    and sands. The Carboniferous limestones and clays (of the so-called Moscow
                    basin) appear in the north-west only at a great depth. The Jurassic clays and
                    marls are covered at several places with a stratum of clay containing good
                    iron-ore, while the Devonian sandstones and limestones are worked for building
                    purposes. The whole is buried under a bed, from 30 to 40 feet thick, of
                    boulder-clay and loess, the last covering extensive areas besides the valleys.
                    The soil—a mixture of “black earth” with clay—is fertile, except in the Desna
                    region, which is covered with sands and tough clays. The principal rivers are
                    the Don, which forms the eastern boundary of the government and has
                    many.tributaries, the chief being the Sosna; the Oka, which rises in the
                    district of Orel and receives the navigable Zusha and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n891/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0891-0826"/> many smaller streams; and the Desna, with the
                    Bolva, draining the marshy lowlands in the west. On the Oka, Zusha, Desna, and
                    Bolva there is a brisk traffic in corn, oil, hemp, timber, metal, glass, china,
                    paper, and buildingstone. Marshes occupy large areas in the basin of the Desna,
                    as also in several parts of that of the Oka; they are mostly covered with
                    forests, which occupy from 50 to 65 per cent, of the districts of Bryansk,
                    Trubtchevsk, and Karatcheff, while towards the east, in the basin of the Don,
                    wood is so scarce that straw is used for fuel. The climate is moderate, the
                    average yearly temperature at Orel being 41 <hi rend="superscript"> o-</hi> 2
                    (14 <hi rend="superscript"> 0,</hi> 8 in January and 67° ’ 0 in July).</p>
                <p>The population, 1,596,900 in 1870, and 1,877,100 in 1881, consists almost
                    exclusively of Great Russians belonging to the Greek Church; the Nonconformists
                    are reckoned at about 12,000, the Catholics at 3000, and the Jews at 1000. The
                    chief occupation is agriculture, which is most productive in the east and
                    towards the centre of the government. In 1877 59 per cent, of the province was
                    under crops, the estimated yield being 7,196,000 quarters of corn and 1,212,000
                    quarters of potatoes. Of the grain not used in the distilleries a large
                    proportion is exported to the Baltic. Hemp and hemp-seed oil are extensively
                    exported from the west to Riga, Libau, and St Petersburg. Tobacco is also
                    cultivated with profit. Cattle-breeding and horse-breeding, though somewhat
                    depressed within the last twenty years, are still in a better condition than in
                    neighbouring governments,—the Orel breeds, both of carriage and of cart horses,
                    being held in estimation throughout Russia. In 1881 there were 500,000 horses,
                    340,000 cattle, and 790,000 sheep. Bee-culture is widely diffused in the forest
                    districts, as are also the timber-trade and the preparation of tar and pitch.
                    Manufactures are rapidly increasing; in 1879 there were 540 larger industrial
                    establishments, employing 14,130 hands, and producing castiron rails, machinery,
                    locomotive engines and railway waggons, glass, hemp-yarn and ropes, leather,
                    timber, soap, tobacco, chemical produce, &amp;c. There are also distilleries and
                    a great many smaller oil-works and flour-mills. Karatcheff and Syevsk are
                    important centres for hemp-carding; Bolkhoff and Elets are the chief centres of
                    the tanning industry; while the districts of Elets, Dmitroff, and partly Mtsensk
                    supply flour and various food-pastes. At Bryansk a Government cannon-foundry
                    employs 700 hands. The so-called “MaltsofFs works” in the district of Bryansk
                    are worthy of mention as an industrial colony comprising several iron,
                    machinery, glass, and rope works, where thousands of peasants find temporary or
                    permanent employment; they have their own technical school, employ engineers of
                    their own training, and have their own narrowgauge railways and telegraphs, both
                    managed by boys of the technical school. Numerous petty trades are carried on by
                    peasants, along with agriculture. The fairs held in many villages are animated,
                    and have some importance for the cattle trade. Orel is divided into twelve
                    districts, the chief towns of which are Orel (76,700 inhabitants), Bolkhoff
                    (29,020), Bryansk (12,660), Dmitrovsk (6560), Elets (41,450), Karatcheff
                    (11,200), Kromy (3050), Livny (21,170), Maloarklιanghelsk (3920), Mtsensk
                    (14,200), Syevsk (9650), and Trubtchevsk (5170).</p>
                <p>In the 9th century the country was inhabited by the Syeveryanes on the Desna and
                    the Vyatichees on the Oka, who both paid tribute to the Khazars. The Syeveryanes
                    recognized the rule of the princes of the Rurik family from 884, and the
                    Vyatichees from the middle of the 10th century; but the two peoples followed
                    different historical lines, the former entering into the Suzdal principality,
                    while the latter fell under the rule of that of Tchernigofl'. In the 11th
                    century both had wealthy towns and villages; during the Tartar invasion these
                    were all burned and pillaged, and the whole territory, lying as it did on the
                    two chief lines of the Tartar advance, became a desert, where the Nogays
                    encamped with their herds. With the fall of the Great Horde the western part of
                    the country fell under Lithuanian rule and was the subject of repeated struggles
                    between Lithuania and Moscow. In the 16th century the Russians began to erect
                    new forts or to fortify the old towns, and the territory was rapidly colonized
                    by immigrants from the north. In 1610 the towns of the present government of
                    Orel (then known as the Ukrayna or “border-region”) had an active share in the
                    insurrection against Moscow under the pseudo-Demetrius, and suffered much from
                    the civil war which ensued. They continued, however, to be united with the rest
                    of Russia, and in the next century formed a basis for further Russian advance
                    towards the south.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Orel,</hi> capital of the above government, lies at the
                    confluence of the Oka with the Orlik, on the great line of railway to the
                    Crimea, 238 miles south-south-west from Moscow. It has railway connexion also
                    with Smolensk and the Baltic ports in the west, and with Saratofl*, Tsaritsyn,
                    and Novotcherkassk in the south-east. It was founded in 1566, but developed
                    slowly, and had only a very few houses at the beginning of the last century. The
                    cathedral, begun in 1794, was finished only in 1861. The town now possesses a
                    military gymnasium (corps of cadets), a few secondary schools, a public library,
                    and a theatre; large storehouses for grain and timber, a spacious <hi
                        rend="italic">gostinoy dvor</hi> with numerous shops, and the offices of the
                    municipal bank are perhaps its best buildings. The manufactures are rapidly
                    increasing; in 1879 the hemp-carding, hempspinning, and rope-making industries
                    produced 1,020,000 roubles, the flour-mills about 300,000 roubles, and the
                    aggregate from all the manufactures exceeded 2,000,000 roubles. Orel is one of
                    the chief markets of central Russia for the trade in corn and hemp, as also in
                    hempseed oil and tallow, which are shipped down the Oka or sent by rail. Metal
                    wares, tobacco, kaolin, and glass ware are also exported, while salt, groceries,
                    and manufactured goods are imported for distribution throughout the villages of
                    the government, or to be sent to the Don Cossacks. The population, 45,000 in
                    1875, was 76,700 in 1881.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
