<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0839-0776-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ONYX</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 776</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k52g">Trapping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:946846">Gravel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839122">Broaching</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:982026">Jasper</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1895604">Tazzas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1202667">Uruguay</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n839/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ONYX</label>, a variety of agate consisting of layers of
                    variegated chalcedony, arranged in parallel bands. The colours of the successive
                    strata vary in different stones, but in the typical onyx they are black and
                    white. If one of the layers consists of the brown chalcedony known as “sard” or
                    the red variety called “carnelian,” the resulting stone is termed a “sardonyx.”
                    It was probably this kind of stone that originally suggested the name “onyx”
                    (from <hi rend="italic">owξ,</hi> a nail), since the contrast between its layers
                    remotely resembles that between the flesh-coloured part of the finger-nail and
                    the white <hi rend="italic">lunula</hi> at its root. It was the practice of
                    certain Greek writers to restrict the word <hi rend="italic">owξ</hi> to the
                    mineral in its natural condition, and to designate it, when worked into
                    ornamental forms, by the diminutive <hi rend="italic">ovvχu&gt;v.</hi> When an
                    onyx presents a thin layer of whitish chalcedony spread over a black ground, the
                    upper stratum often exhibits a bluish tinge, and collectors at the present day
                    term such a stone a <hi rend="italic">nicolo,</hi> evidently a corruption of the
                    Italian diminutive <hi rend="italic">onicolo,</hi> or “little onyx.”</p>
                <p>India has for ages yielded the finest onyxes, and hence jewellers are in the
                    habit of applying the expression “Oriental onyx” to any stone distinguished by
                    beauty of natural colour and by regularity of its layers. The true Indian stones
                    are found as pebbles, associated with moss-agate, jasper, and other silicious
                    minerals in river-gravels, the materials of which have been derived originally
                    from the agate-nodules of trap-rocks, such as those which occur on an enormous
                    scale in the Deccan. As far back as the first century the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Periplus</hi> of the Red Sea mentions the onyx among the products
                    of Plythanae, a locality which may probably be identified with Paithon on the
                    Godavari, whence agates are obtained even at the present day. He further states
                    that the onyxes were taken down to Barygaza, the modern Broach, where a great
                    trade in agates is still carried on. It appears that the lapidaries of Broach
                    and of Cambay are now supplied with raw stones chiefly from Ratanpur, in the
                    territory of the rajah of Rajpipla, where the gravels are systematically worked
                    for the sake of their agates, jasper, onyx, and other silicious stones. See
                    Ball’s <hi rend="italic">Economic Geology of India,</hi> 1881, p. 503.</p>
                <p>The principal European locality for onyx is the neighbourhood of Oberstein on the
                    Nahe, a river which flows into the Rhine at Bingen. Near Idar, about two miles
                    from Oberstem, is a trap-hill called the Galgenberg, which for centuries was
                    largely worked by means of tunnels driven into the hillside, in order to extract
                    the nodules of agate which are embedded in the melaphyre forming the rock. When
                    these nodules are broken open they occasionally yield a banded chalcedony which
                    serves admirably for onyxes. The quarries have, however, been abandoned for many
                    years in consequence of the discovery of larger and finer nodules in Uruguay,
                    principally among the gravels of the Tarquarie and the Rio Pardo. These agates
                    are still sent over in large quantities to Oberstein, where the cutting and
                    polishing of such silicious stones form almost the sole industry of the
                    locality. Coming from South America, they are commonly known in trade as
                    “Brazilian agates”; and it is from these agates that most of our onyx is now
                    obtained.</p>
                <p>It is but rarely that the South-American agates present in their natural
                    condition sufficient diversity of colour to constitute a good onyx, but for many
                    years it has been the practice of the German agate-workers to colour these
                    stones artificially. By this means an agate of dull colour may be rapidly
                    converted into a deep-tinted onyx, the successive layers becoming sharply
                    defined and vividly coloured during the process of staining. How this dyeing is
                    effected has been described in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Agate,</hi> vol.
                    i. p. 277.</p>
                <p>The onyx is largely employed for ring-stones, brooches, beads, and other
                    ornamental objects; but its chief use is as a material for <hi rend="italic"
                    >camei</hi> and <hi rend="italic">intagli.</hi> By taking advantage of the
                    different tints of the strata in this stone, a skilful artist is enabled to
                    produce effects of a very pleasing character. Among the finest examples of
                    ancient stone-engraving<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n840/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0840-0777"/> which have descended to us are certain vessels in
                    onyx, elaborately ornamented with cameo-work, such as the Cup of the Ptolemies,
                    the Farnese Tazza, and the Mantuan or Brunswick Vase.</p>
                <p>According to the Authorized Version of the Old Testament, the onyx formed the
                    eleventh stone in the breast-plate of the high priest; but it is more probable
                    that this stone (DΠ⅛^) is the beryl, and that the onyx is □S∏', Exod. xxxix. 11
                    (E. V. diamond).</p>
                <p>It is pointed out by the Rev. C. W. King that the earliest mention of the onyx as
                    a precious stone is to be found in the inscriptions of the Parthenon, which date
                    from the Peloponnesian War (431-404 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>), where a
                    large engraved onyx is mentioned as an offering. It is to be specially noted
                    that ancient writers applied the term <hi rend="italic">6vυξ</hi> to two
                    entirely different stones. While one of them was the true onyx of modern
                    mineralogists, as described above, the other was merely a stalagmitic variety of
                    carbonate of lime, a mineral much softer, less precious, and much more widely
                    distributed than the chalcedonic onyx, yet resembling it in so far as it also
                    presents a parallel-banded structure. This mineral is still known as
                    “onyx-marble” (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Marble,</hi> vol. xv. p. 529).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
