<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0877-0814-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORCAGNA (9th edition, volume 17, page 814)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984609">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984572">Judgment</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n877/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORCAGNA</label> (c. 1316 <hi rend="italic">-c.</hi> 1376<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The dates of Orcagna’s
                            birth and death are not exactly known. According to Vasari, he died in
                            1389 at the age of sixty; but a document dated 1376 provides a guardian
                            for Tessa and Romola, daughters of Orcagna’s widow Francesca (see
                            Bonaini, <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ined.,</hi> pp. 105-6). Possibly,
                            therefore, 1376 was the year of his death; and if Vasari is right about
                            his age his birth would have been in 1316. Milanesi, the able editor of
                            Vasari, is inclined to think that Orcagna died in 1368, when he is known
                            to have been seriously ill.</p></note>), whose full name was <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Andrea di Cione,</hi> called <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Arcagnuolo,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Of
                            this form, sometimes spelt Orcagnuolo, Orcagna is a
                        corruption.</p></note> was the son of a very able Florentine goldsmith,
                    Maestro Cione, said to have been one of the principal artists who worked on the
                    magnificent silver frontal of the high altar of San Giovanni, the Florentine
                    Baptistery. The result of Orcagna’s early training in the use of the precious
                    metals may be traced in the extreme delicacy and refined detail of his principal
                    works in sculpture. He had at least three brothers who all practised some branch
                    of the fine arts: Lionardo or Nardo, the eldest, a painter; Matteo, a sculptor
                    and mosaicist; and Jacopo, also a painter. They were frequently associated with
                    Orcagna in his varied labours.</p>
                <p>From the time of Giotto to the end of the 14th centurv</p>
                <p>Orcagna stands quite pre-eminent even among the many excellent artists of that
                    time. In sculpture he was a pupil of Andrea Pisano; in painting, though
                    indirectly, he was a disçiple of Giotto. Few artists have practised with such
                    success so many branches of the arts. Orcagna was not only a painter and
                    sculptor, but also a worker in mosaic, an architect, and a poet. His importance
                    in the history of Italian art rests not merely on his numerous and beautiful
                    productions, but also on his widespread influence, transmitted to his successors
                    through a large and carefully-trained school of pupils. In style as a painter
                    Orcagna comes midway between Giotto and Fra Angelico: he combined the dramatic
                    force and realistic vigour of the earlier painter with the pure brilliant colour
                    and refined unearthly beauty of Fra Angelico. His large fresco paintings are
                    works of extreme decorative beauty and splendour,—composed with careful
                    reference to their architectural surroundings, arranged for the most part on one
                    plane, without the strong foreshortening or effects of perspective with which
                    the mural paintings of later masters are so often marred.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Orcagna as a Painter.—</hi> His chief works in fresco were
                    at Florence, in the church of S. Maria Novella. He first covered the walls of
                    the retro-choir with scenes from the life of the Virgin. These, unfortunately,
                    were much injured by damp very soon after their completion, and towards the end
                    of the following century were replaced by other frescos of the same subjects by
                    Ghirlandaio, who, according to Vasari, made much use of Orcagna’s motives and
                    invention. Orcagna also painted three walls of the Strozzi chapel, at the
                    north-east of the same church, with a grand series of frescos, which still
                    exist, though in a much injured and “restored” state. On the northern end wall
                    is the Last Judgment, painted above and round the window, the light from which
                    makes it difficult to see the picture. In the centre is Christ floating among
                    clouds <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi> surrounded by angels; below are kneeling
                    figures of the Virgin and St John the Baptist, with the twelve apostles. Lower
                    still are patriarchs, prophets, and saints, with the resurrection of the blessed
                    and the lost. The finest composition is that on the west wall, unbroken by any
                    win dow. It represents paradise, with Christ and the Virgin enthroned in majesty
                    among rows of brilliantly-coloured cherubim and seraphim tinged with
                    rainbow-like rays of light. Below are long lines of the heavenly hierarchy
                    mingled with angel musicians; and lower still a crowd of saints floating on
                    clouds. Many of these figures are of exquisite beauty, especially the few that
                    have escaped restoration. Faces of the most divine tenderness and delicacy occur
                    among the female saints; the two central angels below the throne are figures of
                    wonderful grace in pose and movement; and the whole picture, lighted by a soft
                    luminous atmosphere, seems to glow with an unearthly gladness and peace.
                    Opposite to this is the fresco attributed by Vasari to Orcagna’s brother
                    Bernardo, or rather Nardo <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> Lionardo); it was
                    completely repainted in 1530, so that nothing but the design remains, full of
                    horror and weird imagination. To some extent the painter has followed Dante’s
                    scheme of successive circles.</p>
                <p>These paintings were probably executed soon after 1350, and in 1357 Orcagna
                    painted one of his finest panel pictures, as a retable for the altar of the same
                    chapel, where it still remains. In the centre is Christ in majesty between
                    kneeling figures of St Peter and St Thomas Aquinas, attended by angel musicians;
                    on each side are standing figures of three other saints. It is a work of the
                    greatest beauty both in colour and composition; it is painted with extreme
                    miniature-like delicacy, and is on the whole very well preserved. This retable
                    is signed, “An. dni. mccclvii Andreas Cionis de Florentia me pinxit.” <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n878/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0878-0815"/> Another fine altar-piece on panel by Orcagna,
                    dated 1363, is preserved in the Cappella de’ Medici near the sacristy of Sta
                    Croce; it represents the four doctors of the Latin church. According to Vasari,
                    Orcagna also painted some very fine frescos in Sta Croce, similar in subjects to
                    those attributed to him in the Campo Santo of Pisa, and full of fine portraits.
                    These do not now exist. In the cathedral of Florence, on one of the northern
                    piers, there hangs a nobly-designed and highly-finished picture on panel by
                    Orcagna, representing S. Zanobio enthroned, trampling under his feet Cruelty and
                    Pride; at the sides are kneeling figures of SS. Eugenius and Crescentius,—the
                    whole very rich in colour. The retable mentioned by Vasari as having been
                    painted for the Florentine church of S. Pietro Maggiore is now in the National
                    Gallery of London. It is a richly decorative composition of the Coronation of
                    the Virgin, between rows of saints, together with nine other subjects painted in
                    miniature. Other paintings on panel by Orcagna were sent by the Pope to Avignon,
                    but cannot now be traced. The frescos also have been destroyed with which,
                    according to Vasari, Orcagna decorated the façade of S. Apollinare and the
                    Cappella de’ Cresci in the church of the Servi in Florence.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The magnificent but much injured frescos
                            of the Last Judgment, Hell, and the Triumph of Death in the Pisan Campo
                            Santo, described with great minuteness and enthusiasm by Vasari, are
                            attributed by him to Orcagna, but internal evidence seems to show that
                            they are productions of the Sienese school. Crowe and Cavalcaselle
                            attribute them to the two brothers Lorenzetti of Siena, but they have
                            been so injured by wet, the settlement of the wall, and repeated
                            retouchings that it is difficult to come to any clear decision as to
                            their authorship. It appears, however, much more probable that they are
                            the work of Bernardo Daddi.</p></note></p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Orcagna as a Sculptor and Architect</hi><note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Orcagna was admitted as a
                            member of the Sculptors’ Guild in 1352. His name occurs in the roll as
                            “Andreas Cionis vocatus Arcagnolus, pictor.”</p></note><hi rend="italic"
                        >?—</hi> In 1355 Orcagna was appointed architect to the chapel of Or San
                    Michele in Florence. This curiously-planned building, with a large upper room
                    over the vaulting of the lower part, had been begun by Taddeo Gaddi as a
                    thank-offering for the cessation of the plague of 1348. It took the place of an
                    earlier oratory designed by Arnolfo del Cambio, and was the gift of the united
                    trade guilds of Florence. As to the building itself, it is impossible to say how
                    much is due to Taddeo Gaddi and how much to Orcagna, but the great marble
                    tabernacle was wholly by Orcagna. This, in its combined splendour of
                    architectural design, sculptured reliefs and statuettes, and mosaic enrichments,
                    is one of the most important and beautiful works of art which even rich Italy
                    possesses. It combines an altar, a shrine, a reredos, and a baldacchino. In
                    general form it is perhaps the purest and most gracefully designed of all
                    specimens of Italian Gothic. It is a tall structure of white marble, with
                    vaulted canopy and richly-decorated gables and pinnacles, reaching almost to the
                    vaulted roof of the chapel. The detail is extremely delicate, and brilliant
                    gem-like colour is given by lavish enrichments of minute patterns in glass
                    mosaic, inlaid in the white marble of the structure. It is put together with the
                    greatest care and precision; Vasari especially notes the fact that the whole was
                    put together without any cement, which might have stained the purity of the
                    marble, all the parts being closely fitted together with bronze dowels. The
                    spire-like summit of the tabernacle is surmounted by a figure of St Michael, and
                    at a lower stage on the roof are statuettes of the apostles. The altar has a
                    relief of Hope between panels with the Marriage of the Virgin and the
                    Annunciation. On the right side, looking east, of the base of the tabernacle are
                    reliefs of the Birth of the Virgin and her Presentation in the Temple; on the
                    left, the Nativity and the Adoration of the Magi; and behind, the Presentation
                    of Christ in the</p>
                <p>Temple, and the Angel warning the Virgin to escape into Egypt. Above the last two
                    subjects are large reliefs of the Death of the Virgin, surrounded by the
                    apostles, and higher still her Assumption; she stands in a vesica, and is borne
                    by angels to heaven. On the base of the Virgin’s tomb is inscribed “Andreas
                    Cionis pictor Florentinvs oratorii archimagister extitit hvjvs mccclix.”
                    Orcagna’s own portrait is given as one of the apostles. In addition to these
                    richly-composed subject-reliefs the whole work is adorned with many other single
                    figures and heads of prophets, angels, and the Virtues, all executed with
                    wonderful finish and refinement. The shrine, which forms an aumbry in the
                    reredos, contains a miraculous picture of the Madonna. A fine bronze screen,
                    with open geometrical tracery, encloses the whole. No work of sculpture in Italy
                    is more magnificent than this wonderful tabernacle, both in general effect and
                    in the delicate beauty of the reliefs and statuettes with which it is so
                    lavishly enriched. It cost the enormous sum of 96,000 gold florins.
                    Unfortunately it is very badly placed and insufficiently lighted, so that a
                    minute examination of its beauties is a work of difficulty.</p>
                <p>No mention is made by Vasari of Orcagna’s residence in Orvieto, where he occupied
                    for some time the post of “capomaestro” to the duomo.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Milanesi, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">dell’ Arte Toscana·,</hi> p. 233
                            (Siena, 1873); Luzι, <hi rend="italic">T)ιwmo d’Orvieto</hi>; and
                            Vasari, ed. Milanesi, i. p. 617 (Florence, 1878).</p></note> He accepted
                    this appointment on 14th June 1358 at the large salary (for that time) of 300
                    gold florins a year. His brother Matteo was engaged to work under him, receiving
                    8 florins a month. When Orcagna accepted this appointment at Orvieto he had not
                    yet finished his work at Or San Michele, and so was obliged to make long visits
                    to Florence, which naturally interfered with the satisfactory performance of his
                    work for the Orviétans. The result was that on the 12th of September 1360
                    Orcagna, having been paid for his work up to that time, resigned the post of
                    “capo-maestro” of the duomo, though he still remained a little longer in Orvieto
                    to finish a large mosaic picture on the west front. When this mosaic (made of
                    glass tesserae from Venice) was finished in 1362, it was found to be uneven in
                    surface, and not fixed securely into its cement bed. An arbitration was
                    therefore held as to the price Orcagna was to receive for it, and he was awarded
                    60 gold florins.</p>
                <p>Vasari mentions as other architectural works by Orcagna the design for the piers
                    in the nave of the Florentine duomo, a zecca or mint, which appears not to have
                    been carried out, and the Loggia dei Lanzi in the Piazza della Signoria. It is,
                    however, more than doubtful whether Orcagna had any hand in this last building,
                    a very graceful vaulted structure, with three semicircular open arches on the
                    side and one at each end, intended to form a sheltered meeting-place for the
                    Priori during elections and other public transactions. This loggia was ordered
                    by the General Council ς&gt;f Florence in 1356, but was not actually begun till
                    the year 1376, after Orcagna’s death. The architects were Benci di Cione
                    (possibly a brother of Orcagna) and Simone di Francesco Talenti, both men of
                    considerable reputation in Florence. The sculptured reliefs of the seven Virtues
                    in the spandrels of the arches of the loggia, also attributed to Orcagna by
                    Vasari, were later still. They were designed by Angelo Gaddi (1383-1386), and
                    were carried out by three or four different sculptors.</p>
                <p>Pupils of Orcagna named by Vasari are Bernardo Nello, a Pisan, Tommaso di Marco,
                    a Florentine, and, chief of all, Francesco Traun, whose grand painting on panel
                    of St Thomas Aquinas enthroned with the arch-heretics at his feet still hangs in
                    the church for which it was painted,—Sta Caterina at Pisa. Orcagna had, in
                    addition to the two daughters mentioned above, a son named Crone, who was a
                    painter of but little eminence. Some sonnets attributed to Orcagna exist in MS.
                    in the Strozzi and Magliabecchian libraries <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0879-0816"/> in Florence. They have been published by
                    Trucchi <hi rend="italic">{Poesie</hi><hi rend="italic">inedite,</hi> ii. p. 25,
                    Prato, 1846). They are graceful in language, but rather artificial and
                    over-elaborated.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Vasari, ed. Milanesi, i. p. 593 (Florence,
                    1878); <hi rend="italic">Giomale degli</hi><hi rend="italic">Archivi</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Toscani,</hi> iii. p. 282, &amp;c.; Passerini, <hi
                        rend="italic">Curiosità</hi><hi rend="italic">storico-artisticħe</hi>; Gaye,
                        <hi rend="italic">Carteggio</hi><hi rend="italic">inedito,</hi> i. pp. 500∙
                    513, ii. p. 5; Rosini, <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">della
                        pittura,</hi> vol. ii.; Baldinucci, <hi rend="italic">Professori</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">del disegno,</hi> vol. i.; Ruinohr, <hi rend="italic">Ricerche
                        Italians,</hi> ii., and <hi rend="italic">Antologia di Firenze,</hi> Hi.;
                    Crowe and Cavalcaselle, <hi rend="italic">Painting in Italy,</hi> i. p. 425
                    (London, 1864); Perkins, <hi rend="italic">Tuscan Sculptors,</hi> p. 77 (London,
                    1865). (J. H. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
