<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0871-0808-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORACLE (9th edition, volume 17, page 808)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888385">Dead</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:975961">Intentionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847420">Carians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7n383">Understanding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1243607">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n871/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORACLE</label>. It was a universal belief in the ancient
                    world that there is a capacity in the human mind to divine the will of God <hi
                        rend="italic">(μαντικόν τι ή ψυχή,</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Plu∕edr.,</hi> 242 C). This capacity is not equally developed in all men,
                    and, practically, a very few persons, in whom it is strong, are distinguished
                    from the mass as ∕Λαvτ∈ts. These are able to understand the methods by which the
                    gods reveal their intentions to men. There occur cases where the gods speak
                    directly to men, where a divine voice is heard issuing its commands or warnings,
                    but these instances are confined, except in a few remarkable historical cases
                    (such as the appearance of Pan to the Athenian messenger, <hi rend="superscript"
                        > i</hi>. 30 B.c., Herod., vi. 105), to the heroic age and to epic oetry.
                    Setting these aside, we find that the divine will was revealed to the
                    interpreting medium in two ways—by inspiration and by signs. In the former case
                    the divine influence overpowers the soul of the medium and takes entire
                    possession of it for the time. The medium cannot himself bring on a revelation,
                    but is at rare intervals affected by the power of the god, his consciousness
                    ceases, and the god speaks through him words which he is himself unable to
                    control or even to understand. So, for example, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >prophetes</hi> of Apollo Ptoios gave a response in the Carian language,
                    which no one except the questioner could understand (Herod., viii. 135). The
                    second method of revelation, by signs, required a distinct art of
                    interpretation; certain events, phenomena in the heavens or in bird or animal
                    life, the conduct of sacrificial animals and the appearance presented by their
                    entrails, &lt;fcc., presaged the will of the god to him who possessed the art of
                    interpreting them. The second method was called <hi rend="italic"
                        >artificial</hi> (∈vτ∈χpoς), in opposition to the first, which is direct and
                        <hi rend="italic">artless</hi> (ατ∈χvos).</p>
                <p>In every case the revelation of the divine will is dependent on the direct act of
                    the god; he affects the soul of the <hi rend="italic">pavτL&lt;i</hi> when and
                    where he pleases; he sends, when he chooses, the signs from which his intentions
                    can be inferred. There was, however, a belief that at certain places the god
                    gave revelations more frequently than at others. Such places were generally
                    characterized by some marked physical feature. At these places there were
                    established regular institutions, with a staff of priests and prophets, to which
                    the neighbours resorted for counsel; the Latin term “oracle” (in Greek μαντεία,
                    χρ^σττ/ρια) is the general name. With regard to these institutions we have to
                    consider (1) their method of interpretation, in so far as this is not most
                    naturally given under the articles treating of the particular localities, and
                    (2) their rank and influence among the Greeks.</p>
                <p>1. The methods of interpretation varied greatly. Even at the same oracle several
                    methods were often practised side by side. In the most primitive the spirits of
                    the dead appeared and conversed directly with the inquirer. This method was rare
                    in Greece; but an undoubtedly good example is recorded (Herod., v. 92) in
                    Thesprotia, where Periander sent to consult the shade of his wife Melissa; a
                    Biblical instance is the apparition of the shade of Samuel to Saul. The visit of
                    Odysseus to the lower world is obviously a mere poetical version of the
                    consultation of a Boeotian oracle of Tiresias, where the hero spoke directly to
                    his devotees. In the oracle of Trophonius at Lebadea in Boeotia the method of
                    inquiry was certainly modelled after the idea of a descent to the infernal
                    world. Beside the oracle were the two springs of Memory and Oblivion, which,
                    according to the mystic teaching, were the two fountains of the lower world. The
                    inquirer descended into an underground place, and, it is said, saw such sights
                    that he never smiled again. This method belonged to a very primitive stage of
                    Greek history; and it is certain that Greek religion in general, and many
                    oracles in particular, had experienced a long development before the time which
                    we know best. Probably this method was originally more widely practised than we
                    can actually trace.</p>
                <p>The common method of revelation in hero-oracles, and in the oracles of some gods,
                    was through dreams. Herooracles were certainly in their earliest form simply
                    oracles of the dead; the word iypωs is a generic term for a dead man. We can
                    trace occasional survivals of the most primitive form of the hero-oracle. The
                    person who seeks advice goes to sleep over the actual grave, and the dead man
                    appears in a dream. A type of the usual method, which was called “incubation” or
                        <hi rend="italic">tγκoiμηστς,</hi> is the oracle of Amphiaraus near Oropus,
                    beside the spring where the hero had risen from the earth to become a god. The
                    inquirer, after abstaining from wine for three days and from all food for
                    twenty-four hours, slept in the temple on the skin of a ram which he had
                    sacrificed. The oracles of Gaea or Ge are closely connected with those of the
                    dead and of heroes. The Earth is giver of responses, as being the home of the
                    dead, who sleep in her womb, but who can be called forth to give counsel to
                    their descendants living on earth. Earth-oracles also belong to a primitive
                    stage of Hellenic religion, and had in historical times either given place to
                    oracles of more developed Hellenic type or occupied a very secondary position.
                    In Olympia it is probable that the oracle of Gaea was the oldest institution,
                    and it is universally recognized in ancient and modern times that the Delphic
                    oracle originally belonged to the same goddess. Probably the cleft in the earth
                    in the Delphic adyton was originally conceived as the passage of communication
                    between the dead under the earth and the living on its surface. A uniform
                    tradition (Paus., x. 5, 3; Aesch., <hi rend="italic">Cho.,</hi> 1 <hi
                        rend="italic">sq.}</hi> recognizes one most important fact: in the progress
                    of Greek history, as religious thought developed, there was a progressive
                    development in the character of the Delphic oracle. Gaea was replaced by Themis,
                    a more moralized conception of the Earth-goddess, as the incarnation of natural
                    order and law; but Apollo, the highest creation of Hellenic religion, finally
                    occupies Delphi as the prophet and counsellor of his people. The oracles of
                    Apollo work through inspiration. In Delphi the seer was a woman, Pythia, who was
                    thrown into a state of ecstatic frenzy by the influence of a vapour ascending
                    from a cleft in the earth within the adyton, and while in this state uttered
                    words and cries which contained the answer of Apollo. All the methods of
                    interpretation by signs were practised at different oracles in Greece; even in
                    Apolline oracles, such as the Delphic, the artificial method was employed along
                    with that by inspiration.</p>
                <p>2. The original purpose of the oracles was not to foretell the future, but to
                    give counsel as to conduct in doubtful and difficult situations. In cases where
                    human prudence and skill seemed to fail, recourse was had to the oracle, and the
                    god gave advice to his people. Now it was the universal practice that the
                    priests should take the answers, usually incoherent and unintelligible, of the
                    seers and reduce them to form, often metrical; practically the oracles were
                    worked by the priests, and it is obvious that their character depended entirely
                    on the character of the priests and of the nation as a whole. The influence of
                    the oracles could be good only so long as the priests were not only honest and
                    of lofty intentions, but also in a more advanced intellectual position than the
                    people. In the early age of Greek history, when there was no education except
                    what was to be gained by wide intercourse, the priests of such an oracle as
                    Delphi occupied a most advantageous position. To Delphi as the γ∙i}s
                    &lt;γc&lt;∕&gt;αλos, the central point of the civilized world, came embassies
                    from every Greek city, and even from great non-Greek states such as Lydia and
                    Phrygia. It was a knot where every strand in civilized <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n872/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0872-0809"/> life was united. In accordance with this we
                    find that almost all the great lawgivers and sages of the 8th and 7th centuries
                    B.c. were in close relation with the Delphic oracle. All questions of
                    colonization were referred to the oracle, and it is due a good deal to this
                    central guiding influence that the overflow of the teeming population of Greece
                    was directed so systematically. It is instructive to compare the position of the
                    oracles in Greece with those of the kindred races of Asia Minor. In the latter
                    country the god is supreme over his people, the government is a pure theocracy,
                    and the priests, as interpreters of the divine will, are absolute masters of the
                    servants of the god. In Greece it is wholly different. In both cases the oracles
                    are the creation of the national genius,—in Asia Minor Oriental and stationary,
                    in Greece living and progressive. In the earliest time we can trace the
                    influence of the oracles discouraging the relentless blood-feud, distinguishing
                    classes of murder, and allowing purification and expiation in suitable cases.
                    They make the sanctity of oaths between man and man a special duty; Apollo
                    regards even hesitation to keep a pledge as already a sin (Herod., vi. 86; <hi
                        rend="italic">cf.</hi> i. 159). They are the centre of unions or
                    amphictyonies which bind their members to observe certain duties and show mercy
                    to their fellow-members; and Delphi, as the oracle of an amphictyony including
                    great part of Greece, had an important share in promoting that ideal unity of
                    the whole country which, though never realized, yet floated always before the
                    Greek mind. The oracles did something towards uniting the efforts of Greeks
                    against foreigners, and towards spreading Greek influence abroad in a systematic
                    way.</p>
                <p>As education became more general the qualification of superior knowledge
                    necessary to the proper working of the oracles was more difficult to keep up. At
                    the same time the growth of political life in the states intensified their
                    mutual enmities, and made it impossible for the oracles to maintain an attitude
                    of perfect justice, neutrality, and superiority. Though the custom continued
                    till a late period in Greek history that each state should consult the oracle in
                    difficulties, yet complaints of partiality become frequent. Concurrently with
                    the degradation in this respect there grew a demoralization in the whole tone of
                    the oracles: they were consulted by all in the most trivial matters. It became
                    an object to the priests to facilitate the access of votaries who contributed to
                    the wealth of the temple. Whereas originally the Delphic oracle spoke only once
                    a year, the number of days on which it was open to inquirers was gradually
                    increased; and other oracles in like manner turned their attention to the wants
                    of every applicant. In Dodona a large number of leaden tablets have been
                    discovered containing the questions addressed to the god by inquirers; they
                    range in date from the end of the 5th century B.c. onwards, and do not give any
                    very high idea of the kind of difficulties in which the god was asked to advise
                    his worshipper.</p>
                <p>See Carapanos, <hi rend="italic">Dodone,</hi> also an important article in
                    Fleckeisen’s <hi rend="italic">Jahrbücher</hi> for 1883. The most complete work
                    on oracles is Bouchy Leclerc’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >de la divination dans Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">antiquité.</hi> (W. Μ.
                    RA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
