<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0872-0809-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 809</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1983040">Andalusians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n872/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORAN</label> (Arabic, <hi rend="italic">Wahrân),</hi> the
                    chief town of the department and military division which form the western part
                    of the French colony of Algeria, lies at the head of a bay on the Mediterranean,
                    in 35° 44' N. lat., and almost on the meridian of Greenwich. The population of
                    the town in 1881 was 58,530; that of the commune, including town and suburbs,
                    59,377. In 1876, when the total for the town, besides 3728 in prisons,
                    hospitals, &amp;c. (5030 in 1881), was 45,640, 11,047 were French, 4948 Jews,
                    4782 natives, and 24,863 foreigners. The town is cut in two by the ravine of
                    Oued Rekhi, now partly covered over by boulevards and buildings. West of the
                    ravine lies the port, and above this the old Spanish town with the ancient
                    citadel looking down on it. On the east side the modern castle and the modern
                    town (built since the Spanish occupation) rise like an amphitheatre, and here,
                    too, are the Moorish houses of the Jews’ quarter. Taken altogether, Oran has the
                    shape of a triangle, the sea forming the base, and the angles at north-west,
                    north-east, and south being respectively the Fort de la Moune, the modern
                    castle, and Fort St André. Ramparts and forts are mainly of Spanish
                    construction; to the east they have been rebuilt since the French occupation in
                    advance of their old position. Of the six gates, three are on the west side, two
                    on the south, and one on the east. The modern castle was formerly the seat of
                    the beys of Oran; it is now occupied by the general in command of the military
                    division, and also serves as barracks, and accommodates most of the military
                    departments. The old castle was the residence of the Mohammedan rulers previous
                    to the Spanish conquest, and continued to be the residence of the governors of
                    the town up to the earthquake of 8th and 9th October 1790. The portion of the
                    building which still remains is used as barracks and a military prison.
                    Immediately behind, the Mourdjadjo hill rises to a height of 1900 feet; on the
                    way up are passed Fort St Grégoire, the votive chapel commemorative of the
                    cholera of 1849, and Fort Santa Cruz, crowning at a height of 1312 feet the
                    summit of the Aidour. Lastly, Fort de la Moune (so called from the monkeys which
                    are said to have haunted the neighbourhood) rises between the sea and the road
                    from Oran to Mers al-Kebir. In the Spanish town the streets are steep, sometimes
                    even becoming stairs; the “places” are mere widenings of the street. In the
                    French town the streets are well laid out and fit for carriages, and there are
                    various public squares, notably the Place d’Armes; the houses too, in spite of
                    the risk from earthquakes, are built in the French style, several stories high.
                    It is only in the Jews’ quarter that the houses are of a peculiar
                    type,—one-storied, with white-washed or red-washed walls, and enclosing an inner
                    court shaded by a vine. Oran is the see of a bishopric dependent on the
                    archbishopric of Algiers. The cathedral (St Louis) is an ancient mosque which
                    has successively been a Roman Catholic chapel, a synagogue, and again a Catholic
                    church according as the town changed hands. The last restoration was in 1839. A
                    fine picture representing the landing of St Louis at Tunis deserves to be
                    mentioned. The grand mosque (in Rue Philippe) was erected at the end of last
                    century in commemoration of the expulsion of the Spaniards, and with money paid
                    as ransom for Christian slaves. The minaret is one of the prettiest in Algeria.
                    Other mosques have been utilized for military purposes. Permanent quarters have
                    not yet been assigned to the prefecture, the courts of justice, and other civil
                    offices; the bank alone occupies a building of an imposing character. The
                    military hospital contains 1400 beds. Oran is well supplied with water; and a
                    number of beautiful promenades greatly increase its attractions. The main
                    peculiarity of the streets is the mixture of races, each with its own type and
                    costume. Arabs, Spaniards, and Turks, successive masters of the town, have all
                    left descendants; and with these are mingled black-gabardined Jews, Spanish
                    immigrants of recent date in Andalusian garb, French soldiers of all branches of
                    the service, Moors with nonchalant gait, and negroes, who serve as porters and
                    day-labourers for the community. The negroes occupy a whole village on the
                    outskirts of the town. While industrially of no importance, Oran is admirably
                    situated for commerce. From Cartagena to Oran is the shortest passage between
                    Europe and Algeria, and there is regular communication with Marseilles, Cette,
                    and Port Vendres in France, with Barcelona, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n873/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0873-0810"/> Valencia, Cartagena, Malaga, and Gibraltar in
                    Spain, and with the various ports on the Barbary coast. A railroad (261 miles)
                    runs to Algiers and is joined at Perregaux by the line from Arzeu to Saida and
                    the Kreider, which serves the high halfa (esparto) plateaus. There is also a
                    railway to Sidi Bel-Abbés. Previous to the French occupation there was no port
                    at Oran, vessels anchoring at Mers al-Kebir at the north-west entrance of the
                    bay. Mers al-Kebir is now reserved for the navy, and a harbour of 60 acres has
                    been constructed by means of a pier 3280 feet long from Fort de la Moune, and
                    two cross piers. A geographical society was founded at Oran in 1878.</p>
                <p>If Oran was not already occupied in the time of the Romans, its foundation must
                    be ascribed to the Andalusian seamen who settled there in the beginning of the
                    10th century. Rapidly rising into importance, it was taken and retaken, pillaged
                    and rebuilt, by the various conquerors of northern Africa. Almoravides,
                    Almolιades, and Merinides succeeded each other, and in the space of half a
                    century the town changed hands nine times. At length, in the latter half of the
                    15th century, it was subject to the sultans of Tlemcen, and reached the height
                    of its prosperity. Active commerce was maintained with the Venetians, the
                    Pisans, the Genoese, the Marseillese, and the Catalans, who imported the produce
                    of their looms, glass-wares, tin-wares, and iron, and received in return ivory,
                    ostrich feathers, gold-dust, tanned hides, grain, and negro slaves from the
                    interior of Africa. Admirable woollen cloth and splendid arms were locally
                    manufactured. The magnificence of its mosques and other public buildings, the
                    number of its schools, and the extent of its warehouses shed lustre on the city;
                    but wealth and luxury began to undermine its prosperity, and its ruin was
                    hastened by the piracy to which the Moorish refugees from Spain betook
                    themselves. Animated by the patriotic enthusiasm of Cardinal Ximenes, the
                    Spaniards determined to put a stop to those expeditions which were carrying off
                    their countrymen, destroying their commerce, and even ravaging their country.
                    Mers al-Kebir fell into their hands on 23d October 1505, and Oran in May 1509.
                    The latter victory, obtained with but trifling loss, was stained by the massacre
                    of a third of the Mohammedan population. From 6000 to 8000 prisoners, 60 cannon,
                    engines of war, and a considerable booty from the wealth accumulated by piracy
                    fell into the hands of the conquerors. Cardinal Ximenes introduced the Catholic
                    religion, with its churches, convents, Inquisition, &amp;c., and also restored
                    and extended the fortifications. Oran became the penal settlement of Spain, but
                    neither the convicts nor the noblemen in disgrace who were also banished thither
                    seem to have been under rigorous surveillance; fêtes, games, bull-fights,
                    &amp;c., were held. Meanwhile the Turks had become masters of Algeria, and
                    expelled the Spaniards from all their possessions except Oran. The bey, finally
                    settling at Mascara, watched his opportunity; and at length, in 1708, the
                    weakness of Spain and the treason of the count of Vera Cruz obliged the city to
                    capitulate. The Spaniards recovered possession in 1732, but found the
                    maintenance of the place a burden rather than a benefit, all the neighbouring
                    tribes having ceased to have dealings with the Christians. The earthquake of
                    1790 furnished an excuse for withdrawing their forces. Commencing by twenty-two
                    separate shocks at brief intervals, the oscillations continued from 8th October
                    to 22d November. Houses and fortifications were overthrown, and a third of the
                    garrison and a great number of the inhabitants perished. Famine and sickness had
                    begun to aggravate the situation when the bey of Mascara appeared before the
                    town with 30,000 men. By prodigies of energy the Spanish commander held out till
                    August 1791, when, having made terms with the dey of Algiers, he was allowed to
                    set sail for Spain with his guns and ammunition. The bey Mohammed took
                    possession of Oran in March 1792, and made it his residence instead of Mascara.
                    On the fall of Algiers the bey placed himself under the protection of the
                    conquerors. The French army entered the town 4th January 1831, and took formal
                    possession on the 17th of August.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
