<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-3046-0248-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARIUS, Caius (7th edition, volume 14, page
                    248)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876196">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844959">Camps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205364">Mauritania</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xp3p">Cimbri</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194203046?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Caius</hi></label>, one of the
                    most celebrated Roman generals, the principal events of whose life are included
                    between B. c. 134 and <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 86. It is difficult to say
                    whether Marius proved a greater curse or blessing to his country; he saved it,
                    indeed, from the cruelties of a barbarous enemy, but his ambition brought on it
                    more disasters than would <pb break="no" facs="nls:194203059?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-3059-0249"/> have arisen from the most calamitous war. Marius
                    was born about B. c. 157, of poor parents, in the village of Cereatae (Plin.
                    iii. 5), belonging to the district of Arpinum, which was afterwards the
                    birth-place of Cicero, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 106. His youth seems to
                    have been passed amidst the rude discipline of the camp; nor was his disposition
                    at all softened by literature or intercourse with the learned. He commenced his
                    military career at Numantia <hi rend="smallcaps">(b. c.</hi> 134), and by his
                    temperance and bravery so won the good opinion of Scipio, that that general
                    answered one of his friends who inquired where they would find another general
                    equal to himself, by putting his hand on the shoulder of Marius and saying,
                    “Here he is.” Many years, however, pass without any allusion to Marius, nor do
                    we know what part he took in the troubled times of the Gracchi. He appears again
                    in history as tribune of the people, <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. 119, which
                    office he is said to have obtained chiefly through the influence of the consul
                    Metellus, whose implacable enemy he afterwards became. He began immediately to
                    court the favour of the people, and proposed a law which tended to lessen the
                    authority of the patricians in matters of judicature. The consul Cotta persuaded
                    the senate to summon Marius to answer for his conduct; but the bold tribune
                    threatened to send even the consul Metellus to prison if he persisted in
                    opposition to this measure. The senate gave way, and the law was subsequently
                    confirmed by the people. He was thus supposed to have embarked in the popular
                    cause; but this opinion changed when it was found that he strenuously opposed
                    the distribution of corn amongst the people. When his year of office had
                    expired, he stood as candidate for that of curule aedile, but was rejected; upon
                    which he applied for that of plebeian aedilc, and in this too he was
                    unsuccessful. Not long afterwards he stood for the praetorship, and was returned
                    last of the six, and not without the suspicion of bribery. He was tried, and
                    escaped only by an equality of votes. The following year he was sent to Farther
                    Spain, which he soon cleared of the banditti who infested the province. On his
                    return to Rome he was anxious to take part in the administration of public
                    affairs, but he had neither riches to buy favour nor eloquence to command it.
                    Still, by his high spirit, by his indefatigable industry and simple mode of
                    living, he became a favourite with the people, and acquired sufficient
                    reputation to be thought worthy of the alliance of the Caesars. He married
                    Julia, the aunt of Julius Caesar. When Metellus was appointed, B. c. 108, to the
                    command of the war against Jugurtha, he took Marius as one of his lieutenants
                    into Africa. Marius does not appear to have considered himself as in the least
                    obliged to Metellus for this appointment, but only regarded it as the means of
                    raising himself to a still higher eminence. He took every method of acquiring
                    the good will of the soldiers, and even pointed out to them the faults which
                    their general had committed. In this way he succeeded in persuading all that he
                    alone was able to terminate the war. Marius determined to stand as candidate for
                    the consulship, and pressed Metellus to grant him leave of absence to proceed to
                    Rome. Metellus ridiculed his pretensions to such a high office, and, laughing,
                    asked him if he would not be satisfied to stay and be consul with his son, who
                    was then very young. He at last, however, granted permission, though only twelve
                    days before the election; and by great good fortune Marius got to Rome in six
                    days. The people were already favourably inclined to Marius; and as he was not
                    scrupulous as to the accusations he brought against Metellus, and the promises
                    he made, the people elected him consul, B. c. 107, with great applause. He
                    immediately began to levy troops, without paying any attention to the
                    respectability of the individuals whom he enlisted. Hitherto only people of
                    property had been intrusted with arms, but now Marius enrolled even slaves
                    amongst his soldiers, or at least <hi rend="italic">capite censu</hi> being
                    those who were so poor as to pay no con tribution to the state. He then returned
                    with his troops to Africa, which Metellus left, grieved and indignant that the
                    honour of closing the war should have thus been snatched from him by a man
                    towards whom he had shown so much kindness. Marius, however, did not reap the
                    glory which he had expected, for he was in a great measure deprived of it by his
                    quaestor Sylla. Jugurtha had fled to his father-in-law Bacchus, king of
                    Mauritania; and that prince, after some deliberation, delivered him alive <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(b.</hi> c. 105) into the hands of Sylla. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Jugurtha.)</hi> It was this circumstance which laid the
                    foundation of that violent and implacable quarrel which almost ruined the
                    empire. Rome was at this time threatened by an invasion from the Cimbri and
                    Teutones, a northern people who, having issued from their woods in Germany, had
                    overrun the whole of Gaul. The Romans were in the utmost consternation, and no
                    one seemed more able to protect them against these barbarians than Marius.
                    Though absent, he was elected consul a second time, B. c. 104, and received
                    orders to return home with his army. On his arrival he obtained the honours of a
                    triumph, and then devoted himself to the discipline of the levies which he
                    raised. The barbarians, however, passed into Spain, and during the whole of this
                    year Italy had a respite from her enemies. Marius was continued in the
                    consulship, B. c. 103, and was elected the fourth time, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.</hi> c. 102, when the barbarians, with an innumerable army, approached the
                    northern frontiers of Italy. Marius, hearing of the enemy’s approach, hastened
                    across the Alps, and pitched his camp near the mouth of the Rhone. The camp was.
                    fortified and well provisioned; and, that it might communicate with the sea, he
                    employed his men in making a cut or canal capable of receiving ships of
                    considerable burden. This canal of Marius has been long filled up, and is now
                    known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Le bras mort.</hi> The Teutones and
                    Am-broncs were the part of the barbarian army opposed to Marius. The Cimbri had
                    gone in the direction of the Tyrol to attack Catulus. The Teutones found the
                    camp of Marius too strong to be taken; and as their numbers soon caused a
                    scarcity of provisions, they determined to proceed into Italy. Marius, however,
                    hung upon their rear; and finding a favourable opportunity to attack them near
                    Aquae Sestiae (now <hi rend="italic">Aix,</hi> in Provence), he completely
                    defeated them, and in memory of his success erected a pyramid, the remains of
                    which are still to be seen near Saint Maximin. Whilst he was sacrificing in
                    honour of this victory, he received intelligence that he had been elected fifth
                    time consul, <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. 101.</p>
                <p>Marius returned to Rome, where he was offered a triumph, which he declined. He
                    then proceeded to the assistance of his late colleague Catulus, who was guarding
                    the north of Italy against the Cimbri. His arrival gave confidence to Catulus;
                    and as soon as the army from Gaul arrived, they crossed the Po to check the
                    barbarians who were ravaging the country on the opposite side. The Cimbri
                    deferred the combat till the arrival of the Teutones, whom they were unwilling
                    to believe to have been destroyed; and in the meanwhile sent to demand lands and
                    cities from Marius, which should be sufficient for themselves and brethren.
                    “Your brethren,” said Marius, “have land enough which we have already given
                    them, and they shall have it for ever.” A decisive battle was fought a short
                    time afterwards (30th July) in the plain of Vercellae; and though the victory
                    was almost wholly due to the bravery and good conduct of Catulus, Marius carried
                    off all the honour, and was named the third founder of Rome. The survivors of
                    the Cimbri are said to have fled to the mountains of Verona, to the district
                    called <hi rend="italic">Les Sept Communes,</hi> and their descendants are
                    supposed still to be found there. (See Marco Pezzo on this people, and their
                    peculiar dialect, Verona, 1763.) Marius then returned to Rome, where he <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194203072?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0714-3072-0250"/>
                    enjoyed the honour of a triumph, along with his colleague Catulus. He then began
                    to exert all his influence to get himself re-elected to the consulship, and he
                    omitted no means, however dishonourable, that might conduce to his success. His
                    rival was his old friend Metellus; and he carried matters so far that Metellus
                    was obliged to go into voluntary banishment. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Metellus.)</hi> Marius succeeded <hi rend="smallcaps">(b. c.</hi> 100) for the
                    sixth time, and now tried to regain the good will of the nobility; but in this
                    attempt he was so little successful, that he refused to stand candidate for the
                    censorship, lest he should suffer a repulse. Metellus was recalled next year,
                    and, that he might not witness his triumphant entrance, Marius left Rome for the
                    East, under the pretence of performing some vow to the mother of the gods. There
                    he tried to excite Mithridates against his country, thinking that he was certain
                    of a return to power if war should arise. For ten years, however, Marius was
                    disconnected with public affairs; but when the Marsian or Social War broke out
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(b. c.</hi> 90), he was appointed to the command. Age,
                    however, had quenched his martial ardour, and his reputation suffered as much as
                    that of Sylla increased. When the Social War had been concluded, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 88, the Romans saw that they must commence the
                    contest with Mithridates. The enmity of Marius and Sylla now broke out in open
                    war, as they were both anxious to be appointed to the command. Sylla was
                    supported by the senate, but Marius excited a sedition through the tribune
                    Sulpitius, and received the appointment. Sylla was already at some distance from
                    Rome, at the head of an army strongly attached to him; and when he received
                    orders to give up the command of the troops, he marched back to Rome, when
                    Marius was forced to fly for his life. Proceeding to Ostia, Marius embarked on
                    board a small vessel which was ready to sail for Africa; but contrary winds
                    obliged him to land at Minturnae, a small town situated at the mouth of the
                    Liris, now <hi rend="italic">Garigliano,</hi> where he was abandoned by the
                    sailors. His enemies came in pursuit of him, and he was obliged to conceal
                    himself in a bog amidst mud and reeds. Here he was discovered and carried to
                    Minturnae, where the magistrates resolved to put him to death; but they could
                    find no citizen willing to undertake the office of executioner. At last a Gaul
                    or Cimbrian is said to have offered his services, but he was so struck with the
                    noble and majestic appearance of Marius, that when the general exclaimed, “Dost
                    thou dare to kill Marius?’’ he threw down his sword and fled. The people of
                    Minturnae then persuaded their magistrates to banish him, and a vessel was found
                    to bear him from his country. He proceeded to OEnaria, now <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ischia,</hi> and thence to Africa. He landed at Carthage; and whilst he was
                    seated there, a messenger came from the governor Sextilius, with an order
                    that.he should leave the province. “Go and tell him,” said the unfortunate man
                    with a sigh, “that you have seen the exiled Marius sitting on the ruins of
                    Carthage.” Marius proceeded to Cercina, a small island not far from the
                    continent, and here received intelligence that the consuls Cinna and Octavius
                    having quarrelled, had had recourse to arms. Marius determined to proceed to the
                    assistance of Cinna, who had been driven by his colleague from Rome; and,
                    landing with a considerable body of exiles, he soon changed the face of affairs,
                    and reinstated Cinna in his office. He himself refused to enter Rome till the
                    decree of his banishment was repealed. This affected deference to the laws of
                    his country was soon laid aside, and the streets of Rome flowed with the blood
                    of the best of her citizens. No age, no sex, no rank, was spared by the
                    executioners of Marius. In the midst of these excesses intelligence was brought
                    from the East that Sylla had put an end to the Mithridatic war, and was
                    returning home with a large army. Marius was elected consul for the seventh
                    time, <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. 86; but his age and infirmities rendered
                    him little able to sustain the weight of public affairs. He became alarmed at
                    the approach of war, and tried to banish his cares by indulging in excessive
                    drinking. This hastened his end, and he died on the seventeenth day of his
                    seventh consulship, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 86, at the age of seventy.
                    The life of Marius has been written by Plutarch; that by Rutilius Rufus has been
                    lost. An account of the proscriptions of Marius may be found in Appian.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
