<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0157-0142-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ADAMS, John Quincy (9th edition, volume 1, page
                    142)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806713">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205150">Florida</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205805">Cuba</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br3k">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n157/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ADAMS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Quincy</hi></label>, eldest
                    son of the preceding, was born at Braintree on the 11th July 1767. The greater
                    part of his education was received in Europe, which he visited in company with
                    his father in 1778, and again in 1780, when he attended for a time the
                    university of Leyden. When only fifteen years old he went, as secretary, with
                    Francis Dana on his unsuccessful mission to St Petersburg. Returning home after
                    an interval spent in Holland, London, and Paris, he graduated at Harvard in
                    1788; and, after spending three years in a lawyer’s office, was admitted to the
                    bar in 1791. Three successive series of letters, on political subjects,
                    contributed to a Boston newspaper, attracted much attention, and Washington
                    appointed him ambassador to the Hague in 1794. An appointment to a similar post
                    in Portugal, made just before the expiry of Washington’s presidency, was set
                    aside by his father, who sent him instead to Prussia, giving him the promotion
                    by the express advice of Washington. During his residence as ambassador at
                    Berlin, he succeeded in negotiating a commercial treaty with Prussia. On
                    Jefferson becoming President (1801), Adams was recalled, and resumed the
                    practice of law in Boston. In 1802 Suffolk county returned him a member of the
                    Massachusetts Senate, and in the following year he was elected to Congress.
                    Indebted for his position to the Federal party, Adams supported their views for
                    four years, but separated from them by voting for Jefferson’s proposed <hi
                    rend="italic">embargo.</hi> This course involved him in much controversy, and
                    cost him his seat in the Senate. During his retirement he added to the
                    employment arising from his profession the duties of the professorship of
                    rhetoric and belles lettres at Harvard University, which he held for three years
                    (1806-9). His lectures—the first ever read in an American university—were
                    published in 1810, and were much thought of at the time, though now almost
                    forgotten. In the winter following the resignation of his professorship, he
                    visited Washington; and, in an interview with Jefferson, brought a charge
                    against some of the Federal leaders of a design to dissolve the union, and form
                    a separate confederation for the north. The charge was afterwards repeated in
                    the newspapers; and, though resting on slender grounds, greatly affected the
                    confidence of the other states in the New England representatives. In 1809
                    Madison, having obtained after some delay the concurrence of the Senate,
                    entrusted Adams with the embassy to St Petersburg,—an appointment which the
                    latter accepted against the wishes of his father, and continued to hold, though
                    offered a seat on the judicial bench of New England some time after his arrival
                    in Russia. When war broke out between England and the United States, Adams
                    induced the Czar to make an offer of intervention, which, however, the English
                    Government declined to accept. Independent negotiations were thereupon carried
                    on for six months at Ghent (the representatives of America being Adams, Russell,
                    and Clay), and resulted in the treaty of peace which was signed 24th December
                    1814. After serving for two years (1815-17) as minister in London, he again
                    entered the arena of home politics as secretary of state under Monroe. In this
                    office he distinguished himself specially by his arrangement of the treaty with
                    Spain, which defined the boundaries of the ceded territories of Florida and
                    Louisiana. An elaborate report on weights and measures gained for him also a
                    name for scientific acquirements. In 1825 the election of a President fell,
                    according to the constitution of the States, to the House of Representatives,
                    since no one of the candidates had secured an absolute majority of the electors
                    chosen by the States, and Adams, who had stood second to Jackson in the
                    electoral vote, was chosen in preference to Jackson, Clay, and Crawford. The
                    administration of Adams was marked by the imposition of a high tariff on foreign
                    goods, with the view of promoting internal industry, and by the unsuccessful
                    attempt to purchase Cuba from Spain. Notwithstanding the efforts of Clay, and
                    the special claim he himself made on the voters of Virginia on account of his
                    discovery of the so-called New England “plot" twenty years before, Adams failed
                    to secure his re-election in 1829. Defeated by Jackson, who had 178 votes to his
                    83, he retired o Quincy, where his father’s fortune, increased by his own
                    efforts, afforded <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n158/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0158-0143"/> him an ample competency. Two years later he was
                    returned to Congress by the district in which he lived, and which he continued
                    to represent until his death. Having been chosen merely on account of his
                    determined resistance to secret societies, his position was independent of party
                    politics, and correspondingly strong. He stood for the office of governor, and
                    then for that of senator, of Massachusetts, but was on both occasions defeated
                    by Davis. As chairman of the committee on manufactures, he strove to devise a
                    middle policy in regard to tariffs, but his greatest effort at this
                    period—perhaps the greatest service of his whole political life—was in
                    connection with the abolition of slavery. In every form which the question took,
                    he was the bold and determined advocate of abolition, gradually gathering an
                    influential party around him, and so preparing for the triumphs, most of which
                    have been won since his death. He himself witnessed, in 1845, the abolition of
                    the “gag-rule,” restricting the right of petition to Congress on the subject of
                    slavery, which he had persistently opposed during the nine years it was in
                    force. He died of paralysis on 23d February 1848, having been seized two days
                    previously while attending the debates of Congress. Adams wrote a number of
                    works, which are now of little importance. The style is fluent, but has none of
                    the vigour and elegance of his father’s. During his whole lifetime he kept a
                    very voluminous journal, some portions of which have been published.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
