<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0226-0209-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AESIR (9th edition, volume 1, page 209)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885243">Cupping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103425">Sagas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r13x">Cupping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sf0p">Sagas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4959cc6w">Eddas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jm0g">Evil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n226/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AESIR</label> (plural of <hi rend="italic">As,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Ass,</hi> god), the gods of the Northmen of Scandinavia and
                    Iceland. There were twelve chief gods or Aesir besides Odin (the <hi
                    rend="italic">All-fađir,</hi> Allfather), viz., Thor, Baldur, Niörd, Frey, Tŷ or
                    Tŷr, Bragi, Heimdal, Höd, Vidar, Ull, Forsetti, Loki or Lopt. The chief
                    goddesses of <hi rend="smallcaps">Asgard</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> the
                    Odinic Olympus, were—Frigg, Freyia, Nanna, Sif, Saga, Hel, Gefion, Eir, Hlin,
                    Lofn, Vör, Snotra. The names of the Aesir, considered in the primary old
                    northern significance of the words, convey in most instances an allusion to
                    their characteristics; but it is impossible to decide whether they merely
                    personify certain physical powers in nature, and abstract ideas of definite
                    mental conditions, or whether they were originally borne by individuals
                    connected with the pre-historic ages of the people. It is probable that the
                    ideas underlying the myths connected with the Aesir have a mixed origin, and may
                    be referred to a blending of physical, material, and historical elements. Our
                    knowledge of northern mythology has been derived principally <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n227/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0227-0210"/> from the fragmentary remains of ancient
                    Scandinavian songs, first collected in Iceland in the 11th century, and embodied
                    in the 13th century with numerous other prose and poetic myths in a compilation
                    now known to us as the <hi rend="italic">Eddas.</hi> From these highly
                    interesting but frequently obscure sources we are able to reproduce to a certain
                    extent the image and conception of each of the Aesir, as they presented
                    themselves to the imagination of their early northern worshippers.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Thor,</hi> who seems to have been a god of that earlier
                    Phoenician form of nature-worship which was superseded in Scandinavia and
                    Northern Germany by the faith of Odin, we have the impersonation of the
                    disturbing and destructive agencies in the universe. He is the son of heaven and
                    earth—of Odin, the All-father, and of Frigg or Fiörgvin, the vivifying—and is
                    the strongest of the Aesir. From his hammer flashed the lightning, and his
                    chariot wheels sent thunder rolling through the clouds as he went on his way,
                    cleaving mountains, loosening the pent-up streams and fires, and slaying all
                    giants and misshapen monsters. Ever busily engaged in these labours, he seldom
                    tarried in Asgard with the other Aesir, but dwelt in his mansion, Bilskirnir, in
                    the densest gloom of the clouds. With his mallet he consecrated the
                    newly-wedded, and hence the sign of the mallet or hammer was made by the
                    Northmen when they took an oath and bound themselves by vows, whether of
                    marriage or any other obligation. The early Christian missionaries of Norway,
                    finding the faith in Thor too strong to be suddenly uprooted, tried to transfer
                    many of his characteristics to their zealous royal convert, St Olaf, who was
                    said to have resembled the old northern god in his comeliness of person, his
                    bright red beard, hot, angry temper, and personal strength; while some of the
                    monks of a later period endeavoured to persuade the Northmen that in Thor their
                    forefathers had worshipped the Christ, the strong and mighty Saviour of the
                    oppressed, and that his mallet was the rude image of the cross. Slaves and all
                    thralls killed in battle were believed to be under the protection of Thor, who,
                    as god of the Finns before the spread of the As religion, was honoured as their
                    special guardian against the tyranny of their new masters.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Baldur</hi> the Northmen honoured all that was beautiful,
                    eloquent, wise, and good, and he was the spirit of activity, joy, and fight; but
                    his name signifies the strong in mind, and the earliest conception of Baldur is
                    that of mental rather than physical or material perfection. His wife, Nanna,
                    reflected these attributes in a less degree. On his life depended the activity
                    and happiness of all the Aesir, excepting only Loki, the earthly fire or
                    incarnation of evil, and hence this As, from envy of the beauty and innocence of
                    Baldur, brought about his death, and hindered his release from the power of Hel,
                    the goddess of death.</p>
                <p>According to the myth, the Aesir, distressed at Baldur’s presenti∙ ment of his
                    own approaching end, joined his mother, Frigg, in exacting an oath from animals,
                    plants, and minerals, not to injure him. The mistletoe alone among plants had
                    been forgotten, and when this was discovered by Loki he pulled a wand of it, and
                    hastening to the assembly of the Aesir, where all were engaged in the sport of
                    shooting at Baldur, as he was supposed to be invulnerable, he gave it to Höd,
                    the blind god of brute strength, and directed him how to aim it. The mistletoe
                    pierced Baldur through, and he fell dead to the ground in the presence of the
                    Aesir, who, foreseeing the evil that would befall them, since light and purity
                    had been taken from them, gave way to sorrow and fear. When all their efforts to
                    release Baldur from Hel had been thwarted by the machinations cf Loki, they
                    resolved to avenge themselves. Having captured their foe, they confined him
                    within a mountaincave, and hung above his head a venomous snake, to drop its
                    poison on his face; but his wife, Sigyn, stood by him, and caught the drops in a
                    cup, and ft was only while she emptied the goblet that the venom touched him,
                    when he shrank aside, and caused the earth to bc shaken as with an earthquake.
                    There Loki will remain till Ragnaröck, the twilight of the world, when the
                    Aesir, the earth. and all dwellers therein, will be destroyed by the powers of
                    evil, the rescuers and companions of Loki. Only Odin, the All-father, will
                    survive, and gather around him on Ida’s plain, where Asgard had once stood, the
                    Aesir, regenerate and purified by Surt’s black fire, and then a new and better
                    world will arise, in which Baldur will again come with his unconscious slayer,
                    Hod, and all evil will cease, and light and darkness will dwell together in
                    unity.</p>
                <p>Under one form of the myth of Baldur’s death he is the bright god of day or
                    summer, and Höd, the blind and the strong, is dark night or fiercely-raging
                    winter, his preordained foe and destroyer. After that final purification by
                    suffering or fire, and the regeneration to which the Northmen looked as the
                    means of the ultimate adjustment of the disturbed balance between evil and good,
                    and from which they did not exempt their gods, the influence of good was to
                    prevail. Baldur would reappear, and Loki, the consuming power of evil, be no
                    more heard of.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Loki,</hi> in the beginning of time, under the name of Lodthur,
                    flame, and as the foster-brother of the All-father, had united with him in
                    imparting blessings to the universe, and had given blood and a fair colour to
                    Ask and Embla, from which the first men were created. Afterwards he left the
                    council of the Aesir, and like a fallen angel wandered away into regions of
                    space, desolating and consuming all things that came in contact with his fierce
                    flame. Descending into the bowels of the earth, where his presence is made
                    manifest by volcanic fires, he consorted with evil giantesses, by whom he became
                    the father of Hel, pallid death; of Augurboda, the announcer of sorrow; and of
                    the wolf Fenrir, and the serpent of Midgard, which are ever threatening the
                    destruction of the world and the peace of the Aesir.</p>
                <p>Loki can assume all fonns. As sensuality he courses through the veins of men, and
                    as heat and fire he pervades nature, causing death and destruction. After the
                    introduction of Christianity, the attributes and mystic deeds of Loki were
                    transferred to Satan by the people of Scandinavia, amongst whose descendants his
                    name still retains its evil reputation. In Iceland an <hi rend="italic">ignis
                    fatuus</hi> is known as Loki’s burning; and in Jutland, when there is a dazzling
                    light or a waving motion in the air which impedes the sight of distant objects,
                    the peasants say, “Loki is <hi rend="italic">sowing his oats.”</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Niörd,</hi> supposed to be the Nerthus known to the Romans, and
                    his children Frey or Fricco and Freyia, appear to have been honoured in the
                    north before the time of Odin, and to have been worshipped by peoples powerful
                    enough to have been admitted into friendly alliance with his followers. Niörd is
                    said to have lived in Vanaheim, and to have ruled over the Vanir, or light
                    elves, long before he became one of the Aesir. He is god of the ocean, the ruler
                    of winds and stiller of waves, and to him the seafarer and fisherman raise
                    altars and make prayers. His attributes and powers seem to point to the
                    existence of a superior knowledge of navigation among those ancient races of
                    Scandinavia who have been idealised in the imagination of the Northmen as good,
                    bright, and agile elves and water-sprites—the <hi rend="italic">Lios Alfar—</hi>
                    or Vanir of their mythology. Niörd’s son <hi rend="italic">Frey</hi> is the god
                    of rain, plenty, and fruitfulness; and his worship, according to the early
                    northern chronicler, Adam of Bremen, was accompanied with phallic rites. His
                    sister and wife, Freyia, who holds a high place among the Aesir, is the goddess
                    of love; but her influence, unlike her husband’s, is not always beneficent, and
                    varies with the form which she assumes in operating on the minds of men. Her
                    chariot is drawn by cats, as emblematic of fondness and passion, and a hog
                    attends upon her and upon Frey, whose name, like her own, implies fructification
                    or enjoyment.</p>
                <p>The Swedes paid especial honour to Frey, while the Norwegians worshipped Thor
                    (who was in all respects his opposite) as their chief As. The latter must also
                    have received divine honours amongst the Germans, as his name is included in the
                    form of objurgation used by the early Saxon missionaries; but this fact and the
                    German name of the fifth day of the week—Donners-tag, the Thunderer’s day—are
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n228/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0228-0211"/> the only evidences still extant of the early
                    worship of Thor in Germany.</p>
                <p>By their alliance with Niörd and his children the Aesir secured fertility to the
                    earth and mankind, and the intervention of mild gentle agencies in nature to
                    counteract the destructive influence of Thor’s power.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Tŷ</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tŷr</hi> we have the Mars of
                    the Northmen. It is he who gives victory, and although he is as wise as he is
                    brave, it is he who stirs men to strife, and not to peace. His name, which
                    signifies honour, is found in the names of the days of the week in O. Nor.,
                    Dan., A.-S., and in our own “Tuesday;” and shows that, like Thor and Frey or
                    Freyia, whose memory is perpetuated in our Thursday and Friday, the worship of
                    this bravest of the Aesir was widely spread among peoples of Northern
                    origin.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Bragi</hi> the Northmen honoured the originator of their
                    Skaldic poetry, the god of eloquence and wise utterances. At guilds and at
                    grave-feasts the Bragi-cup was drunk; and at the funeral of kings or jarls the
                    heir was not permitted to take his father’s seat till the “Bragarfull” was
                    brought in, when, rising to receive it, he drank the contents of the cup, and
                    was led to the high seat of honour. At guild feasts the Bragi-cup was signed
                    with Thor’s mallet, and was drunk after the company had drained Odin’s cup for
                    victory, and Niörd’s and Frey’s cup for a bountiful year.</p>
                <p>The peculiarity of Bragi’s cup was that, on drinking it, a vow —held to be
                    inviolable—was made to perform some deed worthy of a skald’s song. Bragi’s wife,
                    Idun, as the guardian of the casket which contained apples that gave to those
                    who ate them perpetual youth, was specially cherished by the other Aesir. In her
                    abduction by the giant Thiassi, and her removal to the nether world through
                    Loki’s craft, her mute grief, and her release in the spring, we have an analogy
                    with the myth of Proserpine; and like her she presides over fresh verdure.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Heimdal,</hi> whose attribute is the rainbow, is the god of
                    watchfulness, the doorkeeper of the Aesir; while <hi rend="italic">Vidar,</hi>
                    the strongest of the gods after Thor, is the impersonation of silence and
                    caution; <hi rend="italic">Ull</hi> decides the issue of single combats, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Farsetti</hi> settles all quarrels.</p>
                <p>In the goddesses <hi rend="italic">Lofn</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vör</hi>
                    lovers find protectors; the former unites the faithful, the latter punishes the
                    faithless. <hi rend="italic">Gefion,</hi> to whom the Danes owe the formation of
                    the island Seeland, watches over maidens, and knows the decrees of fate. <hi
                    rend="italic">Hlin</hi> guards those whom <hi rend="italic">Frigg,</hi> the
                    queen and mother of heaven, is desirous of freeing from peril; Frigg herself, as
                    Odin’s wife and the mother of the Aesir, knows the destinies of men, but is
                    silent in regard to them. As goddess of the earth, she is known as Frygga, the
                    fertile summer earth, and Rinda the frost-hardened surface, and is attended by
                    <hi rend="italic">Fulla,</hi> the full, <hi rend="italic">Fir,</hi> the young
                    goddess of healing, and many other goddesses.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Saga,</hi> whose name is derived from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Segja,</hi> to narrate, is the goddess of history and narration. Odin and she
                    pledge each other daily in golden cups filled from the copious ever-flowing
                    streams of her abode, <hi rend="italic">Sockquαbek</hi> (from Sökk, abyss, in
                    allusion to the abundant streams of narrative). <hi rend="italic">Snοtra</hi> is
                    the goddess of sagacity and elegance, from whom men and women seek good sense
                    and refinement of manners. The Norns and the Valkyriur, if not actually
                    goddesses, are closely connected with the Aesir. The three principal Norns or
                    Nornir are Urd, past time; Verdandi, present time; and Skulld, future time. They
                    and the Valkyriur, who are known under many names, twist and spin the threads of
                    destiny, and make known what has been decreed from the beginning of time.</p>
                <p>From this brief outline it may be seen that in their Aesir the Northmen
                    recognised the creators, sustainers, and regulators of the world as it now is,
                    from whom emanated the thought and life that pervade and animate all nature, and
                    the efforts to subject it to the spiritual will. With Odin and the Aesir the
                    intellectual life of the northern people began; and although they ascribed to
                    them human forms and acts, these were seldom without something higher and nobler
                    than what pertains to mortals; and while they recognised the existence of a
                    state of chaos and darkness before this world began with the creation of the
                    Aesir, they anticipated the advent of another state, in which gods, like men,
                    would receive their award at the hands of a supreme All-father. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(e. c. o.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
