<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0537-0500-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALEXANDRINE VERSE (9th edition, volume 1, page
                    500)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921600">Fashion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131530">Stanzas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hs7q">Fashion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n537/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALEXANDRINE VERSE</label>, a name given to the leading
                    measure in French poetry. It is the heroic French verse, used in epic narrative,
                    in tragedy, and in the higher comedy. There is some doubt as to the origin of
                    the name; but most probably it is derived from a collection of romances,
                    published early in the 13th century, of which Alexander of Macedon was the hero,
                    and in which he was represented, somewhat like our own Arthur, as the pride and
                    crown of chivalry. Before the publication of this work most of the trouvère
                    romances appeared in octo-syllabic verse. The new work, which was henceforth to
                    set the fashion to French literature, was written in lines of twelve syllables,
                    but with a freedom of pause which was afterwards greatly curtailed. The new
                    fashion, however, was not adopted all at once. The metre fell into disuse until
                    the reign of Francis I., when it was revived by Jean Antoine de Boeuf, one of
                    the seven poets known as the Pleiades. It was not he, however, but Ronsard, who
                    made the verse popular, and gave it vogue in France. From his time it became the
                    recognised vehicle for all great poetry, and the regulation of its pauses became
                    more and more strict. The following is an example of the verse as used by
                    Racine—</p>
                <lg>
                    <l> “Où suis-je? qu’ai-je fait? ∥ que dois-je faire encore? </l>
                    <l> Quel transport me saisit? ∥ quel chagrin me dévore ?” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Two inexorable laws carne to be established with regard to the pauses. The first
                    is, that each line should be divided into two equal parts, the sixth syllable
                    always ending with a word. In the earlier use of this metre, on the contrary, it
                    frequently happened that the sixth and seventh syllables belonged to the same
                    word. The other is, that, except under the most stringent conditions, there
                    should be none of what the French critics call <hi rend="italic"
                    >enjambement,</hi> that is, the overlapping of the sense from one line on to the
                    next. Ronsard completely ignored this rule, which was after his time settled by
                    the authority of Malherbe. Such verses as the following by Ronsard would be
                    intolerable in modern French poetry—</p>
                <lg>
                    <l> “Cette nymphe royale est digne qu’on lui dresse </l>
                    <l part="I"> Des autels. . . . </l>
                    <l> Les Parques se disoient: Charles, qui doit venir </l>
                    <l part="I"> Au monde. . . . </l>
                </lg>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n538/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0538-0501"/>
                <lg>
                    <l> Je veux, s’il est possible, atteindre la louague </l>
                    <l part="I"> De celle. . . . </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Michael Drayton, who was twenty-two years of age when Ronsard died, seemed to
                    think that the Alexandrine might be as pleasing to English as it was to French
                    ears, and in this metre he wrote a long poem in twenty-four books called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Polyolbion.</hi> The metre, however, failed to catch the English
                    ear. Our principal measure is a line of ten syllables, and we use the
                    Alexandrine only occasionally to give it variety and weight. In our ordinary
                    heroic verse it is but rarely introduced; but in the favourite narrative metre,
                    known as the Spenserian, it comes in regularly as the concluding line of each
                    stanza. In English usage, moreover, it is to be observed that there is no fixed
                    rule as to the position of the pause, though it is true that most commonly the
                    pause occurs at the end of the sixth syllable. Spenser is very free in shifting
                    the pause about; and though the later poets who have used this stanza are not so
                    free, yet, with the exception of Shenstone and of Byron, they do not scruple to
                    obliterate all pause between the sixth and seventh syllables. Thus Thomson <hi
                    rend="italic">(Castle of Indolence,</hi> i. 42):—</p>
                <l> "And music lent new gladness to the morning air.” </l>
                <p>The danger in the use of the Alexandrine is that, in attempting to give dignity
                    to his line, the poet may only produce heaviness, incurring the sneer of
                    Pope—</p>
                <lg>
                    <l> “A needless Alexandrine ends the song, </l>
                    <l> That, like a wounded snake, drags its slow length along.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">(e. s. d.</hi>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
