<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0636-0599-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALPES (9th edition, volume 1, page 599)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827603">Barley</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215184">Monaco</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19r5m">Bass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n636/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALPES</label>, the name of three departments in the southeast
                    of France,— <hi rend="italic">Basses</hi><hi rend="italic">Alpes, Hautes
                    Alpes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alpes</hi><hi rend="italic">Maritimes.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Basses Alpes</hi> is bounded on the N. by the department of
                    Hautes Alpes; on the E. by the kingdom of Italy and the department of Alpes
                    Maritimes; on the S. by the departments of Var and Bouches du Rhone; and on the
                    ,W. by those of Vaucluse and Drôme. It extends at the widest points 90 miles
                    from N.E. to S.W., and 70 from E. to W., and contains an area of 2680 square
                    miles. Its surface is mountainous, especially on the north-east, where offshoots
                    of the Maritime Alps penetrate into the country, rising near the river Ubaye to
                    an elevation of over 9000 feet above the level of the sea. With the exception of
                    the south-eastern corner, which is drained by the Var, the whole department is
                    in the basin of the Durance, which for a considerable distance separates Basses
                    from Hautes Alpes, but eventually strikes southward through the former. Its
                    chief tributaries are the Buech and the Jabron on the right, and the Ubaye, the
                    Bléone, the Asse, and the Verdon on the left. The climate in the mountainous
                    districts of the north is cold and variable. The soil there is poor, but it is
                    cultivated with great industry — producing rye, oats, barley, potatoes, and
                    timber. In the south and south-west, however, where the country is comparatively
                    flat, the temperature is milder and the soil more fertile; here plums, almonds,
                    apricots, peaches, and other fruits are produced in large quantities, as well as
                    wine of an excellent description, chiefly for home consumption. Considerable
                    numbers of cattle, sheep, goats, and pigs are reared in the Basses Alpes,
                    besides which many flocks of sheep, from Var and Bouches du Rhone, are pastured
                    during summer in the upper valleys of the department. Game is abundant. There
                    are mines of lead and other metals of some value. The manufactures are few and
                    of little importance, the chief being leather, coarse woollen cloths, cutlery,
                    earthenware, and paper. Basses Alpes, one of the departments formed out of
                    ancient Provence, is divided into five arrondissements—Digne, in the centre;
                    Barcelonnette and Castellane, on the east; Sisteron and Forcalquier on the west;
                    which together contain 30 cantons and 251 communes. Digne is the capital and the
                    seat of a bishop, whose diocese is co-extensive with the department; and among
                    the other towns are Barcelonnette, Castellane, Sisteron, Forcalquier, and
                    Manosque. Population (1871), 139,332.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hautes Alpes</hi> is bounded on the N. by the departments of
                    Isère and Savoir; on the E. by the kingdom of Italy; on the S. by the department
                    of Alpes Basses; and on the W. by that of Drôme. It extends nearly 80 miles from
                    N.E. to S.W., and contains an area of 2158 square miles. Its surface is very
                    mountainous, being traversed in all directions by the Cottian and Dauphiné Alps,
                    which, in Mont Pelvoux and other peaks, rise to an elevation of about 13,000
                    feet above the sea, the highest summits in France. The Drac, flowing northwards
                    into the Isère, and the Durance, with its tributaries the Guil and the Buech,
                    are the chief rivers of Hautes Alpes. The climate is cold in winter, and in
                    summer variable; the soil is barren, yielding only oats, barley, potatoes, rye,
                    and timber, except in a few favoured valleys, where wine of a fair quality and
                    fruits of various kinds are produced. Large numbers of sheep and other domestic
                    animals are reared or pastured in the department. Game, both large and small, is
                    found in great abundance. The mines produce lead, copper, iron, and other
                    metals. There are no manufactures of any commercial importance, although some
                    leather, coarse woollen cloth, hats, woodwork, and iron wares are made. Hautes
                    Alpes, a part of the old province of Dauphiné, is divided into three
                    arrondissements: Gap on the west, Embrun on the south-east, and Briançon on the
                    north-east, with 24 cantons and 89 communes. The capital is Gap, the seat of the
                    bishop; Embrun and Briançon being the only other towns of any size. Population,
                    118,898.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alpes</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Maritimes,</hi> bounded on
                    the N. by Basses Alpes and the kingdom of Italy, which also forms its boundary
                    on the E.; on the S. by the Mediterranean Sea; and on the W. by Var and Basses
                    Alpes. It extends at the widest points 55 miles from N. to S., and 50 from E. to
                    W.; and contains an area of 1517 square miles. The surface of this department,
                    like that of the two former, is more or less mountainous, branches of the
                    Maritimes Alpes covering the greater part of the territory. It is watered by the
                    Roya, the Paillon, the Var (with its tributaries the Tinéa and the Esteron), the
                    Loup, and the Siagne. The climate is on the whole warm and gentle, except among
                    the higher mountains; while the mildness of the temperature along the shores of
                    the Mediterranean has made that portion of the department a favourite resort for
                    invalids. The upper valleys and mountain slopes are chiefly devoted to pasture
                    for sheep, being ill-suited for cultivation, although a little barley and maize
                    is grown; the richer districts of the south produce fruits of various kinds,
                    tobacco, honey, and flowers, used in the making of perfumes. The other
                    manufactures are of dried fruits, olive-oil, preserved anchovies and sardines,
                    silk, soap, and paper. Alpes Maritimes is divided into three
                    arrondissements—Grasse and Nice on the south, and Puget Théniers on the north,
                    containing 25 cantons and 146 communes. The arrondissements of Nice and Puget
                    Théniers constitute the bishopric of Nice; Grasse belongs to that of Fréjus.
                    Nice is the capital; and among the other towns are Mentone, Villafranche,
                    Grasse, Antibes, Cannes, and Puget Théniers. The Marseilles, Nice, and
                    Ventimille railway, skirting the coast, connects Cannes, Antibes, Nice, and
                    Mentone, and joins an Italian line which affords direct railway communication
                    with Genoa. The department of Alpes Maritimes was formed in 1860 from the
                    territory of Nice, which had been ceded to France, together with Mentone and
                    Roccabruna, purchased from the Prince of Monaco, and the arrondissement of
                    Grasse, transferred from Var. It had a population of 119,037 in 1871.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
