<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0787-0744-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMMUNITION (9th edition, volume 1, page 744)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hb3d">Boxers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc86">Bullets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02z952">Cannon</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1074177">Powders</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841495">Bullets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010895">Martinis</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n787/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMMUNITION</label> in its general sense comprises not only
                    the powder and projectiles employed in guns of all classes, but also all stores
                    directly connected with artillery fire, such as friction-tubes, fuses,
                    percussion-caps, and rockets.</p>
                <p>Gunpowder, as manufactured in England, consists of 75 parts of saltpetre, 15
                    parts of charcoal, and 10 parts of sulphur, reduced to a fine powder and
                    mechanically mixed together, pressed into a cake, and granulated to a size
                    varying according to the purpose which it is designed to fulfil. In cannon, a
                    large grain is necessary for regular and thorough burning, a fine powder choking
                    up the interstices, and so preventing the flame from finding its way through the
                    entire charge. On the other hand, a large grain is blown out of a small piece
                    before it is burnt to the centre. For the very heavy guns recently introduced
                    into the British service powder formed into “pellets” or “pebbles” has been
                    adopted, by which the pressure of the gas is kept up till the shell leaves the
                    muzzle, without being at any instant excessive and likely to injure the gun.
                    Modified forms of powder and gun-cotton have been employed experimentally as the
                    charges of guns.</p>
                <p>For heavy guns or cannon the charge is carefully weighed and made up in a serge
                    cartridge sewn with worsted, which entirely consumes in firing—any residue left
                    ignited in the bore being liable to cause explosion when the cartridge of the
                    succeeding round is rammed down on it, and so to blow off the arms of the gunner
                    using the sponge stave. The shell or other projectile employed is forced home on
                    the cartridge <hi rend="italic">{vide</hi> fig. 1) in muzzle-loading guns. In
                    breech-loaders the shell is introduced first, and pressed into the shot chamber,
                    beyond which it can only pass by the “lands” of the rifling cutting into the
                    lead coat, which is effected by the explosion of the charge. The cartridge is
                    pressed forward against the base of the projectile.</p>
                <p>Rifled guns—that is, guns constructed to impart rotation to the projectiles they
                    discharge—have superseded smooth-bored cannon in the armaments of all civilised
                    nations; elongated projectiles, which are impeded by the resistance of the air
                    much less than spherical ones, being in all cases employed. Fig. 1 shows a
                    section of the bore of the muzzle-loading gun, whose projectiles are made to
                    rotate by means of gun-metal studs which fit in the spiral grooves of the bore.
                    The following kinds of projectiles are fired from rifled cannon in the British
                    service :—Common shell, Shrapnel shell, Palliser shell and shot, and case-shot.
                    Light balls, carcasses, and spherical shells are discharged from smooth-bored
                    mortars. The two last mentioned, as well as spherical Shrapnel, round shot,
                    grape, and case, are fired from smooth-bored guns.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Common shell</hi> for rifled guns are simply hollow elongated
                    projectiles filled with powder, which is fired by the action of a fuse, and
                    bursts the shell with great violence, acting in walls or earth into which it has
                    penetrated like a small mine, the largest shells, which are twelve inches in
                    diameter, containing nearly 37 lb of powder. Gun cotton, nitroglycerine, and
                    other substances, have been tried for bursting purposes, but it has been found
                    very difficult to prevent premature explosion from the sudden shock of discharge
                    of the gun. Picrate of potash, or “picric powder,” has been recommended as
                    stronger than gunpowder and quite cafe, but it is not as yet adopted. Common
                    shells are generally fired at earthworks, buildings, and wooden ships. When
                    carried, as in English men-of-war, filled and fused with percussion fuses, they
                    can be discharged as rapidly as shot. The most terrible instance of their use in
                    history is the entire destruction of the Turkish frigates by the Russian fleet
                    at Sinope on November 30th, 1853. At the battle of Sedan in 1870 the Prussians
                    made such havoc among the crowded French troops that the ground became covered
                    with “heaps of flesh and rags ;” and a similar result was produced by the fire
                    of mortars concentrated on the Russian troops in the Redan at the termination of
                    the siege of Sebastopol. The slaughter in the two last named instances is,
                    however, to be attributed to the concentration of fire on masses of men rather
                    than to the description of shell used, for the showers of bullets ejected by
                    Shrapnel shell would have struck many more men, although the ghastly spectacle
                    of dismembered human bodies would not have been exhibited.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Shrapnel shell</hi> are hollow projectiles containing bullets
                    and a very small bursting charge. Fig. 2 exhibits the construction of the Boxer
                    Shrapnel shell for the 40-pounder breech-loading Armstrong gun, and is a good
                    specimen of this class of projectile. The shell follows the usual course of
                    flight up to within about 100 yards of the object, when the time fuse, if
                    properly set, fires the bursting charge, and opens the shell by splitting it
                    along certain grooves forming lines of least resistance. The bullets and
                    fragments then continue their course in the form of a shower of missiles. This
                    class of shell was designed for smooth-bore guns by General Shrapnel. It was
                    used with great effect during the Peninsular war, especially in clearing the
                    breach and ramparts of St Sebastian of defenders, over the heads of the English
                    storming party, who drew back into the ditch for a time. The projectile has
                    never been understood and thoroughly taken up by foreign powers, and has never
                    been used to full advantage on service. In skilful hands it is capable of
                    producing results far beyond any that have as yet been achieved.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Armstrong segment shell</hi> fulfills the same general
                    purpose,—that is to say, it is designed to sweep down bodies <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n788/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0788-0745"/> of troops, but it opens rather more suddenly,
                    segments of iron taking the place of lead and antimony bullets, which segments
                    being built up in a ring with the bursting charge in the centre, are dispersed
                    more widely when the shell opens than·the bullets of the Shrapnel. The segment
                    shell consequently is rather suited for the action of a percussion fuse on
                    striking the head of a column of men, or the ground close in front of it. In
                    this way results have been obtained which are out of all proportion to anything
                    that has ever occurred in actual service. At Dartmoor in 1869 the average number
                    of hits for every segment shell fired during the series of experiments,
                    including failures of all kinds, was 17Ί. The meaning of this estimate maybe
                    appreciated by applying it to some action. For example, at Waterloo the English
                    artillery fired 9467 rounds. On the Dartmoor scale this would give 161,885
                    casualties. This result shows that after making the most liberal deductions for
                    the peculiar circumstances of war, appalling effects might be produced by modern
                    artillery with segment or Shrapnel shells.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Palliser shell and shot</hi> are projectiles made with
                    specially hard and rigid heads, with the object of piercing the sides of
                    armour-clad vessels. The form of the head, which is termed “ogival,” is seen
                    inside the gun in Fig. 1. A point of this shape causes the resistance of the
                    plate to fall on the shell as an increasing pressure, acting inwards towards
                    points distributed along the axis, rather than as the full sudden blow that
                    would be experienced by a round shot. This enables <hi rend="italic">chilled
                    iron</hi> to be used, which has great hardness and crushing strength, but is
                    very brittle. Sir W. Palliser first proposed chilled projectiles; subsequently
                    mottled iron projectiles with chilled heads have been used. Sir J. Whitworth has
                    obtained great results with flat-headed projectiles of a special quality of
                    steel, which have been made to penetrate iron plates at an angle even more
                    oblique than 45°. Solid and hollow shot, as well as shell, have been employed
                    against plates. The shot, having thicker sides or walls, have some advantage in
                    penetration. Shells, by their explosion, destroy wood backing better than shot,
                    when the front plating is not too thick for them to penetrate. They are charged
                    with powder through a filling hole in the base of the shell, closed with a
                    strong screw plug. No fuse is required, impact against thick iron being
                    sufficient to explode the bursting charge of a shell without any fuse. The
                    greatest penetration that has yet been obtained in armour was achieved by the
                    35-ton Woolwich gun (termed the Woolwich “infant”), at Shoeburyness on June
                    2Oth, 1872, the head of a Palliser projectile passing entirely through 18∣
                    inches of iron and 12 of teak, a thickness of armour exceeding that of any
                    iron-clad vessel afloat. <hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">Solid shot</hi>
                    have gradually disappeared since the introduction of rifled guns, and the
                    reasons are obvious. A round shot fired from a smooth-bored gun, after its first
                    graze, continued to ricochet in a straight line; it produced, therefore, a
                    considerable moral effect, and on smooth ground was actually formidable. A
                    rifled shot, on the other hand, is violently deflected after each graze, from
                    the fact that it is rotating rapidly as it touches the ground, and this, coupled
                    with its liability to bury itself, detracts greatly from its efficiency. Shells
                    for any rifled gun may be made of such length as .to bring them to the <hi
                    rend="italic">same weight</hi> as the corresponding shot, which was not the case
                    with smoothbore projectiles, they being all of one <hi rend="italic">size</hi>
                    instead of one <hi rend="italic">weight.</hi> In short, Palliser shell with
                    thick walls (fired as hollow shot) excepted, the only projectiles of the shot
                    class now employed with rifled guns are <hi rend="italic">case shot.</hi> Owing,
                    however, to the fact that the charge of a rifled gun varies from ⅜th to I th the
                    weight of the projectile, while in smooth-bored guns it was sometimes as great
                    as ⅜d that of the shot, the effect of rifled case is comparatively weak. At any
                    time the range of case shot hardly exceeds 300 yards, while its efficiency
                    depends on the ground along which it bounds being hard and level. Each shot
                    consists of a number of balls enclosed in a thin metal cylinder, which breaks up
                    in the gun, the balls scattering from the muzzle, but sweeping the ground with
                    great effect under favourable circumstances. <hi rend="italic">Grape</hi>
                    differs only in the balls being larger. At the battle of Friedland, at the
                    bridge of Lodi, and at Sebastopol, grape and case were fired with great
                    effect.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Time and percussion fuses</hi> have been mentioned. <hi
                    rend="italic">Time fuses</hi> are those which open a shell at any given time,
                    whether in the air or during penetration. Fig. 2 shows the “Boxer 9-second fuse”
                    for breech-loading guns, fixed in the shell. On the shell moving, the hammer in
                    the head, by its inertia, shears a copper wire, fires a detonating patch of
                    composition beneath it, and lights the fuse composition. This burns until it
                    reaches the point at which a hole is bored in the fuse, when it flashes down the
                    channel shown on the left side of the cut, and fires the powder primer and
                    bursting charge of loose powder. The action of this fuse therefore depends on
                    its correct boring and regular burning. A <hi rend="italic">percussion fuse</hi>
                    is one that acts on impact or graze. Fig. 3 shows the Pettman general service
                    fuse. On the first movement of the shell, the detonating ball A, and the plugs
                    above and below it, by their inertia, crush the lead cap C, and shear the copper
                    pin above F. During flight the ball becomes detached from the upper or steady
                    plug B, and on impact is fired by its momentum against the part in front of it.
                    Thè steady plug itself has also a ring of detonating composition, DD, which,
                    should the plug fail to escape from the detonating ball, and so hold against it,
                    is thrown against the little plain ball E. The flash in either case acts down
                    the tube F, and fires the bursting charge of the shell. This fuse is made not to
                    explode against a wave, being chiefly used for sea service. It acts both with
                    smooth-bored and rifled guns. For land service more sensitive ones are employed
                    to explode on graze.</p>
                <p>Friction tubes are copper tubes driven with mealed powder, and pierced from end
                    to end. A friction bar in the head is rubbed against patches of detonating
                    composition by pulling a lanyard, which hooks into a loop at the end of it. The
                    tube is entered in the vent of a gun, which is thus fired by pulling the
                    lanyard.</p>
                <p>For mitrailleuses and breech-loading small arms, lead bullets or lead and tin
                    bullets, fixed in central-fire cartridges, are used. The cases are made of sheet
                    brass, with a thick base disc containing a cap chamber, cap, and anvil. Fig. 4
                    shows the Boxer-Henry ammunition for the Martini-Henry rifle. These metal-cased
                    cartridges are not liable to explode in store, even from the firing of a small
                    charge of powder confined inside the same packing-case with them. They admit of
                    a very rapid rate of firing. The Gatling mitrailleuse has discharged 657 rounds
                    in two minutes at Shoeburyness. The Martini-Henry rifle has fired 25 rounds in a
                    minute.</p>
                <p>Rockets are projectiles containing composition which, as it burns, generates
                    sufficient gas to drive forward the rocket by an action resembling that of the
                    recoil of a gun. Of rockets there are three kinds: first, war rockets, with iron
                    cases, introduced by Sir W. Congreve, and subsequently <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0789-0746"/> brought by Mr Hale to the form shown in Fig. <hi
                    rend="italic">5.</hi> Congreve rockets were kept point first by sticks screwed
                    into their bases, which acted on the principle of the feathers of an arrow. The
                    Hale rocket is kept point first by rotation, caused by the gas escaping from the
                    vents pressing against the curved shields. The second class of rockets are
                    signal rockets, made of paper, and containing stars, which throw a bright light
                    in falling. The third class are the rockets used to carry a line and establish
                    communication between a wrecked vessel and the sea-shore. (c. o. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
