<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0258-0241-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AFGHAN TURKESTAN (9th edition, volume 1, page
                    241)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163443">Uzbeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891230">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:798948">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q77g">Desertion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90f3q">Deserts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n258/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AFGHAN TURKESTAN</label> is a convenient name applied of late
                    years to those provinces in the basin of the Oxus which are subject to the Amir
                    of Kabul. <hi rend="smallcaps">Badakhshan</hi> and its dependencies, now
                    tributary to the Amir, are sometimes included under the name, but will not be so
                    included here. The whole of the Afghan dominions consist of <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Afghanistan</hi> as defined under that heading, <hi rend="smallcaps">Afghan
                    Turkestan,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Badakhshan</hi> with its
                    dependencies.</p>
                <p>The territories included here will be, beginning from the east, the khanates or
                    principalities of Kunduz, Khulm, Balkh with Akcha; and the western khanates of
                    Sir-i-pul, Shibrghân, Andkhûi, and Maimana, sometimes classed together as the
                    <hi rend="italic">Chihâr Vilâyat,</hi> or “Four Domains;” and besides these,
                    such part of the Hazara tribes as lie north of the Hindu Kush and its
                    prolongation, defined in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Afghanistan.</hi> The
                    tract thus includes the whole southern moiety of the Oxus basin, from the
                    frontier of Badakhshan on the east to the upper Murghâb river on the west. The
                    Oxus itself forms the northern boundary, from the confluence of the Kokcha or
                    river of Badakhshan, in 69½ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> E. long., to Khoja
                    Salih ferry, in 65° E. long. nearly. Here the boundary quits the river and
                    skirts the Turkman desert to the point where the Murghâb issues upon it. Along
                    the whole southern boundary we have a tract of lofty mountain country. Thus, in
                    the east, above Kunduz, we have the Hindu Kush rising far into the region of
                    perpetual snow, and with passes ranging from 12,000 to 13,000 feet and upwards.
                    Above Khulm and Balkh is the prolongation of Hindu Kush, called Koh-i-baba, in
                    which the elevation of the <hi rend="italic">cols</hi> or passes seems to be
                    nearly as high, though the general height of the crest is lower. The mountains
                    then fork in three branches westward, viz., <hi rend="italic">Koh-i-Siâh,</hi>
                    “The Black Mountain,” to the south of the Herat river; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kohi-Safed, “</hi> The White Mountain,” between the Herat river and the
                    Murghab, and a third ridge north of the latter river. The second branch
                    (Safed-Koh) has been assumed in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Afghanistan</hi> as the boundary of that region. We know almost nothing of
                    these mountains, except from the journey of Ferrier, who crossed all three
                    watersheds in four days of July 1845. He describes the middle range as very
                    lofty, with a good deal of snow on the pass; the southern range not so high, the
                    northern one not nearly so high.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rivers.</hi> —We shall first describe the rivers of this
                    region in succession.</p>
                <p>For the Oxus itself, see that article.</p>
                <p>Beginning from the eastward, its first tributary within our limits is the river
                    of Kunduz, known also as the river of Aksarai, the Surkhab, and what not. As the
                    principal source of this river we may regard the stream of Bamian, fed close
                    under the Koh-i-Baba by a variety of torrents which join from the pass of
                    Akrobat and other gorges of the Hazara country, adjoining that famous site (8496
                    feet above sea level). The names of some of these seem to preserve a tradition
                    of the ancient population; such are the “Cutlers’ Vale,” “the Smiths’ Vale,” the
                    “Valley of Eye-paint.” At the eastern end of the valley the Bamian stream
                    receives another of nearly equal bulk, descending from the pass of Hajjigak, the
                    most important crossing of the mountains between Kabul and the Oxus, and from
                    which the road descends upon Bamian, and thence by Saighân, Khurram, and Haibak,
                    to Khulm, in the Oxus valley. On the volcanic rock which parts the streams stand
                    extensive ruins, the name of which, Zohâk, connects them with the most ancient
                    legends of Persian history.</p>
                <p>From this the river turns nearly north, passing the country of the Sheikh 'Alis,
                    one of the most famous Hazara clans, and closely skirting the great range of
                    Hindu Kush. About 40 miles N.N.E. of Zohak it receives from the left two
                    confluents, of size probably almost equal to its own—the rivers of Saighan and
                    of Kâmard, both rising to the westward of Bamian, and crossing the highway from
                    Bamian to Khulm. Hereabouts the river seems to take the name of Surkhab. The
                    first considerable confluent on the right is the Andarâb river, draining the
                    valley of that name, and joining at Doshi, about 85 miles in a direct line N.E.
                    of Zohak. About Ghori, still a place of some note, the valley widens out
                    greatly, and becomes in places swampy, with expanses of tall grass, a character
                    which it thenceforth retains. The river is, or has been, bridged at Thomri, a
                    few miles beyond Ghori, a work ascribed to Aurangzîb. It then receives from the
                    right the Baghlan river, coming from N ârî n and the hills of Khost. The only
                    remaining confluent is the important one which joins immediately below the town
                    of Kunduz, sometimes called the Khânâbâd river, sometimes by the names of its
                    chief contributaries, the Farokhar and Bangi.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n259/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0259-0242"/>
                <p>The Farokhar, or river of Talik <hi rend="italic"> â </hi> n, is the most
                    easterly, coming out of Badakhshan, the boundary of which runs along the
                    watershed on its left bank. The Bangi flows through Khost from the highlands of
                    Badakhshan, east of Andarab. A third tributary, the Shorâb, salt, as its name
                    implies, drains the high range called Esk-mushk, above Narim</p>
                <p>The Surkhab or Kunduz river enters the Oxus at a point approximately (no
                    traveller has visited the confluence) 32 miles N.W. of Kunduz, its whole length,
                    exclusive of minor windings, being about 220 miles.</p>
                <p>From Ghori downwards, the hills which bound the valley on either side appear to
                    be of no great elevation, and to be tolerably clothed with grass, and
                    occasionally with fir trees; the aspect of the country gradually approximating
                    to that of Badakhshan, in contrast to the more sterile offshoots of Koh-i-Baba
                    to the westward.</p>
                <p>Kunduz itself lies very low, scarcely 500 feet above sea level, and the roads
                    approaching the town have to pass over piles amid the swampy vegetation. The
                    adjacent plain is in the main richly cultivated and thickly peopled, but it is
                    interspersed with extensive tracts of jungly grass, and is extremely and
                    proverbially unhealthy. The plains, which extend, though not unbroken, from
                    Kunduz to the Oxus, are free from the bare and repulsive character of those
                    further west, and are described as covered in part with rich cultivation, thick
                    with groves and hamlets, and in part with splendid pasture.</p>
                <p>Proceeding westward, the next tributary to the Oxus basin is the Khulm river. The
                    traveller from Bamian northward first touches the Khulm river, on descending
                    from the Kara-Kotal, at a spot called Doâb Shâhpasand, probably 5000 feet above
                    the sea, where its two main sources join, and the main road to Turkestan keeps
                    on or near the river till its exit on the Oxus plain. The character of the mass
                    of mountains which extends from the Koh-i-Baba to Khulm is utter rocky aridity,
                    but broken sometimes in the sudden trench-like valleys by an exuberant vigour of
                    vegetation. Along a chain of these trench-like gorges, walled by stupendous
                    cliffs seeming sometimes almost to close overhead, the traveller descends
                    towards Khulm. At Haibak the valley opens out, but closes in again before Khulm
                    is reached. Here he emerges from a narrow gorge upon the plain of the Oxus, some
                    20 miles from the great river, and leaves the mountains suddenly, as one leaves
                    the gate of a fortress, still rising behind in a bold rampart to the height of
                    2500 feet. The river is believed to be spent in irrigation before reaching the
                    Oxus.</p>
                <p>As far north at least as Khurram, half-way from Bamian to Khulm, the offshoots of
                    Koh-i-Baba, west of the Khulm defile, must reach a height of 11,000 or 12,000
                    feet; for here Ferrier found bitter cold and snow on the top on the 7th of July
                    (latitude nearly 36°).</p>
                <p>The next river westward is the Balkh river, sometimes called Deh â s. It rises
                    not far from some of the tributaries of the Surkhab, nor from the sources of the
                    Herat river, at a remarkable spot which, under the name of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Band-i-Barbar,</hi> or Barbar dam, is the subject of various legends, though we
                    have no distinct account of it. The valley of Yekâlang, on the upper waters of
                    this river, at a height of 7000 feet above the sea, was visited by A. Cono11y,
                    and is described by him as fertile, well-watered, and populous, about 15 miles
                    in length by ¼ to ½ mile in width. Ferrier is the only traveller who has crossed
                    the mature stream, and he merely mentions that he forded it, and that it was
                    rather rapid. We thus know almost nothing of the river. In length it cannot come
                    far short of the Surkhab. Beyond the lofty mountains recently spoken of, some of
                    the hills towards the Balkh-ab have a thin clothing of wood, and the valleys
                    opening on the river are wide and not unfertile. The main valley expands into
                    level tracts of pasture, covered by long grass, and intersected by artificial
                    water-courses; but (as with the Khulm river) the gorge from which the stream
                    issues on the Oxus plain is narrow, and walled in by very high hills on either
                    side. The ruins and gardens of ancient Balkh stand about 6 miles from the hills,
                    but no part of the river appears to reach the site in its natural bed, nor does
                    any part of its waters reach the Oxus in a Tunning stream.</p>
                <p>The plains that slope from the gardens of Balkh to the Oxus are naturally white
                    hard steppes, destitute of spontaneous verdure save sparse brush of tamarisk and
                    other meagre growths; but the soil responds richly to irrigation whenever this
                    is bestowed.</p>
                <p>The next stream that we meet with, and the last that can be considered even as an
                    indirect tributary of the Oxus, is that which fertilises the small khanates of
                    Shibrghan and Andkhui, on the verge of the Turkman desert; whilst the two
                    confluents that contribute to form it have previously watered the territories of
                    Siripul and Maimana. The river, or whatever survives of its water after
                    irrigating Andkhui, is lost in the desert. The taste of the water is abominable,
                    and, though the inhabitants are accustomed to it, strangers suffer from its
                    use.</p>
                <p>The last river that we have to notice is the Murghab, which rises between the two
                    northern branches of the Koh-i-Baba or Paropamisus. Ferrier is the only
                    traveller who has been on the upper waters of the Murghab. He takes no notice of
                    the river itself, but describes a remarkable plain or basin, about 120 miles in
                    circuit, entirely surrounded by mountains, well-watered, and rich in vegetation.
                    The people are Mongol Hazaras, and, according to Ferrier, idolaters. Their
                    country is a part of the old territory of Garjistân. At Shah Mashad, about
                    half-way between this and the plains, the river was crossed by Major Eldred
                    Pottinger, but we have no access to his report. Further down, as the river
                    approaches the foot of Murghab Bâlâ, on the road from Maimana to Herat, it runs
                    with great violence, and the valley narrows to a defile. At Panjdeh, 35 to 40
                    miles below Murghab, it begins to flow through a valley of clay soil, bounded by
                    sandy heights, and gradually opening into the plain of Merv. Hereabouts, too, it
                    quits the Afghan territory, but the boundary does not seem as yet to have been
                    precisely fixed. About 100 miles from Panjdeh the river reaches Merv, where
                    formerly there was a great dam, securing the fertility of that oasis, the
                    nucleus of ancient <hi rend="italic">Margiana.</hi> This was destroyed by the
                    Amir Maasum (otherwise Shah Murad) of Bokhara, about 1785, when he carried off
                    the whole population into slavery. Beyond Merv the river is lost in the
                    desert.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Provinces and Places of Note.</hi> —We do not know the
                    precise divisions maintained under the Afghans, but they coincide generally with
                    the old principalities or khanates, the hereditary rulers of which, in several
                    cases, continue in authority under the Afghan governor of Turkestan. Bamian,
                    Saighan, and the higher valleys belong, it is understood, to a special command
                    over the Hazara tribes.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="italic">Kunduz.—</hi> Beginning again from the east, the first
                    province is <hi rend="italic">Kunduz,</hi> having on the east Badakhshan, on the
                    west Khulm, on the north the Oxus, and on the south Hindu Kush. The districts of
                    Kunduz are approximately as follows:—(1.) <hi rend="italic">Kunduz,</hi> with
                    the chief town of the province, a wretched place, as described by Wood, of some
                    500 or 600 mud huts, intermingled with straw sheds, Uzbek tents, gardens, and
                    corn-fields, and overlooked by a mud fort on an extensive mound. (2. ) <hi
                    rend="italic">Hazrat Imâm,</hi> on the irrigated and fertile Oxus plain. The
                    town, known in the Middle Ages as <hi rend="italic">Arhang,</hi> is described as
                    about the same size as Kunduz, with a better fort, protected by a wet ditch.
                    (3.) <hi rend="italic">Baghlan,</hi> and (4.) <hi rend="italic">Ghori,</hi> in
                    the swampy valley of the Surkhab. (5.) <hi rend="italic">Doshi,</hi> further up
                    the same valley, at the confluence of the Andarab stream. (6.) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Killagai</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Khingan,</hi> near the lower part of the
                    Andarab stream. (7.) <hi rend="italic">Andarab,</hi> at the foot of the Tul and
                    Khâwak passes over Hindu Kush, often supposed to be the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Adrapsa</hi> of Alexander’s historians. This secluded town was a favourite
                    minting place of the Samanid sovereigns of Persia and Turkestan, in the 10th
                    century, probably owing to the vicinity of silver mines at Paryân. (8.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Khost</hi> lies between Andarab and Kunduz. The name often occurs
                    in the history of Baber and his successors. (9.) <hi rend="italic">Narin</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Ish-kimish</hi> lie to the east of Baghlan, at the sources
                    of the Baghlan stream and of the Shorab branch of the Kunduz river. The second
                    name appears to be the same as <hi rend="italic">Eshk-mushk,</hi> which Wood
                    applies to a high mountain in this quarter. (10.) <hi rend="italic">Farhang</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Châl</hi> lie on the borders cf Badakhshan, and are
                    utterly unknown. (11.) <hi rend="italic">Tâlik</hi><hi rend="italic">â</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> also lies on the borders of Badakhshan, but is pretty well
                    known, being on the main road between Kunduz and Faizabad, the capital of
                    Badakhshan. It is now a poor place, but is ancient, and was once famous. A
                    fortress here stood a long siege from Chinghiz Khan, and the place is mentioned
                    by Marco Polo as <hi rend="italic">Taican.</hi> During the rule of Murad Beg of
                    Kunduz this was the seat of a government that included Badakhshan. (12.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Khanabad,</hi> on the river of that name, pleasantly elevated
                    above the swampy level of Kunduz, is, or was, the usual summer residence of the
                    chiefs of that territory.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Khulm</hi> was the next of the khanates, lying between
                    Kunduz and Balkh. The districts, as far as we know them, are the following:—(1.)
                    <hi rend="italic">Tâshkurghân.</hi> The old town of Khulm stood in the Oxus
                    plain, surrounded by watered orchards of famous productiveness; but it lay so
                    exposed to the raids of the Kunduz Uzbeks that the chief, Killich Ali, in the
                    beginning of this century, transferred <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n260/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0260-0243"/> his residence to Tashkurghan, 4 miles further
                    south, and just at the mouth of the defile—a cheerless group of villages,
                    consisting of mud houses with domed roofs, connected by gardens and enclosed by
                    a mud wall; it is supposed to contain at least 15,000 souls, and is a place of
                    considerable trade. (2.) <hi rend="italic">Haibak.</hi> The town presents rather
                    an imposing aspect, clustering round a castle of some strength on an isolated
                    eminence; the domed houses, however, are compared to large brown bee-hives. The
                    Khulm river valley here opens out, and is very fertile; the banks are shaded by
                    luxuriant fruit trees. The site is a very ancient one, and, under the name of
                    <hi rend="italic">Samangân,</hi> was famous in Persian legend. One traveller
                    describes there a remarkable relic of antiquity called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Takht</hi> or Throne of Rustam. This, from the account, would seem to have been
                    a Buddhist dagoba.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Burslem, <hi rend="italic">A Peep into Turkestan,</hi> p. 125.</p></note>
                    (3.) <hi rend="italic">Khurram Sarbâgh,</hi> so called from two villages in the
                    upper defiles of the Khulm river.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="italic">Balkh. Balkh</hi> proper is the populous and well-watered
                    territory upon the eighteen canals which draw off the waters of the Balkh-ab,
                    and on which there are said to be 360 villages.</p>
                <p>No trace has been recovered of the ancient splendours of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bactra,</hi> nor do the best judges appear to accept Ferrier’s belief that he
                    saw cuneiform inscriptions upon bricks dug up there. A late Indian report by an
                    intelligent Mahom-medan speaks of a stone throne in the citadel, to which
                    traditional antiquity is ascribed, but of this we know no more. The remains that
                    exist are scattered over some 20 miles of circuit, but they consist mainly of
                    mosques and tombs of sun-dried brick, and show nothing even of early Mahommedan
                    date. The inner city, surrounded by a ruined wall of 4 or 5 miles in compass, is
                    now entirely deserted; a scanty population still occupies a part of the outer
                    city. In 1858 Mahommed Afzal Khan, ruling the districts of Turkestan on behalf
                    of his father, Dost Mahommed, transferred the seat of the Afghan government and
                    the bulk of the population to Takhtapul, a position which he fortified, some 8
                    miles east of the old city; and this remains the capital of the Afghan
                    territories on the Oxus.</p>
                <p>The only other place of note in the district is <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mazâr-i-Sharîf,</hi> or the “Noble Shrine,” on the road to Khulm, where a
                    whimsical fiction has located the body of ’Ali, the son-in-law of Mahommed. It
                    is the object of pilgrimages, and the scene of a great annual fair. Vámbéry
                    speaks of the roses, matchless for colour and fragrance, that grow on the
                    pretended tomb.</p>
                <p>Of the districts lying on the Balkh river within the hills we know nothing.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Akcha,</hi> some 40 to 45 miles westward from Balkh, was an
                    Uzbek khanate before the last Afghan conquest. It is small, but well-watered and
                    populous. The town is fortified, and has a citadel. Accounts differ as to the
                    population; one writer calls them Uzbeks, another Sarak Turkmans.</p>
                <p>IV. The provinces known as the Four Domains are :— (1.) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shibrghan,</hi> some 20 miles west of Akcha. This was another small Uzbek
                    khanate. The town, which contains about 12,000 Uzbeks and Parsiwans, has a
                    citadel, but is not otherwise fortified. It is surrounded by good gardens, and
                    excellent cultivation, but its water supply is dependent upon Siripul, and, in
                    the frequent case of hostility between the two, is liable to be cut off. Ferrier
                    speaks highly of the climate and the repute of the inhabitants for valour.
                    Shibrghan (Sapurgan) and its fine melons are mentioned by Marco Polo. (2.) <hi
                    rend="italic">Andkhui,</hi> about 20 miles north-west of Shibrghan, forms an
                    oasis in the desert, watered by the united streams from Siripul and from
                    Maimana. It was once a flourishing city, and the oasis was reckoned to contain
                    50,000 inhabitants, but the place has scarcely recovered from the destruction it
                    endured at the hands of Yar Mahommed of Herat in 1840. It was at Andkhui that
                    Moorcroft died in 1825; but his grave is at Balkh. Tre-beck, the last survivor
                    of his party, died and was buried at Mazar. (3.) <hi rend="italic">Maimana,</hi>
                    105 miles from Balkh, and some 50 south-west of Andkhui, contains some ten or
                    twelve villages or townships, besides the capital, and a population estimated at
                    100,000 souls. It is a district of considerable productiveness, industry, and
                    trade, and the Uzbek inhabitants have a high reputation as soldiers. The chief
                    was formerly a notorious slave-dealer. (4.) <hi rend="italic">Siripul.</hi> This
                    khanate lying within the limits of the undulating country south-west of Balkh
                    and east of Maimana, is of about the same calibre as the latter, but somewhat
                    lower in estimated population. Two-thirds of the people are Uzbeks, the rest
                    Hazaras. From the last a tribute of slaves is, or used to be, exacted; and
                    Hazara widows, it is said, were claimed as government property, and sold by
                    auction. The town of Siripul is an irregular mass of houses clustered on the
                    slope of a hill crowned by a fort. Many tents gather round it also, and Ferrier
                    estimates the population of town and tents as high as 18,000. The valley below
                    is abundantly watered, and the breadth of orchards and tillage is
                    considerable.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Population.</hi> —In the estimate of population cited under
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Afghanistan,</hi> that of Afghan Turkestan is reckoned at
                    642,000. This includes 55,000 for Badakhshan (no doubt too low an estimate); and
                    the remainder, for the provinces included under our present article, excluding
                    Hazaras, will be 587,000. Anything but a round number is entirely inappropriate
                    to such an estimate; but we shall probably not be far wrong if we reckon the
                    population at 600,000.</p>
                <p>The Tajiks, or people of Iranian blood, are probably tho representatives of the
                    oldest surviving race of this region. They are found in some districts of Balkh
                    and valleys of Kunduz. Khost, for instance, is said to be chiefly occupied by
                    them. Uzbeks seem to be the most numerous race; and there are some other Turk
                    tribes not classed as Uzbeks.z<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The Uzbeks were, however, a confederation of many Turk and
                    Tartar tribes, not one race.</p></note> There seem to be a good many families
                    claiming Arab descent; Afghans, especially about Balkh and Khulm; and in the
                    towns some Hindus and Jews.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Products and Industry.</hi> —We have no means of giving any
                    systematic account of the products of these provinces, either in natural history
                    or industry. Rock-salt is worked at Chal, near the Badakhshan frontier, as well
                    as beyond that frontier. Pistachio nuts are grown largely in the hill country of
                    Kunduz, as well as the adjoining districts of Badakhshan, and the whole supply
                    of India, Central Asia, and Russia is said to be derived from this region. Fruit
                    is abundant and excellent, especially in Khulm and Balkh. Andkhui, before its
                    decay, was famous for the black sheepskins and lambskins which we call <hi
                    rend="italic">astrakhan;</hi> and also for a breed of camels in great demand.
                    Kunduz produces a breed of horses, highly valued in the Kabul market under the
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Kataghan.</hi> Maimana also is famous for horses,
                    which are often exported to India; and is a mart for carpets and textures of
                    wool and camels’ hair, the work of Turkman and Jamshîdi women. Slavedealing and
                    man-stealing have long been the curse of this region, but late changes have
                    tended to restrict these, and the Russian conquest of Khiva will probably have a
                    most beneficial effect in this respect at least.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Ancient Balkh, or <hi rend="italic">Bactra,</hi>
                    was probably one of the oldest capitals in Central Asia. There Persian tradition
                    places the teaching of Zoroaster. Bactriana was a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n261/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0261-0244"/> province of the Achaemenian empire, and probably
                    was occupied in great measure by a race of Iranian blood. About B.c. 250,
                    Theodotus, governor of Bactria under the Seleucidae, declared his independence,
                    and commenced the history, so dark to us, of the Greco-Bactrian dynasties, whose
                    dominions at one time or another—though probably never simultaneously—touched
                    the Jaxartes and the Gulf of Cutch. Parthian rivalry first, and then a series of
                    nomad movements from inner Asia, overwhelmed the isolated dominion of the Greeks
                    <hi rend="italic">(circa</hi> B.c. 126). Powers rose on the Oxus, known to the
                    Chinese as Yuechi, Kweish-wang, Yetha, Tukhâras, and what not; dimly to western
                    Asia and Europe as Kushâns, Haiâthala, <hi rend="italic">Ephthalitoe</hi> or
                    White Huns, and <hi rend="italic">Tochari</hi> Buddhism, with its monasteries,
                    colossi, and gilded pagodas, spread over the valley of the Oxus. We do not know
                    what further traces of that time may yet be revealed; but we see some in the
                    gigantic sculptures of Bamian. The old Arab historians of the Mahommedan
                    conquest celebrate a heathen temple at Balkh, which they call <hi rend="italic"
                    >Naobihâr,</hi> which Sir H. Rawlinson has pointed out to have been certainly a
                    Buddhist monastery <hi rend="italic">(Nava-Vihâra).</hi> The name Naobihar still
                    attaches to a village on one of the Balkh canals, thus preserving, through so
                    many centuries, the memory of the ancient Indian religion. The memoirs of the
                    Chinese pilgrim Hwen Thsang, in the first part of the 7th century, give many
                    particulars of the prevalence of his religion in the numerous principalities
                    into which the empire of the Tukharas had broken up; and it is remarkable how
                    many of these states and their names are identical with those which still exist.
                    This is not confined to what were great cities like Balkh and Bamian; it applies
                    to Khulm, Khost, Baghlan, Andarab, and many more.</p>
                <p>As <hi rend="italic">Haiathalah,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tokhâristân,</hi> the
                    country long continued to be known to Mahommedans; its political destiny
                    generally followed that of Khorasan. It bore the brunt of all the fury of
                    Chinghiz, and the region seems never to have effectually recovered from the
                    devastations and massacres which he began, and which were repeated in degree in
                    succeeding generations. For about a century these Oxus provinces were attached
                    to the empire of the Dehli Moguls, and then fell into Uzbek hands. In the last
                    century they formed a part of the dominion of Ahmed Khan Durrani (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Afghanistan),</hi> and so remained under his son Timur. But
                    during the fratricidal wars of Timur’s sons they fell back under the independent
                    rule of various Uzbek chiefs. Among these, the Kataghans of Kunduz were long
                    predominant; and their chief, Murad Beg (1815 to about 1842), for some time
                    ruled Kûlâb beyond the Oxus, and all south of it from near Balkh to Pamir.</p>
                <p>In 1850 the Afghans recovered Balkh and Khulm; by 1855 they had also gained Akcha
                    and the four western khanates; Kunduz in 1859. They were proceeding to extend
                    their conquests to Badakhshan, when the Amîr of that country agreed to pay
                    homage and tribute.</p>
                <p>We have noticed, in the conclusion of the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Afghanistan,</hi> the correspondence which recently took place (1872- 73) with
                    Russia regarding the recognition of the Oxus as the boundary of Afghan
                    Turkestan.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Antiquities.—</hi> These are known but very imperfectly. The
                    best known, and probably the most remarkable, are the famous colossi at Bamian,
                    with the adjoining innumerable caves. In the same locality are the ruins of the
                    mediaeval city destroyed by Chinghiz, the great fort called Sayadabad, and the
                    ruins of Zohak. At Haibak are numerous caves like those of Bamian. Balkh seems
                    to have little or nothing to show, though probably excavation would be rewarded.
                    The little known or unknown valleys of Badakhshan probably contain remains of
                    interest, but our only notices of them are so highly spiced with imagination as
                    to be worthless. General Ferrier saw remarkable rock sculptures in a defile in
                    the Hazara country, south of Siripul, and curious rock excavations a little
                    further south.</p>
                <p>(Wood’s <hi rend="italic">Journey,</hi> 2d ed., 1873, with Introductory Essay;
                    Ferrier’s <hi rend="italic">Caravan Journeys;</hi> Burnes’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Travels;</hi> Indian official documents; Vámbéry’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Travels;</hi> &amp;c., &amp;c.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(h. y.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
