<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0698-0661-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMBOYNA (9th edition, volume 1, page 661)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851090">Ceramics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1035341">Neck</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh9h">Ceramics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vx1b">Neck</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n698/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMBOYNA</label>, one of the Moluccas or Spice Islands,
                    belonging to the Dutch, lying south-west of Ceram, in 3° 41' S. lat. and 128°
                    10' E. long. It is 32 miles in length, with an area of about 280 square miles,
                    and is of very irregular figure, being almost divided into two. The southeastern
                    and smaller portion (called Leitimor) is united to the northern (known as Hitoe)
                    by a neck of land about a mile broad. The island is mountainous, but is for the
                    most part fertile and well-watered. Large tracts are covered with rich tropical
                    forests, which embrace a great variety of trees, although ordinary building
                    timber is scarce. The climate is comparatively pleasant and healthy; the average
                    temperature is 80° Fahr., rarely sinking below 72°. The rainfall, however, after
                    the eastern monsoons, is very heavy, and the island is liable to violent
                    hurricanes and earthquakes. Amboyna produces most of the common tropical fruits
                    and vegetables, including the sago-palm, bread-fruit, cocoa-nut, sugar-cane,
                    maize, coffee, pepper, and cotton. Cloves, however, form its chief product, and
                    the only one that is of any real commercial importance. The Dutch have done much
                    to foster the cultivation of this article in the island, and at one time
                    prohibited the rearing of the clove-tree in all the other islands subject to
                    their rule, in order to secure the monopoly to Amboyna. Each tree yields
                    annually from 2 to 5 lb of cloves, and sometimes even more; while the total
                    annual quantity produced probably averages about 500,000 lb. The animal kingdom
                    is poorly represented. Indigenous mammals are feeble in species as well as few
                    in number; birds are more abundant, but of no greater variety. The entomology of
                    the island is, however, very rich, particularly among the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lepi-doptera.</hi> The aborigines of Amboyna are a race called Horaforas, but
                    Malays constitute the main body of the population; there are also Chinese,
                    Dutch, and a few Portuguese. The Malays in most points resemble those of Java.
                    They are naturally lazy and effeminate, but when properly trained make good
                    soldiers. The inhabitants are mostly Christians or Mahometans. Amboyna is the
                    chief island of the Dutch residence of the Moluccas, which comprises, in
                    addition, the islands of Boeroe, Amblauw, Ceram, Manipa, Kilang, Bonoe,
                    Haroekoe, Honimoa or Saparoa, Noesa-laut, and Hila. The Portuguese were the
                    first European nation to visit Amboyna (1512). They established a factory there
                    in 1521, but did not obtain peaceable possession of it till 1580, and were
                    dispossessed by the Dutch in 1605. About the year 1615 the British formed a
                    settlement in the island, at Cambello, which they retained until 1623, when it
                    was destroyed by the Dutch, and frightful tortures inflicted on the unfortunate
                    persons connected with it. In 1654, after many fruitless negotiations, Cromwell
                    compelled the United Provinces to give the sum of £300,000, together with a
                    small island, as compensation to the descendants of those who suffered in the
                    “Amboyna massacre.” In 1796 the British, under Admiral Rainier, captured
                    Amboyna, but restored it to the Dutch at the peace of Amiens in 1802. It was
                    recaptured by the British in 1810, but once more restored to the Dutch in 1814.
                    Population, about 50,000. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Moluccas.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Amboyna,</hi> the chief town of the above island, and also of
                    the Dutch Moluccas, is situated towards the north-west of the peninsula of
                    Leitimor. The streets are broad and unpaved, running at right angles to one
                    another, and intersected by numerous rivulets. The houses are of wood, roofed
                    with palm leaves, and mostly of one storey, on account of the frequent
                    earthquakes. An esplanade of 250 yards reaches from Fort Victoria to the town,
                    and is terminated by a handsome range of houses. The townhouse is a neat
                    structure of two storeys; and among the other buildings are two Protestant
                    churches and a hospital. The government offices are in Fort Victoria. The
                    roadstead of Amboyna is safe and commodious. Population, about 13,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
