<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-8186-0447-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PORSON (Richard)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058861">Persons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914366">Epitaphs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vb8c">Epitaphs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193538186?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PORSON <hi rend="smallcaps">(Richard)</hi></label>,
                    the greatest of the verbal critics and classical scholars of modern times, born
                    on the 25th of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538199?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-8199-0448"/>December 1759, was the son of Mr. Huggin
                    Porson, parish clerk of East Ruston, near North Walsham, in Norfolk.</p>
                <p part="N">His father taught him, in his childhood, to practise all the common
                    rules of arithmetic by memory only; and, before he was nine years old, he had
                    learned to extract the cube root in this manner. At the same time, for teaching
                    him to read and write, he employed the method which has since been generally
                    introduced in the schools of mutual instruction, making him draw the letters
                    with chalk or on sand; and the neatness and accuracy of his hand-writing, for
                    which he was distinguished through life, may be considered as bearing ample
                    testimony to his father’s ingenuity and success.</p>
                <p part="N">At the age of nine he was sent to a village school, kept by a Mr.
                    Summers; but his father still made him repeat by heart in the evening the whole
                    of the lessons of the day; and there seems to be sufficient evidence for
                    considering this practice of exercising the memory continually, in very early
                    life, as the best, if not the only method of cultivating, if not of producing
                    great talent. For though a strong memory by no means constitutes talent, yet its
                    possession is almost a necessary condition for the successful exertion of talent
                    in general; and, indeed, it is very possible that the other faculties of the
                    mind may be strengthened by the early cultivation of this one. It is remarkable
                    that Wallis, who was as deservedly celebrated in his day as Porson, for his
                    unerring sagacity, had also a singular facility of retaining numbers and
                    calculations in his memory, but without having taken any particular pains to
                    acquire the habit. Mr. Hewitt, the vicar of the parish of East Ruston, hearing
                    of young Porson’s uncommon capacity, undertook to instruct both him and his
                    brother Thomas in classical literature; and when he was about fifteen, Mr.
                    Norris, a wealthy and respectable gentleman of the neighbourhood, having
                    ascertained the truth of the reports that he heard of him, resolved to be at the
                    expense of sending him to Eton. Without this assistance it would have been
                    impossible for Porson to have acquired great excellence in any intellectual
                    pursuit; for his father’s situation in life was not such as to exempt his son
                    even from the subordinate occupations of the country. He went out gleaning, in
                    the autumn, with a Horace in his pocket; and he had learned by experience to
                    appreciate the mechanical labours of Penelope, before he was much acquainted
                    with the wisdom and wanderings of Ulysses.</p>
                <p part="N">At Eton, his talents procured him the friendship and admiration of the
                    seniors amongst his schoolfellows, and, upon the unfortunate death of his first
                    patron, Mr. Norris, be found a number of liberal contributors, who stepped
                    forward to supply the deficiency; but by far the most active of them was Sir
                    George Baker, then President of the Royal College of Physicians, a man as much
                    distinguished by his own classical taste and acquirements, as by his laudable
                    disposition to cherish learning in others. He received the boy into his house
                    for a vacation, and undertook, at the request of a relation of Mr. Norris, the
                    disagreeable task of receiving, in small sums, as much as was sufficient to
                    purchase an income of L.80 a-year, for a few years, in the short annuities,
                    which served, with great economy, to enable him to remain at Eton. This favour
                    appears to have been too great to be properly acknowledged, or perhaps even duly
                    appreciated, by its object, who only after many years paid Sir George the tardy
                    compliment of a dedication, not, however, of an edition, but of a handsome copy
                    of a single play of Euripides. In his own opinion, Porson learned little at Eton
                    besides the quantity of syllables, being able to repeat by heart before he went
                    there the principal part of the authors that he had to read; that is, almost the
                    whole of Horace and Virgil, the <hi rend="italic">Iliad,</hi> and many parts of
                    Cicero, Livy, and the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey.</hi> A story is accordingly
                    told of his book having been changed by one of his schoolfellows in joke, when
                    he was going up to a lesson in Horace, and of his having read and translated
                    what was required of him, without at all betraying the change to his master. At
                    the same time, the emulation of a public school must have been a great advantage
                    to him, as affording him a motive for exertion in his exercises, whether they
                    were to be called his own, or to be written for other boys. It was a copy of
                    Toup’s Longinus, presented to him as a reward for a good exercise, that first
                    gave him a decided inclination for the pursuit of critical researches; but he
                    always considered Bentley and Dawcs as his great masters in criticism.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1777 he was sent to Trinity College, Cambridge, and at first he began
                    to apply more particularly to the mathematics, which had been the favourite
                    study of his boyhood, and in which, as he himself remarked, his proficiency
                    first brought him into a certain degree of public notice. He was, however, soon
                    diverted from this pursuit, although he attained a place amongst the <hi
                        rend="italic">senior optimes</hi> of his year. But he was in fact more
                    calculated for classical than for mathematical excellence. His memory would have
                    been in a great measure thrown away, if he had been employed in abstract
                    calculations; and his inventive powers do not appear to have been at all of the
                    same class with his retentive faculties; although certainly in the mechanical
                    pursuit of the fashionable methods of modern analysis, which are intended, like
                    steam engines, to overcome all difficulties by the inanimate force of mere
                    patience and perseverance, he was capable of filling as dis inguished a place as
                    any living algebraist. The classical prize medal, and the university
                    scholarship, he obtained without difficulty, as matters of course. The exercise,
                    which he exhibited upon the examination for the scholarship, is the well known
                    translation of an epitaph into Greek iambics; which, although not free from some
                    inaccuracies in the use of the tenses, is still a very remarkable production,
                    when it is considered as having been completed in less than an hour, with the
                    help of Morrell’s <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi> only, and never afterwards
                    corrected.</p>
                <p part="N">He obtained a fellowship of Trinity College in 1781, and took his degree
                    of Master of Arts in 1785; but not thinking it right to subscribe the Articles
                    of the Church of England, he could not enter into orders, and he was therefore
                    unavoidably deprived of his fellowship in 179L having no dependence left for his
                    subsistence through life, but his own abilities and acquirements. His friends,
                    however, did not abandon him on this urgent occasion, and in order to keep him
                    out of actual want, a private subscription was set on foot, to which Mr.
                    Cracherode was one of the principal contributors, and by which enough was raised
                    to purchase him an annuity of about L.l 00 a-year for life. A small addition was
                    made to bis income, about two years afterwards, by his election to the Greek
                    Professorship at Cambridge, with a salary of only L.40 a-year. The situation,
                    however, gave him the option of at least doubling his whole receipts, by the
                    delivery of an annual course of lectures in the university; and it was supposed
                    that he would have made this exertion, if he had not been discouraged by the
                    difficulty of obtaining rooms in his college, where it would have been his wish
                    to reside.</p>
                <p part="N">Porson married, in 1795, Mrs.Lunan, a sister of the late Mr. Perry, well
                    known as the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Morning Chronicle,</hi> but he had
                    the misfortune to lose his wife two years afterwards. Mr. Perry continued to be
                    his greatest friend through life, and was so far his best benefactor, as he knew
                    how to oblige him essentially, without the appearance of doing him a favour.
                    Person had sometimes chambers in the Temple, and sometimes he lodged at the <hi
                        rend="italic">Morning Chronicle</hi> office; frequently also he was a
                    visitor at Mr. Perry’s house at Merton, where he had the misfortune to leave
                    several of his books, at the time of a fire, which destroyed them all, and
                    amongst them some letters of Rhunkenius, with whom he had begun a correspondence
                    in 1783, and who had committed to him some valuable fragments of AEschylus, <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193538212?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8212-0449"
                    />besides his manuscript copy of the lexicon of Photius, which had cost him ten
                    months’ labour. Hc used indeed to say that this fire had destroyed the fruits of
                    twenty years of his life; but hc had the resolution to complete a second copy of
                    the Photius, which is now in the library of Trinity College. His fondness for
                    the mechanical employment of his pen has been regretted by some of his
                    biographers, as having tempted him to waste much of his most valuable time on a
                    trifling amusement; but in fact, his mode of writing Greek was fully as much
                    calculated for expedition as for beauty; and those who have not been in the
                    habit of correcting mutilated passages of manuscripts, can form no estimate of
                    the immense advantage that is obtained, by the complete sifting of every letter,
                    which the mind involuntarily performs, whilst the hand is occupied in tracing
                    it; so that, if the correction of Photius was really worth the labour of two
                    years of Porson’s life, it would have been scarcely possible to employ the
                    greater part of those years more advantageously, than by copying him twice over.
                    Mr. Weston, in speaking of “his matchless penmanship,” has observed, not very
                    intelligibly, that “here, indeed, hc thought himself surpassed by” another
                    person “not in the stroke, but the sweep, of his letters.” What Porson really
                    said on this subject was, that, with respect to “command of hand,” that person
                    had the advantage, but he preferred the <hi rend="italic">model</hi> on which
                    his own hand was formed. His writing was, in fact, more like that of a scholar,
                    whilst the method explained in Mr. Hodgkin’s <hi rend="italic">Calligraphia</hi>
                    exhibits more the appearance of the work of a writing master; holding, however,
                    a middle place between the neatness of Porson, and the wonderful accuracy of the
                    country schoolmaster who made the fac simile of the Oxford Pindar in the British
                    Museum.</p>
                <p part="N">Upon the establishment of the London Institution, his friends obtained
                    for him the very desirable appointment of principal librarian, with a salary of
                    L.200 a-year, and apartments in the house of the Institution, which was then in
                    the Old Jewry; but although the arrangement was highly honourable to all
                    parties, the librarianship was little more than a sinecure. Porson was, however,
                    in the habit of attending in his place when the reading-room was open, and of
                    communicating, very readily, all the literary information that was required, by
                    those who consulted him respecting the object of their researches. Had the
                    inhabitants of Finsbury Square and its neighbourhood been more disposed to
                    classical studies, and had the librarian of the Institution survived, to witness
                    its completion and prosperity, his sphere of utility would, without doubt, have
                    been greatly extended.</p>
                <p part="N">But it must ever bc lamented that Porson’s habits of life had
                    unfortunately been such as to lay a foundation for a multitude of diseases. He
                    suffered much from asthma throughout the year 1808; his memory began to fail him
                    a little; and in the autumn he had some symptoms of intermittent fever. On
                    Monday the 19th of September he had an apoplectic attack in the street, and he
                    was carried to a neighbouring poor house in a state of insensibility. The next
                    day an advertisement appeared in one of the papers, relating the accident, and
                    describing some manuscripts which were found in his pocket, consisting of Greek
                    fragments and algebraical characters. His friends at the London Institution
                    immediately went in quest of him; he was afterwards well enough to appear in the
                    library, and to receive a visit there from Dr. Adam Clarke; but his speech was
                    impaired, and his faculties evidently imperfect. He survived only through the
                    week, and died in his forty-ninth year, on Sunday the 25th of September 1808, at
                    midnight.</p>
                <p part="N">He was buried at Cambridge, in Trinity College Chapel, near the grave of
                    Bentley, and the monument of Newton. He founded by will an annual prize, to be
                    given to the best Greek translation from an English dramatic author; and several
                    specimens of the successful pieces have been published from time to time in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Classical Journal.</hi> His books were sold by auction,
                    and many of them found purchasers at high prices, especially such as were
                    enriched with any of his manuscript notes in their margins; but more than two
                    hundred of these, which appeared to be the most valuable, were withheld from the
                    sale, and were afterwards purchased, together with the whole of his manuscript
                    papers, by the Society of Trinity College, for the sum of a thousand guineas. He
                    left a sister, married to Mr. Siday Hawes, of Coltishall, Norfolk. His brother
                    Thomas kept a boarding-school at Fakenham, and died, without issue, in 1792: his
                    second brother, Henry, was a farmer in Essex, and died young, leaving three
                    children. His father had lived to 74, his mother to 57.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal works of Porson are his <hi rend="italic">Letters to
                        Travis,</hi> his four plays of Euripides with their prefaces, and the
                    manuscript copy of Photius; the rest, though somewhat voluminous, are chiefly
                    miscellaneous annotations upon detached passages of a multitude of ancient
                    authors. We find nothing in the nature of theory, or of the discovery of general
                    laws, except some canons, which he has laid down, chiefly as having been used by
                    the Greek tragedians in the construction of their verses. These are chiefly
                    contained in the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Hecuba,</hi> together with its
                    supplement. 1. The first is, that when a tragic iambic ends with a trisyllable,
                    or a cretic, this word must be preceded either by a short syllable, or by a
                    monosyllable. For example, an ancient tragedian would not have written the line
                        <hi rend="superscript"> ,z</hi> E <hi rend="subscript"> z</hi> γoι δε <hi
                        rend="italic">μηποτ lξ απfνκrοij</hi><hi rend="italic">δώματος,</hi> though
                    it might have been unexceptionable in a comedy. It seems to have been about the
                    year 1790 that Porson first made this observation. He certainly did not attend
                    to it in his own serious translation of the <hi rend="italic">Epitaph on
                        Alexis</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but it was mentioned, in 179L by one of
                    Porson’s intimate friends, in a moment of conviviality, whilst he was somewhat
                    characteristically attempting to fill his glass out of an empty bottle; and the
                    author of this article observed in answer, that it would certainly sound better,
                    on such an occasion as then occurred, to say, <hi rend="smallcaps">∏Sp</hi>
                    eκ7rε'7rωκαs∙ oυδ <hi rend="superscript"> , w</hi> Ev∈σTI <hi rend="italic"
                        >κότταβος,</hi> than <hi rend="italic">ον</hi> λελewrTAI <hi rend="italic"
                        >n0τταβοs.</hi> 2. The second canon is, that an anapaest is only admissible
                    in a tragic iambic, as constituting the first foot, except in some cases of
                    proper names. This indeed had been cursorily hinted by Dawes. 3. The same critic
                    had also remarked, that the Attic poets never lengthen a short vowel before a
                    mute or aspirate, followed by a liquid, or a middle consonant followed by <hi
                        rend="italic">ρ</hi>; and Porson more amply confirmed the observation as
                    very generally, though not universally correct. On the other hand, Dawes had
                    cursorily observed that Homer, and the other ancient epic poets, generally
                    lengthened the vowel in such cases, and Porson’s great rival, Hermann, has more
                    fully established this distinction, as affording a good criterion of antiquity.
                    4. There are also some original remarks of Porson on the caesura, in iambics,
                    and trochaics, and anapaests. He showed that the scenic poets do not elide the
                    final iota, and that the tragedians do not employ the preposition <hi
                        rend="italic">πepi</hi> before a vowel; and some other general laws, of
                    greater importance than these, may probably be found in some of his
                    publications, which it w ill now be ne-. cessary to enumerate in the order of
                    time.</p>
                <p part="N">1. His first attempts, as an author, consisted of some anonymous
                    articles in Dr. Maty’s <hi rend="italic">Review,</hi> beginning with a part of
                    Shutz’s <hi rend="italic">AEscltylus,</hi> June 1783, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tracts</hi> ii. Brunck’s <hi rend="italic">Aristophanes,</hi> July 1783,
                        <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> iii.; <hi rend="italic">Mus.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Crit.∖∖.</hi> 113; written in a day. In Latin, by Schafer, <hi
                        rend="italic">Class. Jowrη.</hi> v. 136. Weston’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Heτmesiαnax,</hi> April 1784, <hi rend="italic">Tracts,</hi> iv.
                    Huntingford’s <hi rend="italic">Apology for his Menostroplιics,</hi> August
                    1784, <hi rend="italic">Tracts V. Account of the Learned Pig,</hi> April 1785,
                        <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> vi. <hi rend="italic">Note,</hi> with letters
                    of Le Clerc and Bentley, April 1786, <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> vii.</p>
                <p part="N">2. He added some <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> to an edition of
                    Xenophon’s <hi rend="italic">Anabasis,</hi> published by Nicholson, at
                    Cambridge, 4to and 8vo, 1786. They are addressed <hi rend="italic">Lectori si
                        quis erit.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193538225?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8225-0450"/>
                <p part="N">3. <hi rend="italic">Three Panegyrical Epistles to Sir J. Hawkins, Gent.
                        Mag.</hi> August, September, and October, 1787. <hi rend="italic">Tracts
                        ∖κ.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">4. Notes on <hi rend="italic">Toupii</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Emendationes</hi><hi rend="italic">in Suidam.</hi> Oxford, 8vo. 1790.
                    Written in 1787.</p>
                <p part="N">5. <hi rend="italic">Letters on the Three Witnesses, Gent. Mag.</hi>
                    Oct. and Dec. 1788. Feb. April, May, June, Aug. 1789. Feb. 1790. The last was
                    reprinted in <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> xix.; most of the others in the
                    collection of <hi rend="italic">Letters to Mr. Archdeacon Travis,</hi> in answer
                    to his defence of the <hi rend="italic">Three Heavenly Witnesses,</hi> London,
                    1790, 8vo. These letters are generally considered, by critics of all parties, as
                    finally decisive of a question, which had often been agitated before, but never
                    so learnedly argued, nor so satisfactorily discussed inall itsbear-ings.</p>
                <p part="N">6. In the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Review,</hi> Robertson’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Essay on the Parian Chronicle,</hi> Jan. 1789, <hi
                        rend="italic">Tracts</hi> xiii.; satisfactorily answering the principal part
                    of the objections alleged against the authenticity of that monument. Edwards’
                    edition of the work attributed to Plutarch, <hi rend="italic">on Education,</hi>
                    July 1793, <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> xxi∙ Payne Knight’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Greek Alphabet,</hi> Jan. 1794, <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> xxiii.
                    Pybus’s <hi rend="italic">Sovereign,</hi> Dec. 1800; an article affording a good
                    specimen of his talent for humour.</p>
                <p part="N">7. He is supposed to have written some <hi rend="italic">Remarks</hi> on
                    an <hi rend="italic">Essay upon the 'Transfiguration,</hi> but never expressly
                    acknowledged them. <hi rend="italic">Tracts</hi> XV.</p>
                <p part="N">8. He added a few short <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> to the London
                    edition of Heyne’s Virgil, 8vo, 1793, for which he made an agreement with the
                    bookseller to correct the press; but he complained that liis corrections were
                    disregarded; and in fact several hundred errors, of no great importance, were
                    suffered to disfigure it.</p>
                <p part="N">9. He corrected the Greek text of AEschylus for the Glasgow editions,
                    the folio of 1795, and the two volumes octavo, printed in 1794, but only
                    published at London in 1806. The folio is said to have appeared surreptitiously.
                    There arc more than two hundred original corrections, and a further number of
                    passages pointed out as corrupt.</p>
                <p part="N">10. In the <hi rend="italic">Morning Chronicle</hi> he published, at
                    different times, a variety of spirited articles of a temporary nature. One of
                    the most amusing was the <hi rend="italic">Nursery Song</hi> in Greek iambics,
                    13th of April 1796, called <hi rend="italic">A Fragment of Sophocles,</hi> and
                    signed “S. England,” in ridicule of Ireland’s pretended discoveries.</p>
                <p part="N">11. <hi rend="italic">Imitations of Horace. Spirit of the Public
                        Journals,</hi> 1797. <hi rend="italic">Class. Jour.</hi> iv. 97.</p>
                <p part="N">12. The first four plays of Euripides appeared separately at different
                    periods. The <hi rend="italic">Hecuba,</hi> London, 1797, 8vo. Cambridge, 1802,
                    with a Supplement and additional notes; which were also published separately,
                    London, 1808. <hi rend="italic">Orestes,</hi> London, 1798, 1811. <hi
                        rend="italic">Phoeìiissae,</hi> London, 1799, 1811. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Medea,</hi> Cambridge, 1801; London, 1812. The four together, London,
                    1822.</p>
                <p part="N">13. <hi rend="italic">Collation</hi> of the Harleian manuscript of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> for the Grenville <hi rend="italic"
                        >Homer,</hi> Oxford, 1800, 4to; with some short notes. Reprinted, <hi
                        rend="italic">Class. Jour.</hi> ix.</p>
                <p part="N">14. Of the <hi rend="italic">Review of Wakefields Lucretius,</hi> in the
                        <hi rend="italic">British Critic</hi> for May 1801, the principal part
                    appears tobe Porson’s.</p>
                <p part="N">15. <hi rend="italic">A Letter signed by J. N. Dawes, Monthly Mag.</hi>
                    Dec. 1802, on some Greek constructions; admitting also an inaccuracy of his own
                    with respect to a hiatus, pointed out by Mr. C. Falconer.</p>
                <p part="N">16. <hi rend="italic">A Letter to Professor</hi> 7)αZzcZ, dated
                    September, 1803; <hi rend="italic">Mus.</hi><hi rend="italic">Crit.</hi> i. p.
                    326; in answer to some remarks published in the Professor’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Collectanea</hi><hi rend="italic">Majora;</hi> with an Epigram respecting
                    Hermann, in Greek and in English.</p>
                <p part="N">17. <hi rend="italic">Herodotus,</hi> Edinburgh, 1806. Person corrected
                    tlιe press for the first volume.</p>
                <p part="N">18. <hi rend="italic">Supplement to sωne Indices, Tracts</hi> χχχvi.</p>
                <p part="N">19∙ It is well known that Person bestowed considerable pains on the
                    restoration of the text of the <hi rend="italic">Rosetta Stone.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">His <hi rend="italic">Supplements</hi> were added to the plates engraved
                    by the Society of Antiquaries; and they also appear amongst his <hi
                        rend="italic">Tracts,</hi> xxxvii. In Dr. Clarke’s <hi rend="italic">Greek
                        Marbles,</hi> Cambridge, 1809, 8vo, we find a translation of this
                    inscription, communicated to the editor by Porson, and printed from “a <hi
                        rend="italic">corrected copy</hi> in his own beautiful handwriting.” But we
                    may here venture to apply Porson’s favourite remark on the facility of
                    transposition, and to read “a <hi rend="italic">copy corrected</hi> in his own
                    writing,” that is, on the margin of Mr. Gough’s translation, as published in <hi
                        rend="italic">Duands Coins.</hi> For the whole is very negligently
                    performed; and it is not a little remarkable that this translation, which was at
                    least approved by Porson, is decidedly less accurate than the Latin translation
                    of Heync, as appears from the investigation ofthc enchorial inscription
                    published in the sixth number of the <hi rend="italic">Museum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Criticum.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">20. A variety of Porson’s fugitive and miscellaneous pieces have
                    reappeared at different times in the <hi rend="italic">Classical Journal.
                        Authors cited by the Scholiast on Plato,</hi> ii. 619, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tracts,</hi> xxxviii. <hi rend="italic">The Epitaph,</hi> iii. 233; more
                    correctly than in the <hi rend="italic">Tracts,</hi> but still with a gross
                    error in the punctuation of the last line, which stands, in a manuscript copy of
                    his own, <hi rend="italic">Υtθvηχ</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> ó <hi
                        rend="italic">8η</hi><hi rend="italic">τάχιστα πάσχοντ οι</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">'γαθοl.</hi> This reading, though not very elegant, is at
                    least more defensible, than to make <hi rend="italic">πaσχeιv</hi> alone signify
                    to die, and a phrase to end with ó <hi rend="italic">8η.</hi> A <hi
                        rend="italic">Charade</hi> in Latin, vii. 248. Some <hi rend="italic">Notes
                        on AEschylus,</hi> vii. 456; viii. 15, 181; x. 114. <hi rend="italic">A
                        property of the lines</hi> employed in the 47 th proposition of the first
                    book of <hi rend="italic">Euclid,</hi> p. 401. <hi rend="italic">Notes on
                        Apollonius</hi><hi rend="italic">Rhodius,</hi> xviii. 370.</p>
                <p part="N">21. <hi rend="italic">Adversaria.</hi> Cambridge, 1812,8vo, consisting
                    of <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on the Greek Poets, selected from his
                    manuscripts, and arranged by Professor Monk and Mr. C. J. Bloomfield. The first
                    article is an interesting <hi rend="italic">Lecture on Euripides,</hi> delivered
                    upon his appointment to the Greek Professorship. It is followed by a few
                    miscellaneous observations, and by a large collection of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Notes</hi> on Athenaeus, on Euripides, on the <hi rend="italic">Fragments
                        of the Tragic and Comic Poets,</hi> on Stobaeus, and on a variety of poets
                    of miscellaneous descriptions. The volume was reprinted at Amsterdam, without
                    any alteration, but the sale of the foreign edition has never been permitted in
                    Great Britain.</p>
                <p part="N">22. <hi rend="italic">Tracts and Miscellaneous Criticisms,</hi>
                    collected and arranged by the Rev. T. Kidd, Μ. A. London, 1815, 8vo. Besides the
                    articles already noticed as reprinted in this volume, there are a few <hi
                        rend="italic">Notes on Dawes’s</hi><hi rend="italic">Miscellanea
                        Critica,</hi> not before published, No. 51. There are also some
                    supplementary pages of <hi rend="italic">Simplicius and Cebes,</hi> reprinted by
                    Person, for the use of his friends, as restored by Schweighäuser. The want of
                    this leaf of the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Simplicius</hi> had given rise
                    to the mistaken assertion that Xenophon was proclaimed a public benefactor at
                    the Olympic Games, on occasion of the return of the ten thousand. There are
                    likewise some miscellaneous <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Athenaeus, Menander,
                    and Philemon, Aristides, Pausanias, and the lexicographers, and some <hi
                        rend="italic">Indices of</hi> authors quoted by the Scholiasts.</p>
                <p part="N">23. <hi rend="italic">Notae</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Aristophanem,</hi> quibus Plutum comoediam adjecit P. P.
                    Dobree. Cambridge, 1820, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N">24. Gaisford <hi rend="italic">Lectiones Platonicae.</hi> Accedunt R.
                    Porsoni <hi rend="italic">Notae ad Pausaniam.</hi> Oxford, 1820, 8vo.'</p>
                <p part="N">25. <hi rend="italic">Photii</hi><hi rend="italic">Lexicon.</hi>
                    Cambridge, 1822, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N">To attempt to form a just estimate of the merit of such a man as Porson,
                    without servilely following the dictates of common fame, or blindly adopting the
                    opinions of others, is a task of no small difficulty, even to one who had the
                    advantage of his personal acquaintance for the last twenty years of his life.
                    But it may safely be conceded to common fame and to partial friendship, that he
                    was one of the greatest men, and the very greatest critic, of his own or of any
                    other age. “Nothing came amiss,” says Mr. Weston, “to his memory. He would set a
                    child right in his twopenny fable book, repeat the whole of the moral tale of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Dean of</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193538238?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-8238-0451"/><hi
                        rend="italic">Badajoz,</hi> a page of Athenaeus on cups, or of Eustathius on
                    Homer, even though he did every thing to impair his mental faculties.” It
                    cannot, however, be denied, that the talents, and even the industry, that he
                    possessed, might have made him a much greater man, had they been employed in
                    some other department of human intellect. He might <hi rend="italic"
                        >probably</hi> have been as great a statesman or as great a general as he
                    was a scholar, and in these capacities his acquirements would have affected the
                    interests of a much greater multitude of his fellow-creatures, than can ever be
                    benefited by the fruits of his erudition; and he might <hi rend="italic"
                        >possibly</hi> have gained more popularity as an orator or a poet, than his
                    refined investigations of grammar and prosody could ever procure him, although
                    it is not by any means certain that his fancy and invention could have been
                    rendered by anv cultivation at all comparable to his memory and acuteness. But
                    as far as regards the possession of a combination of the faculties which he did
                    cultivate, he appears to have been decidedly the most successful of any man on
                    record in the same department. On the other hand, it must be admitted that the
                    subjects of his pursuits were in their nature incapable of raising a man to the
                    first rank amongst the permanent benefactors of the human race; and, if we
                    calmly consider the ultimate objects of prosody and metre, it will appear almost
                    unfair to allow the discoverer of the prosodiacal rules, adopted by the ancient
                    poets in their mélodrames and choruses, to rank so very high amongst the
                    luminaries of an age, and yet to look down, with so much contempt as we are
                    accustomed to do, on the character of a modern <hi rend="italic">Dieu</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de la daìise,</hi> notwithstanding that he thought himself the
                    third great man of his day, with Vol taire and the King of Prussia, for having
                    given soul and sentiment to the measures and movements of the choric
                    representations of the present times.</p>
                <p part="N">Amongst the talents ofPorson, however, which were so far superior to the
                    importance of the objects on which they were employed, we ought not, perhaps, to
                    consider his remarkable strength of memory as the most to be envied, since many
                    persons who have been possessed of singular and almost miraculous, not to say
                    morbid, memories, have been but little distinguished by any other faculty. It
                    appears to be possible that a memory may in itself be even too retentive for
                    real practical utility, as if of too microscopic a nature; and it seems to be by
                    a wise and benevolent, though by no means an obvious arrangement of a Creative
                    Providence, that a certain degree of oblivion becomes a most useful instrument
                    in the advancement of human knowledge, enabling us readily to look back on the
                    prominent features only of various objects and occurrences, and to class them
                    and reason upon them, by the help of this involuntary kind of abstraction and
                    generalization, with incomparably greater facility than we could do, if we
                    retained the whole detail of what had been once but slightly impressed on our
                    minds. It is thus, for example, in physic, that the experienced practitioner
                    learns at length to despise the relation of individual symptoms, and particular
                    cases, on which alone the empiric insists, and to feel the value of the
                    Hippocratic system of “attending more to the prognostic than the diagnostic
                    features of disease which, to a younger student, appears to be perfect
                    imbecility. And it is perhaps for some similar reason that many persons, besides
                    Barnes, “of happy memory,” have had to wait long in darkness for “the day of
                    judgment.” But it must be repeated, that Person’s judgment and acuteness were
                    really almost paramount to his memory; and with the addition of these faculties,
                    his memory naturally rendered him capable of much that would have been
                    impossible without it.</p>
                <p part="N">The respect that is justly due to classical learning has frequently been
                    exaggerated in this country, partly, perhaps, on account of the awe which is
                    naturally entertained, by an ingenuous mind, for its instructors in the earliest
                    studies, by which it is advanced towards maturity. And classical learning having
                    most wisely been placed by our ancestors the foremost, in the order of a liberal
                    education, which is most commonly adopted in Great Britain, a personal as well
                    as a general respect has been involuntarily paid to the characters of the
                    individuals concerned, and to the dignity of all those who are engaged in
                    similar occupations; besides that, the means being, by a most frequent
                    inattention of the human mind, confounded with the end for which they are
                    sought, the words and syllables, and the phrases and measures of the Greek and
                    Latin authors have often been the almost frivolous occupation of a valuable
                    life, instead of that of a few of the years of boyhood, which it was intended to
                    devote to them, and which could not have been so well engaged in any other way.
                    It is, however, wholly unjust to stigmatize the study of the classics, and of
                    languages in general, as being confined to words instead of things; for it is
                    utterly impossible that words can be learned, without the acquisition of a
                    considerable degree of knowledge of the things to which they relate, and of the
                    historical facts which they have been employed to express, and without an
                    involuntary modelling of the mind to the elegance and elevation of sentiment,
                    which pervade the works of those authors who are habitually put into the hands
                    of boys in the course of their elementary studies; an acquirement which is of
                    still greater value to the orator and the statesman, than the command of
                    language, and facility of expression, and beauty of imagery, and power of
                    reasoning, which he derives from a perfect familiarity with the great masters of
                    antiquity. But granting all the respect that can possibly be claimed for ancient
                    literature, we cannot but lament that such a man as Porson should have lived and
                    laboured for nearly half a century, and yet have left little or nothing to the
                    world that was truly and originally his own.</p>
                <p part="N">After the full admission of the very high rank which is due to the
                    comparative merits of Person’s talents and acquirements, it may be thought
                    almost idle, if not invidious, to dwell on any trifling exceptions to their
                    magnitude. But it is, in fact, of high importance to the progress of human
                    knowledge, to be aware of the degree in which the first of mankind are liable to
                    error. The admission of the few errors of Newton himself, is at least of as much
                    importance to his followers in science, as the history of the progress of his
                    real discoveries. And it is with reason that the detection of an error in such a
                    man is considered as almost paramount to the establishment of a new fact. The
                    English critics have been reproached, and not without some foundation, as paying
                    too servile a deference to Person’s opinions; and it seems to have been very
                    generally believed amongst them, that it was scarcely possible for him to commit
                    an error or an oversight.</p>
                <p part="N">Although Porson was in many respects irregular, and often idle, or even
                    intemperate, yet what he did perform as a critic, may be allowed to leave a
                    large balance, at the end of his life, in favour of his general industry, when
                    compared with that of most of his countrymen. It has indeed been asserted, and
                    perhaps with truth, <hi rend="italic">(Classical Journal,</hi> xxi.) that “with
                    things Porson appears to have possessed but a very inconsiderate acquaintance;
                    and not a trace is to be found amidst his writings, of that combination of
                    universal encyclopaediacal knowledge with language learning which is so
                    abundantly found in the <hi rend="italic">Dissertation on</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Phalaris,</hi> and the countless pages of Scaliger, Salmasius, and
                    Casaubon.” Certainly, however, neither Salmasius nor Casaubon, with all their
                    learning, much less Scaliger, with all his industry and parade, nor even Bentley
                    himself, with all his talent and acuteness, was at all comparable to Person in
                    his own department, that is, as a sound, and accurate, and refined Greek
                    critic.</p>
                <p part="N">But it must be confessed, that at Cambridge, even although Porson had
                    resolved to make the classics his principal study, and although there had not
                    yet been many instances<pb break="no" facs="nls:193538251?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-8251-0452"/> of senior wranglers, who were also senior
                    medallists, it was scarcely reputable for a man, with his undeniable abilities,
                    to be only the twenty-first of his year in mathematics. Amongst the literary
                    objects also, which afterwards engaged his attention, he might easily have found
                    time for the study of some of the modern languages; and he might have derived
                    essential benefit from it on many occasions of critical research. He had,
                    indeed, read a good deal of French, but very little Italian. Hc had studied the
                    Anglo-Saxon, buthe knew nothing of the kindred dialects of the north of Europe,
                    in which it is preserved almost entire; and he was wholly unacquainted with
                    Oriental literature. He might have profited materially by some of these studies,
                    in deriving from them a clearer conception of the distinctions of the tenses
                    than he seems to have possessed, and he might have enlightened us in no small
                    degree, with respect to the history of languages and of nations, by such
                    etymological investigations as his comprehensive mind, thus employed, would have
                    rendered him peculiarly capable of pursuing with success.</p>
                <p part="N">It has been candidly and very truly admitted by a rival critic in
                    Germany, that Porson committed fewer errors than almost any other person; but it
                    is right to be aware that he has now and then committed some errors, even where
                    he would have been expected to be the most correct. There is, for example, a
                    very strange oversight in one of the criticisms contained in his early review of
                    Weston’s <hi rend="italic">Hermesi-ananax,</hi> which implies a palpable blunder
                    with respect to the gender of a participle, <hi rend="italic">Zωpδv μeτpoυσα
                        ßvâ&gt;u ττopφυptηs Λυσβιov éè viλov,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> the cup
                    of purple glass, which <hi rend="italic">measured</hi> the fragrant wine and
                    even in a subsequent correction of the same passage, published in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Adversaria,</hi> he has changed the gender of an adjective in
                    a way that is at least very unusual, if not wholly without example, <hi
                        rend="italic">µerpoôv ðvótvra.</hi> A mere omission, in a criticism on
                    another author, would scarcely be called an error in an ordinary person; but in
                    such a critic as Porson, it is very remarkable that he should have neglected to
                    notice, in his catalogue of the <hi rend="italic">Errors of</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Le Clerc,</hi> omitted by Bentley, <hi rend="italic">(Ada</hi>
                    p. 291,) the grossest of all Le Clerc’s blunders, which is the quotation of the
                    word <hi rend="italic">Hypophauli</hi> cr <hi rend="italic">semibarbarous,</hi>
                    from Pollux, with the translation <hi rend="italic">Sartagines,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">frying pans</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> whilst the real text
                    of Pollux simply and plainly states that the <hi rend="italic">Teganisrni</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">fid-cassations,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hippocomus</hi><hi rend="italic">Menander,</hi> is <hi rend="italic">a
                        semibarbarous word.</hi> These instances, which have occurred in a very
                    cursory perusal of some of Porson’s works, would certainly not deserve to be
                    noticed in a general sketch of his character, any otherwise than as exceptions
                    to bis perfect infallibility.</p>
                <p part="N">It can scarcely be considered as an imperfection in the constitution of
                    Porson’s mind, that he wanted that amiable vanity, which is gratified by the
                    approbation even of the most inconsiderable, and which delights to choose for
                    its objects the most innocent and the most helpless of those who are casually
                    present in society. It has been observed that he would neither give nor take
                    praise; and when he was told that somebody had called him a giant in literature,
                    he remarked that a man had no right to tell the height of that which he could
                    not measure. In fact, having learned “to know how little can be known,” it is
                    not surprising that he found himself “without a second, and without a judge ;”
                    and that he was unwilling to affect a community of sentiment, and an interchange
                    of approbation with those whose acquirements and opinions he felt that he had a
                    right to despise. It might have been wiser, in some instances, to conceal this
                    feeling; but, on the other hand, he had perhaps occasion for something of the
                    habit of retreating into his conscious dignity, from his deficiency in those
                    general powers of ephemeral conversation, which are so valuable in mixed
                    societies; for, with all his learning and all his memory, he was by no means
                    prominent as a talker. He had neither the inclination nor the qualifications to
                    be a fascinating story teller, or to become habitually a parasite at the tables
                    of the affluent; but he was the delight of a limited circle of chosen friends,
                    possessing talent enough to appreciate his merits, and to profit by the
                    information that he afforded them.</p>
                <p part="N">There has not yet been a life of Person that has collected all the
                    particulars that would deserve to be recorded by a biographer, who undertook the
                    task on an extensive scale; but of detached documents there is no deficiency.
                    Mr. Kidd has pointed out almost every work in which his name has been mentioned.
                    The most material articles relating to him will be enumerated here.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Morning Chronicle,</hi> 6th October 1808. <hi
                        rend="italic">A Short Account of the late Mr. Pickard Porson, with some
                        particulars relative to his extraordinary talents</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> by an admirer of great genius (the Rev. S. Weston,) <hi
                        rend="italic">HΑηκiτι πιiπrαιve</hi><hi rend="italic">κόρσιον,</hi> Look for
                    nothing beyond him. London, 1808, 8vo. Republished, with some additions, under
                    the title of <hi rend="italic">Porsoni-ana, or</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Seraps</hi><hi rend="italic">from Porson’s Rich Feast,</hi> London, 1814,
                    8vo. Bloomfield’s <hi rend="italic">Sapphic Ode, Class. Journ.</hi> i. 1. <hi
                        rend="italic">Some anonymous Iambics,</hi> p. 81. <hi rend="italic">Sale of
                        his Libraiy,</hi> p. 385. <hi rend="italic">Athenaeurn,</hi> iv. 426, 521;
                    v. 55. <hi rend="italic">Class. Journ.</hi> ix. 386. Savage’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Librarian,</hi> i. 274. <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine,</hi>
                    lxxviii. <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine. Dr. Adam Clarkds Narrative. Class.
                        Journ.</hi> ii. 720. <hi rend="italic">Correspondence of Wakefield and
                        Fox,</hi> London, 1813, 8vo. <hi rend="italic">Grech Epitaph, Class.
                        Journ.</hi> xxiii. 179; making Porsōnum equal to Newtönuá. Aikin’s <hi
                        rend="italic">General Biography,</hi> X. London, 1815, 4to. Kidd’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Imperfect Outline. Tracts,</hi> 1815. Chalmers’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary,</hi> XXV. London, 1816. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">l. l.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
