<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-0708-0641-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PROJECTILES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jq0t035">Tanning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b03x">Constants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rd9g">Robin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj78012">Calculators</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142827">Tanning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1001952">Logging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098971">Robins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193540708?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PROJECTILES</label>.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> term <hi rend="italic">Projectiles</hi> is
                    applied to that part of mechanical philosophy which treats of the motion of
                    bodies anyhow projected from the surface of the earth, and influenced by the
                    action of terrestrial gravity.</p>
                <p part="N">It is demonstrated in the physical part of astronomy, that a body so
                    projected must describe a conic section, having the centre of the earth in one
                    focus; and that it will describe round that focus areas proportional to the
                    times. It follows also from the principles of that science, that if the velocity
                    of projection exceed 36,700 feet in a second, the body (if not resisted by the
                    air) would describe a hyperbola; if the velocity be just 36,700 feet in a
                    second, the body would describe a parabola; and a body projected with a smaller
                    velocity than this would describe an ellipse. In the first case, if projected
                    directly upwards, it would never return, but proceed for ever, its velocity
                    continually diminishing, but never becoming less than an assignable portion of
                    the excess of the initial velocity above 36,700 feet in a second. In the second
                    case it would never return; its velocity would diminish without end, but never
                    be extinguished. In the third case it would proceed till its velocity was
                    reduced to an assignable portion of the difference between 36,700 feet and its
                    initial velocity, and would then return, regaining its velocity by the same
                    degrees and in the same places as it lost it. These are necessary consequences
                    of a gravity directed to the centre of the earth, and inversely proportional to
                    the square of the distance. But in the greatest projections that we are able to
                    make, the gravitations are so nearly equal, andin directions so nearly parallel,
                    that it would be ridiculous affectation to pay any regard to the deviations from
                    equality and parallelism. A bullet rising a mile above the surface of the earth
                    loses only <hi rend="subscript"> 2δ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript"> δσ</hi> of its weight, and a horizontal range of 4 miles
                    makes only 4' of deviation from parallelism.</p>
                <p part="N">Let us therefore assume gravitation as equal and parallel. The errors
                    arising from this assumption are quite insensible in all the uses which can be
                    made of this theory.</p>
                <p part="N">Gravity must be considered by us as a constant or uniform accelerating
                    or retarding force, according as it produces the descent, or retards the ascent,
                    of a body. A constant or invariable accelerating force is one which produces an
                    uniform acceleration; that is, which in equal times produces equal increments of
                    velocity, and therefore produces increments of velocity proportional to the
                    times in which they are produced. Forces are of themselves imperceptible, and
                    are only sensible in their effects; and they have no measure but the effect, or
                    what <hi rend="italic">measures</hi> the effect; and every thing which we can
                    discover with regard to those measures, we may affirm with regard to the things
                    of which we assume them as the measures. Hence this proposition :—</p>
                <p part="N">The motion of a falling body, or of a body projected directly downwards,
                    is uniformly accelerated; and that of a body projected directly upwards is
                    uniformly retarded; that is, the acquired velocities are as the times in which
                    they are acquired by falling, and the extinguished velocities are as the times
                    in which they are extinguished. The following consequences are readily deduced
                    from the proposition now enunciated:</p>
                <p part="N">1. If bodies simply fall, not being projected downwards by an external
                    force, the times of the falls are proportional to the final velocities; and the
                    times of ascents, which terminate by the action of gravity alone, are
                    proportional to the initial velocities.</p>
                <p part="N">2. The spaces described by a heavy body falling from rest are as the
                    squares of the acquired velocities; and the differences of these spaces are as
                    the differences of the squares of the acquired velocities; and, on the other
                    hand, the heights to which bodies projected upwards will rise, before their
                    motions are extinguished, are as the squares of the initial velocities.</p>
                <p part="N">3. The spaces described by falling bodies are proportional to the
                    squares of the times from the beginning of the fall; and the spaces described by
                    bodies projected directly upwards are as the squares of the times of the
                    ascents.</p>
                <p part="N">4. The space described by a body falling from rest is one-half of the
                    space which the body would have uniformly described in the same time, with the
                    velocity acquired by the fall. And the height to which a body will rise, in
                    opposition to the action of gravity, is one-half of the space which it would
                    uniformly describe in the same time with the initial velocity.</p>
                <p part="N">In like manner, the difference of the spaces which a falling or rising
                    body describes in any equal successive parts of its fall or rise, is one-half of
                    the space which it would uniformly describe in the same time with the difference
                    of the initial and final velocities.</p>
                <p part="N">The last proposition will be more conveniently expressed for our purpose
                    as follows:</p>
                <p part="N">A body moving uniformly during the time of any fall with the velocity
                    acquired thereby, will in that time describe a space double of that fall; and a
                    body projected directly upwards will rise to a height which is one-half of the
                    space which it would describe in the time of its ascent with the initial
                    velocity of projection, if the motion continued uniform.</p>
                <p part="N">It is a matter of observation and experience, that a heavy body falls 16
                    feet and one inch English measure in a second of time; and therefore acquires
                    the velocity of 32 feet 2 inches per second. This cannot be ascertained
                    directly, with the precision that is necessary. A second is too small a portion
                    of time to be exactly measured and compared with the space described; but the
                    observation is made with the greatest accuracy by comparing the motion of a
                    falling body with that of a pendulum. The time of a vibration is to the time of
                    falling through half the length of the pendulum, as the circumference of a
                    circle is to its diameter. The length of a pendulum can be ascertained with
                    great precision; and in this way the space fallen through in a second has been
                    accurately measured.</p>
                <p part="N">As all forces are ascertained by the accelerations which they produce,
                    they are conveniently measured by comparing their accelerations with the
                    acceleration of gravity. This therefore has been assumed by all the later and
                    best writers on mechanical philosophy as the unit by which every other force is
                    measured. It gives us a perfectly distinct notion of the force which retains the
                    moon in its orbit, when we say it is the 3600th part of the weight of the moon
                    at the surface of the earth. We mean by this, that if a bullet were weighed at
                    the surface of the earth by a spring steelyard, and pulled the spring out to the
                    mark 3600; if the body were then taken to the distance of the moon, it would
                    pull the spring out only to the mark 1. And we make this assertion on the
                    authority of our having observed that a body at the distance of the moon falls
                    from that distance <hi rend="subscript"> 5δ</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                        1</hi><hi rend="subscript"> δδ</hi> th part of 16 feet in a second. We do
                    not therefore compare the <hi rend="italic">forces,</hi> which are imperceptible
                    things; we compare the accelerations, which are at the same time their effects
                    and their measures.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540721?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0721-0642"/>
                <p part="N">Philosophers have therefore been at great pains to determine with
                    precision the fall of heavy bodies, in order to have an exact measure of the
                    accelerating power of terrestrial gravity. Now we must here observe, that this
                    measure may be taken in two ways; we may take the space through which the heavy
                    body falls in a second; or we may take the velocity which it acquires in
                    consequence of gravity having acted on it during a second. The last is the
                    proper measure, for it is the immediate effect on the body. The action of
                    gravity has changed the state of the body by giving it a determination to motion
                    downwards; and this both points out the nature, and the degree or intensity, of
                    the force of gravity. The space described in a second by falling, is not an
                    invariable measure; for, in the successive seconds, the body falls through 16,
                    48, 80, 112, &amp;c. fcet, but the changes of the body’s state in each second is
                    the same. At the beginning it had no determination to move with any appreciable
                    velocity; at the end of the first second it had a determination by which it
                    would have gone on for eVer (had no subsequent force acted on it) at the rate of
                    32 -feet per second. At the end of the next second, it had a determination by
                    which it would have moved for ever, at the rate of 64 feet per second. At the
                    cnd of the third second, it had a determination by which it would have moved for
                    ever, at the rate of 96 feet per second, &amp;c. The differences of these
                    determinations are constant, and amount to 32 feet per second. This is therefore
                    the indication and proper measure of the constant or invariable force of
                    gravity. The space fallen through in the first second is of use only as it is
                    one-half of the measure of this determination; and as halves have the proportion
                    of their wholes, different accelerating forces may be safely affirmed to be in
                    the proportion of the spaces through which they uniformly impel bodies in the
                    same time. But we should always recollect, that this is but one-half of the true
                    measure of the accelerating force.</p>
                <p part="N">We now proceed to investigate the formulae of rectilinear motion.</p>
                <p part="N">Let <hi rend="italic">X</hi> b 3 the space described by a moving body in
                    a certain time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and «the velocity acquired at the end
                    of the time <hi rend="italic">t.</hi> When the motion is uniform, the space
                    described is in the compound ratio of the velocity and the time, therefore <hi
                        rend="italic">x~vt.</hi> In the case of accelerated or retarded motion, the
                    velocity varies by infinitely small degrees, and we may therefore assume it to
                    be uniform during an infinitely small portion of time <hi rend="italic">dt.</hi>
                    But the space over which the body moves in the time <hi rend="italic">dt,</hi>
                    with the uniform velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> is <hi rend="italic"
                        >vdt</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> therefore the increment of the space in
                    the time <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> being <hi rend="italic">(lx dx,</hi> we have
                        <hi rend="italic">dx=υdt,</hi> whence <hi rend="italic">v=~τ ∙ dt</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Let <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> = the force which accelerates or retards
                    the moving body at the end of the time <hi rend="italic">t.</hi> The force &lt;p
                    is supposed to act in the straight line in which the body is moving at the
                    instant; and as an accelerating force becomes a retarding force by changing the
                    sign from positive to negative, it is usually called, in both cases, the <hi
                        rend="italic">accelerating force.</hi> In order to obtain the measure of
                    &lt;ρ, we must consider the effect it produces. Since the motion may be regarded
                    as uniform during an infinitely small portion of time <hi rend="italic">dt,</hi>
                    if <hi rend="italic">v</hi> be the velocity at the end of the time <hi
                        rend="italic">t,</hi> then <hi rend="italic">vA-dv</hi> will be the velocity
                    at the end of the time <hi rend="italic">tA-dt,</hi> so that <hi rend="italic"
                        >dv</hi> is the augmentation of velocity produced by the accelerating force
                        <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> in the time <hi rend="italic">dt.</hi> Assume F to
                    be a constant force, which produces a velocity = V in the portion of time which
                    is taken as unit; then the velocity produced by the force F in the time <hi
                        rend="italic">dt</hi> is Vc⅛, and we have this proportion, <hi rend="italic"
                        >φ</hi>: F:: <hi rend="italic">dv</hi>: Vc⅛, the forces being measured by
                    the velocities which they <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> communicate to a given
                    body in the same time. Now, suppose F to be the unit of force, and V the unit of
                    velocity, the proportion becomes <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>: 1:: <hi rend="italic"
                        >dv</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">dt,</hi> whence <hi
                        rend="italic">φ=,-.</hi><hi rend="italic">dt</hi></p>
                <p part="N">On differentiating the equation <hi rend="italic superscript"> υ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">~~^ν</hi><hi rend="superscript"> wc</hi> get whence &lt;p= The
                    relations between the velocity, the space described, the time, and the
                    accelerating force, are consequently given by the three following equations, of
                    which the last is a consequence of the other two, viz.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">dx dv d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ν</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >=α-e</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> φ</hi><hi rend="italic">=Λ'
                        *=*≡∙</hi> ω</p>
                <p part="N">Suppose the accelerating force to be terrestrial gravity, and let it be
                    denoted by <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> We have then, from the third <hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi> of the above equations — <hi rend="italic">—g</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> the integral of which is <hi rend="italic">dx</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-=-gt,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">v∙=zgt</hi> (which requires no correction,
                    since <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> vanish together). We
                    have also <hi rend="italic">dx-gtdt∙,</hi> whence by a second integration <hi
                        rend="italic">x∙=⅛gt</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> which is also the complete
                    integral, since <hi rend="italic">X</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> vanish
                    together. This last equation gives <hi rend="italic">2gχ-g</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">-v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>; whence
                    r=√(2^Λ). We have therefore the following expressions for the velocity, the
                    time, and the space described, or height from which a body must fall <hi
                        rend="italic">in vacuo</hi> to acquire a given velocity, and which we shall
                    denote by <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> viz.</p>
                <p part="N">I. <hi rend="italic">v = gt</hi> = √(25rΛ),</p>
                <p part="N">- Π∙&lt; = i=√⅛</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">9 9</hi><hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> ∙&lt;=⅛=^ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∙</p>
                <p part="N">It is found by experiment that the height through which a heavy body
                    descends by the force <hi rend="subscript"> -</hi> of gravity in a vacuum, in a
                    second of time, is 16 <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ⅛ English feet. For
                    convenience, we shall call this 16 feet. Assuming, therefore, one second as the
                    unit of time, the last equation gives &lt;∕=2Λ=32 feet; and the three equations
                    become, in respect of any time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and height <hi
                        rend="italic">k,</hi></p>
                <p part="N">I. <hi rend="italic">v -</hi> 32i = √(64Λ)=8√¼</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="superscript"> 11</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> = ⅛ =
                    i√¼</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">'</hi><hi rend="italic">ν</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">III. Λ=-- <hi rend="italic">= 16t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">64</p>
                <p part="N">To give some examples of the use of these formulae, let it be
                    required,</p>
                <p part="N">1. To find the time of falling through 256 feet. Here 4=256, <hi
                        rend="italic">f</hi> 256=16, and 16-4-4=4. Therefore <hi rend="italic"
                        >t—4</hi> seconds.</p>
                <p part="N">2. To find the velocity acquired by falling four seconds. Here <hi
                        rend="italic">t—4,</hi> 32 × 4=128 feet per second.</p>
                <p part="N">3. To find the velocity acquired by falling 625 feet. Here 4=625, √4=25,
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">8</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> λ</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">∕4=200</hi> feet per second,</p>
                <p part="N">4. To find the height to which a body will rise when projected with the
                    velocity of 56 feet per second, or the height through which a body must fall to
                    acquire this velocity. In this case we have</p>
                <p part="N">56, 56÷8=7, = √4, 7 <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> =4, =49 feet.</p>
                <p part="N">or 56 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =3136, 3136÷64=49 feet.</p>
                <p part="N">5. Suppose a body projected directly downwards with the velocity of 10
                    feet per second; what will be its velocity after four seconds? In four seconds
                    it will have acquired, by the action of gravity, the velocity of 4 × 32, or 128
                    feet, and therefore its whole velocity will be 138 feet per second.</p>
                <p part="N">6. To find how far it will have moved, compound its motion<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193540734?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0734-0643"/> of
                    projection, which will be 40 feet in four seconds, with the motion which gravity
                    alone would have given it in that time, which is 256 feet; and the whole motion
                    will be 296 feet.</p>
                <p part="N">7∙ Suppose the body projected, as in the 5th example, and that it is
                    required to determine the time it will take topass through 296 feet, and the
                    velocity it will have acquired.</p>
                <p part="N">Find the height <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> through which it must fall to
                    acquire the velocity of projection, 10 feet, and the time <hi rend="italic"
                        >t</hi> of falling from this height. Then find the time <hi rend="italic"
                        >t'</hi> of falling through the height 296 <hi rend="italic">A∙h,</hi> and
                    the velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> acquired by this fall. The time of
                    describing the 296 feet will be <hi rend="italic">tl</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi><hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v</hi> is the
                    velocity required.</p>
                <p part="N">These examples will suffice for the perpendicular ascents or descents of
                    heavy bodies, abstracting from the resistance of the air. We now proceed to
                    consider the motions of bodies projected obliquely. The subject is one of
                    considerable interest, as it forms the foundation of the theory of gunnery.</p>
                <p part="N">Let a body be projected from the point A (fig. 1.) in any direction AK
                    not perpendicular to the horizon, and with a given velocity <hi rend="italic"
                        >—a;</hi> it is required to determine the path of the body, and all the
                    circumstances of its motion.</p>
                <p part="N">Since gravity acts only in the vertical direction, and the body, after
                    being projected, is acted on by no other accelerating force, it is evident, in
                    the first place, that the whole of the trajectory, or path described by the
                    projectile, must be contained in the vertical plane which passes through AK. In
                    the second place, since the action of gravity is constant, the projectile must
                    describe a continuous curve, to which AK is a tangent at A. Through A draw AB
                    horizontal, and AH vertical, and let these lines be taken as the axes of the
                    rectangular co-ordinates to which the different points of the curve are
                    referred. Let P be the place of the projectile at the end of the time 7; draw
                    PQ. perpendicular to AB, and make <hi rend="smallcaps">AQ=z,</hi> PQ=y. The
                    object is now to find the equation of the trajectory by establishing a relation
                    between the co-ordinates <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >y.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Let the angle KAB, which the initial direction of the projectile makes
                    with the horizon, be denoted by A. As we abstract from the resistance of the
                    air, the motion in the direction AK is uniform, and proportional to the time <hi
                        rend="italic">t;</hi> and the velocity of projection being <hi rend="italic"
                        >a,</hi> the velocity in the direction AB (which is not affected by gravity)
                    is also uniform, and equal to <hi rend="italic">a</hi> cos A, therefore the
                    space passed over being equal to the product of the time by the velocity, we
                    have <hi rend="italic">χ-=∙a</hi> cos A. To find <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> we
                    must consider that the motion in the vertical direction is made up of two parts;
                    first, that which is due to the velocity of projection; and, second, that which
                    arises from the action of gravity. The velocity in the direction AH, independent
                    of gravity, is <hi rend="italic">a</hi> sin A; and therefore the space described
                    in that direction in the time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> is <hi rend="italic"
                        >ta</hi> sin A. But by the formula III. the space through which the body is
                    carried in the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> by the accelerating force of
                    gravity is <hi rend="italic">⅛gt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi>; and
                    as this is in the direction opposite to the former, it must be taken with the
                    negative sign. We have therefore <hi rend="italic">y==tα</hi> sin A— <hi
                        rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">gt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        i</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> The values of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">y</hi> are thus given in terms of the time; and on
                    eliminating <hi rend="italic">t</hi> between the two equations, viz.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">x=ta</hi> cos A, <hi rend="italic">y*≈ta</hi> sin
                    A—½yi <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, (2)</p>
                <p part="N">we shall have the equation of the trajectory. The first gives <hi
                        rend="italic">t=zχ-L-α</hi> cos A, on substituting which in the second,
                    there results</p>
                <p part="N">A 1 <hi rend="superscript"> X</hi><hi rend="italic">u==χ</hi> tan A— <hi
                        rend="italic">⅛a</hi><hi rend="italic">— —</hi><hi rend="italic">-,</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> j</hi> ½z <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">which is an equation to the Apollonian parabola, having its axis
                    parallel to the ordinates <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> and its parameter equal to
                    ½5 <hi rend="superscript"> f</hi> ÷α <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A.</p>
                <p part="N">By the formula I. we have α= <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> ∕ (2y7z),
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">cP=2glι</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and on
                    substituting this value of <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> the equation becomes <hi rend="italic"
                        >y—x</hi> tan A— — <hi rend="superscript"> ¾</hi>-=. (3)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> 44 cos A</p>
                <p part="N">Having found the equation of the curve, it is easy to assign its
                    position in the plane of the co-ordinates. Let B be the point in which the
                    parabola meets the horizontal line drawn through A, C the vertex of the
                    parabola, and let CD be perpendicular to AB. The point C is thus found. Let <hi
                        rend="italic">ô</hi> be the angle which the tangent to the curve at any
                    point P makes with the axis AB; we have then for any curve whatever, tan <hi
                        rend="italic">ð dx=dy.</hi> At the vertex, the tangent becomes parallel to
                    AB, consequently <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> vanishes, and we have —0</p>
                <p part="N">Now on differentiating the equation (2), we find tf?/ . <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi> ~ — tan A—— —; <hi rend="italic">dx 2h</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> si</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">therefore at the vertex, 0 = tan A — ——≡-r, whence 24 cos A</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Λ!=27z</hi> cos A sin A. Substituting this value of
                        <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in equation (3), we get, after reduction, <hi
                        rend="italic">y—h</hi> sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A. Hence denoting
                    the co-ordinates of the vertex by α ’ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and y <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> that is, making AD=z <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>,
                    DC==y <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, we have the two equations to determine ∙r
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y,,</hi> namely <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >=2h</hi> cos A sin A, <hi rend="italic">yp=h</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A. ‘ (4)</p>
                <p part="N">To find the point B in which the projectile meets the horizontal line
                    AB, it is only necessary to make <hi rend="italic">y-^</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi> equation (3). This gives
                    0=afran A— <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi>-.; whence <hi rend="superscript
                        smallcaps"> n v j o</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">47zcos*A</hi></p>
                <p part="N">47z cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A tan A=x, and therefore
                    zrz=AB=4Λ cos A sin A=27z sin 2A. (5)</p>
                <p part="N">From this equation it appears that when the velocity of projection α, or
                    the height <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> corresponding to that velocity, is given,
                    the line AB, which is called the <hi rend="italic">amplitude</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">horizontal range,</hi> is a maximum when the angle of
                    elevation A (that is, KAB) is equal to 45°, for then sin 2A=l. In this case we
                    have AB=2∕z, that is to say, when a ball is projected with an angle of elevation
                    equal to 45 degrees, the amplitude or range on the horizontal plane is equal to
                    twice the height from which a body must fall in order to acquire a velocity
                    equal to the velocity of projection.</p>
                <p part="N">To find the velocity at any point P of the trajectory, in the direction
                    of the tangent at that point, let <hi rend="italic">z</hi> denote the arc AP,
                    then, the velocity being equal to the increment of the space passed over,
                    divided by the increment of the time, <hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dz dx dx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">+ dy</hi> wc have <hi rend="italic">v=</hi>-,-, whence <hi
                        rend="italic">v = τ~y~</hi><hi rend="italic">τ-</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    ’ <hi rend="italic">∙</hi> Now, on <hi rend="italic">dt dt</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">~dd</hi> differentiating the two
                    equations (2), we get</p>
                <p part="N">&lt;7∙r <hi rend="italic subscript"> a</hi><hi rend="italic">dy</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">——a</hi> cos A√ <hi rend="italic">^gf ~</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> α</hi> sι∏ A— <hi rend="italic">gt,</hi> the squares of which
                    being added together, give the following relation between the velocity and the
                    time, viz.</p>
                <p part="N">v <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — <hi
                        rend="italic">2agt</hi> sin A +y7 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p part="N">At the point B we have a?=AB=4/z cos A sin A by equation (5), and <hi
                        rend="italic">y—0.</hi> But from the equation <hi rend="italic">x=ta</hi>
                    cos A, we have also <hi rend="italic">t-x÷α</hi> cos A; whence at the point B,
                        <hi rend="italic">t= 4h</hi> sin A÷α; therefore, since by formula I. <hi
                        rend="italic">α</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ν</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >=2gh, gt~</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193540747?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-0747-0644"/>2αsin A. Substituting this value of <hi
                        rend="italic">gt</hi> in the above equation, we get <hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">-a</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi> 4α <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    A+4α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> sin <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> A=α <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; so that the velocity in the parabola at the
                    point B is equal to the initial velocity at A.</p>
                <p part="N">The angle under which the projectile meets the horizontal line AB, is
                    also equal to the angle of elevation A. For since the tangent of the inclination
                    of the curve to the axis of <hi rend="italic">X</hi> is given in general by the
                    equation <hi rend="italic">dy</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a</hi> i’ ae <hi rend="italic">dx 2Jι</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">we have at the point B, where ae=4Ä cos A sin A, <hi rend="italic"
                        >du</hi>. 2 sin A . <hi rend="subscript"> rι</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">a
                        .</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">»</hi></p>
                <p part="N">— = tan A — =tan A —2 tan A = — tan A.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">dx</hi> cos A</p>
                <p part="N">From the equation (3) we readily deduce the solution of the following
                    problem, which contains the most important practical application of the theory.
                    Given the velocity of projection <hi rend="italic">=a,</hi> it is required to
                    determine A, the angle of elevation, in order that the projectile may hit a
                    given mark, or that the trajectory may pass through a given point E.</p>
                <p part="N">Let <hi rend="italic">β,γ</hi> be the co-ordinates of E, namely AF=∕3,
                    FE=χ.</p>
                <p part="N">From equation (3) we have <hi rend="italic">γ=β</hi> tan A—β <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ÷4Λ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A, and the
                    object is to find from this equation the angle of elevation, or the value of A.
                    Transposing, and observing that 1 ÷ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A=1 + tan
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A, the equation becomes <hi rend="subscript
                        smallcaps"> 9</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">. 4ä .</hi><hi rend="italic">4hy</hi>
                    tan <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A— — tan A= —1, which being solved in respect
                    of tan A, gives ,; 2Λ 1</p>
                <p part="N">tan A=y=t=y√(4∕z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- <hi rend="italic"
                        >4hγ-β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >).</hi></p>
                <p part="N">When the quantity under the radical sign is positive, that is, when 47z
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> is greater than 4Äy+ß <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi>, then tan A has two values, and there are consequently two angles of
                    elevation, by either of which the mark may be hit. If 4½ <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> =4Λγ+β <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, then tan A=2∕z÷∕3, and there
                    is consequently only one angle of elevation; and if <hi rend="italic">4h</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> be less than 4Λγ+∕3 <hi rend="superscript"
                        > 2</hi>, then the quantity under the radical sign is negative, and the
                    problem becomes impossible. It may be remarked that, supposing <hi rend="italic"
                        >γ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">β</hi> variable, the equation 4Ä <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — <hi rend="italic">4hγ</hi> —∕3 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =0, or <hi rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">=4h,(Jt-</hi> —γ) is the equation of a
                    parabola, the axis of which is the vertical line AH, the focus at A, and the
                    vertex at a point H, such that AH=7z, the height corresponding to the given
                    velocity of projection. For all points within this parabola <hi rend="italic"
                        >β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> is less than <hi rend="italic"
                        >4h</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">-4Jiγ,</hi>
                    and consequently <hi rend="italic">4lι</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    greater than 4Λγ+ <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> β <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>;
                    and for all points without it <hi rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi> is greater than 47z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    —47zγ, or <hi rend="italic">4lι</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> less
                    than 47⅛γ+∕3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, sp that the parabola, whose
                    equation is <hi rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">=4ħ(h</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">γ)</hi>
                    forms the line of separation between the points within the range of a body
                    projected from the point A with the velocity <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> and which
                    may be each hit by projecting the body under two different angles of elevation,
                    and the points which the projectile cannot reach at all.</p>
                <p part="N">The different expressions which have been found in the preceding
                    solution, may be represented by a very simple geometrical construction. On the
                    vertical line passing through A, (fig. 2.) take AH=7z= height due to the
                    velocity of projection <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> and let AK be the initial
                    direction. On AH describe a semicircle, meeting AK in L, make LM perpendicular
                    to AH, and join IIL. Since ALH is a right angle, and therefore AHL=LAB=</p>
                <p part="N">A, we have AL=Λ sin A, AM=AL sin A=Λ sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    A; and LM=AL cos A=7i cos A sin A. Comparing these expressions with the
                    equations (4), we have ∙r <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 2LM, and yι=AM,a∙ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> l</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> l</hi> being the co-ordinates of the vertex. Hence the vertex of
                    the parabola lies in the straight line MI., and is obtained by making LC=MI.. It
                    follows also from the equation (5), that AB, the horizontal range, is equal to
                    4ML.</p>
                <p part="N">Through L conceive a straight line to be drawn perpendicular to AB, or
                    parallel to AH. This line will either be a tangent to the semicircle, or will
                    meet it in another point L'. In the former case the angle of elevation is 45°,
                    and there is only one parabola corresponding to the given velocity <hi
                        rend="italic">a,</hi> through which a projectile can pass to B. But when the
                    horizontal range AB is less than twice the height AH due to the velocity, the
                    vertical drawn through L again meets the circle in L ’, and AL ’ is the tangent
                    to another parabola which passes through B, and of which the vertex is situated
                    at the intersection of DC with M'L ’ parallel to AB.</p>
                <p part="N">From the equation (3) the parameter of the parabola is <hi rend="italic"
                        >4h</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A. But DC=Λ sin <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A; whence DC + ½ parameter =7z, and consequently
                    MH=½ parameter. But (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Conic Sections,</hi> Part I. prop,
                    xiv.) the distance of the directrix of a parabola from its vertex is equal to
                    one-fourth of the parameter; and hence a straight line drawn through H parallel
                    to AB is the common directrix of all the parabolas which can be described by a
                    body projected from A with the velocity due to the height AH.</p>
                <p part="N">The focus of the parabola A C B is at the point F where H L meets the
                    axis C D, and the focus of A C ’ B at the point F' where H L' meets the axis;
                    and if a circle be described about A as a centre, with a radius = A H, the foci
                    of all the parabolas which can be described with the given velocity of
                    projection, will be in the circumference of that circle.</p>
                <p part="N">These few simple propositions contain the whole theory of the motion of
                    projectiles in vacuo, or independent on the resistance of the air; and being
                    easily investigated, and connected with very interesting practice, they have
                    been much commented on, and have furnished matter for many splendid volumes. But
                    the air’s resistance occasions such a prodigious diminution of motion in the
                    great velocities of military projectiles, that this parabolic theory, as it is
                    called, is hardly of any use. Mr. Robins found that a musket-ball, discharged
                    with the usual allotment of powder, had the velocity of 1700 feet in a second.
                    This requires a fall of45,15β feet, and the range therefore should be 90,312,or
                    17½miles; whereas it does not much exceed half a mile. A twenty-four pound ball,
                    discharged with sixteen pounds of powder, should range about sixteen miles;
                    whereas it is generally short of three miles. It is only in the cases of slow
                    motions, not exceeding 300 or 400 feet in a second, that the theory can be of
                    any use, for then the path of the projectile differs little from a parabola.</p>
                <p part="N">In such experiments as can be performed with great accuracy in a
                    chamber, the coincidence is as great as can be wished. A jet of water or
                    mercury, gives us the finest example, because we have the whole parabola
                    exhibited in the simultaneous places of the succeeding particles. Yet even in
                    these experiments a deviation can be observed. When the jet is made on a
                    horizontal plane, and the curve carefully traced on a perpendicular plane held
                    close by it, it is found that the distance between the highest point of the
                    curve and the mark is less than the distance between it and the spout, and that
                    the descending branch of the curve is shorter than the ascending branch. And
                    this difference is more remarkable as the jet is made with greater velocity, and
                    reaches to a greater distance; and it is evidently produced by the resistance of
                    the air, which diminishes the velocity, without affecting the gravity of a
                    projectile. It is <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540760?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-0760-0645"/>still more sensible in the motion of bombs.
                    These can be traced through the air by the light of their fuzes; and we see that
                    their highest point is always much nearer to the mark than to the mortar on a
                    horizontal plane.</p>
                <p part="N">We now proceed to the problem of determining the path of a projectile in
                    a resisting medium, and as the solution is attended with considerable
                    difficulty, and cannot be obtained without the aid of the integral calculus, we
                    shall endeavour to render it more perspicuous, by considering separately, 1st,
                    the motion of a body allowed to fall from rest; 2d, of a body projected
                    vertically upwards; and, lastly, the general case of a body projected with a
                    given velocity in any direction oblique to the horizon. In order to simplify the
                    subject, we shall suppose the density of the medium to be uniform, which may be
                    considered to be the case of the atmosphere at all altitudes which can be
                    reached by a projectile from the ground; and that the projected body is a
                    sphere, either homogeneous, or composed of spherical strata, for each of which
                    the density is uniform.</p>
                <p part="N">Suppose then the body to be let fall, or submitted to the action of
                    gravity, and let R denote the force with which it is resisted at any given
                    instant. By the principles of dynamics the corresponding accelerating force is
                    equal to the moving force R divided by the mass of the body, (or the moving
                    force referred to the unit of mass,) therefore the accelerating force due to the
                    resistance is R÷m. As this force acts in the direction opposite to gravity, it
                    must be taken with the negative sign, or deducted from <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>
                    and the whole accelerating force, causing the descent of the body being
                    represented by &lt;p, we have τ</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">φ=g</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> R÷?n. (6)</p>
                <p part="N">It is necessary to remark, for the sake of preserving accurate
                    principles, that a body descends in air, not by the whole of its weight, but by
                    the excess of its weight above that of the air which it displaces. It descends
                    by its <hi rend="italic">specific</hi> gravity only as a stone descends in
                    water. Suppose a body 32 times heavier than an equal bulk of air, it will be
                    buoyed up by a force equal to 1-32d part of its weight; and, instead of
                    acquiring the velocity of 32 feet in a second, it will only acquire a velocity
                    of 31, even though it sustained no resistance from the inertia of the air. Let
                        <hi rend="italic">w</hi> be the weight of the body, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >id</hi> the weight of an equal bulk of air, then the <hi rend="italic"
                        >relative</hi> acceleration of gravity will be correctly expressed by <hi
                        rend="italic">g</hi> ^1—— Butin all practical cases, and particularly in the
                    case of military projectiles, which have a great density, the fraction which
                    enters into this expression is so small that it is not ∖Vorth attending to.</p>
                <p part="N">In order to reduce the force R÷røto its simplest expression, let <hi
                        rend="italic">r</hi> denote the radius of the sphere, and δ its mean
                    density. Its volume is then jwr <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, (w being as
                    usual the ratio of the circumference of a circle to its diameter,) and we have
                    for the mass τn=^wδr <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. With respect to the force
                    R, the usual hypothesis is to suppose it to be proportional to the square of the
                    velocity of the moving body, to the surface of the projectile, and also to the
                    density of the air. If then we take <hi rend="italic">ρ</hi> to represent the
                    density of the air, and assume <hi rend="italic">n=</hi> a numerical factor to
                    be found by experiment, we shall have <hi rend="italic">^R=ηp.v</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> and consequently</p>
                <p part="N">R _ <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> p</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">. v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >m Sr '</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> k</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >×</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Since R÷ffl is an accelerating force of the same nature as gravity, and
                    may consequently be represented by a quantity of the same kind as <hi
                        rend="italic">g,</hi> we shall have a homogeneous expression by making ~=^-,
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi> being a constant. The ex-</p>
                <p part="N">• κ v R <hi rend="italic">υ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">. .</hi> pression thus
                    becomes — =#ðā 5 <hi rend="superscript"> and lt ιs</hi> necessary to observe
                    that the constant <hi rend="italic">b</hi> denotes the terminal velocity, or
                    uniform final velocity which the body attains when the resistance becomes equal
                    to gravity, or when R÷m=y, and it is consequently no longer urged by an
                    accelerating or retarding force. For the resistance being assumed proportional
                    to the square of the velocity, and R÷m being the retarding force due to the
                    velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> if δ=the terminal velocity, the retarding
                    force due to which is <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> we shall have the proportion <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >:</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">::</hi><hi rend="italic">q</hi>: —; whence — =σ</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">m m b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Thus the retarding force due to any velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> is
                    expressed in terms of the terminal velocity, but the great difficulty is to
                    procure an absolute measure of this quantity. Sir Isaac Newton has attempted to
                    determine the resistance by theory, and employs a great part of the second book
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Principia</hi> in demonstrating, that the resistance to
                    a sphere moving with any velocity, is to the force which would generate or
                    destroy its whole motion in the time that it would uniformly move over § of its
                    diameter with this velocity, as the density of the air is to the density of the
                    sphere. This is equivalent to demonstrating that the resistance of the air to a
                    sphere moving through it with any velocity, is equal to half the weight of a
                    column of air having a great circle of the sphere for its base, and for its
                    altitude the height from which a body must fall in <hi rend="italic">vacuo</hi>
                    to acquire this ∣velocity. This appears from Newton’s demonstration; for, let
                    the specific gravity of the air be to that of the ball as , 1 to <hi
                        rend="italic">β</hi>; then, because the times in which the same velocity .
                    will be extinguished by the uniform action of different forces are inversely as
                    the forces, the resistance to this velocity would extinguish it in the time of
                    describing <hi rend="italic">§ βd,d</hi> being the diameter of the ball. Now 1
                    is to <hi rend="italic">β</hi> as the weight of the displaced air to the weight
                    of the ball, or as ∣ of the ball to the length of a column of air of equal
                    weight. Call this length <hi rend="italic">k</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">k</hi> is therefore equal to f <hi rend="italic">β d.</hi>
                    Suppose the ball to fall from the height <hi rend="italic">k</hi> in the time
                        <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and acquire the velocity «. If it moved uniformly
                    with this velocity <hi rend="italic">u</hi> during the time <hi rend="italic"
                        >t,</hi> it would describe a space =24, or 1 <hi rend="italic">β d.</hi> Now
                    its weight would extinguish this velocity, or destroy this motion, in the same
                    time, that is, in twice the time of falling. The resistance therefore is equal
                    to half the weight of the ball, or to half the weight of the column of air whose
                    height is the height producing the velocity. But the resistances to different
                    velocities are as the squares of the velocities, and therefore, as their
                    producing heights; and, in general, the resistance of the air to a sphere moving
                    with any velocity, is equal to the half weight of a column of air of equal
                    section, and whose altitude is the height producing the velocity. The result of
                    this investigation has been acquiesced in by all Sir Isaac Newton’s
                    commentators. Many faults have indeed been found with his reasoning, and even
                    with his principles; and it must be acknowledged that his reasoning is liable to
                    serious objections, which his most ingenious commentators have not completely
                    removed. We must add, however, that all the causes of deviation from the
                    duplicate ratio of the velocities, and the causes of increased resistance, which
                    the latter authors have valued themselves for discovering and introducing into
                    their investigations, were pointed out by Sir Isaac Newton, but purposely
                    omitted by him, in order to facilitate the discussion <hi rend="italic">in
                        re</hi><hi rend="italic">difficillima.</hi> (See <hi rend="italic"
                        >Schol.</hi> prop. 37. book ii.)</p>
                <p part="N">It is known that the weight of a cubic foot of water is 62½ pounds, and
                    that the medium density of the air is <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi>-]- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> σ</hi> of water; therefore, let <hi rend="italic">h</hi>
                    be the height producing the velocity (in feet), and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> the
                    diameter of the ball (in inches), and <hi rend="italic">π</hi> the periphery of
                    a circle whose diameter is 1; the p <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. . <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 11 1</hi> 62⅛ w <hi rend="italic">cl</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">h</hi> resistance of the air will be
                    =-," <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> × γ× , -χ-- =</p>
                <p part="N">840 4 144 2 <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540773?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-0773-0646"/><hi rend="strikethrough">4&lt;)28</hi> ⅜ P <hi
                        rend="superscript"> oun</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> s, ver</hi> y <hi
                        rend="superscript"> near</hi> h <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> &gt; <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 0r</hi> &gt; ≡i <hi rend="superscript"> nce</hi> by
                    formula III. <hi rend="italic">h—</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">cP v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > 2</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> ÷</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >2g,</hi> resistances <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> ^-^=- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> fγ</hi> pounds.</p>
                <p part="N">We may take an example. A ball of cast iron weighing 12 pounds, is 4½
                    inches in diameter. Suppose this ball to move at the rate of 25} feet in a
                    second (the reason of this choice will appear afterwards). The height which will
                    produce this velocity in a falling body is 9} feet. The area of its great circle
                    is 0∙11044 feet, or <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 0
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="subscript"> δ</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> 0</hi> θ ’ ⅛⅛ of one foot. Suppose water to be 840 times
                    heavier than air, the weight of the air incumbent on this great circle, and 9⅛
                    feet high, is 0O81151 pounds; half of this is 0O405755, or nearly of a pound.
                    This should be the resistance of the air to this motion of the ball.</p>
                <p part="N">Newton himself attempted to compare his propositions with experiment.
                    Some were made by dropping balls from the dome of St. Paul’s cathedral; and all
                    these shewed as great a coincidence with his theory as they did with each other;
                    but the irregularities were too great to allow him to say with precision what
                    was the resistance. It appeared to follow the proportion of the squares of the
                    velocities with sufficient exactness; and though he could not say that the
                    resistance was' equal to the weight of the column of air having the height
                    necessary for communicating the velocity, it was always equal to a determinate
                    part of it; and might be stated <hi rend="italic">≈n h, η</hi> being a number to
                    be fixed by numerous experiments.</p>
                <p part="N">Newton made another set of experiments with pendulums; and has pointed
                    out some very curious and unexpected circumstances of their motions in a
                    resisting medium. Their results were much more uniform, and confirmed his
                    general theory; which, as we have said above, has been acquiesced in by the
                    first mathematicians.</p>
                <p part="N">But the deductions from this theory were so inconsistent with the
                    observed motions of military projectiles, when the velocities are prodigious,
                    that no application could be made which could be of any service for determining
                    the path and motion of cannon shot and bombs; and although John Bernoulli gave,
                    in 1718, a most elegant determination of the trajectory and motion of a body
                    projected in a fluid which resists in the duplicate ratio of the velocities, it
                    has remained a dead letter. Mr. Benjamin Robins was the first who suspected the
                    true cause of the imperfection of the usually received theories; and in 1737 he
                    published a small tract, in which he showed clearly, that even the Newtonian
                    theory of resistance must cause a cannon ball, discharged with a full allotment
                    of powder, to deviate farther from the parabola, in which it would move <hi
                        rend="italic">in vacuo,</hi> than the parabola deviates from a straight
                    line. But he farther asserted, on the authority of good reasoning, that in such
                    great velocities the resistance must be much greater than this theory assigns;
                    because, besides the resistance arising from the <hi rend="italic">inertia</hi>
                    of the air which is put in motion by the ball, there must be a resistance
                    arising from a condensation of the air on the anterior surface of the ball, and
                    a rarefaction behind it; and there must be a third resistance, arising from the
                    statical pressure of the air on its anterior part, when the motion is so swift
                    that there is a vacuum behind. Even these causes of disagreement with the theory
                    had been foreseen and mentioned by Newton (see the Scholium to prop. .37, book
                    ii. <hi rend="italic">Princip.)</hi>; but the subject seems to have been little
                    attended to.</p>
                <p part="N">Two or three years after this first publication, Mr. Robins invented
                    that ingenious method of measuring the great velocities of military projectiles,
                    which has handed down his name to posterity, and discovered the prodigious
                    resistance of the air by observing the diminution of velocity which it
                    occasioned. This made him anxious to examine what was the real resistance to any
                    velocity whatever, in order to ascertain what was the law of its variation; and
                    he was equally fortunate in this attempt. His method of measuring the resistance
                    has been fully described in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunnery.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">It appears (Robins’s <hi rend="italic">Math. Works,</hi> vol. i. p.
                    205,) that a sphere of 4½ inches in diameter, moving at the rate of 25} feet in
                    a second, sustained a resistance of 0∙04914 pounds, <hi rend="superscript">
                        or</hi> To Boise <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> pound. This is a greater
                    resistance than that of the Newtonian theory, which gave 0∙0405755, in the
                    proportion of 1000 to 1211, or very nearly in the proportion of five to six in
                    small numbers. And we may adopt as a rule in all moderate velocities, that the
                    resistance to a sphere is equal to <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ¾⅛ of the weight
                    of a column of air having the great circle of the sphere for its base, and for
                    its altitude the height through which a heavy body must fall <hi rend="italic"
                        >in vacuo</hi> to acquire the actual velocity.</p>
                <p part="N">This experiment is peculiarly valuable, because the ball is precisely
                    the size of a 12-pound shot of cast iron; and its accuracy may be depended on.
                    There is but one source of error. The whirling motion must have occasioned some
                    whirl in the air, which would continue till the ball again passed through the
                    same point of its revolution. The resistance observed is therefore probably
                    somewhat less than the true resistance to the velocity of 25} feet, because it
                    was exerted in a relative velocity which was less than this, and is, in fact,
                    the resistance due to this relative and smaller velocity. The Chevalier de Borda
                    made experiments similar to those of Mr. Robins, and his results exceed those of
                    Robins in the proportion of 5 to 6. It is much to be regretted, that in a
                    subject so interesting both to the philosopher and the engineer, experiments
                    have not been multiplied. Nothing would tend so much to perfect the science of
                    gunnery, and indeed until this be done, no practical advantage can be derived
                    from the theory.</p>
                <p part="N">Adopting this experimental measure of Robins, we have the product <hi
                        rend="italic">ηρ</hi> of equation (7) =∙04914 pounds in respect of a sphere
                    of 4½ inches diameter, or 2∙25 inches radius, moving at the rate of 25∙2 feet in
                    a second. In order to determine from this experiment the resistance on a sphere
                    of a different size, and moving with a different velocity, it will be convenient
                    to reduce it to the case corresponding to the units of magnitude and velocity;
                    therefore, since the resistance is assumed proportional to the square of the
                    velocity and the surface of the projectile, or <hi rend="italic">ll=npv</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> if we denote by R <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> the corresponding resistance, in respect of a
                    sphere whose radius is 1 inch, moving with the velocity of 1 foot per second, we
                    shall have</p>
                <p part="N">•04914</p>
                <p part="N">B.≈⅞- <hi rend="strikethrough">fr</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough"
                        > iif</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">y</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough">
                        x</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">^</hi> =&lt;)0001≡&gt; pounds.</p>
                <p part="N">The logarithm of this number is 5∙18427∙ The resistance here determined
                    is independent of the density of the ball; but the retardation occasioned by it
                    being in proportion to the quantity of motion, will therefore be proportional to
                    the density of the ball, or its specific gravity. Military projectiles are of
                    cast iron or lead, the specific gravities of which may be taken at 7’207, and
                    11∙37 respectively, tliát of water being 1.</p>
                <p part="N">The following examples will illustrate the application of the above
                    formula.</p>
                <p part="N">1. Let it be proposed to find the resistance to a 24-pound iron ball
                    (whose diameter is 5∙β03 inches), moving with the velocity of 1670 feet in a
                    second, which is nearly the velocity communicated by 16 lbs. of gunpowder.</p>
                <p part="N">Here ’ u≈1670, r=2∙8015, and the formula <hi rend="italic"
                        >"R=npv</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi> gives</p>
                <p part="N">R=∙000015285 × (1670) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ×(2∙8015) <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =≈334∙57 lbs.</p>
                <p part="N">But it is found, by unequivocal experiments, that the retardation of
                    such a motion, is equivalent to 504 lbs. This is owing to the causes often
                    mentioned, the additional resistance<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193540786?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0786-0647"/> to great
                    velocities, arising from the condensation of the air, and from its pressure into
                    the vacuum left by the ball.</p>
                <p part="N">2. Let the terminal velocity of the same ball be required.</p>
                <p part="N">Here the equation (7) gives <hi rend="italic">-~≈≈g-</hi>; therefore in
                    respect of the ball whose velocity is 1 and radius 1, we have R <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = <hi rend="italic">mg-~b</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">, b</hi> being the terminal velocity.
                    Now it is to be observed that the product of the mass of a body into the force
                    of gravity expresses its weight, which we may denote by w; we have then <hi
                        rend="italic">~Α,</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >=,w÷b</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">,</hi> and consequently δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = w÷R
                        <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi>. Now in respect of another body of the same
                    specific gravity, whose radius is r, we have R: R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>::
                    r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: 1, whence R=R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> r
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and the equation becomes δ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =w&gt;4-R <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> r <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Substituting in this equation the numbers given
                    in the question, we get</p>
                <p part="N">24</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="superscript"> 02 =</hi> ∙000015285×(2∙8015) <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ~ <hi rend="superscript"> 20a</hi> ° <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 6</hi> ° <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> whence δ=447 ’ 3
                    feet.</p>
                <p part="N">As the terminal velocity <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> and its producing
                    height <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> enter into all computations of military
                    projectiles, we have inserted the following Table for the usual sizes of
                    cannon-shot, computed both by the Newtonian theory of resistance, and by the
                    resistances observed in Robins’s experiments. A similar table, computed from Dr.
                    Hutton’s experiments, and not materially different, is given in <hi
                        rend="italic">Huttons Tracts,</hi> voh iii. p. 247∙</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Lb. Ball.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Newton.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Robins.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Diam.</p><p part="N"
                                >Inch.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">b</hi>
                                Term Vel.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic"
                                >2k.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">b</hi>
                                Term Vel.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic"
                                >2k.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">289’9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2626∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">263∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2168∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1∙94</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">324∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3298∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">295∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2723∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2∙45</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">348∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3788∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">316∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3127∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2∙80</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">365∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4170∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">331∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3442∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3∙08</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3908</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4472∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">355∙1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3940∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3∙52</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">418∙1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5463∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">379∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4511∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4∙04</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">438∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6010∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">398∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4962-9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4∙45</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">18</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">469∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6883∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">426∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5683∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5∙09</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">24</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">492∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">7576∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">447∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6265∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5∙61</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">32</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">512-6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">8024∙8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">465∙8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6780∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6∙21</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">42</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">540∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">9129-9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">491-5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">7538∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6 ’ 75</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">Having thus explained the nature of the quantities employed in the
                    investigation, we now proceed with the solution of the problem of determining
                    the circumstances of the motion of'a body falling vertically in the atmosphere.
                    In</p>
                <p part="N">R <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    consequence of the equation — <hi rend="italic">—g</hi> the relation between the
                    accelerating force and the resistance given by ∙y2 <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >y</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi> equation
                    (6), becomes <hi rend="italic">φ=g</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >g-^ =g</hi> Hence from the second of equations (1), —ðā—&gt; whence <hi
                        rend="italic">gdt—</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dν</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> τ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">b ( dv , dv</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi></p>
                <p part="N">— f, or, which is the same, <hi rend="italic">gdt=z-</hi> 1 + <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 7</hi> —-1.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        i</hi><hi rend="italic">2</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >b-^-v b</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">v∕</hi></p>
                <p part="N">On integrating this equation, and observing that as <hi rend="italic"
                        >t</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ν</hi> commence together nò correction is
                    required, we get <hi rend="italic">gt—</hi> ½δ{log (Z*+^)—log (5—∙t&gt;)},
                    whence</p>
                <p part="N">5 , ⅛+v <hi rend="subscript"> zoλ</hi></p>
                <p part="N">'=√° <hi rend="superscript"> g</hi> 4-V <hi rend="superscript">
                    (S)</hi></p>
                <p part="N">From -this equation the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> during which a
                    body must fall in a resisting medium in order to acquire the velocity <hi
                        rend="italic">v,</hi> is readily computed, supposing the terminal velocity
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to be known. It will be observed that the logarithm
                    is hyperbolic, and therefore, if the common tables are used, the tabular
                    logarithm of the number in question must be divided by the modulus of the system
                    M=∙43429 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Logakithms,</hi> vol. xiii. p. 429)∙ The
                    terminal velocity <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> as appears by equation (7), varies
                    with the radius of the ball, and the ratio of its density to that of the air,
                    and must be determined by experiment.</p>
                <p part="N">As an example of the formula, assume the terminal velocity =689⅜ feet in
                    a second, and let it be proposed to determine the time in which the body will
                    acquire a velocity of 323∙62 feet per second.</p>
                <p part="N">Here 5=689∙33, α=323∙62, ⅛+v=1012∙95, <hi rend="italic">b-v=</hi>
                    365*71, whence the common logarithm of ^⅛^is 0∙44245 <hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> σ</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi> and hyp. log Now δ÷2y=689 ’ 33÷64=</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic superscript"> j r o</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi> 43429</p>
                <p part="N">44245</p>
                <p part="N">10∙77, therefore i=M0 ’ 77 ×-τ=≈==10∙97 seconds, which 43429</p>
                <p part="N">is the time required.</p>
                <p part="N">Assume <hi rend="italic">τ</hi><hi rend="italic">—gt÷b,</hi> and let <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> denote the base of the Napierean or hyperbolic
                    logarithms, that is, let e=2 ’ 71828;</p>
                <p part="N">Z»+v the equation (8) gives, on passing to numbers c <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2τ</hi> =^ ~&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> or</hi><hi
                        rend="underline">,,</hi> y <hi rend="italic">J) (</hi> J <hi
                        rend="underline">-</hi><hi rend="subscript                     underline">
                        π</hi> g ’-*2 ’ r∖</p>
                <p part="N">e~ <hi rend="superscript"> 2r</hi> =∙≡-r-, whence <hi rend="italic">v
                        =</hi> A———÷. Let the terms of this <hi rend="italic">bA∙v</hi> 1+e- <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2r</hi> expression for <hi rend="italic">v</hi> be
                    multiplied by <hi rend="italic">eτ</hi> and the equation becomes</p>
                <p part="N">5(<hi rend="subscript"> e</hi><hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi>- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> e</hi>- <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>) <hi rend="italic"
                        >v=A</hi> Z ∕Q)</p>
                <p part="N">which gives the velocity in terms of <hi rend="italic">τ,</hi> that is,
                    in terms of the time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and the terminal velocity <hi
                        rend="italic">b.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">To find the space described, the equations (1) givewfc= <hi
                        rend="italic">dx.</hi> Now we have assumed <hi rend="italic">gt÷b=τ,</hi>
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">gdt=bd‰</hi> whence and from equation (9)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 7</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >)dt</hi> ff&lt;⅛=~~ ∙</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">A-e</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The integral of this is <hi rend="italic">gx=b</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi> log (e' <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> +e <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -,</hi> ') + C, (C being a constant). When x=0, then
                    ⅛∙=0, and the equation becomes 0=5 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> log 2 + C;
                    therefore the complete integral is</p>
                <p part="N">⅛2 <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> χ</hi>-- <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> °g ⅜ (e <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> + <hi
                        rend="superscript"> e</hi> ~ ) (10)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">J</hi> which gives the space in terms of the time and
                    final velocity.</p>
                <p part="N">The space may also be expressed in terms of the velocity. From equations
                    (1) we have <hi rend="italic">vdt—dx</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >&lt;l&gt;dt-dν.</hi> Eliminating <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> between these
                    two equations we get <hi rend="italic">φdx=</hi></p>
                <p part="N">, n <hi rend="italic">4-</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> r</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">κ(</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> dν</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >∖</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">-ν</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >b*vdv</hi><hi rend="italic">vdv.</hi> But <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> I = — 1
                        <hi rend="italic">=g</hi><hi rend="italic">———</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic">d x—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ∖
                        (^λ, ∕</hi><hi rend="italic">0</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The integral of this gives <hi rend="italic">gx=</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi><hi rend="italic">⅛b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> log
                        <hi rend="italic">(b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi> r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) + C. To determine the
                    constant, we have v=0, when ar=0, and therefore 0=—5 <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> log (δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + C); whence the complete
                    integral is &lt;7χ=½0 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> {l <hi rend="subscript">
                        θ</hi> g δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- log (⅛ <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi>-v <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)}, or <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">' <hi rend="superscript"> =</hi> ā'°=?=?· &lt; <hi rend="superscript">
                        11</hi> &gt;</p>
                <p part="N">As an example of this formula, suppose, as above, <hi rend="italic"
                        >b==</hi> 689⅜ feet, and let it be required to find the space through which
                    the body has descended when the acquired velocity α==323∙62 feet. Here the
                    common logarithm of <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        i</hi> is 5.67686, and that of δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — <hi
                        rend="italic">v-</hi> is 5-56872; therefore the common logarithm of <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >÷(b</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">υ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> j <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> 0.10814, and
                    its hyperbolic logarithm ==∣We have also δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-÷
                    2^=7429.6 <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540799?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-0799-0648"/>feet, therefore zr=7429∙6 × ½§-«|$=1850 feet
                    per second.</p>
                <p part="N">The formula may also be computed by means of the trigonometrical tables;
                    for since ½ log —5—log <hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps"> λ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic smallcaps"> J -</hi><hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps">
                        g</hi> = logarithmic secant of an arc whose radius is <hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi> and sine <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> or of an arc whose radius is 1
                    and sine =v-⅜-4, if we seek in the table the arc whose logarithmic sine = log
                    (®÷i), its logarithmic secant, or the logarithm of its cosine subtracted from
                    unity, and divided by the modulus Μ <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">=.43429, will be the value of ½ log <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>-. Thus
                    in the last example we have the common logarithm of 1α÷4= 9.67160, which
                    corresponds to an arc of 28°. Now log cos 28° =9∙94593, whence log secant 28°
                    =0.05407. But ⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ÷^=14859.2 (the double of 4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ÷2^ or 7429.6 found above), therefore a,∙=148592
                    × ∕ <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> ¾⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript"> 5</hi> =1850 feet, as before.</p>
                <p part="N">In this manner the equation (11) will also give the velocity when the
                    space <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is known. For let <hi rend="italic">ψ</hi> denote
                    the arc whose logarithmic sine in the common tables is log <hi rend="italic"
                        >(ν÷l), b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> and the equation becomes
                    ∙ι=--- log secant <hi rend="italic">ψ,</hi> whence t∕</p>
                <p part="N">log sec. ψ∙=~^. Having therefore found <hi rend="italic">ψ</hi>
                    corresponding to this secant, we shall have-u÷4= sin ψ, and consequently <hi
                        rend="italic">v=b</hi> sin ý. Suppose, as before, 4=689⅜ feet, and let it be
                    required to find the velocity when the body has fallen 1850 <hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> r +</hi><hi rend="italic">__ gMx</hi> 32×.43429× 1850 , .</p>
                <p part="N">feet. Here = =.05407, which is</p>
                <p part="N">Z&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (689⅛) <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> the logarithmic secant of ψ·; but 1—05407 = .94593 ≡ logcosι½, whence
                        <hi rend="italic">ψ</hi> is found in the tables =28°, and log sin <hi
                        rend="italic">ψ</hi> =9∙67160∙ Adding log 4=2.83843, we have log <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">ψ</hi> =2.51003, whence <hi
                        rend="italic">v=b</hi> sin ψ=323.62 feet.</p>
                <p part="N">We come now to consider the case of a body, supposed, as before, to be a
                    sphere of given magnitude and density, projected vertically upwards. In this
                    case the resistance of the air and the force of gravity act both in the same
                    direc- <hi rend="italic">gv</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> tion, and
                    the accelerating force becomes φ=— <hi rend="italic">g—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-^-∙,</hi> whence, since <hi rend="italic">φ = dv ÷ dt,</hi> we obtain the
                    equation <hi rend="italic">bdv gdt</hi><hi rend="italic">P</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">-}-v</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi></p>
                <p part="N">To integrate the first member of this equation, let <hi rend="italic"
                        >ψ</hi> denote an arc of a circle, then <hi rend="italic">d</hi> tan <hi
                        rend="italic">ψ = d ψ ÷</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∙ψ∙. Now let
                    tan <hi rend="italic">ψ=v÷b,</hi> then <hi rend="italic">d tanψ =dv÷b,</hi> and
                    1÷cos <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">ψ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">b%</hi> I <hi rend="italic">v⅛ bdv</hi></p>
                <p part="N">=1+ tan <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ≠=—~—, and we get dψ= — -, whence
                        <hi rend="superscript"> , τ</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2 τ</hi> 4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +^ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">√</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">*
                        bdv , ( v</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="subscript"> iq</hi>- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> r</hi> =≠=arc(tan=^</p>
                <p part="N">and the integral of the above equation becomes <hi rend="superscript">
                        arc</hi> (<hi rend="superscript"> tan</hi> =τ)=-⅞+ <hi rend="superscript">
                        c</hi> ∙</p>
                <p part="N">To determine the constant, let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> as before denote
                    the initial velocity. When <hi rend="italic">v∙=,α,</hi> then Z=0, and we have
                    arc (tan =-^-^ = + C, therefore the complete ^integral is arc (tan =^^^) = <hi
                        rend="superscript"> arc</hi> itan=y)-y, whence</p>
                <p part="N">í = y { arc (tan =y) — arc (tan =-∣) ∣, (12) which gives the relation
                    between the velocity and time. The quantities within the brackets express a
                    portion of the arc of a circle whose radius is unit, and are therefore abstract
                    numbers, multiplying <hi rend="italic">b÷g,</hi> which is the number of units of
                    time in which a heavy body falling in vacuo, acquires the velocity <hi
                        rend="italic">b,</hi> by formula 11.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">a ,</hi><hi rend="italic">9l</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> 1 1</hi><hi rend="italic">a v</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Assume, as above,-r-= <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> &gt; and make - <hi
                        rend="subscript"> τ</hi>- = tan <hi rend="italic">α, -</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="italic">-=</hi><hi rend="italic">b b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> tan/3; the equation (12) then becomes /3= α —r, whence
                    by trigonometry <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> tan α— tan τ</p>
                <p part="N">tan /3= .</p>
                <p part="N">1 + tan <hi rend="italic">α</hi> tan τ</p>
                <p part="N">On substituting for <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >β</hi> their values as above, this gives <hi rend="italic">a</hi> sin τ</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic underline"> v</hi><hi rend="italic underline">
                        b</hi><hi rend="underline">cos</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> τ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">b , a</hi> sin τ</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">b</hi> cos τ</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">, b(a</hi> cos τ — <hi rend="italic">b</hi> sin τ)</p>
                <p part="N">whence v= -— ×.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">a</hi> sm r + 4 cos τ</p>
                <p part="N">Now, since <hi rend="italic">gt~bτ,</hi> we have <hi rend="italic"
                        >gdt~bdτ,</hi> and consequently ’.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">, b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">(a</hi> cos τ— <hi rend="italic">b</hi> sin τ)dτ <hi
                        rend="italic">qνdt</hi> zzz j 5</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">a</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">τ + b</hi> cos τ</p>
                <p part="N">therefore, integrating, and observing that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jvdt—x,</hi> we have <hi rend="italic">gχ</hi> = 4 <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> log (α sin <hi rend="italic">τ + b</hi> cos τ) + C.</p>
                <p part="N">When ae=0, then i=0, r=0, sin τ=0, cos τ=l; therefore 0=4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> log 4 + C, and the complete integral becomes <hi
                        rend="italic">gx-b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> [log <hi
                        rend="italic">(a</hi> sin τ+4 cos τ)—log 4∣, or <hi rend="italic">gx</hi> =
                    4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (log sin τ + cos <hi rend="italic">τj</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> whence on restoring the value of <hi rend="italic"
                        >τ,</hi></p>
                <p part="N">*=7 <hi rend="superscript"> log</hi> (r <hi rend="superscript"> in</hi>
                    ⅞+ <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi> ⅞) <hi rend="superscript"> , (13)</hi> which
                    gives the space described in a function of the time. ’ To express the space in
                    terms of the velocity, we have</p>
                <p part="N">(4-2+?;2\</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">φdx-vdv.</hi> But in this case tp = — <hi
                        rend="italic">g</hi> ——-, therefore,</p>
                <p part="N">, 4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">vdv</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> dx</hi> = <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi>-- ∙</p>
                <p part="N">The integral of this gives <hi rend="italic">2gx</hi><hi rend="italic">—
                        —</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> log (4 <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> +v <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) + C; and when a?=0, theni=α;
                    therefore 0=—4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    +α) + C, and the complete integral becomes</p>
                <p part="N">4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> α <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> =√ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> og</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> +^∙ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> (14)</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Let <hi rend="italic">h</hi> denote the greatest altitude. When the
                    projectile reaches this altitude, v=0, and the last equation gives <hi
                        rend="superscript"> λ</hi> =¾ <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> ≡-∙ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> (lð)</hi></p>
                <p part="N">This formula may be computed from the trigonometrical 4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ∕5 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +&lt;2 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> _</p>
                <p part="N">tables, by observing that ½ log —— = <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> °g
                        <hi rend="italic">*d</hi> p — logarithmic secant of an arc <hi rend="italic"
                        >ψ∙ of</hi> which the tangent is α÷4. Suppose the velocity of projection to
                    be 411 feet per second, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540812?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-0812-0649"/>and 6=689½, the calculation of the height <hi
                        rend="italic">h</hi> will be as follows:</p>
                <p part="N">log <hi rend="italic">a =</hi> log 411 =-—2∙61384 log <hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi> = log 689⅜ ' <hi rend="underline">= 2-83843</hi> log tan <hi
                        rend="italic">ψ =</hi> 9’77541</p>
                <p part="N">From the table of logarithmic tangents we find ψ = 30° 48 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> z</hi> 20 <hi rend="superscript"> zz</hi>, the
                    logarithmic cosine of which is 9’93395, whence log sec + = 0 ’ 06605. We have
                    therefore 4= <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> ×
                    ∙06605 (689⅛) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × ∙06605 _</p>
                <p part="N">• ^M~~≈ ^32×∙43429 - <hi rend="superscript"> 2259 ieet</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Having reached the greatest altitude <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> the body
                    will immediately begin to fall. From equation (11) we have-r= £1 ] <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 0</hi> g . <hi rend="subscript"> g</hi> for the space
                    through which the body must —Z7 '</p>
                <p part="N">fall to acquire the velocity <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Now, if we make
                        <hi rend="italic">x—h,</hi> we shall have, on comparing this with the
                    equation (15)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Jι</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >a*</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">b* , ∕P+a- ∕
                        b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">I»g -⅜~= '&lt; ’ s <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>-⊂√- <hi
                        rend="superscript"> whence</hi> √ — = √ <hi rend="italic">{rz∑ςr</hi> But
                    the first number of this equation is the secant of an arc, whose tangent is <hi
                        rend="italic">a-~b,</hi> and the second the secant of an arc whose sine is
                        <hi rend="italic">ν÷lr,</hi> and since the secants are equal, the arcs must
                    be equal; therefore the velocity of projection is to the final returning
                    velocity as the tangent to the sine, or as the radius to the cosine of an arc.
                    Suppose the body projected with a velocity equal to the terminal velocity, that
                    is, suppose <hi rend="italic">a—b</hi>; the above equation will then become
                    2(Z&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> —®*) <hi rend="italic">=b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">, or
                        b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">=2v</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> whence <hi
                        rend="italic">v=b÷</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript
                        smallcaps"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ∕2.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >If</hi> 4=689½, then r==487, or the body will reach with a velocity of 487
                    feet per second.</p>
                <p part="N">The time required for reaching the greatest altitude is found by making
                    r=0 in equation (12). In this case the equation becomes <hi rend="italic"
                        >t—-</hi> arc ^tan= -J. We learn from this expression of the time, that
                    however great the velocity of projection, and the height to which the body will
                    rise, may be, the time of its ascent is limited. It never can exceed the time of
                    falling <hi rend="italic">in vacuo</hi> from the height due to the terminal
                    velocity <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> namely <hi rend="italic">t==b ÷g,</hi> in a
                    greater proportion than that of a quadrantal arc to the radius, nearly the
                    proportion of 8 to 5. A 24-pound iron ball cannot continue rising above 14
                    seconds, even if the resistance to quick motions did not increase faster than
                    the square of the velocity. It probably will attain its greatest height in less
                    than 12 seconds, let its velocity be ever so great.</p>
                <p part="N">Having thus determined the relations subsisting between the velocity,
                    the space described, and the time, in the cases of vertical ascent and descent
                    in a resisting medium, we come now to consider the general problem, and to
                    determine the motion of a body projected in any direction whatever. Our readers
                    will readily conceive that this must be a difficult subject, when they see the
                    simplest cases of rectilineal motion abundantly abstruse. In the infancy of the
                    fluxionary calculus, the difficulty was indeed such that Newton himself did not
                    succeed in obtaining a complete solution of the problem. In the tenth and
                    subsequent propositions of the second book of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Principia,</hi> he shows what state of density in the air will comport with
                    the motion of a body in any curve whatever; and then, by applying this result to
                    several curves which have some similarity to the path of a projectile, he found
                    one which is not very different from what may be supposed to obtain in the
                    atmosphere. But even the approximation was involved in calculations of such
                    intricacy, that it seemed impossible to make any use of it. In the second
                    edition of the <hi rend="italic">Principia,</hi> published in 1713, he corrects
                    some mistakes into which he had fallen in the first, and carries the
                    approximation much farther, but still does not attempt a direct investigation of
                    the trajectory. In proposition 14, &amp;c. he shows how a body, actuated by a
                    centripetal force, in a medium of a density varying according to certain laws,
                    will describe an eccentric spiral, of which he assigns the properties, and the
                    law of description. Had he supposed the density constant, and the difference
                    between the greatest and least distances from the centre of centripetal force
                    exceedingly small in comparison with the distances themselves, his spiral would
                    have coincided with the path of a projectile in the air of uniform density, and
                    the steps of his investigation would have led him immediately to the complete
                    solution of the problem. For this is the real state of the case. A heavy body is
                    not acted on by equal and parallel gravity, but by a gravity inversely
                    proportional to the square of the distance from the centre of the earth, and in
                    lines tending to that centre nearly; and it has been only with the view of
                    simplifying the investigation, that mathematicians have adopted the other
                    hypothesis.</p>
                <p part="N">Soon after the publication of this second edition of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Principia,</hi> the dispute about the invention of the
                    fluxionary calculus became very violent, and the great promoters of that
                    calculus upon the continent were in the habit of proposing difficult problems as
                    trials of skill to each other. Challenges of this kind frequently passed between
                    the British and foreigners. Dr. Keill of Oxford had keenly espoused the claim of
                    Sir Isaac Newton to this invention, and had engaged in a very acrimonious
                    altercation with the celebrated John Bernoulli of Basle. Bernoulli had published
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Eruditorum</hi> of Leipsic
                    an investigation of the law of the forees, by which a body moving in a resisting
                    medium might describe any proposed curve, reducing the whole to the simplest
                    geometry; and Dr. Keill proposed to him the particular problem of the trajectory
                    and motion of a body moving through the air. Bernoulli very soon solved the
                    problem in a way much more general than it had been proposed, viz. without any
                    limitation either of the law of resistance, the law of the centripetal force, or
                    the law of density, provided only that they were regular, and capable of being
                    expressed algebraically. Dr. Brook Taylor, the celebrated author of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Method of Increments,</hi> solved it at the same time, in
                    the limited form in which it was proposed. Other authors since that time have
                    given other solutions. But they are all (as indeed they must be) the same in
                    substance with Bernoulli’s. Indeed they are all (Bernoulli’s not excepted) the
                    same with Newton’s first approximations, modified by the steps introduced into
                    the investigation of the spiral motions mentioned above.</p>
                <p part="N">We now proceed to the problem itself, restricted to the case of uniform
                    density and a resistance proportional to the square of the velocity.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Problem.</hi> To determine the trajectory, and all the
                    circumstances of the motion of a body projected through the air, from a given
                    point, and in a given direction, and resisted in the duplicate ratio of the
                    velocity.</p>
                <p part="N">Suppose the body to be projected from A, in the direction AK, with a
                    velocity = <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> and let AB and AH, horizontal and vertical
                    lines drawn through A, be assumed as the axes of the rectangular co-ordinates
                        <hi rend="italic">χ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y.</hi> Let P be the place of
                    the projectile at the end of the time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> make the arc
                    AP=z, and Iet <hi rend="italic">Bp—dz,</hi> bean infinitely small portion of the
                    arc, which may be regarded as coinciding with PM, the tangent to the curve at P;
                    draw PQ and <hi rend="italic">pq</hi> parallel to AH, and Pn paral!el to AB, and
                    let the angle <hi rend="italic">pΡn</hi> (=PMA, which the tangent makes with the
                    horizontal <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540825?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-0825-0650"/>axis), be denoted by M we have then <hi
                        rend="italic">Pn = dx, np — dy,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dιj ~dχ</hi> tan
                    0.</p>
                <p part="N">The intensity of the force of resistance being denoted as before by R,
                    and the mass of the projectile by <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> the accelerating
                    force due to the resistance is R÷m. This force is éxerted in the direction of
                    the tangent at P, and as it tends to diminish the velocity in the direction
                    P∕&gt;, it must be taken with the negative sign. Now, the accelerating force in
                    the direction <hi rend="italic">Yp,</hi> is to the accelerating force in the
                    direction <hi rend="italic">Pn</hi> as 1: cos <hi rend="italic">ð,</hi> and to
                    the force in the direction <hi rend="italic subscript"> η</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >p</hi> as 1: sin <hi rend="italic">6</hi>; therefore in the direction of
                    the axis <hi rend="italic">x</hi> the accelerating force is (R÷m) cos <hi
                        rend="italic">6,</hi> and in the direction of <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi>,
                    cfø . <hi rend="italic">dy</hi> the axis <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> (R÷m) sin <hi
                        rend="italic">θ.</hi> But cos <hi rend="italic">0=~jz&gt;</hi> and sin <hi
                        rend="italic">6 =,-</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> therefore the
                    accelerating forces due to the resistance, in the , , <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi>. R <hi rend="italic">dx</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> R <hi
                        rend="italic">dy</hi> direction of the co-ordmates, are . — and . -ý-</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">m dz in dz</hi> respectively. In the horizontal
                    direction, the sole force acting on the projectile is that which is due to the
                    resistance; in the vertical direction the body is also acted on by the
                    accelerating force of gravity, <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> which, when the body is
                    ascending, acts in the same direction with the resisting force of the
                    atmosphere, and must therefore be taken with the same sign. Now, the
                    accelerating forces in the direc- <hi rend="italic">_ . . d</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        1</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">y ,</hi> tions <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >y,</hi> are respectively — and — by equations <hi rend="italic">CLL</hi><hi
                        rend="italic smallcaps"> (λ&gt;1∕</hi></p>
                <p part="N">(1); we have therefore for the equations of motion, <hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">χ _</hi> R <hi
                        rend="italic">dχ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="underline"
                        >⅜</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> lf</hi> ∙κ</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">~dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">m ' dz</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        9</hi><hi rend="italic">m ' dz’ ' '</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Assuming <hi rend="italic">r</hi> =radius of the projectile, δ = its
                    density, ρ = density of atmosphere, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> = velocity at the
                    point P, and <hi rend="italic">n =.</hi> a constant co-efficient, we have, — =
                    -^--υ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> equation (7). In the case of the vertical
                    motion, we represented the co-efficient of f <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> by
                    the fraction <hi rend="italic">g÷b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">, (b</hi> being the terminal velocity); it will now be more
                    convenient to denote it by a single letter; we shall therefore assume <hi
                        rend="italic">c=np÷δr</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and consequently, as <hi
                        rend="italic">n</hi> and the ratio p÷δ are both abstract numbers, the
                    reciprocal of the constant c, or 1 ÷c, will represent a straight line; in fact,
                    the reciprocal of <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is twice the altitude producing the
                    terminal velocity <hi rend="italic">b in vacuo,</hi> for calling <hi
                        rend="italic">lι</hi> ’ this altitude, we have by formula (III.) <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-2gh</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> therefore <hi rend="italic">g-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> z</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >rb</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">÷2h</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">=c.</hi>
                    We have then R÷m=cυ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; <hi rend="italic">. dz</hi>
                    R <hi rend="italic">dz*</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> o
                        1</hi><hi rend="italic">. . ,. .</hi> whence, since <hi rend="italic"
                        >ν--</hi> — =—. Substituting this in the <hi rend="italic">dt m de °</hi>
                    above equations of motion (16) we get <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">x dz dx</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">^^</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >~dt'~d^</hi> (17)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">(Tg</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">, dz dy</hi><hi rend="italic">-^-+</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic">Λ-^=</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > 0</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> from which the equation of the trajectory
                    must be deduced by integration. &lt;</p>
                <p part="N">To integrate the first of these equations, suppose -y-=≡ <hi
                        rend="italic">ke~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> cz</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">,</hi> where <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is an arbitrary
                    constant, and <hi rend="italic">e</hi> the base of the hyperbolic logarithms.
                    The differential of this equation is, <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic">ho</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> e</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic">^^ dz,</hi> or, dividingby <hi
                        rend="italic">dt,</hi> and substituting for <hi rend="italic">ke~</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> cz</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">x dz dx</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> ¶</hi> its
                    value, _ —c—. —, which is the first of the above equations. Hence the integral
                    of that equation is ⅛=⅛→≡.</p>
                <p part="N">To determine the constant <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> suppose 2=0. WTιen
                    z=0, the velocity in the direction of the tangent AK is the initial velocity <hi
                        rend="italic">a,</hi> and in the direction AB it is <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    cos A, assuming A as before to represent the angle KAB. But — <hi rend="italic"
                        >—v dt</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> the velocity at P, therefore when 2=0,
                    the equation ⅛ = <hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        e</hi><hi rend="italic">~~</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi> gives <hi rend="italic">α</hi>
                    cos <hi rend="italic">A=k.</hi> The complete integral of the first of the
                    equations (17) is therefore <hi rend="italic">dx</hi></p>
                <p part="N">— = σcosAc^^ <hi rend="superscript"> cs</hi>. (18)</p>
                <p part="N">The integral of the second equation (17) is found as follows. Since
                    t(y=tan <hi rend="italic">Ô dx,</hi> we have, on supposing <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">dii</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dx</hi> to be functions of <hi rend="italic">t, -</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">T=Λaη0</hi>
                    Differentiating this equation, and observing that &lt;7 tan <hi rend="italic"
                        >ê=</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> — sec <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J <hi
                        rend="italic">d Ô,</hi> we cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">y dð dx d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">x _ , .</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> get</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">~dr = ⅛ς⅛Z ∙ di</hi><hi rend="superscript"> + tan</hi> ⅛ ≡ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ubstltutin</hi> 8 <hi rend="superscript"> tb</hi> &lt;≈
                        <hi rend="superscript"> sf</hi> ≈ ™'</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">y ,
                        dy . ,</hi> lues ot and — m the equation in question, it becomes <hi
                        rend="italic">XΛΛ&gt; UC</hi><hi rend="italic">dô dx</hi> Γ <hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">χ dz dx</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0&lt;⅛' <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> an</hi> t <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2 jf</hi><hi rend="italic">^</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > c</hi><hi rend="italic">dt’ dt</hi> J ’</p>
                <p part="N">whence, by reason of the first of the equations (17) <hi rend="italic"
                        >dð dx .</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> λ</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> 0iZΓ <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        +9</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> Q</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi><hi rend="italic">dx</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> and on dividing by -y <hi rend="subscript"
                        > τ</hi> =α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> A <hi rend="italic">e~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2cz</hi>
                    (18), we get <hi rend="italic underline"> d∂</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        ι</hi><hi rend="italic">dx _</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> —g</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> e</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >_</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2ca&lt;</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> 4cfe ' <hi rend="italic">dt a</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> cos
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">Now if <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> be regarded as a function of <hi
                        rend="italic">x,</hi> then — ÷ <hi rend="subscript">;</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">dt dt dx</hi> and from the formula
                    (III.) we have also <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">=,2hg (Ji</hi> being the height due to the velocity
                    α); therefore by substitution <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi><hi rend="underline"
                        >1</hi><hi rend="subscript"> c2cs</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Mr
                    2Λcos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">But we have <hi rend="italic">dx=dz</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ô,</hi>
                    therefore this equation becomes</p>
                <p part="N">_ÉL — __ —— <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> 2&lt; », (20)</p>
                <p part="N">cos <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> t) 27a cos <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> A <hi rend="superscript"> v 7</hi> which is the differential equation
                    of the trajectory.</p>
                <p part="N">The integral of this equation is found as follows. By <hi rend="italic"
                        >∕* d)</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">θ P dð</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Fluxions</hi> (^rt∙ 153),y — <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> y — <hi
                        rend="subscript"> }</hi> ·, and r&gt; /7 <hi rend="italic">ð</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">(Art.</hi> 155), ∕ ——-=log tan(45° + ½c&gt;) We have also <hi
                        rend="subscript"> c</hi> ∕ COS0</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Γ ê</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ez</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dz = -c</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2cz</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> therefore assuming K to denote an <hi rend="italic"
                        >J</hi> 2c arbitrary constant, the general integral becomes ~+ log«» (^°+i
                        <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi>)= <hi rend="superscript"> κ</hi>- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ⅛A^∙</p>
                <p part="N">To determine the constant, suppose <hi rend="italic">z=0.</hi> W hen z=0
                    then Ö=A, and the last equation gives</p>
                <p part="N">K= <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>- + + log tan (45° +⅛A). (21)</p>
                <p part="N">2 <hi rend="italic">ch</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A ’ cos
                        <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">For the sake of abridging, let us assume</p>
                <p part="N">F(<hi rend="subscript"> t</hi>)) = + log tan (45° +⅜0), <hi
                        rend="superscript"> x j</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> tf <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193540838?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0838-0651"
                        /><hi rend="superscript"> F</hi> &lt; <hi rend="superscript"> A</hi> &gt;/Èå
                        <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> 0Stan</hi> &lt; <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 45</hi> ’+* <hi rend="superscript"> A</hi>)·</p>
                <p part="N">then the complete integral of equation (20) becomes F <hi rend="italic"
                        >(û)</hi> —F(A)= <hi rend="strikethrough">2&lt;∙⅞ cos</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript                     strikethrough"> a</hi><hi
                        rend="strikethrough">Ā</hi> θ— <hi rend="superscript"> g2cε</hi>)&gt;
                    whence, by transposition, e <hi rend="superscript"> 2cs</hi>-1 =2cΛ cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A{F(A)-F(0)}, (23)</p>
                <p part="N">an equation which gives the length <hi rend="italic">z</hi> of the arc
                    AP in terms of the angle which the tangent at P makes with the horizontal line
                    AB.</p>
                <p part="N">We have now to find expressions for the co-ordinates <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi> and y. In consequence of the equation (21), the last may be
                    otherwise written</p>
                <p part="N">⅛-&gt;.=' <hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> [k-F(0½ (24)</p>
                <p part="N">Substituting this in (20) we get — <hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">dzc</hi> {l&lt;—F (0)}, whence <hi
                        rend="italic">dz=</hi> —7 - . Now, we have also <hi rend="italic">dχ=</hi>
                    ccos <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ffFrø-K}</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">dz</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ð, dy—dz</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="italic">ô,</hi> therefore by substitution, <hi rend="italic">, d∂</hi>
                    c cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> d[F(tf)-K]</p>
                <p part="N">, <hi rend="underline">tan</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> θ dθ</hi>
                    (25)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> ccos^{F(0)—K}</p>
                <p part="N">These expressions are not susceptible of integration in finite terms;
                    but as <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> have the forms <hi
                        rend="italic">x =f ψ(0)d0</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y=f ψ'(0)d 6 (ψ</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">ψ'</hi> denoting known functions of 0) and as <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> varies within given limits, from <hi rend="italic"
                        >6</hi> =A to 0=0 in the ascending branch of the curve, and from 0=0 to
                    0=90° in the descending branch, the problem is thus brought within the method of
                    quadratures; that is to say, it depends on finding the areas of two curves, of
                    which the ordinates are respectively ι½(0) and <hi rend="italic">ψ'(6),</hi>
                    corresponding to the absciss <hi rend="italic">í.</hi> Hence <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> may be found for given values of <hi
                        rend="italic">β,</hi> and consequently any number of points may be found in
                    the trajectory.</p>
                <p part="N">Instead of employing the equations (25), the curve may be constructed by
                    means of equation (24), which is the method followed by Euler. That equation
                    gives e <hi rend="superscript"> 2cz</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">2clι</hi> c0s <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A {K—F(0)J,
                    whence we have logz = ^-log [j2c4cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A
                    fK—F(θ}l∙</p>
                <p part="N">Nòw, if <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> be the angle which the tangent makes
                    with the horizon at the point P of the curve, and <hi rend="italic">z</hi> the
                    length of the arc AP, and if at the pointy? at a small but finite distance from
                    P, the angle becomes <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> —ω, and the arc z + ∆z, then if
                    the formula be computed for a given value of <hi rend="italic">ô,</hi> (for
                    example 30°), and also for <hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ω</hi> (suppose 25°), the difference between the two resulting
                    numbers will give the length of the arc Pjo=∆z. Thus we can find the values of a
                    great number of small portions, and the inclinations of the two tangents at
                    their extremities. We can also assign to each of these portions its proportion
                    of the absciss and ordinate, without having recourse to the values of <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi>; for the portion of the
                    absciss corresponding to P∕&gt; or ∆z being ∆∙r, and <hi rend="italic">6</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi> ½ω being the inclination of its middle point to the
                    horizon, we have ∆∙r=∆zcos(0—}ω); andin like manner Δy=∆z sin <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Ô</hi> —½ω). By adding all these portions together, the co-ordinates will
                    be obtained, and consequently the points of the curve from <hi rend="italic"
                        >6=,</hi> A to 0=0, or through the ascending branch from A to the vertex.
                    Near the point of projection, the variation of the length of the arc is much
                    greater than that of the angle <hi rend="italic">ô,</hi> and therefore at the
                    commencement it may be necessary to compute <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> for each
                    degree, that is, to assume ω=1°; but a sufficiently near approximation will be
                    obtained by taking intervals of 5°, or making ω=5° throughout the rest of the
                    curve. It will be observed that the logarithms of the formulae are hyperbolic;
                    and therefore the logarithms of the common tables must be divided by the modulus
                    Μ.</p>
                <p part="N">We have still to find expressions for the time and velocity. From
                    equation (19) <hi rend="italic">^~⅛</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> θ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dx=</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">gelt</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >.</hi> Multiplying by <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> and substituting for <hi
                        rend="italic">dx,</hi> its value given by the <hi rend="italic">dβ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> first of the equations (25), this becomes
                    =</p>
                <p part="N">cos <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> d{F(d)-K] <hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">cgdt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > 2</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> whence, transposing and
                    extracting the root, <hi rend="italic">/—</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        j</hi><hi rend="italic">dθ</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">tcg
                        . dt=</hi><hi rend="italic">———</hi><hi rend="italic">-,</hi> (26)</p>
                <p part="N">cos 24F(0)-K] <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">In this equation the radical must be regarded as a positive quantity,
                    because when the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> increases, the angle <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> diminishes.</p>
                <p part="N">For the velocity we have from (19) —gcos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    0^-.</p>
                <p part="N">But <hi rend="italic">dx=dz</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi> therefore
                        <hi rend="italic">υ = ⅞- =</hi><hi rend="italic">—g</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="italic">ô ~,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dt do</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >=g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> cos <hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">ð ~</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        y</hi> Substituting in this equation the value <hi rend="italic">Uν</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> of given by (26),
                    we have</p>
                <p part="N">«2 &amp; . /27 ∖</p>
                <p part="N">ccos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0[K—F(0)}</p>
                <p part="N">As the vertex, 0=0, and cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0=1;
                    therefore, assuming <hi rend="italic">u</hi> to denote the velocity at the
                    vertex, the equation becomes w <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =g÷cK∙, or, since
                    c=g÷i <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, ω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =6 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ÷K; whence it appears that K is the ratio of the
                    square of the terminal velocity to the square of the velocity in the vertex.</p>
                <p part="N">If there were no resistance, the smallest velocity would be at the
                    vertex, and beyond the vertex it would immediately increase by the action of
                    gravity conspiring (in a small degree, however) with the motion of the body. But
                    in a resisting medium the velocity at the vertex is diminished by a quantity to
                    which the acceleration of gravity in that point bears no assignable proportion.
                    It is therefore diminished upon the whole, and the point of smallest velocity is
                    a little way beyond the vertex. It is not material for our present purpose to
                    determine the exact position of that point.</p>
                <p part="N">By means of the expressions which have now been found, we are enabled to
                    compute for every value of 0, from the point of projection where 0=A, to the
                    vertex where 0=0, the corresponding point of the trajectory, the time which the
                    projectile takes to arrive at that point, and the velocity with which it is then
                    moving. We now proceed* to, consider the motion in the descending branch.</p>
                <p part="N">Let the origin of the co-ordinates (fig. 4.) be transferred to the
                    vertex C; let CE be horizontal, CD vertical, S a point in the descending branch,
                    SN a tangent at S, meeting CE in N, and ST parallel to CD. Also let <hi
                        rend="italic">x'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> ’ be the co-ordinates of
                    S referred to the vertex, that is.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540851?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0851-0652"/>
                <p part="N">make af==CT, t∕'=ST, and suppose the co-ordinates of the vertex to be
                        <hi rend="italic">p</hi> and <hi rend="italic">q,</hi> namely AD=p, CD==q.
                    Then the co-ordinates of S referred to A being always represented by <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> we have <hi rend="italic"
                        >x-pA-x', y=q</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">y', dx=dx',
                        dy∙=,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">dy</hi> ’ <hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Now it will be observed, that in the descending branch the angle <hi
                        rend="italic">6</hi> is negative, or that ENS=— <hi rend="italic">ð</hi>;
                    whence the first of the two equations in (25) becomes in the present case <hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">∕+-</hi><hi rend="italic
                        underline"> ~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> d,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0 {F(→)-K}</p>
                <p part="N">But from (23), F(— <hi rend="italic">i)=ο</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >^~τy</hi> +log <hi rend="superscript"> tan</hi> (45° —½^); and tan (45°-½*)
                    = cot (45 + ⅛) = <hi rend="superscript"> 5 whence</hi> logtan(45° —½*)==—log tan
                    (45° + ½&lt; ’), and consequently F(—0)=—F(&lt; ’). Equations (25) therefore
                    become <hi rend="italic">, , dθ</hi><hi rend="italic">dpl</hi><hi rend="italic
                        underline"> — —</hi><hi rend="italic                     underline">
                        .</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> i{K +
                    F(^)}</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">txnðdå</hi> (28)</p>
                <p part="N">c cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> i{K+F(^)}</p>
                <p part="N">In like manner the equation (24) becomes in this case e- <hi
                        rend="superscript"> c</hi> ≡'= 2cÄ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A {K+F
                    (∕)}, <hi rend="italic">z</hi> ’ being the arc counted from the vertex; and the
                    expressions for the time and velocity become respectively <hi rend="italic"
                        >√eg.dt=</hi><hi rend="italic">— —</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> ff</hi>.(29)</p>
                <p part="N">co <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> ⅛{K <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> F(,)p
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ccos</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> j</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">4k+F(&lt;)}</hi></p>
                <p part="N">All these expressions are computed for successive values of <hi
                        rend="italic">ð</hi> from <hi rend="italic">ê=0</hi>; and a sufficient
                    approximation will be obtained by assuming <hi rend="italic">ð</hi> to vary by
                    intervals of 5°. The ascending and descending branches of the trajectory are
                    thus computed independently, as if they belonged to different curves.</p>
                <p part="N">In the descending branch the angle 0=ENS continually increases with the
                    distance of the point S from C, until it becomes a right angle, which is its
                    limiting value. But <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        f</hi> can only increase to a certain magnitude, which it would attain when
                    S is at an infinite distance, and consequently this branch of the curve has an
                    asymptote, which is perpendicular to the horizon. To prove this, let the factor
                    K+F(0) be developed, and let us consider what it becomes when <hi rend="italic"
                        >θ</hi> approaches its limit. We have F(0)=</p>
                <p part="N">+ log. tan (45° +½ð). Now when <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> approaches very
                    nearly to a right angle, sin fe≡l, and —(= 1 + tan <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> t))</p>
                <p part="N">= tan <hi rend="italic superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">ð</hi>;
                    therefore <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi>--∕- = tan <hi rend="italic superscript"
                        > 2</hi><hi rend="italic">ô.</hi> With respect to the second term, when <hi
                        rend="italic">ð</hi> is nearly =90°, then tan (45° +½d) becomes very large,
                    and nearly equal to tan <hi rend="italic">ð</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but the
                    logarithm of a very large number may be neglected as insensible in comparison of
                    the square of the number, we have therefore simply F(¢)= tan¾. In like manner,
                    K, which is a finite quantity, may be neglected in comparison of tan <hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">θ</hi>; whence the first
                    of equations (28)becomes <hi rend="italic">dx'χ= dô</hi></p>
                <p part="N">—-——. The integral of this <hi rend="smallcaps">(Fluxions,</hi> art.
                    153) is <hi rend="italic">x' csm</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">lt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> v 7</hi></p>
                <p part="N">=C—where C is an arbitrary constant. Hence <hi rend="italic">x</hi> does
                    not increase indefinitely, but as <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> increases, it ap≡</p>
                <p part="N">proaches nearer and nearer to a constant C, with which it coincides when
                        <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> is infinite. The constant C cannot be determined
                    from this equation; but if we assume ^=- <hi rend="italic">√-∙∞ d¢</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">0</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">⅛qκ</hi><hi rend="subscript
                        strikethrough"> +</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">F&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> the va,ue 0f k may be</hi> ≈W∙° <hi rend="superscript">
                        xι</hi> ≡ <hi rend="superscript"> te</hi>- ly computed by the method of
                    quadratures. Suppose <hi rend="italic">k</hi> to be determined, make CE=4, and
                    draw through E the vertical EF, then EF is the asymptote of the descending
                    branch of the curve.</p>
                <p part="N">The terminal velocity <hi rend="italic">b</hi> may be determined from
                    equation (27). On changing <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> into — <hi rend="italic"
                        >θ</hi> in that equation, and <hi rend="italic">£T</hi> supposing <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> to become a right angle, we have 4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = <hi rend="subscript"> cs</hi>- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 7⅞ <hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >JL</hi><hi rend="subscript">;</hi> whence <hi rend="italic">b=</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic">J</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—,</hi> which agrees with the assumed <hi rend="italic">c c</hi> value of
                        <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> namely c=g÷⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p part="N">Although the motion commences at the point A, the curve may be supposed
                    to be continued infinitely below the line AB. This branch of the curve has also
                    an asymptote, the position of which it is important to determine. If in the
                    equation (23)</p>
                <p part="N">e <hi rend="superscript"> 2c</hi> ≡—1 =2c4 cos <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> A {F(A)—F(d)], we suppose 2 to be negative and infinite, and assume B
                    to denote the value of ¢ when <hi rend="italic">z</hi> is infinite, we shall
                    have</p>
                <p part="N">F(B)= <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi>,- <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>...
                        <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi>- +F(A), (30)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic superscript"> κ 7</hi><hi rend="italic">2ch</hi> cos
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A <hi rend="superscript"> κ</hi> whence from
                    equation (22), F(B)=K. Substituting this value of K in the two equations (25),
                    and observing, that for any point in this branch of the curve below AB, <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> are both negative, we have
                        <hi rend="italic">dx— d</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> tan <hi rend="italic"
                        >6d6</hi> ccos <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> tf{F(B)-F(0)}’ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> y</hi> c cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    d{F(B)-F(0)}</p>
                <p part="N">Now let P (fig. 4.) be a point in the curve, PM a tangent at P, meeting
                    AB in Μ, let AQ and PQ be the co-ordinates of P, and make AM≈=Z. We have then
                    Z=AQ—MQ</p>
                <p part="N">=&lt;r— Suppose now the point P at an infinite distance, then <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> becomes B, the tangent MP becomes an asymptote, and <hi
                        rend="italic">l—x</hi> ^—=. Hence <hi rend="italic">dl—dx</hi> ~; and tan B
                    tan B</p>
                <p part="N">therefore, on substituting the above values of <hi rend="italic">dx</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">dy,</hi> we get</p>
                <p part="N">(<hi rend="superscript"> tan</hi> B—tan <hi rend="italic">∂)dβ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi> tan B cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0{F(B)-F(0)}*</p>
                <p part="N">The integral of this expression from <hi rend="italic">l)=A</hi> to 0=B
                    will give the distance of the asymptote from the point. Let the definite
                    integral be denoted by λ, that is, let</p>
                <p part="N">λ- <hi rend="superscript underline"> 1</hi> (tan B—tan <hi rend="italic"
                        >θ)dθ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> ^^tan B <hi rend="subscript">
                        t</hi> ∕ <hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> a c</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >os</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >4FB-</hi> F(^)Γ <hi rend="superscript">?</hi> then λ may be computed by the
                    method of quadratures. If we then take on the prolongation of AB, AL equal to λ,
                    and draw through L the line LG, making with AB an angle =B, then LG will be the
                    asymptote of the branch AC. The whole curve will then lie between the two
                    asymptotes, which are inclined to each other in an angle =90°-B.</p>
                <p part="N">Such, then, is the process by which the form and magnitude of the
                    trajectory^ and the motion in it may be determined. But it does not yet appear
                    how this is to be appli*</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540864?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0864-0653"/>
                <p part="N">ed to any question in practical artillery. By means of the preceding
                    formulae, we are enabled to compute the motion from any point in the ascending
                    branch to the vertex, where the motion becomes horizontal, and the motion from
                    the vertex to a point in the descending branch, where the motion has acquired
                    another determinate direction; the constants which enter into the formulae being
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and K, of which <hi rend="italic">c</hi> (=y÷6 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) depends on the terminal velocity, and therefore
                    on the nature of the projectile and the ratio of its density to that of the air;
                    and K on the initial velocity, the terminal velocity, and the angle of
                    elevation. We have also shewn that K denotes the ratio of the square of the
                    terminal velocity to the square of the velocity in the vertex; therefore the
                    terminal velocity and velocity in the vertex may be regarded as the two
                    constants of the formulae. The mode in which the formulae are applied to the
                    solution of the usual question, namely, to find the motion of a ball projected
                    in a certain direction, with a certain velocity, is as follows: Suppose a
                    trajectory, computed for a particular terminal velocity <hi rend="italic"
                        >b,</hi> and for a particular velocity at the vertex, and that the velocity
                    at that point of the ascending branch where the inclination of the tangent is
                    30° is 900 feet per second. Then, we are certain, that if a ball, whose terminal
                    velocity is <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> be
                    projected with the velocity of 900 feet per second, and an elevation of 30°, it
                    will describe this very trajectory, and the velocity and time corresponding to
                    every point will be such as is here determined.</p>
                <p part="N">Now this trajectory will, in respect to form, answer an infinity of
                    cases: for its characteristic is the proportion of the velocity in the vertex to
                    the terminal velocity. If, therefore, we compute the trajectories for a
                    sufficient variety of these proportions, we shall find a trajectory that will
                    nearly correspond to any case that can be proposed: and an approximation
                    sufficiently exact will be had by taking a proportional medium between the two
                    trajectories which come nearest to the case proposed.</p>
                <p part="N">Accordingly, a set of tables or trajectories have been computed by the
                    English translator of Euler’s <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Robiηds
                        Gunnery.</hi> They are in number 18, distinguished by the position of the
                    assymptote of the ascending branch. This is given for 5°, 10°, 15°, &amp;c. to
                    85°, and the whole trajectory is computed as far as it can ever be supposed to
                    extend in practice.</p>
                <p part="N">Since the path of a projectile is much less incurvated, and more rapid
                    in the ascending than in the descending branch, and the difference is so much
                    the more remarkable in great velocities, it must follow, that the range on a
                    horizontal or inclined plane depends most on the ascending branch: therefore the
                    greatest range will not be made with that elevation which bisects the angle of
                    position, but with a lower elevation; and the deviation from the bisecting
                    elevation will be greater as the initial velocities are greater. It is difficult
                    to frame a rule for determining with much precision, the elevation which gives
                    the greatest range.</p>
                <p part="N">When the angle of elevation is very small, and consequently the path of
                    the projectile nearly horizontal, the formulae admit of simplifications which it
                    is important to consider. Suppose KAB(fig.5.) the angle of elevation to be
                    small, then 0, the angle which the tangent at any other point of the trajectory
                    makes with AB, will be very small, and sin <hi rend="italic">6</hi> and tan <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> will be very small fractions. Suppose the angle so
                    small that tan <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0 may be neglected as insensible;
                    then cos <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> may be regarded as unit, and the equation <hi
                        rend="italic">dx=dz</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ð</hi> gives <hi
                        rend="italic">dx—dz.</hi> Hence <hi rend="italic">x=z</hi> and equation (20)
                    becomes <hi rend="italic underline"> dβ</hi><hi rend="italic">__</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     underline"> dx</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> 2 er</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0~ 2 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">ä</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A ’ (32)</p>
                <p part="N">the integral of which, since <hi rend="italic">d. e</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> le3,</hi><hi rend="italic">≈2 c ^</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> ca</hi><hi rend="italic">dx,</hi> is tan d= — ————∙ <hi
                        rend="italic">fP</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,x</hi> + C .</p>
                <p part="N">4c4cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A</p>
                <p part="N">To determine the constant we suppose <hi rend="italic">x=0,</hi> in
                    which case 0≡A, and we have tan A= — -- <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>- + C,</p>
                <p part="N">4 <hi rend="italic">ch</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A whence
                    the complete integral is tan 0=tan A — <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> - -- fe
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> «— 1)</p>
                <p part="N">4 <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic">h</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A ∖ <hi rend="italic">P</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Multiplying both sides of this equation by <hi rend="italic">d x,</hi>
                    observing that <hi rend="italic">dyzzd x</hi> tan 0, and integrating, we get
                    v=tan A <hi rend="italic">x —</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi> — <hi
                        rend="subscript"> i</hi>-ι--— <hi rend="italic">(—e?</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> CJC</hi> —aΛ + C.</p>
                <p part="N">4 <hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi rend="italic">h</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A ∖2 <hi rend="italic">c J '</hi></p>
                <p part="N">But when <hi rend="italic">x=Q, y—0,</hi> and this equation becomes <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 0</hi> ≈ Q^ 2A <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ¾Λ + <hi
                        rend="superscript"> c</hi> 5</p>
                <p part="N">8c <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">ä</hi> cos* A</p>
                <p part="N">therefore the complete integral is</p>
                <p part="N">J'='' tan J—_(^_.^_1) <hi rend="subscript">;</hi> (33)</p>
                <p part="N">which gives an approximate equation of the trajectory between the
                    co-ordinates <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">To determine the time corresponding to the horizontal distance <hi
                        rend="italic">x,</hi> we have from equation (19) <hi rend="italic">^</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> ι</hi><hi rend="italic">-
                        dx=</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">gdt</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> whence by reason of (32) <hi
                        rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">=,</hi><hi rend="italic">——</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >-</hi> 6 <hi rend="superscript"> 2c</hi> ⅛ <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi>,andcon-</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">2gh</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> A
                    sequently <hi rend="italic">dt=ο-~-- *</hi><hi rend="italic">- c∞dx.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">√(2y∕z) cos A</p>
                <p part="N">Integrating this expression, and determining the constant so that <hi
                        rend="italic">x≈Q</hi> when ∕=0, we get <hi rend="italic">t=</hi> ï (<hi
                        rend="subscript"> e</hi> ∞ j λ (<hi rend="superscript"> 34</hi>)</p>
                <p part="N">ccosA√(2≠∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The two equations (33) and (34) may be employed for the purpose of
                    determining the co-efficient <hi rend="italic">c</hi> of the resistance on the
                    terminal velocity which depends on it, from experiments. Suppose the trajectory
                    to be continued to D, a small distance below the horizontal line AB. For this
                    point of the curve the approximation may still be regarded as sufficiently
                    accurate. Let DE be vertical, make AE=α, ED=β, and the time in which the
                    projectile passes from A to D=rΓ Substituting these values of∙z∙,y, and Zin the
                    equations (33) and (34), making cos A=1, because A is by supposition a very
                    small angle, and observing that since D is below AB, <hi rend="italic">y</hi>
                    must be taken as negative, the two equations give</p>
                <p part="N">84c <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (∕≡+αtan A)=e <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> **—2cα 1,</p>
                <p part="N">τc√(2≠)=e^-1. (35)</p>
                <p part="N">Now, of <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> the quantities involved in these
                    equations, <hi rend="italic">g</hi> and tan A are known, and α, <hi
                        rend="italic">β,</hi> τ, can be determined by direct experiments, leaving
                    only <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and <hi rend="italic">h</hi> to be computed from
                    the equations. On squaring the second, and substituting the resulting value of
                        <hi rend="italic">h</hi> in the first, we obtain the equation</p>
                <p part="N">, ∕4 <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi><hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> * l) <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">+ (3⅛α tan A)≡≡e <hi rend="superscript"> 2eα</hi> — <hi rend="italic"
                        >2cα</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> 1, (36)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">•J</hi> from which <hi rend="italic">c</hi> may be
                    computed, and thence <hi rend="italic">h</hi> by means of one of the equations
                    (35).</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540877?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0877-0654"/>
                <p part="N">Of the quantities which enter into the equations (35) and which are to
                    be found from experiment, that which can be determined with the least certainty
                    is τ, the time of flight. This, however, may be eliminated by varying the
                    experiment. Suppose the projectile to be discharged at a different height above
                    the ground, for instance the top of a tower, (the angle of elevation A, and the
                    initial velocity remaining the same,) and let <hi rend="italic">a, β,</hi>
                    become respectively <hi rend="italic">a', β',</hi> we have then, from the first
                    of equations (35), <hi rend="italic">8hc</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">(β'+a'</hi> tan A)=e <hi rend="superscript"> 2c</hi>
                    *'-2cα ’-1 87ic <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (3+α tan A)=t∙ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2cα</hi>- <hi rend="italic">2ca</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi> 1, whence</p>
                <p part="N">(∕S'+α' tan A)(e <hi rend="superscript"> 9c</hi> *— <hi rend="italic"
                        >2ca</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> l)=(∕3 + αtan A)(e <hi rend="superscript">
                        2cα</hi> ^— <hi rend="italic">2ca'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> 1) an
                    equation from which the value of <hi rend="italic">c</hi> may be computed when
                    α, <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> and also α' <hi rend="italic">β'</hi> are
                    determined from experiments.</p>
                <p part="N">The solution which we have now given of this celebrated problem is exact
                    in principle, and the application of it by no means difficult or even operose.
                    But let us see what advantage we are likely to derive from it.</p>
                <p part="N">In the first place, it is very limited in its application. There are few
                    circumstances of general coincidence, and almost every case requires an
                    appropriate calculus. Perhaps the only general rules are the two following:</p>
                <p part="N">1. Balls of equal density, projected with the same elevation, and with
                    velocities which are as the square roots of their diameters, will describe
                    similar curves. This is evident, because, in this case, the resistance will be
                    in the ratio of their quantities of motion. Therefore all the homologous lines
                    of the motion will be in the proportion of the diameters.</p>
                <p part="N">2. If the initial velocities of balls projected with the same elevation
                    are in the inverse subduplicate ratio of the whole resistances, the ranges, and
                    all the homologous lines of their track, will be inversely as those
                    resistances.</p>
                <p part="N">These theorems are of considérable use; for by means of a proper series
                    of experiments on one ball projected with different elevations and velocities,
                    tables may be constructed which give the motions of an infinity of others.</p>
                <p part="N">But when we take a retrospective view of what we have done, and consider
                    the conditions which were assumed in the solution of the problem, we shall find
                    that much yet remains before it can be rendered of great practical use. The
                    resistance is all along supposed to be in the duplicate ratio of the velocity;
                    but even theory points out many causes of deviation from this law, such as the
                    pressure and condensation of the air, in the case of very swift motions; and Mr.
                    Robins’s experiments are sufficient to show us that the deviations must be
                    exceedingly great in such cases. Euler and all subsequent writers have allowed
                    that it may be three times greater, even in cases which frequently occur; and
                    Euler gives a rule for ascertaining with tolerable accuracy what this increase
                    and the whole resistance may amount to. Let H be the height of a column of air
                    whose weight is equivalent to the resistance taken, in the duplicate ratio of
                    the velocity. The whole resistance will be expressed by ∏ +</p>
                <p part="N">H <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p part="N">———. This number 28845 is the height in feet of a column of air whose
                    weight balances its elasticity. We shall not at present call in question his
                    reason for assigning this precise addition. They are rather reasons of
                    arithmetical con-veniençy than of physical import. It is enough to observe, that
                    if this measure of the resistance is introduced into the process of
                    investigation, it is totally changed; and it is not too much to say, that with
                    this complication it requires the knowledge and address of a Euler to make even
                    a partial and very limited approximation to a solution. Any law of the
                    resistance, therefore, which is more complicated than what Bernoulli has
                    assumed, namely, that of a simple power of the velocity, must be abandoned on
                    account of the intricacy of the calculations; and’ mathematicians have attempted
                    to avoid the errorarising from the assumption of the duplicate ratio of the
                    velocity, either by supposing the resistance throughout the whole trajectory to
                    be greater than what it is in general, or they have divided the trajectory into
                    different portions, and assigned different resistances to each, which vary,
                    through the whole of that portion, in the duplicate ratio of the velocities. In
                    this manner they make up a trajectory and motion which correspond, in some
                    tolerable degree, not with an accurate theory, but with a series of experiments.
                    For, in the first place, every theoretical computation that we make, proceeds on
                    a supposed initial velocity; and this cannot be ascertained with any thing
                    approaching to precision, by any theory of the action of gunpowder that we are
                    yet possessed of. In the next place, our theories of the resisting power of the
                    air are entirely established on the experiments on the flights of shot and
                    shells, and are corrected and amended till they tally with the most approved
                    experiments we can find. We do not learn the ranges of a gun by theory, but the
                    theory by the range of the gun. Now the variety and irregularity of all the
                    experiments which are appealed to are so great, and the acknowledged difference
                    between the resistance to slow and swift motions is also so great, that there is
                    hardly any supposition which can be made concerning the resistance, that will
                    not agree in its results with many of those experiments. It appears from the
                    experiments of Dr. Hutton of Woolwich, in 1784, 1785, and 1786, that the shots
                    frequently deviated to the right or left of their intended track 200, 300, and
                    sometimes 400 yards. This deviation was quite accidental and anomalous, and
                    there can be no doubt but that the shot deviated from its intended and <hi
                        rend="italic">supposed</hi> elevation as much as it deviated from the
                    intended vertical plane, and this without any opportunity of measuring or
                    discovering the deviation. Now, when we have the whole ranges from one to three
                    to choose among for our measure of resistance, it is evident that the
                    confirmations which have been drawn from the ranges of shot are but feeble
                    arguments for the truth of any opinion. Mr. Robins finds his measures fully
                    confirmed by experiments made at Metz and Minorca. Mr. Muller finds the same.
                    Yet Mr. Robins’s measures, both of the initial velocity and of the resistance,
                    are at least treble of Mr. Muller’s; but by compensation they give the same
                    results. The Chevalier Borda has adduced the very same experiments in support of
                    his theory, in which he abides by the Newtonian measure of the resistance, which
                    is about ½ of Mr. Robins’s, and about ∣ of Muller’s. From all this we may
                    conclude, that we have as yet a very uncertain and imperfect knowledge of the
                    law and the measure of the air’s resistance.</p>
                <p part="N">There is another essential defect in the conditions assumed in the
                    solution. The density of the air is supposed uniform; whereas we are certain
                    that it is less by one-fifth or one-&gt;sixth towards the vertex of the curve,
                    in many cases which frequently occur, than it is at the beginning and end of the
                    flight. This is another latitude given to authors in their assumptions of the
                    air’s resistance. Borda has, with considerable ingenuity, accommodated his
                    investigation to this circumstance, by dividing the trajectory into portions,
                    and, without much trouble, has made one equation answer them all. We are
                    disposed to think that his solution of the problem (in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Memoirs</hi> of the Academy of Paris for 1769) corresponds better with the
                    physical circumstances of the case than any other. But this process is there
                    delivered in too concise a manner to be intelligible to a person not perfectly
                    familiar with all the resources of modern analysis.</p>
                <p part="N">After all, the practical artillerist must rely chiefly on the records of
                    experiments contained in the books of practice at the academies, or those made
                    in a more public manner^</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540890?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0890-0655"/>
                <p part="N">Even a perfect theory of the air’s resistance can do him little service,
                    unless the force of gunpowder were uniform. This is far from being the case even
                    in the same powder. A few hours of a damp day will make a greater difference
                    than occurs in any theory; and, in service, it is only by trial that everything
                    is performed. If the first shell fall very much short of the mark, a little more
                    powder is added; and in cannonading, the correction is made by varying the
                    elevation.</p>
                <p part="N">The experiments of Mr. Robins and Dr. Hutton show, in the most
                    incontrovertible manner, that the resistance to a motion exceeding 1100 feet in
                    a second, is almost <hi rend="italic">three times</hi> greater than in the
                    duplicate ratio of the resistance to moderate velocities. Euler’s translator, in
                    his comparison of the author’s trajectories with experiment, supposes it to be
                        <hi rend="italic">no</hi> greater. Yet the coincidence is very great. The
                    same may be said of Borda’s. Nay, the same may be said of Mr. Robins’s own
                    practical rules: for he assumes the quantity which represents the height due to
                    the terminal velocity, almost double of what these authors do, and yet his rules
                    are confirmed by practice.</p>
                <p part="N">But it must not be inferred from all this, that the physical theory is
                    of no use to the practical artillerist. It plainly shows him the impropriety of
                    giving the projectile an enormous velocity. This velocity is of no effect after
                    200 or 300 yards at farthest, because it is so rapidly reduced by the prodigious
                    resistance of the air. Mr. Robins has deduced several practical maxims of the
                    greatest importance from what we already know of this subject, and which could
                    hardly have been even conjectured without this knowledge. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Gunnery.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">It must also be acknowledged, that this branch of physical science is
                    highly interesting to the philosopher; nor should he despair of carrying it to a
                    greater perfection. The defects arise almost entirely from our ignorance of the
                    law of variation of the air’s resistance. Experiments may be contrived much more
                    conducive to our information here than those commonly resorted to. The oblique
                    flights of projectiles are, as wc have seen, of very complicated investigation,
                    and ill fitted for instructing us; but numerous and well contrived experiments
                    on the perpendicular ascents are of great simplicity, being affected by nothing
                    but the air’s resistance.</p>
                <p part="N">We shall conclude this article, by giving two tables, computed from the
                    principles established above, and which serve to bring into one point of view
                    the chief circumstances of the motion in a resisting medium. Although the result
                    of much calculation, as any person who considers the subject will readily see,
                    they must not be considered as offering any very accurate results; or that, in
                    comparison with one or two experiments, the differences shall not be
                    considerable. Let any person peruse the published registers of experiments which
                    have been made with every attention, and he will see such enormous
                    irregularities, that all expectations of perfect agreement with them must cease.
                    In the experiments at Woolwich in 1785, which were continued for several days,
                    not only do the experiments of one day differ among themselves, but the mean of
                    all the experiments of one day differs from the mean of all the experiments of
                    another no less than one-fourth of the whole. The experiments in which the
                    greatest regularity may be expected, are those made with great elevations. When
                    the elevation is small, the range is more affected by a change of velocity, and
                    still more by any deviation from the supposed or intented direction of the
                    shot.</p>
                <p part="N">The first table shows the distance in yards to which a ball projected
                    with the velocity of 1600 feet in a second will go, before its velocity is
                    reduced one-tenth, and the distance at which it drops 16 feet from the line of
                    its direction. This table is calculated by the resistance observed in Mr.
                    Robins’s experiments. The first column is the weight of the ball in pounds. The
                    second column remains the same whatever be the initial velocity; but the third
                    column depends on the velocity. It is here given for the velocity which is very
                    usual in military service, and its use is to assist us in directing the gun to
                    the mark. If the mark at which a ball of 24 pounds is directed is 474 yards
                    distant, the axis of the piece must be pointed 16 feet higher than the mark.
                    These deflections from the line of direction are nearly as the squares of the
                    distances.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">I.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">II.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">in.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">92</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">420</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">121</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">428</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">159</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">456</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">18</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">200</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">470</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">32</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">272</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">479</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">The next table contains the ranges in yards of a 24- pound shot,
                    projected at an elevation of 45°, with the different velocities in feet per
                    second, expressed in the first column. The second column contains the distances
                    to which the ball would go <hi rend="italic">in vacuo</hi> in a horizontal
                    plane; and the third contains the distances to which it will go through the air.
                    The fourth column is added, to shew the height to which it rises in the air; and
                    the fifth shows the ranges corrected for the diminution of the air’s density as
                    the bullet ascends, and may therefore be called the <hi rend="italic">corrected
                        range.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The initial velocities can never be pushed as far as they have been
                    calculated for in this table; but we mean it for a table of more extensive use
                    than appears at first sight. Recollect, that while the proportion of the
                    velocity at the vertex to the terminal velocity remains the same, the curves
                    will be similar; therefore, if the initial velocities are as the square roots of
                    the diameters of the balls, they will describe similar curves, and the ranges
                    will be as the diameters of the balls.</p>
                <p part="N">Let it be required, for example, to find the range of a 12- pound shot,
                    projected at an elevation of 45°, with the velocity 1500; suppose the diameter
                    of the twelve-pounder to be√, and that of the twenty-four-pounder D; and let the
                    velocities be <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and V: Then say, <hi rend="italic"
                        >sjd:</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> a</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >∕D=15OO</hi>: a fourth proportional V. If the twenty-four-pounder be
                    projected with the velocity V, it will describe a curve similar to that
                    described by the twelve-pounder, having the initial velocity 1500. Therefore
                    find (by interpolation) the range of the twenty-four-pounder, having the initial
                    velocity V. Call this R. Then D: d=R: <hi rend="italic">τ,</hi> the range of the
                    twelve-pounder which was wanted, and which, assuming the diameters of</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">L</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">II.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">III.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">IV.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">V.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">200</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">416</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">349</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">106</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">360</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1664</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1121</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">338</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1150</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">600</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3740</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1812</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">606</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1859</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">800</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6649</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2373</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">866</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2435</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1000</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">10300</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2845</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1138</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2919</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1200</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">14961</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3259</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1378</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3343</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">20364</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3640</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1606</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3734</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1600</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">26597</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3950</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1814</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4050</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1800</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">33663</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4235</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1992</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4345</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2000</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">41559</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4494</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2168</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4610</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2200</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">50286</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4720</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2348</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4842</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">59846</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4917</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2460</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5044</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2600</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">70235</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5106</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2630</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5238</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2800</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">81456</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5293</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2760</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5430</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3000</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">93465</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5455</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2862</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5596</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193540903?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-0903-0656"/>
                <p part="N">the balls to be 4∙45 and 5∙61 inches, respectively, will be found
                    3312.</p>
                <p part="N">This table* shews the immense difference between the motions through the
                    air and in a void. It shews also that the ranges through the air, instead of
                    increasing in the duplicate ratio of the initial velocities, really increase
                    slower than those velocities in all cases of military service; and in the most
                    usual cases, viz. from 800 to 1600, they increase nearly as the square roots of
                    tbe velocities.</p>
                <p part="N">A set of similar tables, made for different elevations, would almost
                    complete what can be done by theory, and would be much more expeditious in their
                    use than Mr. Euler’s <hi rend="italic">Trajectories,</hi> computed with great
                    labour by his English translator.</p>
                <p part="N">The same table may also serve for computing the ranges of bomb -shells.
                    We have only to find what must be the initial velocity of the twenty-four-pound
                    shot which corresponds to the proposed velocity of the shell. This must be
                    deduced from the diameter and weight of the shell, by making the velocity of the
                    twenty-four pounder such, that the ratio£of its weight to the resistance may be
                    the same as in the shell.</p>
                <p part="N">Dr. Hutton, in his <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Tracts</hi> (vol. iii.
                    p. 276), has given a similar table, deduced partly from theory and partly from
                    experiment, but the numbers in the three last columns differ greatly from the
                    above, particularly for the higher velocities. Thus, for the velocity of 1600
                    feet, Dr. Hutton’s corrected range is 2264 yards, and the Height to which the
                    ball rises 650 yards, instead of 4050 and 1814, as in our table.</p>
                <p part="N">For further information on this subject, see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Gunnery;</hi> Robins’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Tracts</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> Brown’s <hi rend="italic">True Principles of
                        Gunnery</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Hutton’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical
                        Tracts</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and for an example of the computation of
                    a trajectory by the method of quadratures, Legendre’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Exercises de Calcul,</hi> tome i. p. 330.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
