<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0500-0434-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SOCIETIES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 434</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166263">Vices</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166236">Vice</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1130862">Sprat</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:832891">Birch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878051">Cooks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1754966">Cooking</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1245821">Polynesia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=500" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SOCIETIES</label>, associations voluntarily formed by a
                    number of individuals for promoting knowledge, industry, or virtue. They may
                    therefore be divided into three classes; societies for promoting science and
                    literature, societies for encouraging and promoting arts and manufactures, and
                    societies for diffusing religion and morality and relieving distress. These,
                    however, are so numerous and fluctuating, that it would be difficult to offer
                    any thing like an accurate account of them. The reader is referred for
                    information on the subject to the articles, <hi rend="smallcaps">London Dublin,
                    Edinburgh,</hi> and the other towns and countries where these institutions have
                    been established. We shall only notice the Royal Societies of London and
                    Edinburgh.</p>
                <p>The Royal Society of London is an academy or body of persons of eminent learning,
                    instituted by Charles II., for the promoting of all the different branches of
                    physical knowledge. The origin of this society is traced by Dr. Sprat, its
                    earliest historian, no farther back than to “some space after the end of the
                    civil wars” in the seventeenth century. The scene of the first meetings of the
                    learned men who laid the foundation of it, is by him fixed in the university of
                    Oxford, at the lodgings of Dr. Wilkins, warden of Wadham College. But Dr. Birch,
                    on the authority of Dr. Wallis, one of its earliest and most considerable
                    members, assigns it an earlier origin. According to him, certain worthy persons,
                    residing in London about the year 1645, being “inquisitive into natural and the
                    new and experimental philosophy, agreed to meet weekly on a certain day, to
                    discourse upon such subjects, and were known by the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Invisible</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Philosophical college”</hi> In the
                    years 1648 and 1649, the company who formed these meetings was divided, part
                    retiring to Oxford and part remaining in London; but they continued the same
                    pursuits as when united, corresponding with each other, and giving a mutual
                    account of their respective discoveries. About the year 1659 the greater part of
                    the Oxford society returned to London, and again uniting with their
                    fellow-labourers, met once, if not twice a-week at Gresham College, during
                    term-time, till they were scattered by the public distractions of that year, and
                    the place of their meeting made quarters for soldiers. On the restoration in
                    1660 their meetings were revived, and attended by a greater concourse of men
                    eminent for their rank and learning. They were at last taken notice of by the
                    king, who having himself a considerable taste for physical science, was pleased
                    to grant them an ample charter, dated the 15th of July 1662, and afterwards a
                    second dated 15th April 1663, by which they were erected into a corporation,
                    consisting of a president, council, and fellows, for promoting natural
                    knowledge; and to give their investigations, against which strange prejudices
                    were entertained, every possible support, he sometimes honoured their meetings
                    with his presence.</p>
                <p>Their manner of electing fellows is by balloting. Their council consists of
                    twenty-one, including the president, vice-president, treasurer, and two
                    secretaries, eleven of which are continued for the next year, and ten more added
                    to them; all being chosen on St. Andrew’s day.</p>
                <p>The services which this illustrious society has rendered to the public are very
                    great. They have improved naval, civil, and military architecture; advanced the
                    security and perfection of navigation; improved agriculture; and put not only
                    this kingdom, but also Ireland, the plantations, &amp;c, upon planting. They
                    have registered experiments, histories, relations, observations, &amp;c., and
                    reduced them into one common stock; and have, from time to time, published those
                    which they reckoned most useful, under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophical Transactions,</hi> &amp;c. They have a library adapted to their
                    institution; towards which Mr. Henry Howard, afterwards duke of Norfolk,
                    contributed the Norfolcian library, and which has been vastly increased by a
                    continual series of benefactions.</p>
                <p>The Royal Society of Edinburgh was incorporated by royal charter on the 29th of
                    March 1783, and has for its object the cultivation of every branch of science,
                    erudition, and taste. Its rise and progress towards its present state was as
                    follows. In the year 1718 a literary society was established in Edinburgh by the
                    learned Ruddiman and others, which in 1731 was succeeded by a society instituted
                    for the improvement of medical knowledge. In the year 1739 the celebrated
                    Maclaurin conceived the idea of enlarging the plan of this society, by extending
                    it to subjects of philosophy and literature. The institution was accordingly
                    new-modelled by a printed set of laws and regulations, the number of members was
                    increased, and they were distinguished from that time by the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Society for Improving Arts and Sciences,</hi> or more
                    generally by the title of <hi rend="italic">The Philosophical Society of
                    Edinburgh.</hi> Its meetings, however, were soon interrupted by the disorders of
                    the country during the rebellion in 1745; and they were not renewed till the
                    year 1752. Soon after this period the first volume of the Transactions of the
                    Philosophical Society of Edinburgh was published, under the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Essays and Observations, Physical and Literary,</hi> and was
                    followed by other volumes of acknowledged merit. About the end of the year 1782,
                    in a meeting of the professors of the university of Edinburgh, many of whom were
                    likewise members of the Philosophical Society, and warmly attached to its
                    interests, a scheme was proposed by the late Dr. Robertson, principal of the
                    university, for the establishment of a new society on a more extended plan, and
                    after the model of some of the foreign academies. It appeared an expedient
                    measure to solicit the royal patronage to an institution of this nature, which
                    promised to be of national importance, and to request an establishment by
                    charter from the crown. The plan was approved and adopted; and the Philosophical
                    Society, joining its influence as a body in seconding the application from the
                    university, his majesty, as we have already observed, was graciously pleased to
                    incorporate The Royal Society of Edinburgh by charter.</p>
                <p>Members are elected by ballot. The general business of the society is managed by
                    a president, two vice-presidents, with a council of twelve, a general secretary,
                    and a treasurer. These officers are chosen by ballot annually on the last Monday
                    of November. All public deeds, whether of a civil or of a literary nature, are
                    transacted by this board, and proceed in the name of the president or
                    vice-president.</p>
                <p>As it was thought that the members would have a greater inducement to punctual
                    attendance on the meetings of the society, if they had some general intimation
                    of the nature of the subjects which were to be considered, and made the topics
                    of conversation, it was therefore resolved to divide the society into two
                    classes, which should meet and deliberate separately. One of these classes is
                    denominated the <hi rend="italic">Physical class,</hi> and has for its
                    department the sciences of mathematics, natural philosophy, chemistry, medicine,
                    natural history, and whatever relates to the improvement of arts and
                    manufactures. The other is denominated the <hi rend="italic">Literary
                    class,</hi> and has for its department literature, philology, history,
                    antiquities, and speculative philosophy. There are many valuable papers in the
                    volumes that have been published of the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of
                    this society.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Society</hi><hi rend="italic">Isles,</hi> a cluster
                    of isles, so named by Captain Cook in 1769. They are situated between the
                    latitudes of 16. 10. and 16.55. south, and between the longitudes of 150. 57.
                    and 152. west. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Polynesia.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
