<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0632-0552-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">SQUARING, or 
                    Quadrature</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 552</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term><term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9rb77">Polygons</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="22" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term><term n="20" ref="fasttopic:914456">Equality</term><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1070488">Polygons</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1174597">White</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=632" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">SQUARING, or <hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                    Quadrature</hi></label><hi rend="italic">of the Circle,</hi> signifies the
                    finding a square exactly equal to the area of a given circle. This problem,
                    however, has not been, and probably cannot be, strictly resolved by the commonly
                    admitted principles of geometry; mathematicians having hitherto been unable to
                    do more than to find a square that shall differ from the area of any proposed
                    circle by as small a quantity as they please. The problem is of the same degree
                    of difficulty, and indeed may be regarded as identical with another geo metrical
                    problem, namely, the <hi rend="italic">rectification of the circle,</hi> or the
                    finding a straight line equal to its circumference; for the area of a circle is
                    equal to that of a rectangle contained by the radius and a straight line equal
                    to half the circumference; therefore, if a straight line exactly equal to the
                    circumference could be found, a rectlineal space precisely equal to the area
                    might also be found, and the contrary. But although no perfectly accurate
                    resolution of the problem has been obtained under either form, we can always
                    find approximate values of the area and circumference; and it is now customary
                    to apply the terms <hi rend="italic">quadrature</hi> and <hi rend="italic">rectification</hi> of the circle also to these.</p><p>The problem of the quadrature of the circle appears to have engaged the attention
                    of geometers at a very early period; for we are told that Anaxagoras, who lived
                    about live hundred years before Christ, attempted its solution while confined in
                    prison on account of his philosophical opinions. We are ignorant of the result
                    of his researches; but al though we cannot suppose they were attended with any
                    success, we may reasonably conclude that we are indebted to them for the
                    discovery of some of the properties of the figure, which are now known as
                    elementary propositions in geometry.</p><p>Hippocrates of Chios was likewise engaged in trying to resolve the same problem,
                    and it was no doubt in the course of his inquiries into this subject, that he
                    discovered the quadrature of the curvilineal space, which is now known by the
                    name of the <hi rend="italic">Lune</hi> of Hippocrates. The nature of this
                    discovery may be briefly explained as follows. Let ABCD be a circle, H its
                    centre, AC its diameter, ADC a triangle inscribed in the semicircle, having its
                    sides, AD, DC equal to one another. On</p><p>D as a centre, with DA or DC as <hi rend="italic">a</hi> ra dius, let the
                    quadrantal arch AEC be described, then shall the curvilineal space bounded by
                    the semicircle ABC</p><p>and the quadrantal arch AEC (which is the <hi rend="italic">Lune</hi> of
                    Hippocrates), be equal to the rectilineal triangle ADC.</p><p>Although Hippocrates’s discovery has led to no important conclusion either
                    relating to the quadrature of the circle or that of any other curve, yet at the
                    time it was made, it might be regarded as of some consequence, chiefly because
                    it shewed the possibility of exhibiting a rectilineal figure equal to a space
                    bounded by curve lines, a thing which we have reason to suppose was then done
                    for the first time, and might have been fairly doubted, considering the
                    insuperable difficulty that was found to attend the quadrature of the circle or
                    its rectification.</p><p>Aristotle speaks of two persons, namely, Bryson and An tiphon, who, about his
                    time, or a little earlier, were occu pied with the quadrature of the circle. The
                    former appears, according to the testimony of Alexander Aphrodiseus, to have
                    erred most egregiously; he having concluded that the circumference was exactly
                    3¾ times the diameter. And the latter seems to have proceeded in the same manner
                    as Archimedes afterwards did in squaring the parabola, that is, by first
                    inscribing a square in the circle, then an isoceles tri angle in each of the
                    segments of the curve, having for its base a side of the square; and next again
                    a series of triangles in the segments, having for their bases the sides of the
                    former series, and so on. This mode of procedure, how ever, was not attended
                    with success, as these spaces do not, as in the case of the parabola, admit of
                    being absolutely summed.</p><p>It may be supposed that Archimedes exerted his utmost efforts to resolve this
                    problem; and probably it was only<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=633" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0633-0553"/>
                    after long meditation on the subject that he lost all hopes of success, and
                    contented himself with that approximation to the ratio of the diameter to the
                    circumference which is contained in his treatise <hi rend="italic">De Circuli
                    Dimensione.</hi> He found his approximation to the ratio, by supposing a regular
                    polygon of ninety-six sides, to be described about the circle, and another of
                    the same number, to be inscribed in it, and by shewing that the perimeter of the
                    circumscribing polygon was less than 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 70</hi>, or 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> times the diameter, but that the perimeter of the
                    inscribed figure was greater than 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 71</hi> times the diameter; now, the circumference of the
                    circle being less than the perimeter of the one polygon, but greater than that
                    of the other; it follows that the circumference must be less than 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> times the diameter,
                    but greater than 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    71</hi> times; so that, taking the first of these limits, as being expressed by
                    the smallest numbers, the circumference will be to the diameter as 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> to 1, or as 22 to 7
                    nearly.</p><p>Although the ratio found by Archimedes be the oldest known in the western world,
                    yet one more accurate was known at a much earlier period in India. This we learn
                    from the Institutes of Akbar <hi rend="italic">(Ayeen Akberry),</hi> where it is
                    said that the Hindoos suppose the diameter of a circle to be to its
                    circumference as 1250 to 3927. Now, this ratio must have required the
                    inscription of a polygon of 768 sides in the circle, and must have been attended
                    with nine ex tractions of the square root, each carried as far as ten places of
                    figures.</p><p>We learn from Simplicius that Nicoedes and Apollonius both attempted to square
                    the circle, the former by means of a curve, which he called the <hi rend="italic">quadratrix;</hi> the invention of which, however, is ascribed to
                    Dinostratus, and the latter, by the help of a curve, denominated the sister to
                    the tortuous line, or <hi rend="italic">spiral,</hi> and which was probably the
                    quadratrix of Dinostratus; the nature of which, and the manner of its
                    application to the subject in question, we shall briefly explain.</p><p>Let AFB be a quadrant of a circle,</p><p>(fig. 2), and C its centre; and conceive the radius CF to revolve uniformly about
                    C, from the position CA, until at last it coincide with CB; while at the same
                    time a line DG is carried with an uniform motion from A towards CB; the former
                    line continuing always parallel to the latter, until at last they coincide; both
                    motions being supposed to begin and end at the same instant; the point E, in
                    which the revolving radius CF, and the moveable line DG intersect one another,
                    will generate a certain curve line AEH, which is the <hi rend="italic">quadratrix</hi> of Dinostratus.</p><p>Draw EK, FL both perpendicular to CB; then because the radius AC and the
                    quadrantal arch AFB, are uniformly generated in the same time by the points D
                    and F, the contemporaneous spaces described will have to one another the same
                    ratio as the whole spaces; that is, AD: AF:: AC: AB; hence we have AC: AB:: DC,
                    or EK: FB. Now, as the moveable point F approaches to B, the ratio of the
                    straight line EK to the arch FB will approach to, and will manifestly be
                    ultimately the same as the ratio of the straight line EK to the straight line
                    FL, which again is equal to the ratio of CE to CF; therefore the ratio of the
                    radius AC to the quadrantal arch AFB is the limit of the ratio of CEtoCF,and
                    consequently equal to the ratio of CH to CB, H being the point in which the
                    quadratrix meets CB. Since therefore CH: CB:: CA, or CB: quad, arch AFB, if by
                    any means we could determine the point H, we might then find a straight line
                    equal to the quadrantal arch, (by finding a third proportional to CH and CB),
                    and consequently a straight line equal to the circumference. The point H,
                    however, can not be determined by a geometrical construction, and there fore all
                    the ingenuity evinced by the person who first thought of this method of
                    rectifying the circle, (which certainly is considerable), has been
                    unavailing.</p><p>The Arabs, who succeeded the Greeks in the cultivation of the sciences, would no
                    doubt have their pretended squavers of the circle. We however know nothing more
                    than that one of them believed he had discovered that the diameter being unity,
                    the circumfernnce was the square root of 10; a very gross mistake; for the
                    square root of 10 exceeds 3162; but Archimedes had demonstrated that the
                    circumference was less than 3·143.</p><p>It appears that, during the dark ages, some attempts were made at the resolution
                    of this famous problem, which, how ever, have always remained in manuscripts,
                    buried in the dust of old libraries. But upon the revival of learning, the
                    problem was again agitated by different writers, and particularly by the
                    celebrated Cardinal De Cusa, who distinguished himself by his unfortunate
                    attempt to resolve it. His mode of investigation, which had no solid foundation
                    in geometry, led him to conclude, that if a line equal to the sum of the radius
                    of a circle, and the side of its inscribed square were made the diameter of
                    another circle, and an equilateral triangle were inscribed in this last, the
                    perime ter of this triangle would be equal to the circumference of the other
                    circle. This pretended quadrature was refuted by Regiomontanus.</p><p>It would be trespassing too much upon the patience of our readers, were we to
                    mention all the absurd and erroneous attempts which have been made during the
                    last three centuries to square the circle. In a supplement to Montucla’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Mathematiques,</hi> we find upwards of forty
                    pretenders to the honour of this discovery enumerated. They were almost all very
                    ignorant of geometry; and many of them were wild visionaries, pretending to
                    discover inexplicable relations between the plain truths of mathematics and the
                    most mysterious doctrines of religion. From such persons as have generally
                    pursued this inquiry, no improvement whatever of the science was to be expected;
                    although, in some instances, it has derived advantage from the labours of euch
                    as have undertaken to expose the ab surdity of their conclusions; as in the case
                    of Metius, who in refuting the quadrature of one Simon à Quercu, found a much
                    nearer approximation to the ratio of the diameter to the circumference than had
                    been previously known in Eu rope, namely, that of 113 to 355.</p><p>Among the most remarkable of those who have under taken to resolve this problem,
                    we cannot fail to enumerate Joseph Scaliger, a man of stupendous erudition. Full
                    of confidence in his own powers, he believed that, entering upon the study of
                    geometry, he could not fail to surmount by the force of his genius, those
                    obstacles which had completely stopped the progress of all preceding inquirers.
                    He gave the result of his meditations to the world in 1592, under the title <hi rend="italic">Nova Cyclometria;</hi> but he was refuted by Clavius, by Vieta,
                    and others, who shewed that the magnitude which he had assigned to the
                    circumference was a little <hi rend="italic">less</hi> than the peri meter of
                    the inscribed polygon of 192 sides, which proved beyond a doubt that he was
                    wrong. Scaliger, however, was not to be convinced of the absurdity of his
                    conclusion; and indeed, in almost every instance, pretenders to this dis covery
                    have not been more remarkable for their egregious errors, than for their
                    obstinacy in maintaining that they were in the right, and all who held a
                    contrary opinion in the wrong.</p><p>The famous Hobbes came also upon the field about the year 1650, with pretensions
                    not only to the quadrature of the circle, but also to the trifection of an
                    angle, the reclification of the parabola, &amp;c.; but his pretended solutions
                    were refuted by Dr. Wallis. And this circumstance aftbrd ed him occasion to
                    write not only against geometers, but even against the science of geometry
                    itself.<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=634" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0634-0554"/> We find it recorded by Montucla, as a sort of
                    phenomenon, that one Richard White, an English Jesuit, having happened upon what
                    he conceived to be a quadrature of the circle, which he published under the
                    title, <hi rend="italic">Chrysaespis, seu Quadratura Circuli,</hi> suffered
                    himself at last to be convinced by some of his friends that he was wrong. But a
                    solution of the same problem, found out by one Mathulen of Lyon, did not end in
                    so much advantage to its author. This man in 1728 announced to the world that he
                    had discovered both the quadrature of the circle, and a perpetual motion; and he
                    was so certain of the truth of these discoveries, that he he consigned 1000 <hi rend="italic">ecus</hi> (about L.125), to be paid to any one who should
                    demonstrate that he was deceived in either. The task was not difficult. Nicoe of
                    the Academy of Sciences demonstrated that he was wrong, and he himself allowed
                    it; but he hesitated to pay the money, which Nicoe had relinquished in favour of
                    the Hotel Dieu of Lyon. The affur went before a court of justice, which adjudged
                    the money to be paid, as Nicoe had destined it, to the poor. At a later period,
                    namely, in 1753, the Chevalier de Causons, a French officer, and a man who was
                    never sup posed to be a mathematician, suddenly found a quadrature of the circle
                    in procuring a circular piece of turf to be cut; and rising from one truth to
                    another, he explained by his quadrature the doctrine of original sin, and the
                    Trinity. He engaged himself, by a public writing, to deposit with a notary the
                    sum of 300,000 francs, to be wagered against such as should oppose him, and he
                    actually lodged 10,000, which were to devolve to him who should demonstrate his
                    error. This was easily done, as it resulted from his disco very that a circle
                    was equal to its circumscribing square, that is, a part to the whole. Some
                    persons came forward to answer his challenge, and in particular a young lady
                    sued him at one of the courts of law; but the French king judg ed that the
                    chevalier’s fortune ought not to suffer on ac count of his whim; for, setting
                    aside this piece of folly, in every other respect he was a worthy man. The
                    procedure was therefore stopped, and the wager declared void.</p><p>We shall not enter further into the history of these vain and absurd attempts to
                    resolve this important problem, but proceed to state what has actually been done
                    by men of sound minds and real mathematical acquirements towards its solution.
                    And in the first place, it may be observed that the problem admits of being
                    proposed under two diffe rent forms; for it may be required to find either the
                    area of the whole circle, or, which is the same thing, the length of the whole
                    circumference; or else to find the area of any proposed sector or segment, or,
                    which is equivalent, the length of the arch of the sector or segment. The former
                    is termed the <hi rend="italic">definite,</hi> and the latter the <hi rend="italic">indefinite</hi> quadrature of the circle. The latter evidently is
                    more general than the former, and includes it as a particular case. Now, if we
                    could find by any means a finite algebraic equation that should express the
                    relation between any proposed arch of a circle, and some known straight line, or
                    lines, the magnitude of one or more of which depended on that arch, then we
                    would have an absolute rectification of the arch, and consequently a
                    rectification or quadrature of the whole circle. We here speak of an analytical
                    solution; the ancients, who were almost entirely ignorant of this branch of
                    mathematical science, must have endeavoured to treat it entirely upon
                    geometrical principles. It is now well known, how ever, that all geometrical
                    problems may be subjected to analysis; and that it is only by such a mode of
                    proceeding they have in many cases been resolved.</p><p>With respect to the definite quadrature of the circle, no unexceptionable
                    demonstration of its impossibility has hitherto been published. It is true, that
                    James Gregory, in his <hi rend="italic">Vera Circuli et Hyperbola
                    Quadratura,</hi> has given what he considered as such a demonstration; but it
                    was objected to by Huygens, one of the best geometers of his time. It is certain
                    that the ratio of the diameter to the circumference, also, that the ratio of the
                    square of the diameter to the square of a straight line equal to the
                    circumference, cannot be expressed by rational numbers, for this has been
                    strictly demonstrated by Lambert in the Berlin Memoirs for 1761. A demonstration
                    is also given in Legendre’s <hi rend="italic">Geometrie.</hi> As to the
                    indefinite quadrature, if Newton’s demonstration of the twenty-eighth lemma of
                    the first book of his <hi rend="italic">Principia,</hi> be correct, the thing
                    ought to be absolutely impossible. For the object of that proposition is to
                    prove, that in no oval figure whatever, that returns into itself, can the area
                    cut off by straight lines at pleasure, be universally found by an equation of a
                    finite dimension, and composed of a finite number of terms. If this be true,
                    then it will be impossible to express any sector of a circle taken at pleasure
                    in finite terms. It is however to be remarked, that the accuracy of the
                    reasoning by which Newton has attempted to establish the truth of the general
                    proposition, has been questioned by no less a geometer than D’Alembert; and in
                    deed we know one oval curve, which returns into itself, and which according to
                    Newton’s proposition ought there fore not to admit of an indefinite quadrature;
                    yet this is by no means the case, for it does really admit of such a quad
                    rature. The curve we mean is the <hi rend="italic">lemniscata,</hi> whose figure
                    is nearly that of the numeral character 8. Upon the whole, then, we may infer
                    that an unexceptionable demonstration of the impossibility of expressing either
                    the whole circle, or any proposed sector of it, by a finite equation, is still
                    among the <hi rend="italic">desiderata</hi> of mathematics.</p><p>Of the different methods which have been found for approximating to the area or
                    to the circumference, that of Archimedes is the only one found by the ancients
                    in the western world that has descended to modern times, and it appears to have
                    been the most accurate known, until about the year 1585, when Metius, in
                    refuting a pretended quadrature, found the more accurate ratio of 113 to 355, as
                    we have already noticed. About the same time Vieta and Adrianus Romanus
                    published their ratios, the former carrying the approximation to ten decimals
                    instead of six, (which was that of Metius’s ratio), and the latter extending it
                    to 17 figures. Vieta also gave a kind of series, which being continued to
                    infinity, gave the value of the circle.</p><p>These approximations, however, were far exceeded by that of Ludolph Van Ceulen,
                    who, in a work published in Dutch in 1610, carried it as far as 36 figures,
                    showing that if the diameter were unity, the circumference would be greater than
                    3.14159,26535,89793,23846,26433,83279,50288, but less than the same number with
                    the last figure increased by an unit. In finding this approximation, Van Ceulen
                    followed the method of Archimedes, doubling continually the number of sides of
                    the inscribed and circumscribed poly gons, until at length he found two which
                    differed only by an unit in the 36th place of decimals in the numbers ex
                    pressing their perimeters. This was rather a work of patience than of genius;
                    indeed the labour must have been prodigious. He seems to have valued highly this
                    singular effort; for in imitation of Archimedes, whose tomb was adorned with a
                    sphere and cylinder, he directed that the ratio he had found might be inscribed
                    on his tomb.</p><p>Snellius abridged greatly the labour of calculation; and although he did not go
                    beyond Van Ceulen, yet he verified his result. Des Cartes also found a
                    geometrical construction, which being repeated continually, gave the
                    circumference, and from which he might easily have deduced an expression in the
                    form of a series. Gregory of St. Vincent distinguished himself also on this
                    subject; he however committed a great error in supposing he had dis covered the
                    quadrature of both the circle and hyperbola. Gregory’s mistake was the cause of
                    a sharp controversy carried on between his disciples on the one side, and by
                    Huygens, Mersenne, and Lestaud, on the other; and it<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=635" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0635-0555"/>
                    was this that gave Huygens occasion to consider particularly the quadrature of
                    the circle, and to investigate various new and curious theorems relating to it,
                    which are contained in his <hi rend="italic">Theoremata de Quadratura
                    Hyperboles, Ellipsis, et Circuli,</hi> 1651; and in his work <hi rend="italic">De Circuli Magnitudine inventa,</hi> 1654. In particular he showed, that if c
                    denote the chord of an arch, and <hi rend="italic">s</hi> its sine, then the
                    arch itself will be greater than c+ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> (c—s), but less titan c+ <hi rend="italic">4c</hi> +
                    <hi rend="italic">s</hi></p><p>——— ×½(c—i): he also showed that the arch is less than 2e+3jt <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> the sum of <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> of its sine and <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> of its tangent.</p><p>James Gregory, in his <hi rend="italic">Vera Circuli et Hyperbolae Quad</hi><hi rend="italic">ratura,</hi> gave several curious theorems upon the relation of
                    the circle to its inscribed and circumscribed polygons, and their ratios to one
                    another; and by means of these he found with infinitely less trouble than by the
                    ordinary methods, and even by those of Snellius, the measure of the circle as
                    far as 20 places of figures. He gave also, after the example of Huygens,
                    constructions for finding straight lines nearly equal to arches of a circle, and
                    of which the degree of accuracy was greater. For example, he found that if A be
                    put for the chord of an arch of a circle, and B for twice the chord of half the
                    arch, and C be taken such that A+B: B:: B: C, then the arch itself is nearly
                    equal to</p><p>—∆, but <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> little less, the error in the case of a
                    15</p><p>complete semicircle being less than its, j&gt; <hi rend="subscript"> δβ</hi>
                    part; and when the arch does not exceed 120°, it is less than its <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 400000</hi> part; and
                    finally, for a quadrant the error is not greater than its <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 300000</hi> part. And farther, that if D be
                    such that A: B::</p><p>„ <hi rend="subscript"> v v</hi>. , , 12C + 4B—D ,</p><p>B: D, then the arch is nearly equal to ⅛, , but</p><p>J 5</p><p>a little greater, the error in the semicircle being less than its <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 1000</hi> part, and in a
                    quadrant less than its <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    60000</hi> part.</p><p>Dr. Wallis gave, in his <hi rend="italic">Arithmetica Infinitorum,</hi> a
                    singular expression for the ratio of the circle to the square of its diameter.
                    He found that the former was to the latter as 1 to the product <hi rend="underline">3×3×5×5×7×7×9×9</hi> × 1 <hi rend="underline">1 ×I1, &amp;</hi>
                    c. 2×4×4×6×6×8×8×10×10×12</p><p>the fractions <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>, &amp;c., being
                    supposed infinite in number. The products being supposed continued to infinity,
                    we have the ratio exactly; but if we stop at any finite number of terms, as must
                    necessarily be the case in its application, the result will be alternately too
                    great and too small, according as we take an odd or an even number of terms of
                    the numerator and denominator.</p><p>An expression of another kind for the ratio of the circle to the square of the
                    diameter was found by Lord Brounker. He showed that the circle being unity, the
                    square of the diameter is expressed by the continued fraction 1</p><p>H 9</p><p><hi rend="italic">2+</hi><hi rend="italic">2+∞</hi></p><p>2+l?_</p><p>2+,&amp;c which is supposed to go on to infinity, the numerators 1, 9, 25, 49,
                    <hi rend="italic">Sic.,</hi> being the squares of the odd numbers 1, 3, 5, 7,
                    &amp;c. By taking two, three, four, &amp;c., terms of this fraction, we shall
                    have a series of approximate values, which are alternately greater and less than
                    its accurate value.</p><p>Such were the chief discoveries relating to the quadrature of the circle made
                    before the time of Newton; many others, however, were quickly added by that
                    truly great man, as well as by his contemporaries. In particular, James Gregory
                    found, that <hi rend="italic">t</hi> being put for the tangent, the arch is
                    expressed by the very simple series <hi rend="italic">t</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic">f . t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> —3^^^ 5—7" + 9— &amp; <hi rend="superscript">
                    c</hi></p><p>By supposing that <hi rend="italic">t</hi> =1, in which case the arch is one
                    eighth of the circumference, we have the corresponding arch expressed by the
                    series <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 4</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">&lt;⅛M+⅛+*</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> c</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">∙&gt;</hi> which was also given by Leibnitz as a quadrature of the circle in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Acta Eruditorum</hi> in the year 1682, but was dis covered
                    by him 1673. Gregory had however found the series under its general form several
                    years before. This series is altogether inapplicable in its present form, on ac
                    count of the slowness of its convergency; for Newton has observed, that to
                    exhibit its value exact to twenty places of figures, there would be occasion for
                    no less than five thou sand millions of its terms, to compute which would take
                    up above a thousand years.</p><p>The slowness of the convergency has arisen from our supposing <hi rend="italic">t</hi> =1. If we had supposed <hi rend="italic">t</hi> greater than 1, then the
                    series would not have converged at all, but on the contrary diverged. But by
                    giving to <hi rend="italic">t</hi> a value less than 1, then the rate of
                    convergency will be increased, and that so much the more, as <hi rend="italic">t</hi> is smaller.</p><p>If we suppose the arch of which <hi rend="italic">t</hi> is the tangent to be
                    30°, then <hi rend="italic">t</hi> will be √ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> /
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> = <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> √3, and therefore half the circumference to radius
                    unity, or the circumference to the diameter unity, will be</p><p>*∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 12</hi> (<hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> X3 <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> 53 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ~73 <hi rend="superscript"> s +</hi> 9∑∙ <hi rend="superscript"> &amp;C</hi> ')·</p><p>Mr. Machin, enticed by the easiness of the process, was induced, about the
                    beginning of the last century, to continue the approximation as far as 100
                    places of figures, thus finding the diameter to be to the circumference as 1 to
                    3.14159,26535,89793,23846,26433,83279,50288,41971,69
                    399,37510,58209,74944,59230,78164,06286,20899,86280, 34825,34211,70680. After
                    him, De Lagny continued it as far as 128 figures. But he has also been outdone;
                    for in Radcliffe’s library at Oxford, there is a manuscript in which it is
                    carried as far as 150 figures!</p><p>Although this last series, which was first proposed by Dr. Halley, gives the
                    ratio of the diameter to the circumference with wonderful facility when compared
                    with the operose method employed by Van Ceulen, yet others have been since found
                    which accomplish it with still greater ease.</p><p>We have given such a method in our treatise on <hi rend="smallcaps">Algebra,</hi>
                    (see article 272.) In the same treatise, (article 273), we have given a very
                    elementary method, which may be understood by the mere elements of geometry. For
                    the analytical methods, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Fluxions.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>