<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0636-0556-07" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">STAFFA</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 556</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m3m">Caves</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22m9r">Giants</term><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pz6r">Pillars</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:849907">Caves</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:849926">Caving</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=636" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">STAFFA</label>, one of the Hebrides or Western Islands of
                    Scotland, remarkable for its basaltic pillars. It was visited by Sir Joseph
                    Banks, who communicated the following ac count of it to Mr. Pennant: “The little
                    island of Staffa lies on the west coast of Mull, about three leagues north-east
                    from Iona, or Icolumbkill: its greatest length is about an English mile, and its
                    breadth about half a one. On the east side of the island is a small bay where
                    boats generally land, a little to the southward of which the first appearance of
                    pillars is to be observed; they are small; and instead of being placed upright,
                    he down on their side, each forming a segment of a circle. From thence you pass
                    a small cave, above which the pillars, now grown a little larger, are in dining
                    in all directions: in one place in particular, a small mass of them very much
                    resembles the ribs of a ship. From hence having passed the cave, which, if it is
                    not low water, you must do in a boat, you come to the first ranges of pillars,
                    which are still not above half as large as those a little beyond. Over against
                    this place is a small island, called in Erse <hi rend="italic">Boo-sha-la,</hi>
                    separated from the main by a channel not many fathoms wide. The whole island is
                    composed of pillars without any stratum above them; they are still small, but by
                    much the neatest formed of any about the place.</p><p>“The first division of the island, for at high water it is divided into two,
                    makes a kind of a cone, the pillars con verging together towards the centre: on
                    the other they are in general laid down flat: and in the front next to the main,
                    you see how beautifully they are packed together, their ends coming out square
                    with the bank which they form. All these have their transverse sections exact,
                    and their surfaces smooth, which is by no means the case with the large ones,
                    which are cracked in all directions. I must question, how ever, if any part of
                    this whole island of Boo-sha-la is two feet in diameter.</p><p>“The main island opposite to Boo-sha-la, and farther to wards the northwest, is
                    supported by ranges of pillars pretty erect, and though not tall, (as they are
                    not uncover ed to the base), of large diameters; and at their feet is an
                    irregular pavement, made by the upper sides of such as have been broken off,
                    which extends as far under water as the eye can reach. Here the forms of the
                    pillars are apparent; these are of three, four, five, six, and seven sides; but
                    the numbers of five and six are by much the most prevalent. The largest I
                    measured was of seven; it was four feet five inches in diameter.</p><p>“The surfaces of these large pillars, in general, are rough and uneven, full of
                    cracks in all directions; the transverse figures in the upright ones never fail
                    to run in their true directions. The surfaces upon which we walked were often
                    flat, having neither concavity nor convexity; the larger number, however, was
                    concave, though some were very evidently convex. In some places, the interstices
                    within the perpendicular figures were filled up with a yellow spar: in one
                    place, a vein passed in among the mass of pillars, carrying here and there small
                    threads of spar. Though they were broken and cracked through in all directions,
                    yet their perpendicular figures might easily be traced: from whence it is easy
                    to infer, that whatever the accident might have been that caused the
                    dislocation, it happened after the formation of the pillars.</p><p>“From hence proceeding along shore, you arrive at Fingal’s Cave. Its dimensions I
                    have given in the form of a table:</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Length of the cave from the rock without,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Feet.</p><p>371</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>In.</p><p>6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">From the pitch of the arch, ,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">250</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">0</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Breadth of ditto at the moutb,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">53</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">7</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">At the farther end,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">0</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Height of the arch at the moutb,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">117</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">At the end,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">70</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">0</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Height of an outside pillar,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">39</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">6</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Of one at the northwest corner,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">54</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">0</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Depth of water at the moutb, .</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">18</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">0</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">At the bottom,</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">9</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">0</cell></row></table><p>“The cave runs into the rock in the direction of north east-by-east by the
                    compass.</p><p>“Proceeding farther to the northwest, you meet with the highest ranges of
                    pillars, the magnificent appearance of which is past all description. Here they
                    are bare to their very bases, and the stratum below them is also visible: in a
                    short time it rises many feet above the water, and gives an opportunity of
                    examining its quality. Its surface is rough, and has often large lumps of stone
                    sticking in it as if half immersed: itself, when broken, is composed of a
                    thousand heterogeneous parts, which together have very much the appearance of a
                    lava; and the more so, as many of the lumps appear to be of the very same stone
                    of which the pillars are formed. This whole stratum lies in an inclined
                    position, dipping gradually towards the southeast. As bere abouts is the
                    situation of the highest pillars, I shall mention my measurements of them, and
                    the different strata in this place, premising, that the measurements were made
                    with a line held in the hand of a person who stood at the top of the cliff, and
                    reaching to the bottom; to the lower end of which was tied a white mark, which
                    was observed by one who stayed below for the purpose: when this mark was set off
                    from the water, the person below noted it down, and made signal to him above,
                    who made then a mark in his rope: whenever this mark passed a notable place, the
                    same signal was made, and the name of the place noted down as before: the line
                    being all hauled up, and the distances between the marks measured and noted
                    down, gave, when compared<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=637" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0637-0557"/>
                    with the book kept below, the distances, as for instance in the cave:</p><p>“No. 1, in the book below, was called from the water to the foot of the first
                    pillar in the book above; No. 1 gave 36 feet 8 inches, the highest of that
                    ascent, which was corn posed of broken pillars.</p><p>“No. 1. Pillar at the west corner of Fingal’s cave.</p><p>Feet In.</p><p>1. From the water to the foot of the pillar, 12 10</p><p>2. Height of the pillar, . . 37 3</p><p>3. Stratum above the pillar, . 66 9</p><p>“No. 2. Fingal’s cave.</p><p>1. From the water to the foot of the pillar, 36 8</p><p>2. Height of the pillar, . . 39 6</p><p>9. From the top of the pillar to the top of the arcb, . . . 31 4</p><p>4. Thickness of the stratum above, . 34 4</p><p>By adding together the three first measure ments, we got the height of the arch
                    from the water, . . 117 6</p><p>“No. 3. Corner pillar to the westward of Fingal’s cave.</p><p>Stratum below the pillar of lava-like matter, 11 0 Length of pillar, . . 54 0</p><p>Stratum above the pillar, . 61 6</p><p>“No. 5. Another part to the westward.</p><p>Stratum below the pillar, . 17 1</p><p>Height of the pillar, . . 50 0</p><p>Stratum above, . . 51 1</p><p>“No. 5. Another pillar farther to the west ward.</p><p>Stratum below the pillar, . . 19 8</p><p>Height of the pillar, . . <hi rend="italic">55</hi> 1</p><p>Stratum above, . . . 54 7</p><p>“The stratum above the pillars, which is here mention ed, is uniformly the same,
                    consisting of numberless small pillars, bending and inclining in all directions,
                    sometimes so irregular that the stones can only be said to have an incli nation
                    to assume a columnar form; in others more regular, but never breaking into or
                    disturbing the stratum of large pillars, whose tops everywhere keep an uniform
                    and regular line.</p><p>“Proceeding now along the shore round the north end of the island, you arrive at
                    <hi rend="italic">0ua na scarce,</hi> or the Corvorant’s Cave. Here the stratum
                    under the pillars is lifted up very high; the pillars above are considerably
                    less than those at the northwest end of the island, but still very considerable.
                    Beyond is a bay, which cuts deep into the island, rendering it in that place not
                    more than a quarter of a mile over. On the sides of this bay, especially beyond
                    a little valley, which almost cuts the island into two, are two stages of
                    pillars, but small; however, having a stratum between them exactly the same as
                    that above them, formed of innumerable little pillars, shaken out of their
                    places, and leaning in all directions.</p><p>“Having passed this bay, the pillars totally cease; the rock is of a dark-brown
                    stone, and no signs of regularity occur till you have passed round the southeast
                    end of the island, (a space almost as large as that occupied by the pil lars),
                    which you meet again on the west side, beginning to form themselves irregularly,
                    as if the stratum had an inclination to that form, and soon arrive at the
                    bending pillars where I began.</p><p>“The stone of which the pillars are formed, is a coarse kind of basaltes, very
                    much resembling the Giant’s Cause way in Ireland, though none of them are near
                    so neat as the specimens of the latter which I have seen at the British Museum,
                    owing chiefly to the colour, which in ours is a dirty brown, in the Irish a fine
                    black; indeed the whole production seems very much to resemble the Giant’s
                    Causeway.”</p><p>Views of Fingal’s Cave are given in plates CCCLXIV and CCCLXV, under the head <hi rend="smallcaps">Minerology</hi>.</p></div></body></text></TEI>