<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0597-0523-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPALLANZANI, Lazzaro</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 523</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93g2m">Friendship</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:935174">Friendship</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:964151">Hunters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=597" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPALLANZANI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lazzaro</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated naturalist, was born at Scandiano, in the duchy of Modena, on the
                    12th of January 1729∙ He began his studies in his native country, and at the age
                    of fifteen, went to Reggio de Mo dena, where he was instructed in rhetoric and
                    philosophy by the Jesuits, who contended with the Dominicans in or der to secure
                    his attachment. His thirst for knowledge determined him to go to Bologna, where
                    his relative Laura Bassi, a woman highly celebrated for her genius, eloquence,
                    and skill in natural philosophy and mathematics, was one of the most
                    distinguished professors of Italy. Under this enlightened guide, he was taught
                    to prefer the study of nature to that of her commentators, judging of the real
                    value of the commentary by its resemblance to the original. He availed himself
                    of the wisdom of that lady’s counsels, the happy effects of which he very soon
                    experienced. Spallanzani’s taste for philosophy was not exclusive, for he
                    carefully studied his own language, became a proficient in the Latin tongue, and
                    attached himself above every other to the Greek and French. By the advice of a
                    father whom he ardently loved, he applied himself to jurisprudence; but being
                    urged by Antonio Vallisnieri to renounce his vocation, by procuring the consent
                    of his father, he gave himself up to the study of mathematics with more zeal
                    than ever, at the same time devoting himself to the study of languages, both
                    living and dead.</p>
                <p>It was not long before he was known all over Italy, and, what is seldom the case,
                    his own country first made that estimate of his talents which they justly
                    merited. In the year 1745, he was chosen professor of logic, metaphysics, and
                    Greek, in the university of Reggio, where he taught during ten years, devoting
                    every moment of his leisure to the study and contemplation of the works of
                    nature. The attention of Haller and Bonnet was fixed by his observa tions on the
                    animalculae of infusions, the latter assisting him in his laudable career, and
                    ever after distinguishing him as one of the learned interpreters of nature. He
                    was invited to the university of Modena in 1760; and some years after he
                    declined to accept of the advantageous öfters made to him by the academy of
                    Petersburg, as well as similar ones from Coimbra, Parma, and Cesena. He
                    preferred his native spot, and therefore continued at Modena till the year 1768,
                    and saw raised up by his care a generation of men constituting at that time the
                    glory of Italy, among whom we find Venturi, Belloni, Lucchesini, and Angelo
                    Mazzo.</p>
                <p>In 1765, while he resided at Modena, he published his “Saggio di Osservazioni
                    Microscopiche concernenti il Sistema di Needham e di Buffon ;” in which he
                    establishes, by a number of the most ingenious and solid experiments, the <hi
                    rend="italic">animality of microscopic animalculae.</hi> This work was sent by
                    the author to Bonnet, who drew from it a prediction respecting the future
                    celebrity of Spallanzani, which he Iived to see accomplished. This circumstance
                    gave birth to the most intimate friendship, which lasted to the close of life,
                    and constituted their chief happiness. During the same year he published a truly
                    original work, entitled “De Lapidibus ab Aqua resilientibus ;” in which he
                    proves, by the most satisfactory experiments, and in opposition to the common
                    received opinion, that what are called <hi rend="italic">ducks and drakes,</hi>
                    are not produced by the elasticity of the water, but by the effect naturally
                    resulting from the change of direction experienced by the stone in its movement,
                    after it has struck the water, and has been carried over the hollow of the cup
                    formed by the concussion.</p>
                <p>When the university of Padua was reestablished upon a larger scale, the Count de
                    Firmian was directed by the empress Maria Theresa, to invite Spallanzani to be
                    professor of Natural History, although the chair was solicited by many
                    celebrated characters. His reputation justified this prefer ence, and immense
                    crowds of students thronged to his lectures. He possessed much ingenuity, and
                    his knowledge was of vast extent: his method was simple, but rigorous in its
                    nature, and what he knew he connected with principles firmly established.</p>
                <p>In the year 1776 he published, in two volumes quarto, his work entitled “Opuscoli
                    di Fisica Animale e Vegetabile,” containing the explanation of part of the
                    microscopic observations which were previously given to the world. It must be
                    admitted, that the art of accurate observation is one of the most difficult, and
                    it cannot be denied, that it is at the same time the most necessary, and
                    requires a rare combination of talents. These were possessed by Spallanzani in a
                    remarkable degree, as is fully evinced by the researches which his admirable
                    writings have re corded. The polite manner in which he conducted his dispute
                    with Needham respecting the phenomena of gene ration, secured for him a high
                    degree of applause. On this occasion, he treated of the influence of cold upon
                    animals, and proved that the torpidity of some during winter, does not depend on
                    the impression which the blood may receive from it, since a frog deprived of
                    blood becomes torpid when reduced to the same cold state, by being immersed in
                    ice,<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=598"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0720-0598-0524"/> and swims as formerly when restored to a proper
                    degree of warmth.</p>
                <p>Spallanzani travelled through Switzerland and the Gri sons in the year 1779,
                    after which he went to Geneva, spending a month with his friends, by whom his
                    conversation was not less admired than his masterly writings. In the year 1780
                    he published, in two volumes quarto, his “Dissertazioni di Fisica Animale e
                    Vegetabile,” in which heun folded the secrets of the interpretation of two very
                    intricate phenomena, concerning the economy of animals and vege tables. To this
                    study he was led, from some experiments made by him upon <hi rend="italic"
                    >digestion;</hi> and he repeated the experiments of Reaumur on gallinaceous
                    birds, remarking that the trituration which in this case is favourable to
                    digestion, could not be a very powerful means. He perceived that the gizzard of
                    those birds, by which the stones of fruit are pulverized, did not digest the
                    powder thus formed; it being necessary that it should undergo a new operation in
                    the stomach, previous to its becoming chyle for the production of the blood and
                    other humours. This subject may be regard ed as one of the most difficult in
                    physiology, because the observer is always under the necessity of finding his
                    way in the midst of darkness: the animal must be managed with care, that the
                    derangement of the operations may be avoid ed; and when the experiments are
                    completed with great labour, it is requisite that the consequences be well
                    distinguished. In this work, Spallanzani analyses facts with scrupulosity, in
                    order to ascertain their causes with certainty; comparing nature with his
                    experiments, in order to form a correct judgment respecting them; laying hold of
                    every thing essential to them in his observations, and measuring their solidity
                    by the increase or diminution of supposed causes. John Hunter appears to have
                    been greatly hurt by this work; and in the year 1785, he was induced to publish
                    “Some Observations upon Digestion,” in which he throws out some bitter sarcasms
                    against the Italian naturalist. Spallanzani took ample revenge by publishing
                    this work in the Italian language, and addressing to Caldani in 1788, “Una
                    Lettera Apologetica in Risposta alle Osservazioni del Signor Giovanni Hunter.”
                    Here he exposed with great moderation, but at the same time with logic which
                    nothing could resist, the mistakes and errors of the British physiologist.</p>
                <p>The generation of animals and plants is discussed in the second volume of his
                    Dissertazioni; where, by experiments as satisfactory as surprising, he proves
                    the pre-existence of germs to fecundation, shewing also the existence of
                    tadpoles in the females of five different species of frogs, insalaman ders, and
                    toads, before their fecundation. He likewise re counts the success of some
                    artificial fecundations upon the tadpoles of those five species, and even upon a
                    quadruped.</p>
                <p>In the year 1781, he took the advantage of the academical vacation, for the
                    purpose of making a journey, in order to add to the cabinet of Pavia. In the
                    month of July he set out for Marseilles, where he began a new history of the
                    sea, which presented him with many new and curious facts on numerous genera of
                    the natives of the ocean. He went also to Finale, Genoa, Massa, and Carrara, to
                    make observations on the quarries of marble, held by statuaries in such
                    estimation. He then returned to Spezzia, and brought from thence to Pavia a vast
                    number of fishes, which he deposited in the cabinet of that city, wholly
                    collected by himself. With the same view and success he visited the coasts of
                    Istria in 1782, and the Apennine mountains the subsequent year, taking notice of
                    the dreadful hurricanes, and the astonishing vapours by which that year became
                    so noted in meteorology. The emperor Joseph, on examining this cabinet,
                    presented Spallanzani with a gold medal. In 1785, he was offered the chair of
                    natural history by the university of Padua, vacant by the death of Antonio
                    Vallisnieri; but in order to prevent his acceptance of it, his salary was
                    doubled by the archduke, and he went to Constantinople with Zuliani, who had
                    been appointed ambassador from the Venetian republic. He set out on the 21st of
                    August, and on the 11th of October reached the Turkish metropolis, where he
                    remained during eleven months. His attention was fixed by the physical and moral
                    phenomena of this country, which were new even to Spallanzani. He wandered along
                    the borders of the two seas, and ascended the mountains in the vicinity; he paid
                    a visit to the island of Chalki, discovering to the Turks a copper mine, the
                    existence of which they had never once conjectured. In the island of Principi,
                    not far from Constantinople, he discovered an iron mine, of which the Turks were
                    equally ignorant.</p>
                <p>A voyage by sea was undoubtedly the safest, but the dangers to which he would be
                    exposed by land were regarded as nothing when contrasted with the idea of being
                    beneficial to science and to man. Having reached Bucharest, Mauroceni, the
                    friend of science, received Spallanzani with marks of distinction, presented him
                    with many rarities which the country produced, and supplied him with horses for
                    travelling, with an escort of thirty troopers, to the confines of his own
                    dominions. The philosopher passed by Hermanstadt in Transylvania, and on the 7th
                    of December 1786, reached Vienna, where he remained during five days, and had
                    two long conferences with the emperor. He was much esteemed by the nobility of
                    that city, and respectfully visited by many literary characters. When he arrived
                    at Pa via, the students advanced from the city-gates to meet him, and testified
                    their joy at his return by repeated acclamations. He was almost instantly drawn
                    to the auditory, and compelled to ascend the chair from which he had been
                    accustomed to deliver his fascinating lectures; but in the midst of these
                    demonstrations of joy and shouts of applause, he requested them to indulge him
                    with that repose in his own house which was now so absolutely necessary. His
                    students this year exceeded 500.</p>
                <p>The reputation of Spallanzani was sufficiently brilliant to excite envy and
                    detraction. His discoveries were too original and solid to be successfully
                    disputed; but some of those who could not rival his successful ingenuity, began
                    to call in question his integrity in the management of the museum at Pavia. A
                    judicial investigation completely established the purity of his character; and
                    it must be mentioned to his honour, that he had the fortitude to forget this
                    event. His enemies in general confessed their mistake, renounced their
                    unprovoked animosity, and still hoped to regain a friendship of which they had
                    proved themselves so unworthy.</p>
                <p>In 1792 he published at Pavia, in 6 vols. 8vo, his “Viaggialle due Sicilie, ed al
                    alcune parti dell’ Appennino.” Here we meet with what may be denominated a new
                    volcanology. We are instructed how to measure the intensity of volcanic fires,
                    and almost to touch the particular gas which tears those torrents of stone in
                    fusion from the bowels of the earth, and raises them to the top of Mount Etna.
                    This delightful work is closed by some important inquiries into the nature of
                    swallows, the mildness of their dispositions, the rapidity of their flight;
                    discussing the celebrated problem respecting their remaining torpid during the
                    winter season proving that artificial coId, much more intense than what is ever
                    naturally experienced in our climates, does not reduce these birds to the torpid
                    state.</p>
                <p>Things apparently impossible were discovered by Spallanzani. In the year 1795 he
                    made one of this description, which he gave to the world in his “Lettere sopra
                    il Sospetto di un nuovo Senso nei Pippistrelli.” In that work we are informed
                    that bats, deprived of sight, act with the same precision in every instance as
                    those which have their eyes; that they shun in the same manner the most trivial
                    obsta cles, and also know where to fix themselves when their flight is
                    terminated. Several philosophers confirmed these<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=599" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0599-0525"/>
                    astonishing experiments, from which a suspicion arose, that these animals must
                    have a new sense, as it appeared to Spallanzani that the other known senses
                    could not compen sate for the want of sight; but he was afterwards inclined to
                    think, in consequence of Professor Jurin’s experiments on the organ of hearing
                    in bats, that in this particular in stance the sense of hearing might possibly
                    supply the want of sight.</p>
                <p>He published many other works, which we cannot here enumerate.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Biographie Universelle, tom.
                    xliii. p. 246, where a catalogue of Spallanzani’s works may be found.</p></note>
                    ' He had nearly finished an account of his voyage to Constantinople, and had
                    collected many valuable materials for a history of the sea, when his life and
                    labours were brought to a termination. He was seized with a retention of urine,
                    on the 30th of February 1799, and next morning was so far deprived of the use of
                    his faculties, that he only enjoyed a sound mind during very short intervals.
                    Tourdes and Scarpa did every thing to save him, which could be produced by the
                    joint exertions of genius, expe rience, and friendship, but in vain. He died on
                    the twelfth of the same month, after having completed the seventieth year of his
                    age. His works have been translated into a great variety of languages, and he
                    was enrolled as a member of many foreign academies.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
