<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0860-0716-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">STENOGRAPHY</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 716</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1169292">Vowels</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1127099">Sounds</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=860" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">STENOGRAPHY</label>.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The value of stenography is not unknown to the learned; and
                    the care and success with which it has been lately cultivated in these kingdoms
                    will, in all probability, soon render it an object of general attention. No one,
                    however, appears to us to have simplified and improved the art so much as Dr
                    Mavor, author of <hi rend="italic">Universal Stenography.</hi></p></note> The
                    art of stenography, or short writing, was known and practised by most of the
                    ancient civilized nations. The Egyptians, who at an early period were
                    distinguished for learning, at first expressed their words by a delineation of
                    figures called <hi rend="italic">hieroglyphics.</hi> A more concise mode of
                    writing seems to have been afterwards introduced, in which only a part of the
                    symbol or picture was drawn. This answered the purpose of short-hand in some
                    degree. After them the Hebrews, the Greeks, and the Romans, adopted different
                    methods of abbreviating their words and sentences, suited to their respective
                    languages. The initials, the finals, or radicals, often served for whole words;
                    and various combinations of these sometimes formed a sentence. Arbitrary marks
                    were likewise employed to determine the meaning, and to assist legibility; and
                    it seems probable that every writer and every author of antiquity had some
                    peculiar method of abbreviation, calculated to facilitate the expression of his
                    own sentiments, and intelligible only to himself. It is also probable that some
                    might by these means take down the heads of a discourse or oration; but few,
                    very few, it is presumed, could have followed a speaker through all the meanders
                    of rhetoric, and, in a manner legible even to themselves, could have noted with
                    precision every syllable as it dropt from his month. To arrive at such
                    consummate perfection in the art was reserved for more modern times, and is
                    still an acquisition by no means general.</p><p>In every language of Europe, till about the close of the sixteenth century, the
                    Roman plan of abbreviating (viz. substituting the initials or radicals, with the
                    help of arbitraries, for words) appears to have been employed. Till then no
                    regular alphabet had been invented expressly for stenography, when an English
                    gentleman of the name of Willis invented and published one.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Mr Locke says, u regular method of short
                    writing seems to be known and practised only in Britain. This is not now the
                    case; and indeed there is no reason to doubt whether characters may not be
                    invented to express the various sounds or letters employed in any language,
                    either ancient or modern.</p></note> His plan was soon improved, or at least
                    altered. One alteration succeeded another; and at intervals, for a series of
                    years past, some men of ingenuity and application have composed and published
                    systems of stenography, and doubtless have themselves reaped all the advantages
                    that attend it. But among the various methods which have been proposed, and the
                    different plans which have been adopted by individuals, none has yet appeared
                    fortunate enough to gain general approbation, or proved sufficiently simple,
                    clear, and concise, to be universally studied and practised. Some systems are
                    replete with unmeaning symbols, perplexing arbitraries, and ill-judged
                    contractions; which render them so difficult to be attained by a common
                    capacity, or ordinary application, that it is not to be wondered at if they have
                    sunk into neglect, and are now no longer known. Other systems, by being too
                    prolix, by containing a multiplicity of characters, and those characters not
                    simple or easily remembered, become ineffectual to the purpose of expedition,
                    and are only superior in obscurity to a common hand. Some, again, not only
                    reject all arbitraries and contractions, but even prepositions and terminations;
                    which last, if not too lavishly employed and badly devised, highly contribute to
                    promote both expedition and legibility; and though they reduce their characters
                    to fewer than can possibly express the various modifications of sound, yet they
                    make nearly one half of them complex. In the disposition of the vowels there is
                    the greatest perplexity in most systems. A dot is sometimes substituted for all
                    the vowels indiscriminately, and the judg ment is left to determine which letter
                    out of six any dot is intended to express; or a minute space is allotted them;
                    so that unless they be arranged with mathematical precision; they cannot be
                    distinguished from one another; but such a minute attention is inconsistent with
                    the nature of shorthand, which should teach us to write down in a short time, as
                    well as in small bounds, what we wish to preserve of what we hear. Nor is the
                    plan of lifting the pen and putting the next consonant in the vowel’s place, in
                    the middle of words, less liable to objections; or that of representing all the
                    vowels by distinct characters, being obviously ill calculated for facility and
                    despatch, and consequently inadmissible into any useful system.</p><p>It is to be confessed, that the person who first proposed the omission of vowels
                    in the middle of words,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Mr Byron rejected vowels entirely in the middle of words, as others before
                    him had only done partially. Without critically examining the executive part of
                    his performance, which is very defective, it must be owned that it is above the
                    reach of human ingenuity to exceed his general plan, which for ever must be the
                    basis of every future rational system.</p></note> which it is obvious are not
                    wanted, and invented letters which could be connected as in a running hand
                    without lifting the pen in the middle of the word, made a real improvement on
                    the works of his predecessors. But, in fine, most systems, either in their plan
                    or execution, labour under some capital defect, attended with circumstances
                    highly discouraging to the learner, and which in a great measure defeat the end
                    of their invention, by being too complicated to be learned with ease and
                    remembered with accuracy, or to be practised with the expedition which is
                    requisite; and so difficult to be deciphered, that a man can scarcely read wh.it
                    he has just written. To obviate these defects, to provide against prolixity and
                    conciseness, which might occasion obscurity, to exhibit a system founded on the
                    simplest principles, which might be easily learned and read, and yet be capable
                    of the utmost expedition, were the motives that gave rise to the present
                    attempt.</p><p>This method will be found different from any yet published, and superior to all
                    in the disposition of the vowels and the facility of arranging them; the
                    confusion in placing which seems to detract from the merit of the best
                    performances on the subject; and it may without ostentation be affirmed, that
                    characters simpler in their form, and more perfect in their union, have not been
                    applied to the art of stenography. As well as it could be determined, the
                    simplest characters are appropriated to the letters most usually employed;
                    indeed, as far as possible, those which are complex have been rejected; but as
                    it was an object always kept in view that the writing should be on a line, a few
                    are admitted into the alphabet for that reason. The characters for the double
                    and triple consonants are the easiest that could be invented, consistent with
                    perspicuity; for care has been taken to provide against all obscurity which
                    might arise by adopting letters too similar in their formation; and with respect
                    to the prepositions and terminations, those which occur most frequently are
                    expressed by the simplest characters, which will be found perfectly easy in
                    their application. The arbitraries are few in number, and the arbitrary
                    abbreviations, as they are entirely from the letters of the alphabet, and chosen
                    from some thousands of words in common use, will well repay the learner for an
                    hour’s trouble in committing them to memory.</p><p>The last section lays down a scheme of abbreviation, comprised in a few rules,
                    perfectly easy to be understood and practised by proficients in this art; and we
                    hope it will answer the expectation of the writer, and will be found free from
                    the perplexity complained of in many systems<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=863" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0863-0717"/>
                    where abbreviation is admitted. The principal rules are new, are so easy, so
                    extensive in their use, and so consistent with expedition and legibility, if
                    applied with judgment, that they alone might suffice. The learner is however
                    advised by no means to adopt any of them till experience has convinced him that
                    they may be used without error, or injury to legibility. All abbreviating rules
                    are suited to those only who have made some progress in the stenographic art;
                    for although they certainly promote expedition in a wonderful manner, and afford
                    the greatest ease to a proficient, yet a learner, as expedition is not his
                    first, though his ultimate view, should admit of nothing that in the least
                    renders the reading difficult.</p><p>II. The English alphabet consists of twenty-six letters; six of which are vowels,
                    <hi rend="italic">a, e, i</hi>, <hi rend="italic">o, u,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y;</hi> and the other twenty consonants, <hi rend="italic">b, c,
                    d, f g, h, j, h, l, m, n, p, g, r, s, t, v, w, x,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z</hi>. This alphabet, as is observed by the best grammarians that have written
                    on the language, is both defective and redundant in expressing the various
                    modifications of sound.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Lowth’s Grammar. Priestley’s Grammar. Sheridan’s Lectures on Elocution. «
                    Preface to Johnson’s Dictionary.</p></note> Custom or prejudice has assigned
                    some letters a place, when others would with much more propriety express the
                    same sound; and to this may be added, that several letters, sometimes in one
                    word, seem to be admitted for no other reason than to perplex a young beginner
                    or a foreigner, as an obstruction to true pronunciation, and to add to the
                    apparent length of the word, when they are entirely quiescent and useless. That
                    this is the genius of the orthography of our language, must be perceived by the
                    most superficial observer; but no modern tongue is absolutely free from the same
                    exceptions. In particular, the French has a great number of dormant etters,
                    which, it is obvious, render the pronunciation more difficult and perplexing to
                    learners. In this respect, the Latin and Greek claim a just superiority over the
                    modern tongues. In them no confusion or doubt can arise from the manner of
                    spelling; and the reader can scarcely be wrong, unless in quantity, in sounding
                    all the letters that he sees.</p><p>But as it is neither our business nor our intention to propose a mode of spelling
                    different from that in common use, when applied to printing or long-hand writing
                    (since several innovators in orthography have fallen into contempt, and their
                    plans have been only preserved as beacons to warn others of the folly of
                    endeavouring to subvert established principles<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• By this rule likewise <hi rend="italic">q</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v</hi> in the middle of words, but never in the
                    beginning, may be exchanged for <hi rend="italic">h</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f</hi> when they admit of an casier connecting with the following character, or
                    will make the writing appear neater.</p></note>), we shall only observe, that in
                    stenography, where the most expeditious and concise method is the best, if
                    consistent with perspicuity, the following simple rules are studiously to be
                    regarded and practised.</p><p>1. All quiescent consonants in words are to be dropped, and the orthography to be
                    directed only by the pronunciation; which being known to all, will render this
                    art attainable by those who cannot spell with precision in long-hand.</p><p>2. When the absence of consonants, not entirely dormant, can be easily known,
                    they may often be omitted without the least obscurity.</p><p>3. Two or sometimes more consonants may, to promote greater expedition, be
                    exchanged for a single one of nearly similar sound; and no ambiguity as to the
                    meaning ensue.’</p><p>4. When two consonants of the same kind or same sound come together, without any
                    vowel between them, only one is to be expressed; but if a vowel or vowels
                    intervene, both are to be written: only observe, if they arc perpendicular,
                    horizontal, or oblique lines, they must only be drawn a size longer than usual;
                    and characters with loops must have the size of their heads doubled.</p><p>Might is to be written <hi rend="italic">mit,</hi> fight <hi rend="italic">fit,</hi> machine <hi rend="italic">mashin,</hi> enough, <hi rend="italic">enuf,</hi> laugh <hi rend="italic">laf,</hi> prophet <hi rend="italic">profit,</hi> physics <hi rend="italic">fisiks,</hi> through <hi rend="italic">thro',</hi> foreign <hi rend="italic">foren,</hi> sovereign <hi rend="italic">soveren,</hi> psalm <hi rend="italic">sam,</hi> receipt <hi rend="italic">reset,</hi> write <hi rend="italic">rite,</hi> wright <hi rend="italic">rti</hi>, island <hi rend="italic">iland,</hi> knavery <hi rend="italic">narery,</hi> temptation <hi rend="italic">tentation,</hi> knife <hi rend="italic">nife,</hi> stick <hi rend="italic">stih,</hi> thigh <hi rend="italic">thi,</hi> honour <hi rend="italic">onoιιr,</hi> indictment <hi rend="italic">indilement,</hi> acquaint <hi rend="italic">aquaint,</hi> chaos
                    <hi rend="italic">haos,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>Strength <hi rend="italic">strenlh,</hi> length <hi rend="italic">tenth,</hi>
                    friendship <hi rend="italic">frenship,</hi> connect <hi rend="italic">conek,</hi> commandment <hi rend="italic">comanment,</hi> conjunct <hi rend="italic">conjunt,</hi> humble <hi rend="italic">hurnle,</hi> lumber <hi rend="italic">lumer,</hi> slumber <hi rend="italic">slumer,</hi> number <hi rend="italic">numer,</hi> exemplary <hi rend="italic">exemlary,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>Rocks <hi rend="italic">roτ,</hi> acts <hi rend="italic">ahs</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ax,</hi> facts <hi rend="italic">fahs</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fax,</hi> districts <hi rend="italic">dis-triks</hi> or <hi rend="italic">distrix,</hi> affects <hi rend="italic">afeks</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nfix,</hi> afflicts <hi rend="italic">afliks</hi> or <hi rend="italic">aflix,</hi> conquer <hi rend="italic">konkr,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>Letter <hi rend="italic">leter,</hi> little <hi rend="italic">litle,</hi> command
                    <hi rend="italic">comand,</hi> error <hi rend="italic">eror,</hi> terror <hi rend="italic">teror,</hi> &amp;c. But in <hi rend="italic">remember, moment,
                    sister,</hi> and such like words, where two consonants of the same name have an
                    intervening vowel, both of them must be written.</p><p>These four rules, with their examples, being carefully considered by the learner,
                    will leave him in no doubt concerning the disposition and management of the
                    consonants in this scheme of short writing; we shall therefore proceed to lay
                    down rules for the application of the vowels with ease and expedition.</p><p>1. Vowels, being only simple articulate sounds, though they are the connectives
                    of consonants, and employed in every word and every syllable, are not necessary
                    to be inserted in the middle of words; because the consonants, if fully
                    pronounced, with the assistance of connection, will always discover the meaning
                    of a word, and make the writing perfectly legible.</p><p>2. If a vowel is not strongly accented in the incipient syllable of a word, or if
                    it is mute in the final, it is likewise to be omitted; because the sound of the
                    incipient vowel is often implied in that of the first consonant, which will
                    consequently supply its place.</p><p>3. But if the vowel constitutes the first or last syllable of a word, or is
                    strongly accented at its beginning or end, that vowel is continually to be
                    written.</p><p>4. If a word begins or ends with two or more vowels though separated, or when
                    there is a coalition of vowels, as in diphthongs and triphthongs, only one of
                    them is to be expressed, which must be that which agrees best with the
                    pronunciation.</p><p>5. In monosyllables, if they begin or end with a vowel, it is always to be
                    inserted, unless the vowel be <hi rend="italic">e</hi> mute at the end of a
                    word.</p><p>Such are the general principles of this art; in vindication and support of which
                    it will be needless to offer any arguments, when it is considered that brevity
                    and expedition are the cbief objects, if consistent with legibility; and the
                    subsequent specimens in the orthography recommended will, we hope, be sufficient
                    to show that there is no real deficiency in the last-mentioned particular.</p><p>He who and us mst be etrnl, grt, nd mnptnt. It is or dty, as rsnl bngs, to sry,
                    lv, nd oby hm A nm tht wd avd blm, slid be srkmspk in al hs axns, nd ndvr wth al
                    hs mt to pls evry bdy.—I wd nt frm any knxns wth a nm who hd no rgrd fr hmslf;
                    nthr wd 1 blv a mn who hd ons tld me a li. —Onr is of al thngs the mst dfklt to
                    prsry ntrnshd; nd whn ons mpchd, lk the chstty of a wmn, nvr shns wth its wntd
                    lstr.—Wth gd mnrs, kmplsns, nd an esy pit adrs, mny mk a fgr in the wrl, whs mnl
                    ablts wd skrsly hv rsd thm aby the mk of a ftmn.—Idins is the prnt of a thsnd
                    msfrtns, wch ar nvr fit by the ndstrs: it is a pn nd a prishmnt of itslf, and
                    brngs wnt nd bgry in its tm Vrtu is the frst thng tht shd be rgrdd; it is a rwrd
                    of itslf; mks a man rspktbl hr, nd wl mk hm etrnly hpy hrftr.—Prd is a mst pruss
                    psn, wch yt ws plntd by hvn in ur ntr, to rs ur emlsn<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=864" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0864-0718"/>
                    to imtt grt nd wrthy krktrs or axns, to xt in us a si fr wht is rt nd gst, and a
                    ldbl ndgnsn gnst oprsrs nd wrkrs of ny and of nkyty; in shrt, to mk us st a prpr
                    vlu upn urslvs, nd dsps a wrthls flo, hu evr xltd. Ths fr prd is avrtu, nd my
                    gstly be kid a grins of si. Bt prd, lk othr psns, gnrly fxs upn rng obgks, or is
                    apld in rng prprsns. Hu kmn is it to sq a rtch whm evry vs hs rndrd msrbl, nd
                    evry fly kntmbl, vlng hmslf on hs hi brtb, nd bstng ths ilstrs nsstrs, of whm he
                    nhrts nthng bt the nm or ttl! nsstrs who, if thy nu hm, wd dsn thr dsndnt wth
                    kntmt But al prd of ths srt is fly, nd evr to be avdd.</p><p>III. As the whole of this art depends upon a regular method and a simple
                    alphabet, we have not only endeavoured to establish the former on satisfactory
                    principles, but have been careful to appropriate, according to the comparative
                    frequency of their occurrence, such characters for the letters as, after
                    repeated trials and alterations, were conceived to be the best adapted for
                    despatch.</p><p>The stenographic alphabet consists of eighteen distinct characters (viz. two for
                    the vowels and the rest for the consonants), taken from lines and semicircular
                    curves; the formation and application of which we shall now explain, beginning
                    with the vowels.</p><p>For the three first vowels, <hi rend="italic">a, e,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> a comma is appropriated in different positions; and for the other
                    three, o, <hi rend="italic">u</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> a point. The
                    comma and point, when applied to <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">o</hi>, are to be placed at the top of the next character; when for <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> opposite to the middle; and
                    when for <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> at the
                    bottom.</p><p>This arrangement of the vowels is the most simple and distinct that can easily be
                    imagined. Places at the top, the middle, and the bottom of characters, which
                    make three different positions, are as easily distinguished from one another as
                    any three separate characters could be; and a comma is made with the same
                    facility as a point.</p><p>Simple lines may be drawn four different ways; perpendicular, horizontal, and
                    with an angle of about forty-five degrees to the right and left. An ascending
                    oblique line to the right, which will be perfectly distinct from the rest when
                    joined to any other character, may likewise be admitted. These characters being
                    the simplest in nature, arc assigned to those five consonants which most
                    frequently occur, viz. <hi rend="italic">l, r, t, c</hi> hard or <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> soft or <hi rend="italic">s.</hi></p><p>Every circle may be divided with a perpendicular and horizontal line, so as to
                    form likewise four distinct characters. These being the next to lines in the
                    simplicity of their formation, we have appropriated them for <hi rend="italic">b, d, n,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nι.</hi></p><p>The characters expressing nine of the consonants are all perfectly distinct from
                    one another; eight only remain which are needful, viz. <hi rend="italic">f
                    g</hi> or <hi rend="italic">j, h, p, q, υ, w,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">x;</hi>
                    to find characters for which we must have recourse to mixed curves and lines.
                    The characters which we have adopted are the simplest in nature after those
                    already applied, admit of the easiest joining, and tend to preserve lineality
                    and beauty in the writing.</p><p>It must be observed, that we have no character for <hi rend="italic">c</hi> when
                    it has a hard sound, as in <hi rend="italic">castle;</hi> or soft, as in <hi rend="italic">city;</hi> for it naturally takes the sound of <hi rend="italic">k</hi> or <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> which in all cases will be sufficient to
                    supply its place.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R</hi> likewise is represented by the same character as <hi rend="italic">l;</hi> only with this difference, <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is
                    written with an ascending stroke,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> The character for A, when lineality requires it, may be
                    made from the bottom and inverted. And often <hi rend="italic">h</hi> may be
                    omitted entirely, or a vowel may be substituted in its stead, without any injury
                    to legibility, it being rather a breathing than a letter.</p></note> and <hi rend="italic">l</hi> with a descending; which is always to be known from the
                    manner of its union with the following character; but in a few monosyllables
                    where <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is the only consonant in the word, and
                    consequently stands alone, it is to be made as is shown in the alphabet, for
                    distinction’s sake.</p><p>Z, as it is a letter seldom employed in the English language, and only a coarser
                    and harder expression of s <hi rend="italic">,</hi> must be supplied by <hi rend="italic">s</hi> whenever it occurs; as for <hi rend="italic">Zedekiah</hi>
                    write <hi rend="italic">Sedekiah, Sec.</hi></p><p>IV. The prepositions and terminations in this scheme are so simple, that the
                    greatest benefit may be reaped from them, and very little trouble required to
                    attain them; as the incipient letter or the incipient consonant of all the
                    prepositions and of several of the terminations is used to express the whole.
                    But in order to give every assistance, we have subjoined the following
                    directions.</p><p>1. The preposition is always to be written without joining, yet so near as
                    plainly to show what word it belongs to; and the best way is to observe the same
                    order as if the whole was to be connected.</p><p>2. A preposition, though the same letters that constitute it may be met with in
                    the middle or end of a word, is never to be used, because it would expose to
                    obscurity.</p><p>3. Observe that the preposition <hi rend="italic">omni</hi> is expressed by the
                    vowel <hi rend="italic">o</hi> in its proper position; and for <hi rend="italic">anti, anta, ante,</hi> by the vowel <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> which the radical
                    part of the word will easily distinguish from being only simple vowels.</p><p>The first rule for the prepositions is to be observed for the terminations; and
                    also the second, <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis;</hi> except that whenever
                    <hi rend="italic">sis, sus, sys, cious, tious,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ces</hi> occur, they are to be expressed as directed in the fourth rule for the
                    consonants, whether in the beginning, middle, or end of words.</p><p>4. The terminative character for <hi rend="italic">tion, sion, cion, dan,
                    tian,</hi> is to be expressed by a small circle joined to the nearest letter,
                    and turned to the right; and the plurals <hi rend="italic">lions, cions, cians,
                    tians,</hi> by a dot on the same side.</p><p>5. The terminative character for <hi rend="italic">ing</hi> is to be expressed
                    likewise by a small circle, but drawn to the left hand; and its plural <hi rend="italic">ings</hi> by a dot.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In horizontal characters, by the left hand is meant the top,
                    and by the right the space below the letter. In all other charactere the right
                    and left positions will naturally be known.</p></note></p><p>6. The plural sign <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is to be added to the terminative
                    characters when necessary.</p><p>7. The separated terminations are never to be used but in polysyllables, or words
                    of more syllables than one.</p><p>These rules duly observed will point out a method as concise and elegant as can
                    be desired, for expressing the most frequent and longest prepositions and
                    terminations in the English language. If it should be thought necessary to
                    increase their number by the addition of others, it will be an easy matter for
                    any one of the least discernment to do so, by proceeding on the principles
                    before laid down.</p><p>V. Though a more concise method of writing, or more numerous abbreviations, may
                    not be indispensably necessary, if the foregoing directions be practised for a
                    considerable time, yet contractions will be found extremely useful and
                    convenient to those who have attained a proper knowledge of the subject, and w
                    ill lead to a greater degree of expedition, at the same time that they diminish
                    the labour of writing. It has been observed in the introduction, that
                    abbreviations are only to be employed by proficients in this art; because
                    expedition is not the first, though the ultimate, object in view; and that an
                    easy legibility is of the utmost consequence to the learner; which however
                    cannot be preserved, if he adopts too soon those very rules which in time will
                    afford him the greatest ease when applied with judgment.</p><p>The following short and practical rules will be found, we hope, fully adequate to
                    every purpose for which they were intended, and are far superior in the facility
                    of their application to any which we have seen.</p><p>1. The usual abbreviations in long-hand are always to<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=865" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0865-0719"/>
                    be followed; as Mr for Master, Μ. D. for Doctor of Physic, and Abp. for
                    Archbishop, &amp;c.</p><p>2. Substantives, adjectives, verbs, and participles are to be expressed by their
                    initial consonant with distinguishing marks, viz. a substantive must have a dot
                    exactly over its initial consonant; an adjective must have a dot under it; a
                    verb is to be expressed by a comma over its initial consonant; and a participle
                    by a comma under.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    dot or comma being placed thus will never occasion them to be mistaken for
                    vowels, because they should always be on one side or other; whereas the mark for
                    parts of speech may constantly be placed exactly over or under.</p></note>
                    These, being the four principal parts of speech, will be sufficient; and an
                    adept will never be at a loss to know when he can with safety apply this rule to
                    them.</p><p>3. To render the writing more legible, the last letter of the word may be joined
                    to the first, and the proper mark applied.</p><p>4. The constituent or radical part of words, especially if they are long, will
                    often serve for the whole or sometimes the first syllable: as we ought to
                    moderate our <hi rend="italic">ex.</hi> by our <hi rend="italic">circum.;</hi> a
                    man’s <hi rend="italic">man.</hi> commonly shape his <hi rend="italic">for.</hi><hi rend="italic">5.</hi> All long words without exception may have their
                    prepositions or terminations expressed by the incipient consonant of such
                    preposition or termination.</p><p>6. When there is a great dependence between the parts of a sentence, the initial
                    letter will often suffice; as <hi rend="italic">L.</hi> is the capital of Great
                    <hi rend="italic">B.;</hi> the eldest <hi rend="italic">S.</hi> of the king of
                    Great <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> is styled prince of <hi rend="italic">W.</hi>
                    Every one, it is presumed, will allow this to be perfectly legible in long-hand;
                    then why may it not in stenography?</p><p>7. The terminations <hi rend="italic">ness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">less</hi>
                    may be omitted; as <hi rend="italic">faithfulness</hi> is only to be written <hi rend="italic">faithful; forwardness, forward; heedless, heed; stubbornness,
                    stubborn, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>8. The second and third persons of verbs, ending in <hi rend="italic">eth</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">est,</hi> may be expressed by <hi rend="italic">s;</hi>
                    as, he <hi rend="italic">loves,</hi> thou <hi rend="italic">teaches;</hi>
                    instead of he <hi rend="italic">loveth,</hi> thou <hi rend="italic">teachest:</hi> or even without <hi rend="italic">s;</hi> as, he <hi rend="italic">love,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>9. Words may often be entirely omitted, and yet no ambiguity ensue; as, <hi rend="italic">In beginning God created heaven and earth,</hi> fo? In <hi rend="italic">the</hi> beginning God created <hi rend="italic">the</hi> heaven
                    and <hi rend="italic">the</hi> earth.</p><p>10. When there is an immediate repetition of a sentence or word, a line is to be
                    drawn under the sentence or word to be repeated; as, Amen, Amen, is to be
                    written <hi rend="italic">Amen;</hi> but if any words intervene before a word or
                    sentence is to be repeated, the line must be drawn as before, and a A or mark of
                    omission placed where the repetition should begin; as, <hi rend="italic">Is it
                    just the innocent should be</hi> condemned A reviled?</p></div></body></text></TEI>