<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0091-0077-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SEINE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 77</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=91" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SEINE</label>, one of the departments of the north-eastern
                    part of France, taking its name from the river which passes through it, and
                    containing Paris, the capital of that mighty kingdom. As that city is the most
                    important portion of the department, the account of it in this work comprehends
                    what is most remarkable. It is on every side surrounded by the department of the
                    Seine and Oise, and extends over 47,548 French hectares, equal to 167 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> square miles, or
                    106,983 English acres. It is generally a level district, but intersected with
                    some hills of inconsiderable height. The river Seine receives within the
                    department the navigable river Marne, and the smaller streams of the Oureq and
                    the Erould. The Canal of St Denis unites the Seine with the Oise; and the Canal
                    of Oureq, which terminates in a reservoir between La Vilette and La Chapelle,
                    supplies Paris with water, and being navigable, serves to maintain an
                    intercourse between that city and the north of France. The canal is supplied
                    with water from the small streams of the Grisette, the Mai, the Therouanne, and
                    the Beuvronne. The soil is for the most part by nature poor and sandy, but
                    brought to a highly productive state by the vast quantities of manure furnished
                    by the capital, and by the high state of the cultivation, which is mostly garden
                    husbandry, whose products find advantageous markets in the metropolis. There are
                    still some woods preserved, but mostly for the purpose of ornament, and to serve
                    for the recreation of the inhabitants of Paris. The woods of Boulogne and of
                    Vincennes occupy together about six thousand English acres. It is divided into
                    three arrondissements, eight cantons, and eighty-one communes. The population,
                    which includes Paris, amounted in 1821 to 822,171, in 1831 to 935,108, and in
                    1836 to 1,106,891, of which 909,126 were within the city.</p>
                <p>S <hi rend="smallcaps">eine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lower,</hi> a department of
                    the north-west of France, formed out of those northern parts of Upper Normandy
                    which were in ancient times distinguished as the Roumais, Bezin-Normandy, Caux,
                    and Bray. It is bounded on the north by the sea, on the east by the departments
                    of the Somme and of the Oise, on the south by Eure and Calvados, and on the west
                    by the Channel. It is 2144¼ square miles in extent, and comprehends five
                    arrondissements, fifty cantons, and 757 communes. The population amounted in
                    1836 to 720,525 persons, who mostly adhere to the Kυman Catholic church; but
                    among them are 55,000 Protestants, having two consistorial and 113 other
                    churches.</p>
                <p>The surface is generally level, but intersected by some hills of moderate height,
                    mostly composed of chalk. To-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=92" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0092-0078"/>
                    wards the east the valleys are widest, and run from east to west. Along the
                    whole coast are chalky cliffs from 150 to 700 feet in height, but interrupted in
                    places by the bays and harbours. The soil is on the whole the most fertile in
                    France, though there are portions of it very unproductive of corn, and generally
                    covered with wood, which woods comprehend one seventh of the whole department.
                    The agriculture is tolerably conducted, but the greater part of it is on the
                    ancient system of a fallow succeeded by two crops of grain. About 340,000 acres
                    are sown with wheat, and about 250,000 with oats, which is a large portion out
                    of the 1,372,302 acres; yet it appears that the corn produced is scarcely equal
                    to the consumption. The best lands are the meadows in the valleys through which
                    the Seine and the other rivers run, and these afford nourishment for numerous
                    herds of cows, which supply both meat and the products of the dairy. It is,
                    however, in the interior of the department that the best breed of cows are to be
                    seen, which are a mixture of the Flanders race, whereas on the coast they are
                    commonly of a much smaller size.</p>
                <p>The breed of the ancient Norman horses is now nearly extinct. Those now bred are
                    of a mixed race, and more remarkable for their strength than for their beauty,
                    and are well adapted for the plough, for which they are almost exclusively used.
                    The sheep are numerous, and those of the fine woolled kind have of late years
                    been rapidly on the increase. In the valleys of Arques and of Pouville the
                    mutton is highly valued. In the more woody portions of the department are kept
                    very great numbers of swine, in which the acorns are found of great benefit.
                    Most kinds of fruit are abundant, with the exception of vines; but the
                    deficiency of them is counterbalanced by the great quantity of apples, which are
                    converted into cider, and form a good substitute for wine. The fishery on the
                    sea-coast affords considerable occupation, and a great additional supply of
                    food. The herring-fishery is extensively practised from Dieppe and Fecamp; and
                    from other places on the shore enormous quantities of mackerel are taken, whilst
                    the oyster-fishery employs many hands. The manufacturing industry is very
                    active, especially in the arrondissement of Rouen. Woollen and cotton goods of
                    every kind are made, and the best kinds of machinery are in full exercise. Large
                    establishments exist which provide paper, glass, pottery, and china ware; and on
                    the coast much linen is spun and woven. There are many ship and boat builders;
                    and the cordage and equipments contribute their share to furnish occupation to
                    labourers. There is much internal trade, especially with Paris, by the river
                    Seine. The principal places within the department are Rouen, Havre de Grace,
                    Dieppe, Fecamp, and Yvetot.</p>
                <p>S <hi rend="smallcaps">eine</hi><hi rend="italic">and Marne,</hi> a department of
                    the north of France. It has been formed out of parts of the ancient provinces of
                    the Isle of France and of Champagne, called French Ga-tinois, and the Upper and
                    Lower Brie. It is bounded on the north by the department of the Oise, on the
                    east by the Aisne and the Marne and Aube, on the south by the Yonne and Loiret,
                    and on the west by the Seine and Oise. It extends over 1981 square miles, is
                    divided into five arrondissements, twenty-nine cantons, and 556 communes, and in
                    1836 contained 325,881 inhabitants. The capital of the department is the city of
                    Melun, with a population of 6846 inhabitants in 1836. Besides the two rivers
                    from which it is named, it is watered by the Great and Little Morin, the Bouzie,
                    the Yonne, the Essonne, the Yres, the Therouanne, the Beuvronne, and the Otrin,
                    all of whose waters reach the sea through the Seine. The surface is a plain, but
                    intersected by some hills of very moderate height. The soil is fruitful,
                    especially near the principal rivers; and though woods cover more than one tenth
                    of the department, it is the chief granary from whence the capital draws its
                    supply of corn, flour, garden-fruits, and fattened cattle.</p>
                <p>The rivers abound with fish, and the woods with game. The meadows are of great
                    fertility, yielding abundance of hay and other fodder, and supporting numerous
                    cows, whose dairies supply Paris with the greater part of its milk, butter, and
                    veal, whilst the cheese of Brie has attained great celebrity. It yields some
                    wine, but its quality is only moderate, and does not equal the consumption.
                    There is much manufacturing industry applied to the making of glass, of paper of
                    the best kind, of leather, of steel articles, of hosiery, of linen goods, and of
                    various smaller articles. The chief towns are Coulommiers, Meaux, Fontainebleau,
                    and Provins.</p>
                <p>S <hi rend="smallcaps">eine</hi><hi rend="italic">and Oise,</hi> a department in
                    the north of France. It is bounded on the north by the Eure and the Oise, on the
                    east by the Seine-Marne, on the south by the Loiret, and on the west by the Eure
                    and Loire. It extends over 1970 square miles, is divided into six
                    arrondissements, thirty-six cantons, and 687 communes, and in 1836 contained
                    449,582 inhabitants, who elect four deputies to the legislative chamber; The
                    chief river is the Seine, with which the Oise is united, and then it receives
                    the waters of the Marne, the Essonne, the Juine, the Ept, and the Maudre, and of
                    the various tributary streams which empty themselves into these rivers. It is
                    generally a level district, with a few ranges of hills of moderate height. The
                    soil is not naturally fertile, but has been rendered productive by careful
                    cultivation, and the abundance of manure, arising from its vicinity to the
                    metropolis. It surrounds the department of the Seine on every side, has easy
                    water-communication with Paris, and, besides, contains within it the city of
                    Versailles and some other populous places. There is much fruit raised, and some
                    wine, not of the best quality. It breeds many sheep; and of late years the race
                    of the merinos and other fine-woolled sheep has prodigiously increased. There
                    are in many parts manufactures of linen, woollen, and cotton goods, and they are
                    on the increase.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
