<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0865-0719-05" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">STEPHANUS Byzantinus</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 719</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57r7v">Printers</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1076585">Printers</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=865" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">STEPHANUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Byzantinus</hi></label>, a
                    learned grammarian, who flourished about the close of the fifth century. He
                    wrote a large work, in which he made a great number of observations, borrowed
                    from mythology and history, which showed the origin of cities and colonies; of
                    which we have little remaining but an abridgement by Hermolaus the grammarian.
                    Even in this state, it has been found a work of no inconsiderable value. It is
                    alphabetically arranged, and bears the inscription <hi rend="italic">∏εϑl
                    ∏0όλεωv, or</hi> “Concerning Cities.” The first edition was printed by Aldus,
                    Venet. 1502, fol. This was followed by an edition printed by the heirs of P.
                    Junta, Florent. 1521, fol. The text received many emendations in the edition of
                    Xylander, Basil. 1568, fol. All these editions contain the Greek text, without
                    any Latin version. An edition, with a translation, and copious annotations, was
                    published by Thomas de Pinedo, Amst. 1678, fol. Another edition, with a
                    translation and a commentary, was prepared by Berkelius, and after his death was
                    completed by J. Gronovius, Lugd. Bat. 1688, fol. Nor must we here omit the
                    posthumous “Notae et Castigationes” of Holstenius, Lugd. Bat. 1684, fol.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stephanus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Henry,</hi> the founder of
                    a most remarkable and meritorious family of printers, was born at Paris in the
                    year 1470. The French name is Estienne, which is frequently transformed into the
                    English <hi rend="italic">Stephens,</hi> although the correct translation would
                    be <hi rend="italic">Stephen.</hi> He began the business of a printer about the
                    year 1503. This is the date of Boethius’s treatise on arithmetic, the first book
                    that is known to have issued from his press. A great proportion of the books
                    which he published were Latin. They are printed in the Roman letter, and are not
                    inelegant, though some of them abound rather too much in contractions. He died
                    about the year 1520, and left behind him three sons, Francis, Robert, and
                    Charles. His widow married Simeon de Colines <hi rend="italic">(Colinceus</hi>
                    in Latin), who thus got possession of Henry’s printing-office, and continued the
                    business till his death.</p><p>Of Francis, the eldest son, little more is known than that he carried on business
                    along with Colinaeus, and that he died at Paris in 1550.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Stephanus,</hi> the second son, was born at Paris in
                    1503. In his youth he made great proficiency in the Latin, Greek, and Hebrew
                    languages, and at the age of nineteen had acquired so much knowledge that his
                    step-father intrusted him with the management of his press. He soon afterwards
                    began business himself, and married Perrete, the daughter of Jodocus Badius, a
                    printer and an author. She was a woman of learning, and understood Latin, which
                    indeed was the necessary consequence of her situation. Her husband always
                    entertained a number of learned men as correctors of the press. Being
                    foreigners, and of different nations, they made use of no other language but
                    Latin; which Perrete being accustomed to hear, was able in a short time not only
                    to understand, but even to speak with tolerable ease.</p><p>In 1531 he published his “Thesaurus Linguae Latins ;” a work of great labour, and
                    of great value. The device which he exhibited in all his books was a tree
                    branched, with a man looking upon it, and these words <hi rend="italic">Noli
                    altum sapere,</hi> to which he sometimes added <hi rend="italic">sed time.</hi>
                    In 1539, Francis I. made him his printer, and ordered a new set of elegant types
                    to be founded for him. His frequent editions of the New Testament gave great
                    offence to the doctors of the Sorbonne, who accused him of heresy for his
                    annotations, and insisted upon the suppression of some of his books. Although
                    Henry, the French king, in some measure protected him, the persecution of these
                    divines rendered him so unhappy, not to mention the expense and loss of time
                    which an almost constant attendance at court unavoidably occasioned, that in
                    1552 he abandoned his country and settled<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=866" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0866-0720"/>
                    at Geneva. Here he embraced the Protestant religion, and thus justified in some
                    measure the suspicions of his theological enemies. It has been affirmed by
                    several writers that he carried along with him the royal types, and the moulds
                    in which they were cast; but it is certain that he never afterwards made use of
                    those types. Besides, is it possible that the author of so daring a theft could
                    have been not only protected in Geneva, but even courted and honoured by the
                    most eminent men of the age? Is it credible that such a crime could have been
                    concealed for sixty years; or that Henry, the son and heir of the perpetrator,
                    would have enjoyed the favour of the French king, if Robert Stephanus had acted
                    such a shameful part? If he was burnt in effigy at Paris, it was not for theft,
                    but for having renounced the popish faith. After his arrival at Geneva, he
                    published an account of the dispute between him and the Paris divines, which
                    does as much honour to his abilities as his <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi>
                    does to his learning. He died in 1559, after a life of the most extraordinary
                    industry. The books of which he was the editor were not fewer than 360. Many of
                    them were ancient classics in different languages. Several were accompanied with
                    annotations which he collected, and all of them were corrected by the collation
                    of manuscripts. He was so anxious to obtain perfect accuracy, that he used to
                    expose his proofs in public, and reward those who discovered a mistake. His
                    books consequently were very correct. It is said that his New Testament, called
                    <hi rend="italic">O Mirificam</hi> (because the preface begins with these
                    words), has not a single fault. It was Robert Stephanus who first divided the
                    New Testament into verses, during a journey between Paris and Lyon. The
                    advantages of this improvement are fully counterbalanced by its defects. It has
                    destroyed the unity of the books, and induced many commentators to consider
                    every verse as a distinct and independent aphorism. By his last will his estate
                    was left exclusively to such of his children as should settle at Geneva. He left
                    behind hint three sons, Henry, Robert, and Francis.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Stephanus,</hi> the third son of Henry, was, like
                    the rest of his family, familiarly acquainted with the learned languages. This
                    recommenaed him to Lazarus de Baif, who made him tutor to his son, and in 1540
                    carried him along with him to Germany. He studied medicine, and took his
                    doctor’s degree at Paris. He did not however forsake the profession of his
                    family, but exercised it at Paris, where he became the editor of many books
                    remarkable for neatness and elegance. He wrote above thirty treatises on
                    different subjects, particularly on botany, anatomy, and history. Having been
                    unsuccessful in business, he was imprisoned for debt in the Chatelet in 1561,
                    and died there in 1564.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Stephanus,</hi> the son of Robert the first of that
                    name, did not accompany his father to Geneva, but continued to profess the
                    Romish religion, and to reside at Paris. His letter was remarkably beautiful. He
                    was made king’s printer, and died about 1589. His brother Francis, who was also
                    a printer, embraced the Protestant religion, and resided at Geneva.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Stephanus,</hi> the eldest brother, was born at Paris
                    in 1528. He became the most learned and most celebrated of all his family. From
                    a very early age he gave proofs of uncommon abilities, and displayed an ardent
                    passion for knowledge. The Medea of Euripides, which he saw acted while at
                    school, first kindled his love for poetry, and inspired him with the desire of
                    acquiring the language in which that tragedy is written. He entreated his father
                    not to condemn him to study Latin, which he already understood from
                    conversation, but to initiate him at once in the knowledge of Greek. His lather
                    willingly acceded to his request; and Henry applied with such vigour, that in a
                    short time he could repeat the Medea by heart. He afterwards studied Greek under
                    Danesius, who was tutor to the Dauphin, and finally heard the lectures of
                    Tusanus and Turnebus. At an early age he became eager to understand astrology,
                    and accordingly attended a professor of that mysterious art; but he was not Jong
                    in discovering its absurdity. At the age of nineteen he began his travels, which
                    he undertook in order to examine foreign libraries, and to become acquainted
                    with learned men. He spent two years in Italy, and returned into France
                    completely master of Italian, and bringing along with him copies of several
                    scarce authors, particularly a part of' Anacreon, which previously was supposed
                    to be lost. He found his father publishing an edition of the New Testament, to
                    which he prefixed some Greek verses. Soon after, he visited England and the
                    Netherlands, where he met with John Clement, an Englishman, to whom he was
                    indebted for the remaining odes of Anacreon. During this journey he learned the
                    Spanish language, which was very much spoken at that time in the Low
                    Countries.</p><p>Whether Henry accompanied his father to Geneva, is uncertain: if he did, he must
                    have returned immediately to France, for we find him soon after established at
                    Paris, and publishing the odes of Anacreon. In 1554 he went to Rome, and thence
                    to Naples. This journey was undertaken at the request, and in the service, of
                    the French government. He was discovered, and would have been arrested as a spy,
                    had he not by his address and skill in the language of the country been able to
                    pass himself for a native of Italy. On his return to France, he assumed the
                    title of printer to Ulric Fugger, a very rich and learned German nobleman, who
                    allowed him a considerable pension.</p><p>In 1560 he married a relation, ns is generally supposed, of Henry Scrimger, a
                    Scotish scholar and civilian, with whom he was intimately acquainted. She was a
                    woman, as he himself informs us, endowed with the noblest spirit and the most
                    amiable disposition. Her death, which happened in 1586, brought on a disease
                    that had twice attacked him before. It was a disgust at all those pursuits which
                    had formerly charmed him, an aversion to reading and the sight of books. It was
                    probably occasioned by too constant and severe an application to literary
                    pursuits. In 1572 he published, in four vols. folio, his <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Lingua: Graecae,</hi> one of the greatest works, perhaps, that ever
                    was executed by one man, if we consider the wretched materials which more
                    ancient dictionaries could furnish, the size and perfection of the work, and the
                    immense labour and learning which must have been employed in the compilation. In
                    1573, he added <hi rend="italic">Glossaria duo, e situ vetustatis cruta.</hi>
                    This work had been carried on at a greater expense than he could well bear. He
                    expected to be reimbursed by the sale of the book, but he was unfortunately
                    disappointed. Scapula, one of his own correctors, extracted from it whatever he
                    thought would be most serviceable to students, and published it beforehand in
                    quarto. By this act of treachery Henry was reduced to poverty.</p><p>About this time he was much beloved by Henry III. of France, who treated him so
                    kindly, and made him stich flattering promises, that he resided frequently at
                    court. But these promises were never fulfilled, owing to the civil wars which
                    soon after distracted France, and the unfortunate death of Henry himself. During
                    the remainder of his life, his situation was very unsettled. We find him
                    sometimes at Paris, sometimes at Geneva, in Germany, and even in Hungary. He
                    died at Lyon in 1598, at the age of seventy. His temper during the latter part
                    of his life is represented as haughty and severe, owing probably to his
                    disappointments. He was twice married, and by his first wife had a son and two
                    daughters, one of whom was married to the learned Isaac Casaubon.</p><p>This most erudite printer was fond of poetry from his very infancy. It was his
                    practice to compose verses on<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=867" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0867-0721"/>
                    horseback, and even to write them, though he generally rode a very mettlesome
                    steed. His Thesaurus was his great work, but he was also the author of many
                    other treatises in the French and Latin languages. His poems are numerous. His
                    “Apologie pour Herodote” is a very singular performance. It has been illustrated
                    by the annotations of Duchat. The number of books which he published, though
                    fewer than his father, was great, and they were superior in elegance to any
                    thing which the world had then seen. A great proportion of them were Greek. He
                    was the editor, however, of many Latin and even of some oriental writings. His
                    Greek classics are remarkably correct; and many of his editions are accompanied
                    by most learned notes. His Thesaurus still maintains an unrivalled reputation.
                    An edition, with very ample additions, was recently published by Barker and
                    Valpy; and another elaborate edition is now in progress at Paris.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Paul Stephanus,</hi> the son of Henry, continued his
                    father’s profession at Geneva. He was a man of learning, executed translations
                    of several books, and published a considerable number of the ancient classics;
                    but his editions possess little of his father’s elegance. He died in 1627, at
                    the age of sixty, after selling his types to one Chouet, a printer. His son
                    Antony, the last printer of the family, abandoned the Protestant religion, and
                    returned to France, the country of his ancestors. He received letters of
                    naturalization in 1612, and was made printer to the king; but managing his
                    affairs ill, he was reduced to poverty, and obliged to retire into an hospital,
                    where he died in 1674, miserable and blind, at the age of eighty.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Almeloveen de Vitis
                    Stephanorum Amst. 1683, 8vo. Maktaire, Historia Stephanorum. Loud. 1709, 8vo.
                    Biographie Universelle, tom. xiii. p. 380.</p></note><hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen’s Island,</hi> in Torres Strait, north of Darnley’s Island. Long. 143.
                    E. Lat. 9. 0. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen’s Islands,</hi> two small islands in the Eastern
                    Seas, the one about three miles long, and the other about six. The passage
                    between them is three miles broad. Long. 138. 39. E. Lat. 0. 22. S.</p></div></body></text></TEI>