<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0208-0190-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SHASTER or Shastrah</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 190</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=208" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SHASTER or <hi rend="smallcaps">Shastrah</hi></label>, the
                    name of a sacred book, in high estimation among the idolaters of Hindustan,
                    containing all the dogmas of the religion of the Brahmins, and all the
                    ceremonies of their worship, and serving as a commentary on the <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Vedam.</hi></p>
                <p>The term <hi rend="italic">Shuster</hi> denotes science or system; and is applied
                    to other works of astronomy and philosophy, which have no relation to the
                    religion of the Indians. None but the Brahmins and rajahs of India are allowed
                    to read the Vedam; the priests of the Banians, called Shuderis, may read the
                    Shaster; and the people in general are allowed to read only the Paran or Pouran,
                    which is a commentary on the Shaster.</p>
                <p>The Shaster is divided into three parts, the first containing the moral law of
                    the Indians; the second, the rites and<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=209" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0209-0191"/>
                    ceremonies of their religion; and the third, the distribution of the people into
                    tribes or classes, with the duties pertaining to each class.</p>
                <p>The principal precepts of morality, contained in the first part of the Shaster,
                    are the following. That no animal be killed, because the Indians attribute souls
                    to brute animals as well as to mankind; that they neither hear nor speak evil,
                    nor drink wine, nor eat flesh, nor touch any thing that is unclean; that they
                    observe the feasts, prayers, and washings which their law prescribes; that they
                    tell no lies, nor be guilty of deceit in trade; that they neither oppress nor
                    offer violence to one another; that they celebrate the solemn feasts and fasts,
                    and appropriate certain hours of ordinary sleep to cultivate a disposition for
                    prayer; and that they do not steal or defraud one another.</p>
                <p>The ceremonies, contained in the second part of the Shaster, are these. That they
                    wash often in the rivers, thereby obtaining the pardon of their sins; that they
                    mark their forehead with red, in token of their relation to the Deity; that they
                    present offerings and prayers under certain trees, set apart for this purpose;
                    that they pray in the temples, make oblations to their pagodas or idols, sing
                    hymns, and make processions; that they make pilgrimages to distant rivers, and
                    especially to the Ganges, there to wash themselves and make offerings; that they
                    make vows to particular saints, according to their respective departments; that
                    they render homage to the Deity at the first sight of the sun; that they pay
                    their respect to the sun and moon, which are the two eyes of the Deity; and that
                    they treat with particular veneration those animals that are deemed more pure
                    than others, because the souls of men have transmigrated into these animals.</p>
                <p>The third part of the Shaster records the distribution of the people into four
                    classes; the first being that of the Brahmins or priests, appointed to instruct
                    the people; the second, that of the kutteris or nobles, who are the magistrates;
                    the third, that of the shudderis or merchants; and the fourth, that of the
                    mechanics. Each person is required to remain in the class in which he was born,
                    and to pursue the occupation assigned to him by the Shaster. According to the
                    Brahmins, the Shaster was imparted by God himself to Brahma, and by him to the
                    Brahmins, who communicated the contents of it to the people.</p>
                <p>Modem writers have given us very different accounts of the antiquity and
                    importance of the Shaster. Mr Hol well, who had made considerable progress in
                    the translation of this book, apprehends that the mythology as well as the
                    cosmogony of the Egyptians, Greeks, and Romans, was borrowed from the doctrines
                    of the Brahmins contained in it, even to the copying of the exteriors of
                    worship, and the distribution of their idols, though grossly mutilated and
                    adulterated. With respect to the Vedam and Shaster, or scriptures, of the
                    Gentoos, this writer informs us, that Vedam, in the Malabar language, signifies
                    the same as Shaster in the Sanscrit; and that the first book is followed by the
                    Gentoos of the Malabar and Coromandel coasts, and also of the island of Ceylon.
                    The Shaster is followed by the Gentoos of the provinces of Bengal, and by all
                    the Gentoos of the rest of India commonly called India Proper, along the course
                    of the rivers Ganges and Jumna, to the Indus. Both these books, he says, contain
                    the institutes of their respective religion and worship, as well as the history
                    of their ancient rajahs and princes, often couched under allegory and fable.
                    Their antiquity is contended for by the partisans of each; but he thinks that
                    the similitude of their names, idols, and great part of their worship, leaves
                    little room to doubt, nay plainly evinces, that both these scriptures were
                    originally one. He adds, if we compare the great purity and chaste manners of
                    the Shaster with the great absurdities and impurities of the Vedam, we need not
                    hesitate to pronounce the latter a corruption of the former.</p>
                <p>with regard to the high original of these scriptures, the account of the Brahmins
                    is as follows. Brahma or the Mighty Spirit, about 4866 years ago, assumed the
                    form of man, and the government of Hindustan. He translated the divine law,
                    designed for the restoration of mankind, who had offended in a pre-existent
                    state, and who are now in their last scene of probation, to the dignity from
                    which they were degraded, out of the language of angels, into the well-known
                    Sanscrit language, and called his translation the <hi rend="italic">Six
                    Scriptures of Divine Words of the Mighty Spirit.</hi> He appointed the Brahmins,
                    deriving their name from him, to preach the word of God; and the doctrines of
                    the Shaster were accordingly preached in their original purity a thousand years.
                    About this time there was published a paraphrase on the Chartah Bhade, or Six
                    Scriptures; and about five hundred years afterwards a second exposition
                    appeared, called the <hi rend="italic">Eighteen Books of Divine Words,</hi>
                    written in a character compounded of the common Hindustan and the Sanscrit. This
                    innovation produced a schism among the Gentoos; on which occasion, it is said,
                    those of Coromandel and Malabar formed a scripture of their own, which they
                    pretended to be founded on the Chartah Bhade of Brahma, and called it the Vedam
                    of Birmah, or <hi rend="italic">Bivine Words of the Mighty Spirit.</hi> The
                    original Chartah Bhade was thrown aside, and at length wholly unknown, except to
                    a few families, who can still read and expound it in the Sanscrit character.
                    With the establishment of the Aughtorrah Bhade and Vedam, which, according to
                    the Gentoo account, is 3366 years ago, their polytheism commenced; and the
                    principles of religion became so obscure, and their ceremonies so numerous, that
                    every head of a family was obliged to keep a Brahmin as a guide both in faith
                    and practice. Mr Holwell is of opinion that the Chartah Bhade, or original
                    scriptures, are not copied from any other system of theology promulgated to or
                    obtruded upon mankind. The Gentoos do not attribute them to Zoroaster; and Mr
                    Holwell supposes that both Zoroaster and Pythagoras visited Hindustan, not to
                    instruct, but to be instructed.</p>
                <p>From the account of Mr Dow, we learn that the books which contain the religion
                    and philosophy of the Hindus are distinguished by the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vedas;</hi> that they are four in number, and, like the sacred writings of
                    other nations, are said to have been penned by the Divinity. Veda he says, in
                    the Sanscrit language, literally signifies <hi rend="italic">science;</hi> and
                    these books treat not only of religion and moral duties, but of every branch of
                    philosophical knowledge. The Brahmins maintain that the Vedas are the divine
                    laws which Brahma, at the creation of the world, delivered for the instruction
                    of mankind; but they affirm that their meaning was perverted in the first age by
                    the ignorance and wickedness of some princes, whom they represent as evil
                    spirits, who then haunted the earth.</p>
                <p>The first credible account we have of the Vedas is, that about the commencement
                    of the Cal Jug, of which era the year 1768 was the 4886th year, they were
                    written, or rather collected, by a great philosopher and reputed prophet, called
                    Beass Muni, or Beiiss the Inspired.</p>
                <p>The Hindus, says Mr Dow, are divided into two great religious sects: the
                    followers of the doctrine of Bedang, which is the original Shaster or commentary
                    upon the Vedas; and those who adhere to the principles of the Nea-dirsen. The
                    original Shaster is called <hi rend="italic">Vedang,</hi> and is a commentary
                    upon the Vedas. This book, he says, is erroneously called in Europe the <hi
                    rend="italic">Vedam.</hi> It is ascribed to Beass Muni, and is said to have been
                    revised some years after by one Serrider Swami, since which time it has been
                    reckoned sacred, and not subject to any farther alterations.</p>
                <p>Almost all the Hindus of the Deccan, and those of the Malabar and Coromandel
                    coasts, are of this sect. The followers of the Vedang Shaster do not allow that
                    any physical evil exists. They maintain that God created all things<pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=210"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0720-0210-0192"/> perfectly good; but that man, being a free agent,
                    may be guilty of moral evil, which may be injurious to himself, but can be of no
                    detriment to the general system of nature. God, they say, being perfectly
                    benevolent, never punished the wicked otherwise than by the pain and affliction
                    which are the natural consequences of evil actions; and hell, therefore, is no
                    other than a consciousness of evil.</p>
                <p>The Neadirsen Shaster is said to have been written by a philosopher called
                    Goutam, nearly four thousand years ago. The Brahmins, from Mr Dow’s account of
                    their sacred books, appear to believe invariably in the unity, eternity,
                    omniscience, and omnipotence of God; and the polytheism of which they have been
                    accused is no more than a symbolical worship of the divine attributes, which
                    they divide into three classes. Under the name of Brahma, they worship the
                    wisdom and creative power of God; under the appellation of Vishen, his
                    providential and preserving quality; and under that of Shevah, that attribute
                    which tends to destroy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
