<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0872-0726-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STILLINGFLEET, Edward</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 726</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:844160">Calendar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:844227">Calendars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1123835">Socinianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1076230">Pricing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb3h">Calendar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0330j">Calendars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp6p">Socinianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p83w">Prices</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=872" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STILLINGFLEET, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi></label>,
                    bishop of Worcester, was the son of Samuel Stillingfleet, gentleman, and was
                    born at Cranborn in Dorsetshire in 1635. He was educated at St John’s College,
                    Cambridge; and having received holy orders, was, in 1657, presented to the
                    rectory of Sutton in Nottinghamshire. By publishing his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Origines Sacra,</hi> one of the ablest defences of revealed religion that has
                    ever been written, he soon acquired such reputation, that he was appointed
                    preacher of the Rolls Chapel; and in January 1665 was presented to the rectory
                    of St Andrews, Holborn. He was afterwards chosen lecturer at the Temple, and
                    appointed chaplain in ordinary to King Charles II. In 1668 he took the degree of
                    D.D.; and was soon after engaged in a dispute with those of the Romish religion,
                    by publishing his discourse concerning the idolatry and fanaticism of the church
                    of Rome, which discourse he afterwards defended against several antagonists. In
                    1680 he preached at Guildhall chapel a sermon on Phil. iii. 26, which he
                    published under the title of “The Mischief of Separation ;” and this being
                    immediately attacked by several writers, he in 1683 published his
                    Unreasonableness of Separation. In 1685 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Origines
                    Britannica,</hi> or the Antiquities of the British Churches, in folio. During
                    the reign of King James II. he wrote several tracts against popery, and was
                    prolocutor of the convocation, as he had likewise been under Charles II. After
                    the revolution he was advanced to the bishopric of Worcester, and was engaged in
                    a dispute with the Socinians, and also with Mr Locke; in which last contest he
                    is generally thought to have been unsuccessful. He died at Westminster in 1699,
                    and was interred in the cathedral of Worcester, where a monument was erected to
                    his memory by his son. Dr Stillingfleet wrote other works besides those here
                    mentioned, which, with the above, have been reprinted in 6 vols. folio.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stillingfleet,</hi><hi rend="italic">Benjamin,</hi> an
                    ingenious naturalist, born in 1702, was the bishop’s grandson. His father,
                    Edward Stillingfleet, M.D., was fellow of St John’s College, Cambridge, and
                    Gresham professor of physic: but marrying in 1692, he lost his lucrative offices
                    and his father’s favour; a misfortune that affected both himself and his
                    posterity. Having however entered the church, he obtained, by his father’s
                    means, the living of Newington-Butts, which he immediately exchanged for those
                    of Wood-Norton and Swanton in Norfolk. He died in 1708. Benjamin, his only son,
                    was educated at Norwich school, which he left in 1720, with the character of an
                    excellent scholar. He then went to Trinity College in Cambridge, at the request
                    of Dr Bentley, the master, who had been private tutor to his father, domestic
                    chaplain to his grandfather, and much indebted to die family. Here he was a
                    candidate for a fellowship, but was rejected by the master’s influence. This was
                    a severe and unexpected disappointment, and but little alleviated afterwards by
                    Bentley’s apology, that it was a pity that a gentleman of Mr Stillingfleet’s
                    parts should be buried within the walls of a college.</p>
                <p>Perhaps, however, this ingratitude of Dr Bentley was not of any real disservice
                    to Mr Stillingfleet. By being thrown into the world, he formed many honourable
                    and valuable connections. He dedicated some translations of Linnaeus to the late
                    Lord Lyttelton, partly, he says, from motives of private respect and honour.
                    Lord Barrington gave him, in a very polite manner, the place of master of the
                    barracks at Kensington; a favour to which Mr Stillingfleet, in the dedication of
                    his Calendar of Flora to that nobleman, alludes with the greatest politeness, as
                    well as the warmest gratitude. His Calendar of Flora was formed at Stratton in
                    Norfolk in the year 1755, at the hospitable seat of his very worthy and
                    ingenious friend Mr Marsham, who had made several observations of that kind, and
                    had communicated to the public his curious observations on the growth of trees.
                    But it was to Mr Wyndham of Felbrig in Norfolk that he appears to have had the
                    greatest obligation: he travelled abroad with him, spent much of his time at his
                    house, and was appointed one of his executors (Mr Garrick being another), with a
                    considerable addition to an annuity which that gentleman had settled upon him in
                    his lifetime.</p>
                <p>Mr Stillingfleet’s genius seems, if we may judge from his works, to have led him
                    principally to the study of natural history; which he prosecuted as an ingenious
                    philosopher, an useful citizen, and a good man. In this walk of learning he
                    mentions as his friends, Dr Watson, Dr Solander, Mr Hudson, Mr Price of Foxley,
                    and some others; to whom may be added the ingenious Mr Pennant. Nor can we omit
                    the flattering mention which Mr Gray makes of him in one of his letters, dated
                    from London in 1761: “I have lately made an acquaintance with this philosopher,
                    who lives in a garret here in the winter, that he may support some near
                    relations who depend upon him. He is always employed, consequently (according to
                    my old maxim) always happy, always cheerful, and seems to me a very worthy,
                    honest man. His present scheme is to send some persons, properly qualified, to
                    reside a year or two in Attica, to make themselves acquainted with the climate,
                    productions, and natural history of the country, that we may understand
                    Aristotle, Theophrastus, &amp;c. who have been heathen Greek to us for so many
                    ages; and this he has got proposed to Lord Bute, no unlikely person to put it in
                    execution, as he is himself a botanist.”</p>
                <p>Mr Stillingfleet published a volume of Miscellaneous Tracts, which is in much
                    esteem, and does great honour to his head and heart. They are chiefly
                    translations of some essays in the <hi rend="italic">Amaenitates Academica,</hi>
                    published by Linnaeus, interspersed with some observations and additions of his
                    own. In this volume he shows also a taste for classical learning, and entertains
                    us with some elegant poetical effusions of his own. But his Essay on
                    Conversation, published in the first volume of Dodsley’s Collection of Poems,
                    entitles him to a respectable station among our English poets. This poem is
                    addressed to Mr Wyndham, with all that warmth of friendship which distinguishes
                    Mr Stillingfleet. As it is chiefly didactic, it does not admit of so many
                    ornaments as some compositions of other kinds. However, it contains much good
                    sense, shows a considerable knowledge of mankind, and has several passages that,
                    in point of harmony and easy versification, would not disgrace the writings of
                    our most admired poets. Here more than once Mr Stillingfleet shows himself still
                    sore for Dr Bentley’s cruel treatment of him; and towards the beautiful and
                    moral close of it, where it is supposed he gives us a sketch of himself, seems
                    to hint at a mortification of a more delicate nature, which he is said to have
                    suffered from the other sex. To these disappointments it was perhaps owing that
                    Mr Stillingfleet neither married nor went into orders. His London residence was
                    in lodgings in Piccadilly, where he died in 1771, at the age of sixty-nine,
                    leaving several valuable papers behind him. He was buried in St James’s church,
                    without the slightest monument to his memory,</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
