<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0210-0192-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">SHAWLS, Figured</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 192</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9v878">Wool</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rp5c">Drawings</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44m9198r">Drawing</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1115379">Shawls</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1179993">Wool</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:897725">Drawing</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=210" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">SHAWLS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Figured</hi></label>. This
                    article has, within less than forty years, become a very considerable branch of
                    our manufactures. For a long period the district of Cashmere, a province of
                    Hindustan, formerly subject to the king of Candahar, produced articles of this
                    description in such perfection as to make them highly prized both in Europe and
                    in Asia. The date at which this manufacture took its rise is not known; but ever
                    since the British established themselves in India, Cashmere shawls have been
                    considered as one of the most valuable manufactures of the East.</p><p>These shawls are made both long and square, the former generally measuring
                    fifty-four inches wide, and a hundred and twenty-six long; the latter are from
                    sixty-three to seventy-two ioches square. The finest of them are composed of a
                    material exquisitely soft and warm, surpassing in this respect probably any
                    other material that has ever been fabricated into clothing. It is recorded that,
                    at the most flourishing period of this manufacture, the district of Cashmere had
                    not less than 40,000 looms or frames employed in it. This district produced also
                    a fine article of cloth, which has also been imitated in this country, and is in
                    extensive use, called Cashmeres or Cassimeres. These manufactures were
                    sufficient to draw to the district of Cashmere, merchants and commercial agents
                    from Northern India, Turkey, Persia, and Tartary; and the increasing prosperity
                    of this industrious and ingenious people was only checked by the oppressions of
                    their own government, or the rapacity of the bordering states.</p><p>These shawls were not more prized for their fine, soft texture, than for the
                    chaste beautiful-coloured flowering with which they were ornamented. Long
                    practice, united to a natural delicacy of taste, enabled the manufacturers to
                    dye the numerous colours of an unfading and brilliant hue, and to arrange them
                    in such a manner as to produce a harmony and elegance such as no article made in
                    Europe has ever fully equalled. The value put upon them by the traders who
                    brought them to the different markets runs from L.5 to L.100, and those of the
                    finest texture and greatest extent of figure sold for still higher prices. At a
                    time when there was a duty of eighty per cent. upon their importation into this
                    country (when, however, many were smuggled), a celebrated dealer in the article
                    in London possessed a shawl for which he asked five hundred guineas.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The duty
                    is now (1840) thirty per cent.</hi></p></note> *</p><p>As this country became more and more engaged in a variety of manufactures, and
                    the ingenuity of so many persons was put upon the stretch, it was but natural
                    that attention should be turned to a manufacture at once so curious and so much
                    prized. It was long before the manufacturers of this country ascertained the
                    material of which the Cashmerian shawls were made, or by what process they were
                    fabricated; and hence the first specimens that were produced in imitation of
                    them in this country were very inferior. The merit of commencing, and bringing
                    to a high degree of perfection, British shawls, belongs exclusively to
                    Edinburgh, and the principal seat of the manufacture all along has been in
                    Scotland. About thirty-four years ago the late Miss Bowie, who, with her father,
                    had for a number of years been engaged in the gold-lace manufacture, attempted
                    to make square shawls of the more simple patterns, in imitation of the Cashmere,
                    by means of the sewing-needle, from a fabric made of silk, spun from the waste
                    made in reeling the finest Italian silk. This plan was tedious and expensive,
                    and in effect fell far short of the originals.</p><p>The manufacture of damask had been carried on in Edinburgh for a long period. The
                    process by which the figures are produced in this elegant fabric first suggested
                    the idea that a similar contrivance might produce a close imitation of the
                    Indian shawls, both in the form of the figures and the distribution of the
                    colours attained. To accomplish this, and to train children to insert the
                    coloured yam with their fingers, were simultaneously attempted by several
                    manufacturers in Edinburgh; but although this article was manufactured by means
                    of the fingers in Cashmere, it was soon found that the higher price of labour in
                    Britain ren-<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=211" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0211-0193"/> dered it hopeless to establish the
                    shawl-manufacture on this principle.</p><p>The part of a loom termed a lay was at last constructed, and fitted up with boxes
                    to hold the number of shuttles for the colours required. This the weaver managed
                    by a simple application of the thumb of his left hand, whereby he was enabled,
                    without stopping his loom, to throw in the coloured yarn, and make it catch the
                    threads of the warp as they were raised by the draw-boy, and thus form the
                    intended figure. Patterns required from five to twelve different colours, and
                    consequently as many shuttles. The loom being mounted on a plan similar to that
                    employed for weaving damask, required one, two, and sometimes three boys,
                    according to the extent of the pattern, to draw up the threads in their order,
                    the shuttle being driven through: where not required to form the figure, the
                    coloured yarn remained loose and useless over the whole breadth of the shawl,
                    and required to be cut off with scissors. There was thus a great waste of
                    material; but as one weaver, with one or two boys, could produce as much work in
                    a single week, as a Cashmerian, with still more hands, on his plan of working,
                    could produce in twelve months, the saving was still very great. In place of
                    using any thing like an ordinary loom, the Cashmere manufacturer had the threads
                    called the warp placed in an upright frame, and the piece worked with the
                    fingers much in the same way as tapestry used to be made. A single shawl of some
                    of the most extensive patterns occupied a whole family from one to two
                    years.</p><p>The material of which the finest shawls were made, was procured from a goat found
                    in the range of mountains lying to the north and north-west of the district of
                    Cashmere. This animal is called by them the Thibet-goat, after the mountains
                    they inhabit. The skins of these animals are covered with a coat of strong hair
                    five or six inches in length; at the roots of this hair is found, in small
                    quantities, the very soft woolly substance of which the shawls are made.
                    Napoleon caused a breed of these goats to be brought to France, from the hair of
                    which shawls were made; and it has now become an article of commerce, and is
                    spun in considerable quantities both in Britain and in France. France spun and
                    manufactured it for several years before this country succeeded in importing or
                    making it; and to that country we are still indebted for a superior article of
                    yarn, which sells in this country, the doubled or warp at 48s. per pound weight,
                    and the single or weft at 30s. There are two circumstances which must at all
                    times make this article costly: the wool is obtained from the skin after death,
                    and not while the animal is alive; and the fine part requires to be picked from
                    the hairy part by the hand, no machine having yet been found capable of
                    performing the separation adequately. It farther appears that these goats are
                    found, in their natural state, only in ranges of the highest mountains; and as
                    they do not yield a fleece like sheep, it is manifest that the supply of the
                    article must at all times be very limited. During the earlier period of the
                    manufacture of shawls in this country, they were either compost'd of silk spun
                    from waste, or from a mixture of this article with the finest Saxony wool,
                    carded and spun together; the flowering being composed of the same material, or
                    of worsted; and some of the colours were of cotton only. In this state of the
                    manufacture, the makers in Edinburgh received from L.2 to L.10 sterling for each
                    shawl; and for several years the demand was good.</p><p>The shawl-manufacture was soon established in several places, more particularly
                    at Norwich, Glasgow, Paisley, and at Lyons in France, and a variety of trials
                    continued to be made to lessen the expense of production. The plan of mounting,
                    at this stage of the manufacture, in preparing the loom and figure, cost in many
                    instances from L.40 to L.50 before weaving was commenced; each loom requiring
                    one, and some of the large patterns two and even three boys, to draw the cords
                    during the process of weaving. There was also the expense of clipping off all
                    the coloured yam except such as was taken up to form the figure. To lessen these
                    expenses various means had been tried, but without success.</p><p>During the short peace of Amiens in 1802, a straw-hat maker in Lyons, of the name
                    of Jacquard, happened to see, in an English newspaper, an advertisement offering
                    a premium to any one who should contrive a machine for making nets. This led him
                    to turn his attention to the study of mechanics, and after many fruitless trials
                    he succeeded in contriving a machine which fully answered the purpose. He was
                    sent for, on this account, by Napoleon, and while at Paris, a superb shawl was
                    about to be woven for the Empress Josephine; and for its production they
                    employed a very costly and complicated loom, which had cost more than 20,000
                    francs. It appeared to Mr Jacquard that the same results might be produced by
                    less complicated machinery. Intense study and perseverance enabled him to
                    produce the machine that now bears his name. Mr Jacquard was rewarded with a
                    decoration of honour, and a pension of a thousand crowns per annum, and sent
                    with his machine to Lyons, the seat of the shawl and figured silk manufactures.
                    This contrivance not only superseded the use of the draw-boy, but also rendered
                    a great deal of tackling unnecessary; thus greatly simplifying and cheapening
                    the production, not only of shawls, but also that of figured articles of every
                    description.</p><p>It is a striking instance of the ignorance and shortsightedness of the operatives
                    of Lyons, that when Jacquard introduced his invention, the people broke out into
                    open rebellion. He was denounced as an enemy of the people, and as the man who
                    had been scheming the destruction of their trade, and the starvation of
                    themselves and their families. Three several plots were laid to assassinate him,
                    and twice he was in great danger of losing his life. So strong was the tide of
                    prejudice and indignation, that the machine was ordered to be openly destroyed
                    by the public authorities, and was accordingly broken in pieces in the great
                    square of the city.</p><p>The successful competition of foreigners, and the consequent decline of trade at
                    a subsequent period, induced some of the more intelligent manufacturers to think
                    of the man whose discovery was likely to bring some relief to the then depressed
                    manufacturers of Lyons. They made an experiment, and succeeded. Silks of the
                    greatest beauty were introduced at a lower cost, and now (1840) there is not a
                    mechanic, either in France or in Britain, who does not acknowledge the great
                    importance of Mr Jacquard’s invention. This may be fully conceived, from the
                    fact, that not only has it been very generally adopted by shawl-manufacturers,
                    but by makers of all kinds of damask, whether of silk or of linen, in Britain.
                    This improvement, together with a machine which the French had also contrived
                    about the same time, for cutting off the spare yam used in making the figures
                    (which completely superseded hand-labour), were both adopted in France some time
                    before they were introduced into Britain, which, with the advantage they derived
                    from having good yarn from the wool of the Thibet-goat, procured for the French
                    manufactures a decided advantage over the British for several years; and
                    notwithstanding a nominal protecting duty of thirty per cent. (but in reality
                    not affording more than twelve per cent. as facilities for smuggling were such,
                    that any one could have had an insurance for goods being safely delivered in
                    London, on paying to the French merchant twelve per cent. extra), goods were
                    brought over in great quantities, which, together with a general desire for
                    foreign productions, had the effect of ruining several British shawl-makers, as
                    well as some extensive dealers in the article. The improvements invented<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=212" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0212-0194"/> by the French, however, quickly found their way
                    to this country, and being applied with energy, soon produced a re-action in
                    favour of Scotch manufacturers, and caused the French to suffer in their turn,
                    from having made too large quantities in the hopes of retaining the London
                    trade. British figured shawls are now manufactured equal, in point of elegance,
                    with any produced in France, and superior to those of every other country in
                    lowness of price. They are manufactured from the wool of the Thibet-goat, which
                    is as soft as, and more perfect in figure than, the best Cashmere, and probably
                    less than a tenth part of the cost. The material, however, used for the
                    flowering, being finer, and the colours being more durable in the manufactures
                    of Cashmere, they still retain a superiority over those of Europe.</p><p>Edinburgh, from the commencement of this manufacture, has taken the lead in most
                    of the improvements connected with it, always producing the best goods of the
                    kind; but from the circumstance of labour of various kinds being lower in
                    Paisley and Glasgow, the manufacture has mostly been transferred to these
                    places. At one time there were about a thousand hands employed in Edinburgh in
                    this manufacture; now it scarcely gives work to one hundred.</p><p>Shawls in imitation of Cashmere are made of a very great variety of qualities.
                    While some of those made of the finest materials and richest patterns still sell
                    for L.8 or L.10 each, there are a great many made of a mixture of silk and
                    cotton, silk and wool, cotton and wool, and some are made wholly of cotton, so
                    that figured shawls can be purchased at five shillings each. It is computed
                    that, at the present time, this description of shawls gives employment to at
                    least 20,000 hands. A great many are exported to America, as well as to other
                    parts of the world. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Weaving. (b. y.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>