<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-7014-0780-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PAN (7th edition, volume 16, page 780)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:943979">Goats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050321">Paganism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40v89n0g">Goat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wv7t">Paganism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194567014?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PAN</label>, the god of shepherds, of hunters, and of all
                    country exercises. But he bore a higher character amongst the earliest Greeks,
                    as well as amongst the Egyptians, from whom his worship was borrowed by the
                    former people. In Egypt he was known by the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mendes,</hi> which, according to Jablonski,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Pantheon.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Egyptiorιrn.</hi></p></note> signifies fecundity. Hence his symbol was a living
                    he-goat, the most salacious of all animals: “Hircum Mendesium colunt AEgypti, eo
                    quod virtuti pro-lificae ac genitivae consecratus est. Namque animal hoc coitus
                    valde cupidum est.” His principal temple was a magnificent building in a city of
                    Lower Egypt, called after his name. It is well known, that from dedicating
                    certain animals to certain gods, the Egyptians proceeded to consider the animals
                    themselves as actuated by the divinities to whom they were sacred. Hence,
                    perhaps, the origin of animal worship. In the temple of Mendes w as kept a
                    he-goat, to which sacrifices of a very monstrous kind were offered.</p>
                <p>The deity whom the Egyptians adored by the name of Mendes was no other than the
                    Soul of the Universe, for he was their most ancient god; and we are told by
                    Plutarch, “that they took the first God and the Universe for one and the same
                    thing.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Iside et Osiride.</hi></p></note> Hence
                    his name of ∏αv amongst the Greeks. Not that either the Greeks or their masters
                    in theology worshipped, as their first god, mere brute matter, but that spirit
                    which they conceived to be co-eternal with matter, and to animate all things,
                    making them <hi rend="italic">one.</hi> Thus Orpheus, who imported the Egyptian
                    doctrine into</p>
                <p>Greece, declares that all things are one; and after him Parmenides and other
                    philosophers taught <hi rend="italic">tv 'ειναι το ∙καν,</hi> that “one is the
                    universe,” and that the “universe is immoveable.” That the ancient Grecian Pan,
                    or the Egyptian Mendes, was not the corporeal world, as senseless and inanimate,
                    but the whole system of things animated and eternal, appears further from the
                    following testimony of Macrobius: “Hunc deum Arcades colunt, appellantes m <hi
                    rend="italic">της</hi><hi rend="italic">iιλης κυξιοv,</hi> non sylvarum dominum,
                    sed universae sub-stantiae materialis dominatorem.” The Arcadians worship this
                    god, calling him the lord of Hyle, that is, not the lord of the woods, but the
                    lord of all material substance. In the same manner Pharnutus describes the Pan
                    of the other Greeks, not as the mere corporeal world, but as the intellectual
                    principle actuating it and presiding over it; and he adds, that “Pan was feigned
                    to be lascivious, because of the multitude of spermatic reasons in the world,
                    and the continual mixtures and generation of things.”</p>
                <p>The Egyptians, as we learn from Jablonski, had nearly the same notion with the
                    Greeks of the spirit which they worshipped as the soul of the universe, only
                    they ascribed to it both sexes. As the maker, governor, and bountiful father of
                    universal nature, they considered it as a male, whose symbol was the he-goat of
                    Mendes; and as a female it was adored by the name of Isis, to whom the she-goat
                    was consecrated, though not held in such veneration as the male. From this view
                    of the Egyptian creed, the sacrifice which we have mentioned appears no longer
                    unaccountable. It was made to a god, believed to be the universal source of
                    fecundity, and to whom, from the well-known character <hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                    the animal which he was supposed to actuate, they had reason to believe that it
                    would be most acceptable.</p>
                <p>The Greeks never worshipped their Pan by the emblem of a living goat; but they
                    painted him with the lower parts of a goat, for a reason which will be
                    afterwards mentioned. How he came to degenerate amongst that people, from one of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Dii majorum</hi><hi rend="italic">gentium,</hi> or rather
                    from the first principle of all things, to the rank of a demon or demi-god, we
                    cannot pretend to say. But that such was his fate is certain, for under this
                    last character mention is made both of his birth and his death.</p>
                <p>It is not agreed whose son he was. Homer makes him the son of Mercury, and says
                    he was called <hi rend="italic">Pan,</hi> from τα∣⅛ <hi rend="italic"
                    >οrnne,</hi> because he charmed all the gods with his flute; but others say that
                    he was the son of Demogorgon, and first invented the organ, of seven unequal
                    reeds, joined together in a particular manner. Having upon a time fought with
                    Cupid, the latter in spite made him fall in love with the nymph Syrinx, who,
                    flying from him to the banks of Ladon, a river of Arcadia, was, at the instant
                    prayers of the Nymphs, turned into a reed, as her name in Greek signifies, which
                    the god grasping instead of her, made a pipe of, and for his music was
                    worshipped by the Arcadians. The most common opinion was, that he was the son of
                    Mercury and Penelope. But Naturae Comes makes his birth scandalous, by saying he
                    was called παv, because begotten by all Penelope’s suitors. He was painted
                    half-man half-goat, with large goats’ horns, a chaplet of pine on his red face,
                    a pleasant laughter, with the feet and tail of a goat; a motley skin covered his
                    body, and he had a crooked stick in one hand, and his pipe in the other. He is
                    described by Silius Italicus (xiii. 326, <hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">seq.)</hi> as a sight enough to frighten women and children, nay,
                    even armed men too; for when Brennus the Gaul was about to pillage the temple of
                    Apollo at Delphos, Pan struck such a terror into his army, that he quitted his
                    sacrilegious design; and hence <hi rend="italic">Panici terrores.</hi> Yet,
                    homely as he was, he pleased the goddess Luna<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194567027?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-7027-0781"/>, turning
                    himself easily into a white ram (Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Georg.</hi> iii. 392,
                    <hi rend="italic">et deinceps)</hi>; and also the nymph Dryope, almost putting
                    off his divinity, and turning shepherd, for her sake. Neither was he displeasing
                    to other nymphs, who are generally represented dancing around him to hear the
                    charms of his pipe. The usual offerings made to him were milk and honey, in
                    shepherds’ wooden bowls. A dog, the wolf’s enemy, was also sacrificed to him;
                    and hence his usual epithet is ∖ <hi rend="italic">vκαιος,</hi> and his priests
                    are called <hi rend="italic">Luperci.</hi></p>
                <p>His festival, celebrated on the 15th of February by the Romans, was brought into
                    Italy by Evander the Arcadian, and revived afterwards by Romulus, in memory of
                    his preserver. He was also called by the Romans Inuus, <hi rend="italic">ab
                    ineundo.</hi> (Liv. i. 5; Macrob. <hi rend="italic">Sat.</hi> i. 21; and Serv.
                    <hi rend="italic">in Virg. AEn.</hi> vi. 775.) The ancients, by giving so many
                    adjuncts and attributes to this idol, seem to have designed him as the symbol of
                    the universe. His upper parts are human, because the upper part of the world is
                    fair, beautiful, and smiling, like his face; his horns symbolize the rays)of the
                    sun and of the moon; his red face indicates the splendour of the sky; the
                    spotted skin wherewith he is clothed, the stars which bespangle the firmament;
                    the roughness of his lower parts, beasts and vegetables; his goat’s feet, the
                    solidity of the earth; his pipe, compacted of seven reeds, the seven planets,
                    which, they say, produce the harmony of the spheres; and his crook, bending
                    round at the top, the years circling into one another.</p>
                <p>Having said so much of Pan, both as a self-existent god and as a generated demon,
                    we shall conclude this article with some observations on Plutarch’s account of
                    the prodigy which happened at his death; for, in the Pagan creed, demons were
                    not all believed immortal. “In the reign of Tiberius,” says he,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Lit&gt;. de
                    Oracul. Defect.</hi></p></note> “certain persons on a voyage from Asia to Italy,
                    and sailing towards the evening by the Echinedes, were there becalmed, and heard
                    a loud voice from the shore calling on one Thamus, an Egyptian pilot, whom they
                    had on board. Thamus, as may be supposed, listened with attention; and the
                    voice, after repeating his name thrice, commanded him when he came to the
                    Pelodes, to declare that the Great Pan was dead. The man, with the advice of his
                    companions, resolved, that if they should have a quick gale off the Pelodes, he
                    would pass by in silence; but that if they should be becalmed, he would perform
                    what the voice had commanded. Adhering to this resolution, they soon arrived off
                    the destined islands, andwere immediately becalmed, there being neither breath
                    of wind nor agitation of water. Upon this, Thamus, looking from the hinder part
                    of the ship towards the land, pronounced with a loud voice, ‘ the Great Pan is
                    dead,’ and was instantly answered from the shore by numberless bowlings and
                    lamentations.”</p>
                <p>This story, which has so much the air of imposture, has not only been admitted as
                    true by men of the first eminence for learning and acuteness, but has been
                    applied to our Saviour, whose death, says Cudworth, the demons mourned, not from
                    love, but from a presage that it would put a period to the tyranny and
                    domination which they had so long exercised over the souls and' bodies of men.
                    In support of this opinion, he quotes several passages of Scripture, such as,
                    “Now is the prince of this world judged ;"’ and, “Having spoiled principalities
                    and powers (by his death upon the cross), he triumphed over them in it.” He
                    affirms likewise, that “Pan being taken for that reason or understanding by
                    which all things were made, and by which they are all governed, or for that
                    divine wisdom which diffuseth itself through all things, is a name which might
                    very well signify <hi rend="italic">Gcd manifested in the fleshy</hi></p>
                <p>The authority of Cudworth is great; but a groundless opinion has seldom been
                    propped by weaker reasoning than he makes use of on this occasion. Plutarch
                    indeed says, and seems to believe, that this prodigy fell out during the reign
                    of Tiberius; but as he mentions not the year of that reign, there is no evidence
                    that it was at the crucifixion of our Saviour. The demons who inhabited the
                    Echinedes knew what had been transacted at Jerusalem, far distant from their
                    islands; they knew the name of the pilot of a strange ship; they knew that the
                    mariners of that ship had resolved to disobey their command, unless becalmed off
                    the Pelodes; they had power over both the winds and waves at the Pelodes, and
                    exerted that power to enforce obedience to their command; and yet these
                    all-knowing and powerful beings were under the necessity of calling in the aid
                    of a man to deliver a message to their companions, inhabiting a place to which
                    the very same story assures us that their own power and knowledge reached.
                    Should it be said that the demons were compelled by divine power thus publicly
                    to make known to man Christ’s triumph over the kingdom of darkness, we beg leave
                    to ask why they were not likewise compelled to give him another name, since it
                    is certain, that at the era of Tiberius, and long before, illiterate Pagans,
                    such as common seamen must be supposed to have been, knew no other Pan than the
                    fabled son of Penelope and Mercury? Indeed the other Pan, taken for that reason
                    or understanding by which all things were made, could not possibly be the being
                    here meant. For, erroneous as the Pagan system was, there is nothing in it so
                    completely absurd as the death of the soul of the universe, the maker of all
                    things; nor do we believe that any Pagan ever existed, who dreamed that such a
                    death was possible.</p>
                <p>What, then, it will be asked, are we to understand by this story? Plutarch was
                    eminent for knowledge and integrity, and he relates it without expressing a
                    doubt of its truth. But many a man of worth has been credulous; and though that
                    was not his character, this prodigy may be accounted for by natural means.
                    Germanicus was believed to have been poisoned, at least with the knowledge, if
                    not by the command, of Tiberius; and there was nothing which the Romans so
                    deeply deplored as the untimely death of that accomplished prince.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tacitus, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Annal,</hi> cap. 72, 83, <hi rend="italic">et</hi> lib. iii. cap. 1.</p></note>
                    They fancied that his body was animated, not by a human soul, but by a superior
                    demon; and they decreed to him statues, religious ceremonies, and even
                    sacrifices. His widow was highly honoured, as having been nearly related to a
                    divinity, and his children were adored as demi-gods. These facts being admitted,
                    nothing appears to us more probable than the opinion of the learned
                    Mosheim,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Cudworth’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Intel. Syst.</hi> cap. iv. note 132.</p></note> who thinks that
                    some shrewd statesman, in order to excite the popular fury against Tiberius to
                    the highest pitch, invented this story, and bribed foreign mariners to spread it
                    amongst the people, who would naturally believe, that by the Great Pan was meant
                    their favourite Germanicus. This hypothesis is at least countenanced by what
                    Plutarch tells us of the anxiety of the emperor to discover what personage could
                    be meant by the Pan whose death was announced to the seamen. He consulted the
                    learned men of Rome, who, in order to restore peace to the city, declared that
                    they understood it of none other than the son of Penelope and Mercury.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
