<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0090-0079-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAPUCHIN’S (9th edition, volume 5, page 79)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:877187">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz4b">Conventions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41g0hw2j">Capuchins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204166">Venezuela</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n90/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAPUCHIN’S</label>. The Capuchin friars are one branch of the
                    great Franciscan order, and their rule is in all essentials the same as that of
                    the other friars minor, or Minorites. It was in the first decade of the 13th
                    century that St Francis established his order; but it was not till 1528 that a
                    bull of Clement VII. erected into a separate order the disciples of a certain
                    minorité friar, who had conceived that he was inspired to reform the practices
                    of his order in some respects. This man’s name was Mathew da Bassi, a Franciscan
                    of the March of Ancona. The legend of the order states that, having seen a
                    representation of St Francis wearing a square-cut pyramidal hood, he made a
                    similar one for himself, sewed it on to his monastic habit and began to wear it.
                    This was in 1525. This audacious innovation drew down on the author of it much
                    blame, and some persecution on the part of his superiors; but as usual in
                    similar cases, that did not prevent others from following his example. Specially
                    two brothers Ludovico and Raffaelle of Fossombrone, the first a priest and the
                    second a lay brother of the Franciscan order, joined themselves to Mathew, and
                    underwent punishment from their superiors for so doing. They, however, obtained
                    the countenance and patronage of the Duchess Cibo, a connection of the then
                    reigning Pope Clement VII. (Giulio de’ Medici), and the wife of Giorgio Varano,
                    duke of Camerino. That lady gave her protégés a letter of recommendation to the
                    pope, armed with which they went to Rome, and, despite the fact that they were
                    disobedient to their superiors and therefore had broken their monastic vows,
                    obtained from the pope the bull known as <hi rend="italic">Religioni*</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Zelus,</hi> by which they were permitted to impart their
                    hooded habit to any disciples who might be willing to join them, to live as
                    hermits in wild and desolate places, to go barefoot, to wear beards, and to call
                    themselves “Hermit Friars Minor.” The populace, however, gave them a nickname
                    which has supplanted the more formal one. “Cappuccio” is a hood in Italian; and
                    the diminutive “Cappuccino,” formed half affectionately, half contemptuously, as
                    is the Italian wont, means “little hooded fellow.” When this bull had been
                    obtained, a place for the first congregation of the new order was soon found in
                    an abandoned convent at Colmenzone, near Camerino, given to them by the duchess.
                    Disciples thronged to the “new religion,” and three other convents were shortly
                    built. Mathew, the disobedient monk who had rebelled against his superiors and
                    abandoned his con <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n91/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0091-0080"/> vent, had fully succeeded in the objects to
                    which his ambition had prompted him. He had been made, of course, superior of
                    the first convent, and, subsequently, when the “families” of his new
                    congregation had multiplied, he became vicar-general, subject only to the
                    general of all the Franciscans.</p>
                <p>In 1538, in a chapter of the new congregation convoked at Florence—so rapidly had
                    the order of Capuchins spread itself—the celebrated Bernardino Ochino of Siena
                    was elected vicar general, and a second time in 1541. But having shortly
                    afterwards fallen into heresy, and taken refuge in Switzerland, the society to
                    which he had belonged, and on which his celebrity had thrown a lustre which has
                    never since belonged to it, fell under grave suspicions of heterodoxy. The
                    recently established congregation ran great risk of being dissolved, and its
                    leading members were cited by Paul III. to Rome to give an account of their
                    opinions. The Capuchins were forbidden to preach, and would have been abolished,
                    but for a warm and eloquent defence pronounced in Consistory by the Neapolitan
                    Cardinal Antonio Sanseverino, which warned the Pope of the danger of “plucking
                    up tares and wheat together!” This privilege was restored to the society in
                    1545; and the congregation multiplied itself largely in Italy. Paul III. had
                    forbidden them to extend themselves beyond the Alps; but Gregory XII 1., at the
                    request of King Charles IX., revoked this decree, and permitted them to
                    establish convents in any part of the world. Gregory XI <hi rend="italic"
                        >V.</hi> in 1591 forbade the Capuchins by bull to hear confessions and grant
                    absolution; but these functions were restored to them by Clement VIII. in 1602.
                    Paul V. in 1619 gave the congregation the rank and status of a distinct order,
                    gave their vicar the title of Minister General, relieved him from the necessity
                    (which heretofore had marked the <hi rend="italic">quasi</hi> subjection of the
                    society to that of the parent Franciscan <hi rend="italic">observantive</hi> or
                        <hi rend="italic">conventual</hi> friars) of asking the confirmation of his
                    election from the general of the Conventuals, exempted the Capuchin convents
                    from the right of visitation previously exercised by the superiors of the elder
                    branch, and conferred on them the muchvalued privilege of carrying a cross of
                    their own in all processions, instead of being obliged to walk after that of the
                    elder branch. It is stated that at this time the Capuchins numbered 15,000
                    members. Urban VIII. was a notable protector of the order, and created his
                    brother, who was a member of it, cardinal. It was mainly by him that the convent
                    in the Piazza Barberini,—which has been from that day to the recent one when the
                    generals of all the orders were removed from their convents, the residence of
                    the Capuchin generals,—was founded. Benedict XIV. gave the order the privilege
                    that the preacher of the Sacred Apostolic Palace should always be a member of
                    their society.</p>
                <p>The Capuchins have from a very early period of their separate existence had the
                    reputation of being great converters of heretics and infidels. It is related
                    that they converted a thousand Calvinists in Poitou alone to the orthodox faith.
                    From an early period they specially dedicated themselves to the work of
                    missionaries. Up to the year 1641 the Capuchins, though sending missionaries to
                    all parts of the world, had never had a missionary college. In that year their
                    general, Eugenio di Rumilly of Savoy, founded a college in Rome for the express
                    education of their members for the work of missions. In the first eighteen
                    months after the foundation of this college thirty-six Italian Capuchins were
                    sent to Hindustan and Brazil, and eighty Spaniards of the order to
                    Venezuela.</p>
                <p>The order at present maintains eighty-two missions, served (according to the
                    latest accounts) by a few more than two hundred missionaries. They have
                    twenty-three stations in Switzerland; in the north of Italy, nine; in the
                    Levant, eleven. In Asia also they have stations at Beyrout, Gazir, Saida,
                    Damascus, Mount Lebanon, and Aleppo In Georgia there are five stations, and four
                    in Mesopotamia In the East Indies they have fourteen missions, seven in Africa,
                    and four in South America. It is a result which might be expected from such a
                    field of labour, that the Capuchin Martyrology is a specially extensive one.</p>
                <p>The saints and martyrs of the order have been recorded by Father Charles of
                    Brussels in two volumes, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Flores Seraphicae.
                        A Biblioteca degli scrittori Cappuñni</hi> was printed in Venice in 1747.
                    The history of the order has been written by Zachariah Boverius in Latin, Lyons,
                    1632-39, 2 vols, folio. A decree of the Congregation of the Index in 1651
                    ordered the suppression of this work on account of the absurd tales with which
                    it abounds. A subsequent decree of the following year, however, permitted the
                    publication of it on condition of certain emendations. The work has been
                    translated into French, Italian, and Spanish. A continuation of the <hi
                        rend="italic">History</hi> of Boverius, by Father Marco of Pisa, was
                    published in folio at Lyons, 1676. The curious reader may also consult the work
                    of Giuseppe Zarlino, <hi rend="italic">On the Origin of the Congregation of the
                        Capuchins,</hi> Venice, 1579; also the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> of
                    Wadding; and Helyot’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Monastic Orders,</hi>
                    tom. vii. ch. 21</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
