<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0783-0770-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CICERO, Marcus Tullius</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 770</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dj16">Stoics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1021893">Milo</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n783/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CICERO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marcus Tullius</hi></label>,
                    born at Arpinum (Arpino) on the northern border of the Volscian territory, 3d
                    January 647 A.U.C., 106 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> His family was of
                    equestrian rank, and his father, though living in retirement, was intimate with
                    some of the public men of the day. The orator Crassus took an early interest in
                    the young Μ. Cicero and his brother Quintus, and directed their education. As an
                    orator, a statesman, and a man of letters Marcus became the most consummate
                    specimen of the Roman character under the influence of Hellenic culture. He was
                    first placed under the tuition of the Greek poet Archias, a teacher at Rome,
                    with whom he read the poets and orators of Greece, composed in the Greek
                    language, and also wrote Latin verse. This literary training he combined with
                    study under the two Scaevolas, the augur and the pontifex, and from these Roman
                    masters he imbibed the spirit of the national law and ritual. His aim was to
                    prepare himself by liberal as well as technical training for the career of an
                    advocate; but the Roman institutions required him to serve in the field also,
                    and he took part in the campaign of Sulla against the Italian confederates in
                    the year 87. Returning to the city he betook himself once more to the pursuits
                    most congenial to him, and attended on the teaching of Philo the chief of the
                    Academics, of Diodotus the Stoic, and of Molo a philosopher of Rhodes. Many
                    teachers had been driven at that moment from the schools of Greece by the
                    invasion of Mithridates. Cicero, at the age of twenty-six, pleaded a civil cause
                    in the speech <hi rend="italic">pro Quinctio</hi> (81 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.),</hi> and again in a criminal action against Roscius Amerinus in the
                    following year. After these efforts, which brought him some distinction, he
                    suddenly withdrew to ^.thens, on the plea of weak health, but probably to avoid
                    the displeasure of the dictator Sulla. Here he studied under Molo and others,
                    with a special view to the practice of declamation, and the management of his
                    physical powers in a profession which made severe demands upon them. He
                    travelled also through the Roman province of Asia, and stored up a vast amount
                    of information in a mind singularly acquisitive and endowed with extraordinary
                    facility of arrangement and expression, but with comparatively little fertility
                    of invention or breadth and strength of character. Cicero was from the first an
                    imitator and an adapter rather than an original thinker He was throughout a
                    follower rather than a leader in action as well as in speculation. His mental
                    training disposed him specially to admire past models or cling to existing
                    institutions, and he was always too easily subjected to the influence of
                    characters stronger than his own. His position, indeed, as a new man, or a
                    struggling candidate for political honours which neither his birth nor his means
                    could naturally command, made it necessary for him to attach himself to the
                    leaders of party; but his versatile talents soon rendered him a valuable
                    adherent, and it speaks well for the times in which his lot was cast, amidst the
                    deep corruption which pervaded them, that his honest and enlightened patriotism
                    was on the whole appreciated and rewarded.</p>
                <p>It was from policy, but partly also from his own kindly feelings, that the young
                    orator, on resuming his profession, preferred to distinguish himself in defence
                    rather than in attack. This course impressed the good-natured public in his
                    favour. Moreover, the class from which the judices were taken, conscious that
                    the position of defendants in a criminal suit might at any time be its own, was
                    often glad of an excuse for screening public delinquents. It may be said that
                    even the impeachment of Verres was rather a defence of the injured Sicilians
                    than a hostile attack upon an individual, who was allowed to withdraw quietly
                    from the city. Cicero’s triumph in this famous cause (70 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi>) raised him to the pinnacle of reputation. He had already attained
                    the quaestorship (77 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>). He succeeded to the
                    aedileship in 69, and became praetor in 68, a year memorable in his career for
                    the passing of the Manilian law, which he warmly supported, by which Pompeius
                    was constituted commander against Mithridates with extraordinary powers, in the
                    place of Lucullus. Pompeius was at this period accepted by the oligarchy as
                    their leader, though not without reluctance and distrust. Cicero gladly attached
                    himself to their cause, and flattered himself with the hope of reconciling the
                    senate with the knights by a more liberal and genial policy. Meanwhile he hoped,
                    by favour of the dominant party, to attain the consulship. He found himself a
                    candidate for that magistracy along with Catiline, a man of ruined character and
                    already under suspicion of plotting against the state. Nevertheless he did not
                    hesitate <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n784/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0784-0771"/> to combine with him in his canvass, and to
                    undertake his defence on a charge of malversation. Cicero obtained the
                    consulship; Catiline was defeated, and thereupon betook himself to treasonable
                    machinations. It was the business of his late ally to track these intrigues and
                    defeat them. The vigour and courage with which Cicero conducted himself at this
                    crisis won for him by popular acclamation the title of “Father of his Country”
                    (63 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> But the nobles ill requited the service he
                    had done them. They now felt themselves secure in their ascendency. They
                    affronted Pompeius, they made light of Cicero, and allowed him to be treated
                    contumeliously by a tribune, who, under pretence that he had condemned citizens
                    unheard, forbade him to make the usual declaration of the services he had
                    performed in his consulship. Cicero, in laying down his office, was only
                    permitted to exclaim—“I swear that I have saved the state.” Caesar, at the head
                    of the popular party, countenanced this affront; while Pompeius, perhaps a
                    little jealous of the rising statesman, on his return from the East vouchsafed
                    him no cordial support. The real weakness of his position was made painfully
                    manifest to him. He would not consent, however, to remove to a distance, and
                    declining to sue for the government of a province, devoted himself for a time
                    mainly to literary pursuits, composing among other things a poem on the glories
                    of his own consulship. Meanwhile the enemies he had made became more emboldened.
                    Clodius, a worthless demagogue, assailed him with a formal charge for putting
                    citizens to death summarily without appeal to the people. In vain did he assume
                    the garb of mourning, and traverse the streets as a suppliant. The magnates
                    stood coldly aloof, and the factions arrayed against him did not scruple to
                    menace his scanty defenders with violence. Cicero was obliged to seek safety in
                    flight, and withdrew to Thessalonica. Clodius obtained a decree of the people
                    for his banishment 400 miles from the city, and the destruction of his -house on
                    the Palatine, the site to be devoted to the erection of a temple of Liberty (58
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>)</p>
                <p>Pompeius and Caesar had suffered Cicero to undergo this humiliation for their own
                    purposes, but they were not disposed to submit to the arrogance of the upstart
                    Clodius, who was now making himself generally obnoxious. In the following year
                    they let it be understood that the persecution should cease. The partizans of
                    Clodius raised tumults in the city, but they were speedily put down, and a
                    resolution for the exile’s recall was carried in the assembly of the people.
                    Cicero had betrayed much weakness under banishment. The exultation with which he
                    triumphed on his return was hardly more dignified. The senate, however,
                    complimented him, by coming forth to meet him, and the state undertook the
                    restoration of his mansion. The armed opposition of Clodius was met by a counter
                    demonstration on the part of Milo, a no less turbulent instrument of the
                    oligarchy. But Cicero now felt himself powerless in the presence of chiefs of
                    armies and leaders of factions. He attached himself more closely to Pompeius,
                    and devoted his eloquence to the defence of his patron’s creatures, while he
                    courted more and more the pursuit of literature in retirement. The attainment of
                    a seat in the college of augurs on the death of Crassus (53 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c)</hi> placed him in a position of dignity well suited to the taste of a
                    constitutional antiquarian. But Caesar, though now absent in Gaul, was rapidly
                    becoming a great power in the state, and Cicero did not fail to pay court to him
                    also, proposing to celebrate his British wars in an epic poem. The death of
                    Clodius (52 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>), whose slayer, Milo, he defended,
                    relieved him from the apprehensions he had never yet shaken off. He accepted,
                    though not without reluctance, the lot which assigned him the government of
                    Cilicia for the year following. His conduct in this post seems to have been
                    highly meritorious. He checked the corruption of his officials while he
                    preserved his own purity, and distasteful as warlike affairs were to his
                    studious and quiet temper, he did not shrink from leading his troops against the
                    restless mountaineers. His vanity induced him to pretend to a triumph for his
                    success in these trifling operations; but in those degenerate days greater
                    victories than his would have failed to secure such an honour, unless backed by
                    the influence of the leaders of party, and neither Pompeius nor Caesar was
                    disposed to indulge him.</p>
                <p>The civil war between these two rivals was now imminent. Cicero naturally threw
                    himself into the ranks of the senatorial or conservative party, which was
                    blindly following the lead of Pompeius; but he was coldly received by the
                    violent men who ruled it, to whom his old-fashioned patriotism was utterly
                    distasteful. Reluctantly and with much misgiving he quitted Italy in the train
                    of the senate and consented to set up a shadow of the commonwealth on a foreign
                    shore; while Caesar attached to himself in the city, as dictator and consul,
                    both the substance and the forms of constitutional power. After the disaster of
                    Pharsalia and the rout of the senatorial forces, Cicero quickly threw aside his
                    arms and returned to Italy, where Caesar had left Antonius in command. He was
                    soon relieved from apprehensions for his own safety by kind assurances from the
                    victor, and while Caesar was occupied in Egypt, Africa, and Spain, he withdrew
                    altogether from public life. With his wife Terentia he had never lived happily;
                    but he now took the step of repudiating her, which according to the ideas of the
                    times caused no unfavourable remark, nor was it made matter of reflection upon
                    him that he straightway married again his own ward Publilia, wealthy as well as
                    beautiful. Theyoung bride seems, however, to have contributed nothing to his
                    domestic happiness, and her, too, he soon repudiated for the satisfaction she
                    had seemed to evince at the death of his much-loved daughter Tullia. During this
                    period, however, he abstained from making advances to Caesar, and did himself
                    honour by composing a panegyric upon Cato, to which Caesar condescended to make
                    an ill-tempered reply. But the conqueror’s clemency to Marcellus at last won his
                    heart, and now, after the death of Pompeius, Cato, and Scipio, with all the
                    other chiefs of his party, he could not refrain from declaring warmly in favour
                    of the new ruler. Caesar felt the compliment, and repaid it by sparing at his
                    instance the life of Ligarius. The conduct of Cicero at this critical moment was
                    undoubtedly the most truly politic. Other republicans, such as Brutus and
                    Cassius, who had espoused the senatorial cause with feverish zeal or angry
                    factiousness, did not scruple to give their actual support to the new
                    government, and to accept office under it, while they secretly chafed against it
                    and threw themselves into a conspiracy against the life of their master. The
                    difference between their spirit and that of Cicero is marked by the fact that in
                    a plot which numbered, it was said, as many as eighty men of public note, Cicero
                    himself was not included. The covert assassins dared not consult with men of
                    true honour. When the deed was done, indeed, Cicero might fairly take part with
                    its perpetrators in the name of the free state which in his sanguine view might
                    still he restored. When, however, the liberators, as they called themselves,
                    repaired to the provinces to strengthen their party against the Caesarians,
                    Cicero declined to undertake active service. He remained in Italy, and employed
                    himself in guiding, as he thought, the conduct of the young Octavius, the nephew
                    and heir of the dictator. This crafty dissembler promised well, and Cicero
                    expected to be able to use him as a convenient opponent to Antonius. It must be
                    confessed that the veteran statesman was himself playing a part, and dissembling
                    with the youth whom he meant eventually to get rid of. It was a game on both
                    sides, and Octavius <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n785/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0785-0772"/> won it. He looked on with satisfaction while
                    Cicero excited the passions of the citizens against Antonius in the series of
                    orations to which he gave the name of Philippics, while he armed the consuls
                    Hirtius and Pansa to overthrow him. The orator, now advanced in years, showed at
                    this crisis all the vigour with which he had encountered Catiline twenty years
                    earlier. To him the people entrusted the government of the city, and while all
                    the forces of the republic were concentrated under various leaders on the
                    Cisalpine, he might fancy himself for a moment the real controller of affairs.
                    But after the deaths of Hirtius and Pansa in the battles before Mutina, and the
                    discomfiture of the republicans under Decimus Brutus, Octavius, Antonius, and
                    Lepidus formed a compact, and assumed to be a triumvirate, or a board of three
                    special officers for the regulation of the commonwealth. Their arrival at Rome
                    was followed by bloody proscriptions of their public and private enemies.
                    Antonius demanded the head of Cicero, and Octavius yielded it. The orator fled,
                    together with his brother, but he could not endure to abandon Italy, and after
                    some weeks’ delay, which seems to show that the pursuit was not keen, he was
                    overtaken at the door of his Formian villa and his throat cut by the bravo
                    Popilius. His head and hands were cut off and sent to Rome, where Antonius
                    caused them to be affixed to the rostra, and Fulvia, the widow of Clodius and
                    the wife of Antonius, pierced with her needle the tongue which had declaimed
                    against both her husbands. Cicero perished at the close of the year 43, at the
                    age of sixty-three. Octavius, in his later years, as the Emperor Augustus, could
                    coolly say of the great statesman and patriot to whose murder he had consented,
                    “He was a good citizen, who really loved his country.” The saying was indeed
                    well deserved, but it should have come from purer lips.</p>
                <p>Cicero was indeed not only a good citizen, but a good man; he loved not his
                    country only but mankind in general; he loved them not merely from a kindly
                    nature, but from reflection and self-discipline. As a specimen of the highest
                    culture of the ancient world both moral and intellectual he must ever stand
                    pre-eminent. He was a wiser if not a more sincere patriot than Cato; his private
                    virtues were subjected .to a severer test than those of Μ. Aurelius. His
                    intellectual superiority is sufficiently attested by the important place he
                    attained, in the face of many disadvantages, in the conduct of public affairs.
                    But a large portion of his multifarious writings still remains, and constitutes
                    an enduring monument to his fame, which has been recognized through all ages.
                    The great bulk of these works may be conveniently classed as (1) political, (2)
                    philosophical, (3) personal. The first division comprises a collection of
                    fifty-six speeches professing to have been delivered in the forum or the curia,
                    though some of them certainly, as for instance that for Milo and the greater
                    number of the Philippics, were written for publication but not actually
                    delivered. The genuineness of that for Marcellus, and of the four which refer to
                    the orator’s return from exile, has been much questioned. Besides the speeches
                    themselves, Cicero produced several treatises on the subject of oratory, which
                    as part of the Roman training for public life may be regarded as political Of
                    these the principal are the <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Oratore,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Orator,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Brutus.</hi> The origin of the strictly technical treatises <hi rend="italic"
                    >de</hi><hi rend="italic">Inventione</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rhetoricorum</hi> is involved in much perplexity. To this division belong still
                    more strictly the important works <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Legibus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">de Republisa,</hi> which contain valuable
                    references to the events of early Roman history. To our second division belong
                    the famous treatises on philosophy, from which we derive all our knowledge of
                    the Greek systems which succeeded to the schools of Plato and Aristotle, and in
                    which it becam the fashion to affect an interest at Rome. Of these the <hi
                    rend="italic">Academica,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Tusculanoe,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Finibus,</hi> and others which have been
                    lost were devoted to speculative questions; the <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Divinatione</hi> and <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Natura Deorum</hi> refer more strictly to theological traditions; while the
                    book <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Officiis</hi> is an elaborate
                    treatise on moral obligations. The smaller works, <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Senectute,</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Amicitia,</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Consolatione,</hi> and
                    probably the lost essay <hi rend="italic">de Gloria,</hi> may also be ranged
                    more or less definitely under the head of practical philosophy. The third
                    division embraces Cicero’s letters in two series, the one those to his friend
                    Atticus, the other <hi rend="italic">(ad</hi><hi rend="italic">familiares)</hi>
                    to his correspondents generally. To these may be added a collection of letters
                    addressed to his brother Quintus. These together give an account of the writer’s
                    life almost from day to day; they are the most valuable of his works for the
                    historical information they afford us, as well as for the insight they give us
                    into the character not of the writer only but of many of the leading personages
                    of the day. In both these respects they stand unique among the remains of
                    antiquity, and few men of historical note even in recent times have been so
                    fully presented to us in their correspondence as Cicero, whose life acquires
                    thereby its transcendent interest for all students of human nature. It may be
                    added that the great philosopher and orator amused himself further with more
                    than one ambitious flight in poetry. His verses on his consulship attracted some
                    attention from his countrymen, and a specimen of them has come down to us. He
                    made also a Latin translation of the astronomical poem of Aratus, and proposed
                    at least, as has been above mentioned, to execute an epic on the invasion of
                    Britain by Caesar.</p>
                <p>The latest critical and complete edition of Cicero’s works is that of J. Caspar
                    Orellius, printed at Zurich (1826-1838). The text, accompanied by a full
                    apparatus of various readings, is followed by a collection of the ancient
                    scholiasts, an elaborate Onomasticon, and other valuable supplements. This
                    edition is comprised in eight, but may be more conveniently bound in twelve
                    large octavo volumes. (C. Μ. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
