<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0691-0678-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHLORINE (9th edition, volume 5, page 678)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p29x">Process</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078061">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078016">Process</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888378">Deacons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1074177">Powders</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n691/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHLORINE</label>, one of the chemical elements (symbol, Cl),
                    discovered by Scheele in 1774. It was long regarded as a compound; Scheele
                    termed it <hi rend="italic">depldogisticated muriatic add,</hi> and Berthollet
                    about 1785 gave it the name of <hi rend="italic">oxygenized muriatic acid,</hi>
                    which Kirwan contracted into <hi rend="italic">oxymuriaiw acid.</hi> In 1809 an
                    abstract of a paper was published by Gay-Lussac and Thénard, in the 2d vol. of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Arcueil,</hi> in which they demonstrated the possibility of the absence of
                    oxygen from oxymuriatic acid. The attention of Davy being drawn to the subject,
                    he in 1810 communicated to the Royal Society a paper in which he showed that
                    there was no evidence in support of the opinion that oxymuriatic acid contained
                    oxygen; and in a paper published in the following year he comes to the
                    conclusion that oxymuriatic acid is an uncompounded substance, and gives to it
                    the name of <hi rend="italic">chlorins,</hi> on account of the greenish colour
                    it possesses. Chlorine and its combinations with other elements having been
                    already treated of under the heading <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> it
                    will be necessary here only to give some account of the more important
                    commercial chlorine compounds hydrochloric acid, bleaching powder, and potassium
                    chlorate, and of the methods of preparing them.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hydrochloric Acid</hi> (HC1).—Practically, the whole of the
                    hydrochloric acid now employed in the manufacturing arts is obtained as a
                    collateral product in the celebrated soda process of Leblanc. The first stage in
                    that process consists in treating common salt with sulphuric acid in the
                    salt-cake roasting furnace, by which sodium sulphate and hydrochloric acid are
                    formed :—2NaCl + H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    = Na <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> &gt;SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 2HCL</p>
                <p>Till the year 1863 the acid fumes given off in alkali works were allowed to
                    escape freely into the atmosphere, and being dissolved and brought down by every
                    shower, destroyed or seriously damaged vegetation for miles around the works. In
                    that year the Alkali Act was passed, by which manufacturers were obliged to
                    condense not less than 95 per cent, of the total amount of hydrochloric acid
                    evolved in their establishments; and since that time great attention has been
                    paid to the condensation, so that now in many works practically no acid fumes
                    escape. The hydrochloric acid gas liberated in the roasting furnace is conveyed
                    through a range of stoneware pipes, in connection with which are various devices
                    for cooling it in its passage. It is then conducted into condensing towers—long
                    wide funnels packed with coke—through which a stream of water is made to
                    percolate from the top, an enormous surface of moisture being thus presented to
                    the acid fumes. The solution of the gas in the water constitutes the
                    hydrochloric acid, muriatic acid, or spirit of salt of commerce. So prepared,
                    the acid always contains several impurities, such as arsenious acid, ferric
                    chloride, and sulphurous acid; but these do not interfere with its application
                    to the preparation of bleaching powder, in which it is chiefly consumed. Without
                    any purification it is also employed for “souring * ’ in bleaching, and in tin
                    and lead soldering.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bleaching Powder,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Chloride of
                        Lime.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The history of the application of
                    chlorine to bleaching purposes before the introduction of the so-called chloride
                    of lime will be found under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Bleaching.</hi>
                    Bleaching powder is made by exposing pure slaked lime to an atmosphere of
                    chlorine till the lime will absorb no more of the gas. Many plans for the
                    preparation of the chlorine have been proposed, and various important processes
                    adopted, since the manufacture of bleaching-powder was established by Messrs
                    Tennant and Co. The original process was as follows. A mixture of native
                    peroxide of manganese ground to a fine powder, common salt, and sulphuric acid
                    was put into a large, nearly spherical, leaden vessel furnished at the top with
                    an air-tight lid. In this vessel an agitator was placed by which its contents
                    could be from time to time stirred up. From the lid a lead pipe conveyed the
                    liberated chlorine into the chamber in which the lime to be saturated was spread
                    in a thin layer. The exterior of the leaden vessel was cased with an iron
                    covering, space for the circulation of a current of steam between it and the
                    covering being left. Upon the charging of the still chlorine was at first given
                    off without heat; but after some time a current of steam was made to circulate
                    around the still, so as to maintain a sufficient temperature to disengage all
                    the chlorine. The materials used consisted of common salt, manganese peroxide,
                    and sulphuric acid, and the resulting products were manganous sulphate, sodium
                    sulphate, water, and chlorine:—</p>
                <p>MnO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2NaCl + 3H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi> = MnSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 2NaHSO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + C1 <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Through the development of Leblanc’s well-known soda process large quantities of
                    hydrochloric acid became available for the manufacture of chlorine, in place, as
                    formerly, of a mixture of common salt and sulphuric acid; and for many years
                    hydrochloric acid alone has been used. Coarsely ground manganese oxide is placed
                    within an oblong stone still, into which the necessary charge of strong
                    hydrochloric acid is admitted. Steam is then allowed to circulate in the outer
                    case of the still till the temperature of the mixture is raised to about 180°
                    Fahr. When this point is reached, steam at a pressure of 20 to 25 lb. is blown
                    through the charge at intervals for about six hours, after which the reaction is
                    complete—the whole occupying about twenty-four hours. The chemical changes that
                    take place are expressed in the following equation :—</p>
                <p>MnO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 4HC1=MnCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2H
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + Cl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Native binoxide of manganese being an impure and variable compound has to be used
                    in quantities proportionate to the MnO <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> it
                    contains.</p>
                <p>For each molecule of chlorine obtained by the above reaction, it will be observed
                    that one of manganous chloride is foιτned, a substance that was formerly run off
                    as a waste product. Apart from the nuisance thereby created, the drain on the
                    supply of manganese ore became serious, supplies diminished, and prices rose in
                    proportion. It became therefore an object of much importance to obviate the
                    waste of manganese, and this was sought in two different directions.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n692/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0692-0679"/>
                <p>Efforts in the first place were made to regenerate the manganese waste, so as
                    render it continuously available for manufacturing purposes; and secondly, it
                    was frequently attempted to dispense altogether with the use of manganese in the
                    process.</p>
                <p>The first really successful plan for the recovery and reoxidation of manganese
                    was devised by Mr Charles Dunlop, and was introduced at Messrs Tennant’s works,
                    at St Rollox, Glasgow, where it is still (1876) in operation. By Dunlop’s
                    process the residual still-liquor is first treated with carbonate of lime to
                    neutralize its free acid and decompose the contained ferric chloride, which thus
                    gives a precipitate, ferric oxide. The clear liquor obtained is a second time
                    mixed with carbonate of lime, then introduced into an enormous iron boiler, in
                    which it boils at a pressure of four atmospheres for about twelve hours. Under
                    the influence of the heat applied the manganese exchanges its chlorine for the
                    carbonic acid of the carbonate of lime, and a hydrated manganese carbonate,
                    suspended in a solution of chloride of calcium, is produced, thus :—</p>
                <p>MnCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + CaCO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> a</hi> O=MnCO <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + CaCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>The manganese carbonate is subsequently allowed to subside, and the solution of
                    chloride of calcium is washed out. The manganese carbonate is drained till it
                    becomes a white putty-like mass, when it is put into shallow iron trays, and
                    roasted in a furnace at a heat gradually increasing to 550° or 600° Fahr. Under
                    the influence of the heat the carbonic acid is driven off, and by degrees, from
                    being a white powder, the manganese compound darkens till on the completion of
                    the process it is a soot-like mass. Owing principally to the expensive nature of
                    the plant necessary, the Dunlop process never extended beyond St Rollox; but it
                    has satisfactorily maintained its position in that gigantic establishment.</p>
                <p>The method of artificially oxidizing manganese which is now almost universally
                    adopted, and has during the past few years quite revolutionized the bleaching
                    powder manufacture, is that invented by Mr Walter Weldon. Manganous chloride by
                    treatment with lime becomes changed into the lower oxide of manganese (MnO), a
                    body which with great difficulty is raised to the higher sesquioxide (Mn <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> 0 <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>), beyond which stage
                    of oxidation no exposure to oxygen raises it. But when treated with excess of
                    lime the manganous oxide rapidly unites with oxygen, and becomes transformed
                    into the peroxide (MnO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>), which is the chemical
                    compound available for the preparation of chlorine. It was this fact which Mr
                    Weldon discovered, and has turned to advantage in his process. The phenomenon he
                    accounts for on the assumption that the sesquioxide (Mn <hi rend="subscript">
                        2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>) formed by the exposure of manganous
                    oxide (M⅞O) to oxygen is really a manganous manganite, or a combination of MnO
                    with MnO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, the former having basic, the latter acid
                    functions. The lime added, by Mr Weldon supplies a more powerful base, and
                    enables the whole of the manganese to attain to the condition of peroxide,
                    uniting as it does in such a manner with the lime as to form a calcium manganite
                    (CaMnO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>). By employing a diminished quantity of lime
                    along with an increased current of air, it has been found possible to effect the
                    complete oxidation of the manganese, an acid manganite (CaMnO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> MnO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 3</hi>) being probably formed.</p>
                <p>In his treatment of the still-liquors Mr Weldon first neutralizes the acid,
                    &amp;c., as is done in Mr Dunlop’s process. The clear rose-tinted liquor thereby
                    obtained is passed into a vessel called the oxidizer, at a temperature of about
                    140° Fahr. A pipe for conveying a current of air passes down the centre of the
                    vessel, terminating near the bottom in a series of distributing pipes, and
                    connected at the other end with a blowing engine. The liquor being at, or
                    brought by injected steam to the proper temperature, then, according to Air
                    Weldon (Soc. <hi rend="italic">of Arts Lecture,</hi> May 1874), the injection of
                    air is commenced, and there is rapidly added, in the state of very fine
                    division, 1 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 6 times the quantity of lime
                    equivalent to the manganese in the liquor. This converts the charge into a thin
                    white mud, which consists of solution of calcic chloride holding in suspension
                    manganous oxide, or MnO, and also holding partly in suspension partly in
                    solution six-tenths of an equivalent—reckoned on the manganese present—of free
                    lime. When a little of this white mud is thrown on to a filter, the clear
                    filtrate is naturally found, owing to the quantity of free lime present, and to
                    the powerfully solvent action upon lime of hot solution of calcic chloride, to
                    possess a strongly alkaline reaction. As the injection of air goes on, the mud
                    becomes gradually darker in colour, owing to the white hydrated MnO becoming
                    converted into black Mn0 <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> by absorption of oxygen
                    from the injected air, what was originally a thin white mud being at length
                    converted into a thin black mud. During the progress of this conversion of the
                    originally white mud into a black mud, it is found that the alkaline reaction of
                    the filtrate from the mud gradually diminishes in intensity, until at length it
                    entirely disappears; and it is found, too, that when this alkaline reaction
                    ceases, the absorption of oxygen from the injected air ceases also. "When this
                    stage is reached, which is at the end of two, three, four, or five hours,
                    according to the relation between the size of the oxidizer and the size of the
                    blowing-engine employed, a little more liquor is run into the oxidizer from the
                    settlers above, the injection of air is continued for a few minutes longer, and
                    the charge is then run off from the oxidizer into one or other of a range of
                    settlers placed below it. In these it separates, in the course of a few hours,
                    into rather more than half perfectly clear solution of calcic chloride, and a
                    little less than half black mud of rather more than twice the density of that
                    which left the oxidizer. The solution of calcic chloride is now decanted, and
                    the settled mud is then ready for use for the liberation of chlorine from
                    hydrochloric acid.</p>
                <p>The now practically universal use of regenerated manganese oxide in a state of
                    fine division has considerably modified the older operations for the manufacture
                    of chlorine. Hydrochloric acid, according to the plan at present in use, is
                    first run into the still, and the manganese mud is admitted gradually to it in a
                    carefully regulated stream. Instead of the old oblong trough-like still, one
                    much more capacious, of pentagonal form, is generally employed. The details of
                    working vary in almost every establishment, but the following may be taken as an
                    example of ordinary practice. A charge of hydrochloric acid, equal to the amount
                    yielded by about 55 cwt. of common salt, is led into the still, and to it is
                    added from 14 to 15 cwt. of 70 per cent, manganese. Finely slaked lime to the
                    amount of 40 cwt. is spread in a uniform layer on the floor of the chamber, and
                    from these quantities 70 or 71 cwt. of bleaching powder containing from 35 to 37
                    per cent, of available chlorine is obtained. The lime, after receiving a first
                    charge of gas, is left 24 hours, when it is turned by workmen. Another charge is
                    then admitted, and on the expiry of twenty-four hours more the bleaching powder
                    is ready to be drawn off and packed in barrels.</p>
                <p>Of the many chlorine processes without manganese which have been proposed, the
                    only plan which has stood the test of wide practical applicationis that
                    introduced in recent years by Mr Henry Deacon, of Widnes, in Lancashire.
                    Doubtless his is a process which would have been widely introduced but for the
                    economy and satisfactory nature of Mr Weldon’s method. A process for liberating
                    chlorine from hydrochloric acid gas by exposing it with atmospheric air to a
                    high temperature was patented by Mr Robert Oxland in 1845. Mr Deacon discovered
                    that in this process, when the air and gas are brought into contact with
                    sulphate of copper the hydrochloric acid is decomposed much more completely and
                    at a far lower temperature than without that salt. In practice hot hydrochloric
                    acid gas and atmospheric air are passed over pieces of brick which have been
                    dipped in a solution of sulphate of copper and sulphate of soda, and dried.
                    Chlorine and water are produced by the decomposition, and some traces of
                    hydrochloric acid also pass undecomposed. The water and acid are condensed, and
                    the chlorine mixed with the residual nitrogen of the air passes on to the
                    absorbing chambers. As the chlorine is greatly diluted by the nitrogen, the lime
                    has to be exposed in thin layers over a large area, and Mr Deacon so arranges
                    his chambers that the mixed gases as they enter meet almost completely saturated
                    lime, but as the chlorine becomes absorbed, less highly chlorinized lime is met,
                    till at the end it is almost fresh hydrate of lime over which they pass. Mr
                    Deacon obtains from the acid of 1500 cwt. of salt, with the expenditure of 50
                    tons of small coal, upwards of 50 tons of 35 per cent, bleaching powder. The
                    process is in operation in his own manufactory at Widnes, and in some
                    Continental establishments Mr Deacon’s plant was introduced, but it has been
                    practically abandoned.</p>
                <p>Bleaching powder when fresh is a dry, white lime-like powder emitting a strong
                    odour of hypochlorous acid. Commercial samples vary considerably in strength,
                    but when newly made and of good quality they should contain from 35 to 37 per
                    cent, of available chlorine. On exposure bleaching powder parts with its
                    chlorine with considerable rapidity, losing, according to some experimenters, at
                    the rate of 0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 63 per cent, per month. On the
                    composition of bleaching powder see <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> page
                    494.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Potassium Chlorate</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Chlorate of
                        Potash.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The preparation of potassium chlorate
                    is an example of the employment of chlorine on an extensive scale, its function,
                    according to the ordinary process of manufacture, being to transform potassium
                    chloride (KC1) into potassium chlorate (KC1O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>) by
                    supplying the necessary oxygen from lime. It is obtained by passing excess of
                    chlorine into solution of potassium chloride and milk of lime, according to the
                    equation</p>
                <p>KC1 + 3CaO + 3C1 <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =3CaCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    + KC1O <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>.</p>
                <p>The operation is conducted in close leaden vessels, fitted with agitators and
                    heated with steam. On the completion of the above reaction the liquid is
                    filtered and evaporated to near dryness, and the residue is again dissolved in
                    hot water. The two salts—calcium chloride and potassium chlorate—are then easily
                    separatedby crystallization; the former, being exceedingly soluble, remains in
                    solution, while the latter deposits in tabular crystals, which may be purified
                    by a slight washing. The salt is very largely used in the manufacture of lucifer
                    matches and various detonating compounds, and in pyrotechny. It is also employed
                    in calico printing as an oxidizing agent in the fixing of certain colours, and
                    it is a convenient source of pure oxygen in laboratory work.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
