<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0085-0074-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAPPADOCIA (9th edition, volume 5, page 74)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023088">Minorities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023465">Minors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n85/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAPPADOCIA</label>, an extensive province of Asia Minor, that
                    for a considerable period constituted an independent kingdom. It was originally
                    a country of much greater extent; in the time of Herodotus, the Cappadocians
                    occupied the whole region from the chain of Mount Taurus on the south to the
                    shores of the Euxine. That author tells us that the name of Cappadocians was
                    that applied to them by the Persians, while they were termed by the Greeks
                    Syrians, or White Syrians (Leucosyri). The fact that they were a branch of the
                    same race with the Syrians appears indeed to admit of no doubt. Under the
                    Persian empire they were divided into two separate satrapies or governments, the
                    one comprising the central and inland portion of the country, to which the name
                    of Cappadocia continued to be applied, while the other was called Cappadocia ad
                    Pontum, and gradually came to be known simply as Pontus. As after the fall of
                    the Persian government the two provinces continued to be subject to separate
                    rulers, this distinction was perpetuated, and the name of Cappadocia came to be
                    restricted to the inland province <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n86/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0086-0075"/> (sometimes called Great Cappadocia), which
                    alone will be considered in the present article. The history and geography of
                    the region bordering on the Euxine will be found under <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Pontus.</hi></p>
                <p>Cappadocia, in this sense, was bounded on the 8. by the chain of Mount Taurus, on
                    the E. by the prolongation of that ridge and the Euphrates, on the N. by Pontus,
                    and on the W. by Galatia and Lycaonia. But it had no natural boundaries except
                    on the south and east, so that it is impossible to define its limits with
                    accuracy on the other sides. Strabo is the only ancient author who gives any
                    circumstantial account of the country, but he has greatly exaggerated its
                    dimensions; it was in reality about 250 miles in length by less than 150 in
                    breadth. With the exception of a narrow strip of the district called Melitene,
                    on the east, which forms part of the valley of the Euphrates, the whole of this
                    extensive region is a high upland tract, attaining to the level of more than
                    3000 feet above the sea, and constituting the central and most elevated portion
                    of the great table-land of Asia Minor. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Asia
                        Minor.)</hi> The western parts of the province, where it adjoins Lycaonia,
                    and extending thence to the foot of Mount Taurus, are open treeless plains,
                    affording pasture in modern as well as ancient times to numerous flocks of
                    sheep, but almost wholly desolate and uncultivated. But out of the midst of this
                    great upland level rise detached groups or masses of mountains, mostly of
                    volcanic origin, of which the loftiest is Mount Argaeus (still called by the
                    Turks Erdjish Dagh), which attains to a height of 13,000 feet above the sea,
                    while that of Hassan Dagh to the southwest of it rises to about 8000 feet.</p>
                <p>The eastern portion of the province is of a more varied and broken character,
                    being traversed by the mountainchain called by the Greeks Anti-Taurus, as well
                    as by several subordinate ridges, some of them parallel with it, others
                    extending eastwards from thence towards the Euphrates. Between these mountains
                    and the southern chain of Taurus properly so called lies the region called in
                    ancient times Cataonia, occupying an upland plain in a basin surrounded on all
                    sides by mountains. This district in the time of Strabo formed a portion of
                    Cappadocia, and though several ancient writers had regarded the Cataonians as a
                    distinct people from the Cappadocians, Strabo, who had himself visited the
                    country, could find no distinction between them either in language or
                    manners.</p>
                <p>The River Pyramus (now called the Jihun) rises in the table-land of Cataonia, and
                    forces its way through narrow and rocky defiles across the chain of Taurus to
                    the plains of Cilicia. The Sarus, or Sihun, rises much farther north, in the
                    Anti-Taurus, near the frontiers of Pontus, and flows through a deep and narrow
                    valley between two parallel ridges of mountains, for a distance of more than 150
                    miles, till it in like manner forces its way through the main range of the
                    Taurus, and emerges into the plains of Cilicia. The Halys, or Kizil Irmak, which
                    has its sources within the confines of Pontus, traverses the northern part of
                    Cappadocia throughout its whole extent, passing within about 20 miles of the
                    capital city of Kaisariyeh. The other rivers of Cappadocia are of little
                    importance.</p>
                <p>The kingdom of Cappadocia, which was still in existence down to the time of
                    Strabo, as a nominally independent state, was divided, according to that
                    geographer, into ten districts, viz., Melitene, Cataonia, Cilicia, Tyanitis, and
                    Garsauritis in the south, or adjoining Mount Taurus; and five others,
                    Laviniasene, Sargarausene, Saravene, Cha-manene, and Morimene, on the side of
                    Pontus. The position and limits of these northern subdivisions cannot be
                    determined with any certainty, but the others are better known. Cataonia has
                    been already described, and the adjoining district of Melitene, which did not
                    originally form part of Cappadocia at all, but was annexed to it by Ariarathes
                    I., was a fertile tract adjoining the Euphrates, the chief town of which still
                    retains the name of Malatiyeh. Cilicia was the name given to the district in
                    which Caesarea, the capital of the whole country, was situated, and in which
                    rose the lofty and conspicuous mass of Mount Argaeus. Tyanitis, as its name
                    shows, was the region of which Tyana was the capital,—a level tract in the
                    extreme south of the province, extending quite to the foot of Mount Taurus.
                    Garsauritis appears to have comprised the western or south-western districts
                    adjoining Lycaonia; its chief town was Archelaïs, now Ak Serai</p>
                <p>The only two cities of Cappadocia in the days of Strabo which were considered by
                    the geographer to deserve that appellation were—Mazaca, the capital of the
                    kingdom under its native monarchs, but which, after it had passed under the
                    Roman government, obtained the name of Caesarea, which it has ever since
                    retained under the scarcely altered form of Kaisariyeh; and Tyana, not far from
                    the foot of the Taurus, the site of which is marked by some ruins at a place
                    called Kiz Hissar, about 12 miles south-west of Nigdeh. Archelaïs, founded by
                    Archelaus, the last king of the country, subsequently became a Roman colony, and
                    a place of some importance. At the present day the only considerable town in
                    this part of Asia Minor is Kaisariyeh, which has a population of about 25,000
                    souls, and is an important centre of trade, and’the resort of merchants from aU
                    parts of Asia Minor, as well as Syria and Armenia.</p>
                <p>The ancient Cappadocians were much devoted to the practice of religious and
                    superstitious rites, and several localities in their country were the sites of
                    temples that enjoyed a great reputation for sanctity. Among these the most
                    celebrated was that of Comana, dedicated to the goddess Mā, whom the Greeks
                    identified with Enyo, the Bellona of the Romans, and the same deity who was
                    worshipped at the Pontic Comana. The high priest enjoyed consideration second
                    only to the king, and exercised rule over the greater part of Cataonia, of which
                    Comana was the chief place. It was situated on the river Sarus, but the site has
                    not been identified. Next to him ranked the high-priest of Zeus at Venasa, in
                    Morimene, which had not less than 3000 slaves. The temple of Artemis Perasia at
                    Castabala also enjoyed a great reputation of sanctity. Cappadocia was remarkable
                    for the number of slaves, which constituted indeed the principal wealth of its
                    monarchs. They were sent in large numbers to Rome, but did not enjoy a good
                    reputation. The province was also celebrated for the number and excellence of
                    its horses, as well as for its vast flocks of sheep; but from its elevation
                    above the sea, and the coldness of its climate, it could never have been a rich
                    and fertile country.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Histσry.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Nothing is known of the
                    history of Cappadocia before it became subject to the Persian empire. It was
                    included in the third satrapy of that empire in the division established by
                    Darius, but continued to be governed by satraps or rulers of its own, who
                    apparently retained the title of kings. These derived their descent from a
                    Persian named Anaphas, who was one of the seven conspirators that slew the false
                    Smerdis. The first ruler who succeeded in establishing himself in a position of
                    virtual independence was Ariarathes (hence called Ariarathes I.), who was a
                    contemporary of Alexander the Great, and. maintained himself on the throne of
                    Cappadocia after the fall of the Persian monarchy.</p>
                <p>After the death of Alexander, Perdiccas, marching into Cappadocia with a powerful
                    and well-disciplined army, succeeded in taking Ariarathes prisoner, and
                    crucified him and all those of the royal blood who fell into his hands. His son
                    Ariarathes II., however, having escaped the generaI <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n87/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0087-0076"/> slaughter, fled into Armenia, where he lay
                    concealed till the civil dissensions which arose among the Macedonians after the
                    death of Eumenes (to whom Perdiccas had surrendered the kingdom) gave him a
                    favourable opportunity of recovering the throne. Having defeated Amyntas in a
                    pitched battle, he compelled the Macedonians to abandon all the strongholds, and
                    after a long and undisturbed reign, left his kingdom to his son Ariamnes II.,
                    under whose peaceful administration, as well as that of his successor Ariarathes
                    III., Cappadocia made great progress.</p>
                <p>He was succeeded by Ariarathes IV., who joined Antiochus the Great against the
                    Romans, and after his defeat was obliged to atone for taking up arms against the
                    people of Rome by paying a fine of two hundred talents. He afterwards assisted
                    the republic with men and money against Perseus king of Macedon, and was
                    honoured by the senate with the title of the friend and ally of the Roman
                    people. He left the kingdom to his son Mithridates, who took the name of
                    Ariarathes V.</p>
                <p>During the reign of this prince, surnamed <hi rend="italic">Philopator,</hi> the
                    Cappadocians remained in close alliance with Rome. Notwithstanding this, he was
                    for a time expelled from his kingdom by Orophernes, who had been set up against
                    him by Demetrius Soter, king of Syria, as a rival claimant to the throne of
                    Cappadocia; but Ariarathes succeeded in expelling Orophernes, and afterwards
                    united his arms with those of Alexander Balas against Demetrius, who was
                    defeated and killed in battle. Some years afterwards Ariarathes, having espoused
                    the cause of the Romans in their contest with Aristonicus, a claimant of the
                    throne of Pergamus, was slain in the same battle in which Crassus, pro-consul of
                    Asia, was taken, and the Roman army cut to pieces (130 B.c.) He left six sons by
                    his wife Laodice, on whom the Romans bestowed Lycaonia and Cilicia. But Laodice,
                    fearing lest her children when they came of age should take the government out
                    of her hands, poisoned five of them,— the youngest only having escaped her
                    cruelty by being conveyed out of the kingdom. She was soon, however, put to
                    death by her subjects, who rose in rebellion against her tyrannical
                    government.</p>
                <p>Laodice was succeeded by Ariarathes VI., who soon after his accession married
                    Laodice, daughter of Mithridates the Great, wishing to gain the alliance of that
                    powerful prince in his contest with Nicomedes king of Bithynia, who laid claim
                    to part of his kingdom. Mithridates, however, instead of assisting, procured the
                    death of Ariarathes by poison, and under pretence of maintaining the rights of
                    the Cappadocians against Nicomedes, proclaimed himself regent till the children
                    of Ariarathes should be competent to govern the kingdom. The Cappadocians at
                    first acquiesced; but finding him unwilling to resign the regency in favour of
                    the lawful king, they rose in arms, expelled the foreign garrisons, and placed
                    Ariarathes VIL, eldest son of the late king, on the throne.</p>
                <p>The new prince found himself immediately engaged in a war with Nicomedes; but,
                    being assisted by Mithridates, he not only drove him out of Cappadocia, but
                    stripped him of a great part of his hereditary dominions. On the conclusion of
                    the peace, the refusal of Ariarathes to recall Gordius, the murderer of his
                    father, led to a war with Mithridates. When the two armies met on the frontiers
                    of Cappadocia, Mithridates invited Ariarathes to a conference, and openly
                    stabbed him with a dagger which he had concealed in his dress. The
                    terror-stricken Cappadocians immediately dispersed, and submitted to the yoke of
                    Mithridates; but, unable to endure the tyranny of his prefects, they quickly
                    rose in rebellion, and recalling the exiled brother of the late king they placed
                    him on the throne. He had scarcely ascended the throne when Mithridates invaded
                    the kingdom at the head of a numerous army, defeated the army of the
                    Cappadocians with great slaughter, and compelled Ariarathes VIII. to abandon the
                    kingdom. The unhappy prince soon after died of grief, and Mithridates bestowed
                    the kingdom on his own son, a youth only eight years old, giving him also the
                    name of Ariarathes. But Nicomedes Philopator, king of Bithynia, dreading the
                    increase of power in a rival already so formidable, claimed the throne for a
                    youth who pretended to be the third son of Ariarathes, and whom he sent with
                    Laodice to Rome to advocate his cause. Having received the declaration of
                    Laodice that the petitioner was one of three sons which she had borne to
                    Ariarathes, and whom she had kept concealed lest he should share the fate of his
                    brothers, the senate assured him that they would reinstate him in his kingdom.
                    Mithridates, receiving notice of these transactions, despatched Gordius to Rome
                    to advocate his cause, and to persuade the senate that the youth to whom he had
                    resigned the kingdom of Cappadocia was the lawful son of the late king, and
                    grandson to Ariarathes, who had lost his life in the service of the Romans
                    against Aristonicus. On receiving this embassy, the senate inquired more
                    narrowly into the matter, discovered the whole plot, and ordered Mithridates to
                    resign Cappadocia. The Cappadocians enjoyed their freedom for a short time, but
                    soon sent ambassadors to Rome, requesting the senate to appoint a king. Leave
                    was given them to elect a king of their own nation; and as the old royal family
                    was now extinct, they chose Ariobarzanes, who received the sanction of the
                    senate, and continued steadily attached to the Roman interest (93 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi></p>
                <p>Ariobarzanes had scarcely taken possession of his kingdom when he was driven out
                    by Tigranes, king of Armenia, who resigned Cappadocia to the son of Mithridates,
                    in terms of an alliance previously concluded between them. Ariobarzanes fled to
                    Rome, and by the assistance of Sulla, who routed Gordius the general of
                    Mithridates, he was quickly reinstated in his kingdom. On the return of Sulla,
                    however, Ariobarzanes was again driven out by Ariarathes, the son of
                    Mithridates, whom Tigranes had set up as king. By the intervention of Sulla,
                    Ariobarzanes was again placed on the throne; and immediately after Sulla’s death
                    he was a third time forced to abandon his kingdom, when Pompey, after defeating
                    Mithridates near Mount Stella, restored the unfortunate monarch, and rewarded
                    him for his services during the war with the provinces of Sophene, Gordyene, and
                    a great part of Cilicia. Wearied with such a succession of disasters, soon after
                    his restoration he resigned the crown to his son Ariobarzanes (63 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> and spent the rest of his life in
                    retirement.</p>
                <p>Ariobarzanes II. proved no less faithful to the Romans than his father had been.
                    On the breaking out of the civil war between Caesar and Pompey he sided with the
                    latter; but after the death of Pompey he was received into favour by Caesar, who
                    bestowed upon him a great part of Armenia. While the dictator was engaged in war
                    with the Egyptians, Pharnaces, king of Pontus, invaded Cappadocia and stripped
                    Ariobarzanes of all his dominions; but Caesar, after defeating Pharnaces,
                    restored the king of Cappadocia, and honoured him with new titles of friendship.
                    After the murder of Caesar, Ariobarzanes, refusing to join Brutus and Cassius,
                    was declared an enemy to the republic, and was soon afterwards taken prisoner
                    and put to death (42 B.c.) His brother, Ariarathes IX. was then for a few years
                    raised to the throne, but was in his turn put to death by Antony, and with him
                    the royal family became extinct.</p>
                <p>Archelaus, the grandson of the general of the same name who commanded against
                    Sulla in the Mithridatic war, owed his elevation to the throne of Cappadocia
                    solely to the intrigues of his mother Glaphyra with Mark Antony, to whom he
                    remained faithful in the contests with Augustus.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n88/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0088-0077"/>
                <p>Ou the defeat of Antony, he was pardoned by the emperor at the intercession of
                    the Cappadocians, and received Armenia Minor and Cilicia Trachea as a reward for
                    having assisted the Romans in clearing the seas of pirates who infested the
                    coast of Asia. He contracted a strict friendship with Herod the Great, king of
                    Judea, and married his daughter Glaphyra to Alexander, Herod’s son. On the
                    accession of Tiberius (who entertained a secret hostility to Archelaus on
                    account of his previous neglect of his merits during the lifetime of Caius
                    Caesar), he was decoyed to Rome by the fair promises of Livia, the emperor’s
                    mother; but being accused before the senate, and loaded with reproaches at the
                    court, he died of grief, after a reign of fifty years.</p>
                <p>On the death of Archelaus (17 A.D.) the kingdom of Cappadocia was reduced to a
                    Roman province, and governed by men of the equestrian order. It continued under
                    the Roman empire to enjoy a high state of prosperity, and its capital, Caesarea,
                    became a great and flourishing city. But in the reign of Valerian, it was
                    overrun by the Persian king Sapor, who took Caesarea after a long siege, and put
                    most of the inhabitants to the sword. Cappadocia, however, continued to form
                    part of the Byzantine empire, till it was conquered by the Seljukian Turks in
                    1074. It has ever since remained incorporated with the Turkish empire.</p>
                <p>During the Roman period Cappadocia assumes rather a prominent part in
                    ecclesiastical history. Its capital, Caesarea, was the birthplace of St Basil,
                    who long occupied its episcopal see, while that of Nyssa was held by his brother
                    Gregory; and the small town of Nazianzus, in the south-west of the province, was
                    at once the birthplace and the residence of the more celebrated Gregory,
                    commonly known from thence as St Gregory Nazianzen. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. h.
                        b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
