<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0046-0037-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANTON, or more correctly Kwang-cπow (9th edition,
                    volume 5, page 37)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017057">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136941">Suburbs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jj0k">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r851">Tigers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7721j">Pigeons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h12v74r">Arrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rg7r">Banners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n46/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANTON, or more correctly <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Kwang-cπow</hi></label> Foo, is a large and. populous commercial city
                    of China, in the province of Kwang-tung, situated on the eastern bank of the
                    Pearl River, which at Canton is somewhat broader than the Thames at London
                    Bridge, and is navigable 300 miles farther into the interior. The Pearl River
                    has an additional course of 80 miles to the sea, the first part of which lies
                    through a rich alluvial plain. Beyond this rises a range of hills terminating in
                    abrupt escarpments along the course of the river. The bold shore thus formed
                    compresses the stream at this point into a narrow pass, to which the Chinese
                    have given the name of Hu-mun, or Tiger’s mouth. This the Portuguese translated
                    into Boca Tigre, whence the designation of “the Boque,” by which it is commonly
                    known among Europeans. When viewed from the hills on the north, Canton appears
                    to be little more than an expanse of reddish roofs relieved by a few large
                    trees,—two pagodas shooting up within the walls, and a five-storied tower near
                    the northern gate, being the most conspicuous objects. These hills rise 1200
                    feet above the river. Little or no vegetation is seen on them; and their
                    acclivities, covered for miles with graves and tombs, serve as. the necropolis
                    of this vast city. Three or four forts are built on the points nearest the
                    northern walls. Facing the city on the opposite side of the river is the suburb
                    and island of Honan. The part of Canton enclosed by walls is about six miles in
                    circumference, and has a partition wall, running east and west, and dividing the
                    city into two unequal parts. The northern and larger division is called the old,
                    and the southern the new city. Including the suburbs, the city has a circuit of
                    nearly ten miles. The houses stretch along the river for four miles, and the
                    banks are almost entirely concealed by boats and rafts. The walls of the city
                    are of brick, on a foundation of sandstone and granite, are 20 feet thick, and
                    rise to an average height of 25 feet. On the north side the wall rises to
                    include a hill which it there meets with, and on the other three sides the city
                    is surrounded by a ditch, which is filled by the rising tide, when, for a time,
                    the revolting mass of filth that lies in its bed is concealed from view. There
                    are twelve outer gates— four of which are in the partition wall, and two water
                    gates, through which boats pass from east to west across the new city. The gates
                    are all shut at night, and in the day time a guard is stationed at them to
                    preserve order. The streets, amounting in all to upwards of 600, are long,
                    straight, and very narrow. They are mostly paved and are not as dirty as those
                    of some of the other cities in the empire; in fact, considering the habits of
                    the people and the inattention of Government to these matters, Canton may be
                    said to be a well-governed and comparatively cleanly city. The houses are in
                    general small, seldom consisting of more than two stories, the ground floor
                    serving as a shop in which goods are exhibited for sale, and the rest of the
                    house, with the court behind, being used as a warehouse. Here are to be found
                    the productions of every quarter of the globe; and the merchants are in general
                    extremely attentive and civil. The Chinese are remarkably expert men of
                    business, and are generally of the most assiduous habits.</p>
                <p>The temples and public buildings of Canton are numerous, but none of them present
                    features worthy of special remark. There are two pagodas near the west gate of
                    the old city, and 124 temples, pavilions, halls, and other religious edifices
                    within the city. One of the pagodas called the <hi rend="italic">Kwangtah,</hi>
                    or Plain Pagoda, is a Mahometan mosque, which was erected by the Arabian
                    voyagers who were in the habit of visiting Canton about ten centuries ago. It
                    rises in an angular tapering tower to the height of 160 feet. The other is an
                    octagonal pagoda of nine stories, 170 feet in height, and was first erected more
                    than thirteen centuries ago. A Buddhist temple at Honan, opposite the foreign
                    factories, and named in Chinese <hi rend="italic">ílaì-chwang-sze,</hi> or the
                    Temple of the Ocean Banner, is one of the largest in Canton. Its grounds, which
                    cover about seven acres, are surrounded by a wall, and are divided into courts,
                    gardens, and a burial-ground, where are deposited the ashes of priests, whose
                    bodies are burned. There are about 175 priests connected with this
                    establishment. Besides the <hi rend="italic">Hai-dιwang-sze</hi> the most
                    noteworthy temples in and about the city are those of the Five Hundred Gods, and
                    of Longevity, both in the western suburbs; the Tartar City Temple, and the
                    Temple of the Five Genii. The number of priests and nuns in Canton is not
                    exactly known, but they probably exceed 2000, nine-tenths of whom are Buddhists.
                    The temples are gloomy-looking edifices. The areas in front of them are usually
                    occupied by hucksters, beggars, and idlers, who are occasionally driven off to
                    make room for the matsheds, in which the theatrical performances got up by the
                    wealthy inhabitants are acted. The principal hall, where the idol sits
                    enshrined, is lighted only in front, and the inner apartments are inhabited by a
                    class of men almost as senseless as the idols they serve.</p>
                <p>The residences of the high officers of government are all within the walls of the
                    old city. The residence of the governor-general used to be in the south-west
                    corner of the new city, but it was utterly destroyed by the bombardment in 1856.
                    The site remained desolate until 1860, when it was taken possession of by the
                    French authorities, who have erected a Roman Catholic Cathedral upon it The
                    residence of the commander-in chief is in the old city, and is said to be one of
                    the best houses in Canton. There are four prisons in the city, all large
                    edifices. For the space of four or five miles opposite Canton boats-and vessels
                    are ranged parallel to each other in such close order that it resembles a
                    floating city; and these marine dwellings are occupied by numerous families, who
                    reside almost constantly on the water. In the middle of the river lie the
                    Chinese junks, some of them of from 600 to 1000 tons burden, which trade to the
                    north and to the Strait Settlements. The various guilds and associations among
                    the people and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n47/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0047-0038"/> the merchants from other provinces have
                    public halls each for its own particular use. The number of these buildings is
                    not less than 150. Canton was long the only seat of British trade with China,
                    and was no doubt fixed upon by the Chinese Government for the European trade, as
                    being the most distant from the capital Peking.</p>
                <p>Formerly only a limited number of merchants, called the <hi rend="italic"
                        >hong</hi> or security merchants, were allowed to trade with foreigners.
                    They were commonly men of large property, and were famed for integrity in their
                    transactions. All foreign cargoes passed through the hands of these merchants,
                    and by them also the return cargoes were furnished. They became security for the
                    payment of customs duties, and it was criminal for any other merchant to engage
                    in the trade with foreigners.</p>
                <p>Accounts are kept at Canton, in common with the rest of China, in <hi
                        rend="italic">taels, mace, candarines,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >cash.,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> ten cash being one candarine, ten
                    candarines one mace, ten mace one tael, which last is converted into English
                    money at about 6s. 8d. The coin called cash is of base metal, cast, not coined,
                    and very brittle. It is of small value, and varies in the market from 750 to
                    1000 cash for a tael. Its chief use is in making small payments among the lower
                    classes. Spanish and other silver coins are current, and are estimated by their
                    weight,—every merchant carrying scales and weights with him. All the dollars
                    that pass through the hands of the hong merchants bear their stamp; and when
                    they lose their weight in the course of circulation they are cut in pieces for
                    small change. The duties are paid to Government in sycee, or pure silver, which
                    is taken by weight. In delivering a cargo, English weights and scales are used,
                    which are afterwards reduced to Chinese catties and peculs. A pecul weighs 133⅜
                    &amp; avoirdupois, and a catty 1½ tt&gt;. Gold and silver are also weighed by
                    the tael and catty, 100 taels being reckoned equal to 120 oz. 16 dwt. troy.</p>
                <p>The foreign trade at Canton was materially damaged by the opening of Shanghai and
                    the ports on the Yangtsze, but it is yet of very considerable importance, as the
                    subjoined table of the total value of the foreign trade with Canton between the
                    years 1861 and 1874 inclusive is sufficient to show:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total Value of Imports.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total Value of I</p><p>Exports. 1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total Value.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Dollars.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Dollars.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Dollars.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1861</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,977,353</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,811,512</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28,788,865</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1862</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10,580,928</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>17,742,590</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28,323,518</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1863</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9,505,285</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16,083,062</p><p>13,659,177</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25,588,347</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1864</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8,192,795</p><p>10,556,602</p><p>14,171,101</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>21,851,972</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1865</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>. 18,054,557</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28,611,159</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1866</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>18,832,622</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>33,003,723</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1867</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14,090,581</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18,403,154</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>32,493,735</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1868</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,991,266</p><p>11,487,679</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18,491,156</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31,482,422</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1869</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>20,010,626</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31,498,305</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,053,394</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19,857,543</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31,910,937</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1871</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,661,889</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>23,612,439</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>39,274,328</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1872</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16,802,553</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25,691,712</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>42,494,265</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Shanghai Taels.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Shanghai Taels.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Shanghai Taels.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1873</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9,843,819</p><p>9,499,447</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16,156,437</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>26,900,256</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1874</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>16,640,525</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>26,139,972</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Although it is in the same parallel of latitude as Calcutta, the climate of
                    Canton is much cooler, and is considered superior to that of most places
                    situated between the tropics.. The extreme range of the thermometer is from 38°
                    to 100° Fahr., though these extremes are rarely reached. In ordinary years the
                    winter minimum is about 42°, and the maximum in summer 96°. From May to October
                    the hot season is considered to last; during the rest of the year the weather is
                    cool. In shallow vessels ice sometimes forms at Canton; and so rarely is snow
                    seen that when in February 1835 a fall to the depth of two inches occurred, the
                    citizens hardly knew its proper name. Most of the rain falls during May and
                    June, but the amount is nothing in comparison with that which falls during a
                    rainy season in Calcutta. July, August, and September are the regular monsoon
                    months, the wind coming from the southwest with frequent showers, which allay
                    the heat. In the succeeding months the northerly winds commence, with some
                    interruptions at first, but from October to January the temperature is
                    agreeable, the sky clear, and the air invigorating. Few large cities are more
                    generally healthy than Canton, and epidemics rarely prevail there.</p>
                <p>Provisions and refreshments of all sorts are abundant, and in general are
                    excellent in quality and moderate in price. It is a singular fact, that the
                    Chinese make no use of milk, either in its natural state, or in the form of
                    butter or cheese. Among the delicacies of a Chinese market are to be seen
                    horse-flesh, dogs, cats, hawks, owls, and edible birds’-nests. The business
                    between foreigners and natives at Canton is generally transacted in a jargon
                    known as “Pigeon English,” the Chinese being extremely ready in acquiring a
                    sufficient smattering of English words to render themselves intelligible.</p>
                <p>The intercourse between China and Europe by the way of the Cape of Good Hope
                    began in 1517, when Emmanuel, king of Portugal, sent an ambassador, accompanied
                    by a fleet of eight ships, to Peking, on which occasion the sanction of the
                    emperor to establish a trade at Canton was obtained. It was in 1596, in the
                    reign of Queen Elizabeth, that the English first attempted to open an
                    intercourse with China, but ineffectually, for the two ships which were
                    despatched on this mission were lost in the outward voyage, and it was not till
                    about 1634 that English ships visited Canton. Unfortunately at this time a
                    misunderstanding having occurred with the Chinese authorities owing to the
                    treachery of the Portuguese, a rupture and a battle took place, and it was with
                    difficulty that peace was again restored. In 1673 China was again visited by an
                    English ship which was subsequently refused admission into Japan, and in 1677 a
                    factory was established at Amoy. But during an irruption of the Tatars three
                    years later this building was destroyed, and it was not til] 1685 that the
                    emperor permitted any trade with Europeans at that port. Upon the union of the
                    two East India Companies in London, an imperial edict was issued, restricting
                    the foreign commerce to the port of Canton.</p>
                <p>Tea was first imported in England about the year 1667, and in 1689 a customs duty
                    of 5s. per lb was for the first time imposed. From this date to 1834 the East
                    India Company held a monopoly of the trade at Canton, and during this period the
                    prosperity of the port increased and multiplied, notwithstanding the
                    obstructions which were constantly thrown in the way of the “Barbarians” by the
                    Chinese Government. The termination of the Company’s monopoly brought no
                    alteration in the conduct of the native authorities, whose oppressions became
                    before long so unbearable that in 1839 war was declared on the part of Great
                    Britain. In 1841, while the forces under Sir Hugh (afterwards Lord) Gough were
                    preparing to capture Canton, Capt. Elliott entered into negotiations with the
                    Chinese, and consented to receive a pecuniary ransom in lieu of occupying the
                    city. Meanwhile the war was carried on in central China, and finally resulted in
                    the conclusion of the Nanking Treaty in August 1842, under the terms of which
                    four additional ports, viz., Shanghai, Ningpo, Fuh-chow Foo, and Amoy, were
                    thrown open to foreign trade, and foreigners were granted permission to enter
                    the city of Canton, from which they had hitherto been excluded. This latter
                    provision of the treaty, however, the Chinese refused to carry out; and after
                    endless disputes about this and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0048-0039"/> other improper acta of the Chinese
                    Government, war was again declared in 1856, the immediate cause of which was an
                    insult offered to the British flag by the capture of certain Chinese on board
                    the “Arrow,” a small craft trading under English colours. The outbreak of
                    hostilities was followed by the pillage and destruction of the foreign
                    “factories,” in December 1856, by a Chinese mob, and twelve months later Canton
                    was taken by assault by a force under Sir Charles Straubenzee, which had been
                    sent out from England for the purpose. From this time until October 1861, the
                    city was occupied by an English and French garrison, and the administration of
                    affairs was entrusted to an allied commission, consisting of two English
                    officers and one French officer, acting under the English general. Since the
                    withdrawal of this garrison, the city of Canton has been freely open to
                    foreigners of all nationalities, and the English consul at the present time has
                    his residence in the Yamun formerly occupied by the allied commissioners, within
                    the city walls.</p>
                <p>On the conclusion of peace it became necessary to provide a foreign settlement
                    for the merchants whose “factories” had been destroyed, and after some
                    consultation it was determined to fill in and appropiate as the British
                    settlement an extensive mud flat lying to the westward of the old factory site,
                    and known as Sha-mien, or “The Sand Flats.” This site having been leased, it was
                    converted into an artificial island by building a massive embankment of granite
                    in an irregular oval form. Between the northern face of the site and the Chinese
                    suburb, a canal of 100 feet in width was constructed, thus forming an island of
                    about 2850 feet in length and 950 feet in greatest breadth. The expense of
                    making this settlement was 325,000 Mexican dollars, four-fifths of which were
                    defrayed by the British Government, and one-fifth by the French Government. The
                    British portion of the new settlement was laid out in eighty-two lots; and so
                    bright appeared the prospect of trade at the time of their sale that 9000
                    dollars and upwards was paid in more than one instance for a lot, with a river
                    frontage, measuring 12,645 square feet. The depression in trade, however, which
                    soon followed acted as a bar to building, and it was not until the British
                    consulate was •erected in 1865 that the merchants began to occupy the settlement
                    in any numbers. The British consulate occupies six lots, with an area of 75,870
                    square feet in the centre of the site, overlooking the river, and is enclosed
                    with a substantial wall. A ground-rent of 15,000 cash (about L'3) per <hi
                        rend="italic">mow</hi> (a third of an acre) is annually paid by the owners
                    of lots to the Chinese Government.</p>
                <p>The Sha-mien settlement possesses many advantages. It is close to the western
                    suburb of Canton, where reside all the wholesale dealers as well as the
                    principal merchants and brokers; it faces the broad channel known as the Macao
                    Passage, up which the cool breezes in summer are wafted almost uninterruptedly,
                    and the river opposite to it affords a safe and commodious anchorage for
                    steamers up to 1000 tons burden. Steamers only are allowed to come up to Canton,
                    sailing vessels being restricted to the anchorage at Whampoa. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">China. (r. k. d.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
