<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0110-0099-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARDS, Playing</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 99</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1939006">Cards</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:847103">Carding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:853777">Chess</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1137633">Suites</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr79">Carding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jj4b">Cards</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07359">Chess</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n110/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARDS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Playing</hi></label><hi
                    rend="italic">(χάρτης,</hi> paper, probably, as Chatto thinks, <hi rend="italic"
                    >square</hi> paper), rectangular pieces of pasteboard, used atgames. The
                    invention of playingcards has been attributed to various nations. In the Chinese
                    dictionary, <hi rend="italic">Ching-tsze-tung</hi> (1678), it is said that cards
                    were invented in the reign of Sèun-ho, 1120 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> for
                    the amusement of his numerous concubines. There is a tradition that cards have
                    existed in India from time immemorial, and that they were invented by the
                    Brahmans. A pack of cards, said to be a thousand years old, is preserved in the
                    museum of the Royal Asiatic Society; but modern critics are of opinion that
                    these cards are of recent date. The invention of cards has also been assigned to
                    the Egyptians, but apparently on no better authority than the belief that the
                    representations on tarots may be so interpreted as to connect them with Egyptian
                    philosophy. To the Arabs, Germans, Spaniards, and French have also been ascribed
                    the invention of cards, but on grounds of varying feebleness.</p>
                <p>There are numerous singular resemblances between the ancient game of chess <hi
                    rend="italic">(chaturanga,</hi> the four <hi rend="italic">angas</hi> or members
                    of an army) and cards (see “Essay on the Indian Game of Chess,” by Sir William
                    Jones, <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Researches,</hi> vol. ii.), from which it has
                    been conjectured, with some show of reason, that cards were suggested by chess.
                    The presumption, then, is in favour of the Asiatic origin of cards.</p>
                <p>The time and manner of the introduction of cards into Europe are also moot
                    points. The 38th canon of the council of Worcester (1240) is often quoted as
                    evidence of cards having been known in England in the middle of the 13th
                    century; but the games “de rege et regina” there mentioned were a kind of
                    mumming exhibition (Strutt says chess). No queen is found in the earliest
                    European cards.</p>
                <p>In the wardrobe accounts of Edward I. (1278), Walter Stourton is paid 8s. 5d. “ad
                    opus regis ad ludendum ad quatuor reges.” This passage has been translated to
                    mean cards; but as chess was known in the East by a term signifying the four
                    kings <hi rend="italic">(chaturaji),</hi> it is now believed that this entry
                    relates to chess. If cards were known in Europe in 1278, it is very remarkable
                    that Petrarch, in his dialogue which treats of gaming, never mentions them; and
                    that though Boccaccio and Chaucer and contemporary writers notice various games,
                    there is not a single passage in any one of them that can be fairly construed to
                    refer to cards. Passages are quoted from various works, of or relative to this
                    period, but modern research leads to the belief that in every instance the word
                    rendered “cards” has either been mistranslated or interpolated.</p>
                <p>The earliest unquestionable mention of a distinct series of playing cards is the
                    well-known entry of Charles or Charbot Poupart, treasurer of the household of
                    Charles VI. of France, in his book of accounts for 1392 or 1393. It runs
                    thus—“Donné à Jacquemin Gringonneur, peintre, pour trois jeux de cartes, à or et
                    à diverses couleurs, ornés de plusieurs devises, pour porter devers le Seigneur
                    Roi, pour son ébatement, cinquante-six sols parisis.” From this entry it has
                    hastily been concluded that Jacquemin Gringonneur (it is not certain whether
                    Gringonneur was the painter’s surname, or only his designation as a maker of <hi
                    rend="italic">grangons)</hi> invented cards; but the payment is clearly for
                    painting, not for inventing them.</p>
                <p>The safe conclusion with regard to the introduction of cards is that, though they
                    may possibly have been known to a few persons in Europe about the middle of the
                    14th century, they did not come into general use until the end of the century,
                    and that whence they were brought has not yet been ascertained. But if the
                    testimony of Covelluzzo can be relied on, cards were introduced into Italy from
                    Arabia in the year 1379. Covelluzzo, who wrote in the 15th century, gives as his
                    authority the chronicle of one of his ancestors. His words are—“Anno 1379, fu
                    recato in Viterbo el gioco delle carte, ehe venne de Seracinia, e chiamisi tra
                    loro naib.” (In the year 1379 was brought into Viterbo the game of cards, which
                    comes from the country of the Saracens, and is with them called naib. See “<hi
                    rend="italic">Istoriα della Citta di Viterbo,”</hi> Feliciano Bussi, Roma,
                    1743.)</p>
                <p>Soon after the Rate of Poupart’s entry, cards it would seem became common; for in
                    an edict of the provost of Paris, 1397, working people are forbidden to play at
                    tennis, bowls, dice, cards, or nine-pins on working days. From the omission of
                    cards in an ordonnance of Charles V. (1369), forbidding certain games, it may
                    reasonably be concluded that cards became popular in France between 1369 and the
                    end of the century.</p>
                <p>It does not follow that because the earliest positive mention of a series of
                    cards is French, they were not previously known in other parts of Europe. It
                    seems more likely, if their Eastern origin is accepted, that they travelled
                    quickly through Europe to France. Early in the 15th century, card-making had
                    become a regular trade in Germany, whence cards were sent in small casks to
                    other countries. Cards were also manufactured in Italy at least as early as
                    1425, and in England before 1463; for by an Act of Parliament of 3 Edw. IV. the
                    importation of playing cards is forbidden, in consequence, it is said, of the
                    complaints of manufacturers that importation obstructed their business. No cards
                    of undoubted English manufacture have been discovered of so early a date; and
                    there is reason to believe, notwithstanding the Act of Edward IV., that our
                    chief supplies came from France or the Netherlands. In the reign of Elizabeth
                    the importation of cards was a monopoly; but from the time of James I. most of
                    the cards used in this country were of home manufacture. In the reign of James
                    I. a duty was first levied on cards; since when they have always been taxed.</p>
                <p>It has been much disputed whether the earliest cards were printed from wood
                    blocks. This is a question of some importance, as, if answered in the
                    affirmative, it would appear that the art of wood engraving, which led to that
                    of printing, may have been developed through the demand for the multiplication
                    of implements of play. The belief that the early card-makers or card-painters of
                    Ulm, Nuremberg, and Augsburg, from about 1418-1450, were also wood-engravers, is
                    founded on the assumption that the cards of that period were printed from
                    wood-blocks. It is, however, clear that the earliest cards were executed by
                    hand, like those designed for Charles VI. Many of the earliest woodcuts were
                    coloured by means of a stencil, so it would seem that at the time wood-engraving
                    was first introduced, the art of depicting and colouring figures by means of
                    stencil plates was well known. There are no playing cards engraved on wood to
                    which so early a date as 1423 (that of the earliest dated wood-en <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n111/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0111-0100"/> graving generally accepted) can be fairly
                    assigned; and as at this period there were professional card-makers established
                    in Germany, it is probable that wood-engraving was employed to produce cuts for
                    sacred subjects before it was applied to cards, and that there were hand-painted
                    and stencilled cards before there were wood-engravings of saints. The German <hi
                    rend="italic">Briefmaler</hi> or card-painter probably progressed into the
                    wood-engraver; but there is no proof that the earliest wood-engravers were the
                    card-makers.</p>
                <p>It is undecided whether the earliest cards were of the kind now common, called
                    <hi rend="italic">numeral</hi> cards, or whether they were <hi rend="italic"
                    >tarocchi</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tarots,</hi> which are still used in some
                    parts of France, Germany, and Italy, but the probability is that the tarots were
                    the earlier. A pack of tarots consists of seventy-eight cards, four suits of
                    numeral cards and twenty-two emblematic cards, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >atutti</hi> or <hi rend="italic">atouts.</hi> Each suit consists of fourteen
                    cards, ten of which are the pip cards, and four court (or more properly <hi
                    rend="italic">coat</hi> cards), viz., king, queen, chevalier, and valet. The
                    atouts are numbered from 1 to 21; the unnumbered card, called the∕ow, has no
                    positive value, but augments that of the other atouts. (See <hi rend="italic"
                    >Académie des Jeux,</hi> Corbet, Paris, 1814, for an account of the mode of
                    playing tarocchino or tarots.)</p>
                <p>The marks of the suits on the earliest cards (German) are hearts, bells, leaves,
                    and acorns. No ace has been discovered corresponding to the earliest known pack,
                    but other packs of about the same date have aces, and it seems unlikely that the
                    suits commenced with the deuces.</p>
                <p>Next in antiquity to the marks mentioned are swords, batons, cups, and money.
                    These are the most common on Italian cards of the late 15th century, and are now
                    used both in Italy and in Spain. French cards of the 16th century bear the marks
                    now generally used in France and England, viz., coeur, trèfle, pique, and
                    carreau.</p>
                <p>The French trèfle, though so named from its resem blance to the trefoil leaf, was
                    in all probability copied from the acorn; and the pique similarly from the leaf
                    (grün) of the German suits, while its name is derived from the sword of the
                    Italian suits. It is not derived from its resemblance to a pike head, as
                    commonly supposed. In England the French marks are used, and are named— hearts,
                    clubs (corresponding to trèfle, the French symbol being joined to the Italian
                    name, bastoni), spades (corresponding to the French pique, but having the
                    Italian name, spade [dissyl.]), and diamonds. This confusion of names and
                    symbols is accounted for by Chatto thus—“If cards were actually known in Italy
                    and Spain in the latter part of the 14th century, it is not unlikely that the
                    game was introduced into this country by some of the English soldiers who had
                    served, under the banners of Hawkwood and other free captains, in the wars of
                    Italy and Spain. However this may be, it seems certain that the earliest cards
                    commonly used in this country were of the same kind, with respect to the marks
                    of the suits, as those used in Italy and Spain.”</p>
                <p>About the last quarter of the 15th century, packs with animals, flowers, and
                    human figures, for marks of the suits, were engraved upon copper; and later,
                    numerous variations appeared, dictated by the caprice of individual card-makers;
                    but they never came into general use.</p>
                <p>The court cards of the early packs were king, chevalier, and knave. The Italians
                    were probably the first to substitute a queen for the chevalier, who in French
                    cards is altogether superseded by the queen. The court cards of French packs
                    received fanciful names, which varied from time to time.</p>
                <p>Abbé Rive, <hi rend="italic">Éclaircissements sur l'invention des Cartes à
                    jouer,</hi> Paris, 1780; J. G. I. Breitkopf, <hi rend="italic">Versuch den
                    Ursprung der Spielkarten zu erforschen,</hi> Leipsic, 1784; Samuel Weller
                    Singer, <hi rend="italic">Researches into the History of Playing Cards, with
                    Hlustratiσrs of the Origin of Printing and Engraving on Wood.,</hi> London,
                    1816; G.</p>
                <p>Peignot, <hi rend="italic">Analyse Critique</hi><hi rend="italic">et raisonnée de
                    toutes les Recherches publiées jusqu'à ce jour, sur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >l'</hi><hi rend="italic">Origine des Cartes à jouer,</hi> Dijon, 1826; M. C.
                    Leber, <hi rend="italic">Etudes historiques sur les Cartes à jouer,
                    principalement sur les Cartes Françaises,</hi> Palis, 1842; William Andrew
                    Chatto, <hi rend="italic">Facts and Speculations on the Origin and History of
                    Playing Cards,</hi> London, 1848; P. Boiteau D’Ambly, <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Cartes</hi><hi rend="italic">à jouer et la Cartomancie,</hi> Paris, 1854,
                    translated into English with additions under the title of <hi rend="italic">The
                    History of Playing Cards, with Anecdotes of their use in Conjuring,
                    Fortune-telling, and Card-sharping,</hi> edited by the Rev. E. S. Taylor, B.A.,
                    London, 1865; W. Hughes Willshire, Δ1.D., <hi rend="italic">A Descriptive
                    Catalogue of Playing and other Cards in the British Museum,</hi> printed by
                    order oí the Trustees, London, 1876. (H. J.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
