<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0228-0217-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATALONIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 217</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:918764">Exports</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49882n4f">Berbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h03c">Exports</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n228/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATALONIA</label> (in Spanish, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cataluña),</hi> an old province of Spain and principality of the crown of
                    Aragon, triangular in shape, and forming the north-east corner of the peninsula,
                    lies between 40° 30' and 42° 51' N. lat., and 0’ 15' and 3° 2Γ E. long., and is
                    bounded on the N. by the Pyrenees, W. by Aragon, S. by Valencia, E. by the
                    Mediterranean. The greatest breadth is 130 miles, the greatest length 185 miles;
                    area, 12,483 square miles. The coast, which is partly sandy, partly rocky,
                    extends about 240 miles; the harbours are mostly unprotected from the wind. The
                    surface is much broken by spurs of the Pyrenees, the direction of which is
                    generally south. Running south-west to north-east, and united on the north with
                    one of the offsets of the Pyrenees, is the range of the Sierra Llena, which
                    bisects the province, and forms its central watershed. The principal rivers are
                    the Ter, the Llobregat, and the Ebro, which all run into the Mediterranean. None
                    of them is navigable. The climate, in spite of frequent mists and rains, sudden
                    changes of temperature, and occasional great mid-day heat, is healthy and
                    favourable to vegetation. The soil is light and loamy. Amongst the rocks of the
                    province maybe mentioned granite, chiastolite schists, porphyry and lava. Near
                    Olot, towards the northeast, is a district containing extinct volcanoes. Oolitic
                    limestone is found in the neighbourhood of Figueras; and in other localities,
                    nummulitic and Miocene deposits are represented. Mining is not much prosecuted;
                    but copper, zinc, manganese, marble, sulphur, and coal are worked, and rock salt
                    in abundance is procured from Cardona. The vegetation of Catalonia varies
                    according to the altitude and nature of different regions. The dwarf-palm,
                    orange, lime, and olive grow in the warmer tracts; and on the higher grounds the
                    thorn-apple, pomegranate, myrtle, esparto, and heaths flourish. There is much
                    woodland, "but meadows and pastures are rare. Maize, millet, rye, flax,
                    liquorice, and fruits of all sorts—especially nuts, almonds, oranges, figs,
                    walnuts, and chestnuts—are produced. "Wheat sufficient for one-fourth of the
                    population is grown, and the vine is extensively cultivated. Few cattle, but
                    numbers of sheep, goats, and swine are reared. Game is plentiful, and thö
                    fisheries on the coast are excellent. The exports are chiefly fruits, cork, and
                    wines. The wines are for the most part rough and strong, though some are very
                    good, especially when matured. They are much used to adulterate those of Oporto,
                    or, after undergoing the operation termed <hi rend="italic">compage,</hi> are
                    passed off as Bordeaux wines in France. The best of them, <hi rend="italic"
                    >“</hi><hi rend="italic">prior ato"</hi> is chiefly known in England under the
                    disguise of second or third-rate port; it was much used in the military
                    hospitals of America during the Civil War. The imports are chiefly textiles,
                    coal, coke, machinery of all kinds, and salt-fish. The value of imports in 1870
                    was £5,996,143; of the exports, £2,884,306; the loss of the balance of
                    £3,111,837 against Catalonia being partly borne by the other provinces of Spain,
                    and to a great extent paid in wines, fruits, and corks. The value of exports to
                    the Spanish American colonies in 1873 exceeded £2,220,000. The manufactures of
                    Catalonia are cotton, silk, woollen goods, brandy, paper, cordage, and firearms.
                    The Catalonians are a frugal, sharp-witted, and industrious people, having much
                    national pride, and a strong revolutionary spirit. They are distinct in origin
                    from the other inhabitants of Spain, from whom they differ both in their dialect
                    and costume and in their great energy and their love of enterprize. Irrigation,
                    careful husbandry, and railroad communication have much developed the resources
                    of their country, in themselves excellent; and there are many manufacturing
                    towns and industrial establishments. Catalonia is divided into the provinces
                    Gerona, Barcelona, Tarragona, and Lerida. Its chief towns are the ports of
                    Rosas, Mataro, Tarragona, and the capital Barcelona; and Tortosa, Gerona,
                    Figueras, Lerida, and Manresa. The population, in 1867. was 1,744,520.</p>
                <p>Catalonia was one of the first of the Roman possessions in Spain, and formed the
                    north-eastern portion of <hi rend="italic">Hispania Tarraconensis.</hi> About
                    470 it was occupied by the Alans and Goths, and thus came to be called <hi
                    rend="italic">Gothalanιa,</hi> whence the modern name of the province. It was
                    taken possession of by the Berbers in 712, who were in turn dispossessed by the
                    Spaniards and the troops of Charlemagne in 788, and was after that ruled by
                    French counts, who soon, however, made themselves independent of France. By the
                    marriage of Count Raymond Berenger of Barcelona with Petronilla of Aragon, in
                    1137, Catalonia became annexed to the latter province; but this union was
                    frequently severed. In 1640, when Philip IV. attempted to deprive Catalonia of
                    its rights and privileges, it gave itself up to Louis XIII. of France. It was
                    restored to Spain in 1659, and was once more occupied by the French from 1694 to
                    1697. _ Under Philip V. Catalonia, in 1714, was deprived of its Cortes and
                    liberties. From 1808 to 1813 it was held by France. It was the scene of civil
                    war in 1823, and of important revolutionary operations in the Carlist war.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
