<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0779-0766-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHURCHILL, Charles</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 766</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1105812">Satirists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104962">Sandwiches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942434">Ghosts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x32m">Sandwiches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zd0b">Ghosts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n779/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHURCHILL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi></label>
                    (1731-1764), the satirist, was born in Westminster, where for many years his
                    father held the curacy and lectureship of St John’s. At eight years of age he
                    was sent to Westminster School, where he made no figure except by his
                    irregularities. At nineteen he applied for matriculation at Oxford, but was
                    rejected. He was afterwards admitted of Trinity College, Cambridge, which he
                    quitted immediately, and to which he never returned. A Fleet marriage contracted
                    about this time obliged him to retire, first to his father’s house, and
                    afterwards to Sunderland, where he began to study for the church. In 1756 he was
                    ordained priest, and officiated in his clerical capacity at Cadbury, in
                    Somersetshire, and at Rainham, in Essex, at which latter place he was obliged to
                    eke out his living by teaching. On his father’s death in 1758, Churchill
                    succeeded to his curacy and lectureship, and officiated for some time, employing
                    his leisure in reading the classics at a ladies’ boarding school and with
                    private pupils. But his innate Bohemianism was too strong to allow of such a
                    quiet way of life for long together. He gave himself over, in conjunction with
                    Lloyd the poet, who afterwards died in the Fleet, to every kind of loose living,
                    ran into debt, was pursued, and had a composition of five shillings in the pound
                    paid by the father of his boon companion. Part of the experience gained during
                    this period he used in his first published poem, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Rosciad</hi> (1761), a reckless but amusing satire on the artists of the several
                    London theatres, which was issued anonymously. The success of this work was
                    astonishing; Churchill was not backward in avowing its authorship; and the same
                    year he avenged himself on its critics in <hi rend="italic">The Apology,</hi> a
                    poem in which he adopted the systematic and scurrilous personality that was to
                    make him rich and famous. He was at this time in his thirtieth year, and in the
                    plenitude of his powers. His conduct, which had scandalized his parishioners,
                    drew down the censure of his dean. The satirist at once resigned his charges,
                    discarded his cassock and bands, and appeared <hi rend="italic">en viveur.</hi>
                    He separated from his wife, and apologized in the poem of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Night</hi> (1762), which is a sufficiently impudent piece of irony; and in the
                    same year he published, at irregular intervals, four books of Hudibrastic
                    doggrel called <hi rend="italic">The Ghost,</hi> in which Samuel Johnson and his
                    associates are ridiculed with some point and much brutality. An acquaintance
                    with John Wilkes, which seems to have ripened rapidly into friendship, gave
                    occasion for two of Churchill’s strongest efforts, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Prophecy of Famine,</hi> a violent attack on the Scottish influence and
                    character, and <hi rend="italic">The Epistle to Hogarth,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> the latter, which is said to have hastened the great artist’s death,
                    being a reply to Hogarth’s two carica <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n780/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0780-0767"/> tures of Wilkes and his friend. In 1763 appeared
                    <hi rend="italic">The Conference,</hi> a second apology; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Duellists,</hi> three books of loose octosyllabics, called forth by the duel
                    between Wilkes and Martin; and <hi rend="italic">The Author,</hi> a satire of
                    more general scope. These were followed in 1764 by <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gotham,</hi> another piece of indiscriminate censure; by <hi rend="italic">The
                    Candidate,</hi> an attack on Lord Sandwich; by <hi rend="italic">The Times,</hi>
                    the last of Churchill’s successes; and by <hi rend="italic">The Farewell</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Independence,</hi> which are worth little except as proofs
                    of their author’s decay. In the October of the same year he accompanied Humphrey
                    Cotes to Boulogne, where Wilkes was then in exile, and died there of fever in a
                    few days. He left some property, the proceeds of his writings, and bequeathed
                    the editorship of his poems, with the material for illustrations and notes, to
                    John Wilkes, who contrived to elude the bequest.</p>
                <p>Churchill was a literary bravo, a man who liked broils and beating, and who was
                    at the same time not indifferent to the rewards earned by the conflict. His
                    satires are generally rough and loose in texture, disjointed in structure, and
                    insolent in tone. They are full of good metal, it is true, but the ore lies
                    heaped over with too much schist to repay research. His extreme facility of
                    composition is perhaps a reason for this, as it is a reason why, writing from
                    day to day, he should have gained and kept the public favour. Cowper praised
                    him, but at best he was but an admirer and imitator of Dryden.</p>
                <p>See Churchill’s <hi rend="italic">Complete Works,</hi> London, 1774, 3 vols. The
                    best edition of the poems is that of Tooke, London, 1804, 2 vols., which has
                    been reprinted (1844) in the Aldine Poets.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
