<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0114-0103-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARICATURE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 103</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46w9686s">Leeches</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:995307">Leeches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:817559">Artists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n114/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARICATURE</label> (Italian <hi rend="italic">caricatura,
                    Ce.,</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> u</hi><hi rend="italic">ritratto
                    ridi-colo,”</hi> from <hi rend="italic">caricare,</hi> to load, to charge;
                    French <hi rend="italic">charge)</hi> may be defined as the art of applying the
                    grotesque to the purposes of satire. The word “caricatura” was first used as
                    English by Sir Thomas Browne (1605-1682), in his <hi rend="italic">Christian
                    Morals,</hi> a posthumous work; it is next found, still in its Italian form, in
                    No. 537 of the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> it was
                    adopted by Johnson in his Dictionary (1757), and only assumed its modern guise
                    toward the end of the 18th century, when its use and comprehension became
                    general.</p>
                <p>Little that is not conjectural can be written concerning caricature among the
                    ancients. Few traces of the comic are discoverable in Egyptian art,—three papyri
                    only of a satirical tendency being known to exist, and these appearing to belong
                    rather to the class of ithyphallic drolleries than to that of the ironical
                    grotesque. Among the Greeks, though but fewand dubious data are extant, itseems
                    possible that caricature may not have been altogether unknown. Their taste for
                    pictorial parody, indeed, has been sufficiently proved by plentiful discoveries
                    of pottery painted with burlesque subjects. Aristotle, moreover, who disapproved
                    of the grotesque in art, condemns in strong terms the pictures of a certain
                    Pauson, who, alluded to by Aristophanes, and the subject of one of Lucian’s
                    anecdotes, is hailed by Μ. Champfleury as the <hi rend="italic">doyen</hi> of
                    caricaturists. That the grotesque in plastic art was practised by the Romans is
                    evident from the curious frescoes unearthed at Pompeii and Herculaneum; from the
                    mention in Pliny of certain painters celebrated for burlesque pictures; from the
                    curious fantasies graven in gems and called Grylli; and from the number of
                    ithyphallic caprices that have descended to modern times. But in spite of these
                    evidences of Greek and Roman humour, in spite of the famous comic statuette of
                    Caracalla, and of the more famous <hi rend="italic">graffito</hi> of the
                    Crucifixion, the caricaturists of the old world must be sought for, not among
                    its painters and sculptors, but among its poets and dramatists. The comedies of
                    Aristophanes and the epigrams of Martial were, to the Athens of Pericles and the
                    Rome of Domitian, what the etchings of Gillray and the lithographs of Daumier
                    were to the London of George III. and the Paris of the Citizen King.</p>
                <p>During the long dusk of the Middle Ages a vast mass of material was accumulated
                    for the study ot the grotesque, but selection becomes even more difficult than
                    with the scarce relics of antiquity. With the building of the cathedrals
                    originated a new style of art; a strange mixture of memories of paganism and
                    Christian imaginings was called into being for the adornment of those great
                    strongholds of urban Catholicism, and in this the coarse and brutal materialism
                    of the popular humour found its largest and freest expression. On missal-marge
                    and sign-board, on stall and entablature, in gurgoyle and initial, the grotesque
                    displayed itself in an infinite variety of forms. Often obscene and horrible,
                    often quaint and fantastic, it is difficult, if not absolutely impossible, to
                    determine the import of this inextricable tangle of imagery. It has been
                    pretended that it constituted an immense network of symbolism, in which the
                    truths of the Church were set forth in forms intelligible to the popular mind. A
                    second interpretation is that it is merely the result of the decorative artist’s
                    caprice. A third school has sought to discover in much of it the evidences of
                    the struggle for supremacy between the secular clergy and the friars. Leaving
                    all this on one side, however, until the application to archaeology of the
                    comparative method shall have made the matter somewhat clearer, it will be
                    sufficient in this place to remark the prevalence of three great popular types,
                    or figures, each of which may be credited with a satirical intention,—of Reynard
                    the Fox, the hero of. the famous mediaeval romance; of the Devil, that
                    peculiarly mediaeval antithesis of God; and of Death, the sarcastic and
                    irreverent skeleton. The popularity of the last is evidenced by the fact that no
                    less than forty-three towns <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n115/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0115-0104"/> in England, France, and Germany are enumerated as
                    possessing sets of the Dance of Death, that grandiose all-levelling series of
                    caprices in the contemplation of which the Middle Ages found so much
                    consolation. It was reserved for Holbein (1498-1554), seizing the idea and
                    resuming all that his contemporaries thought and felt on the subject, to
                    produce, in his fifty-three magnificent etchings of the Danse Macabre, the
                    first, and perhaps the greatest, set of satirical moralities known to the modern
                    world.</p>
                <p>It is in the tumult of the Renaissance, indeed, that caricature in its modern
                    sense may be said to have been born. The great popular movements required some
                    such vehicle of comment or censure; the perfection to which the arts of design
                    were attaining supplied the means; the invention of printing ensured its
                    dissemination. The earliest genuine piece of pictorial irony that has been
                    discovered is a caricature (1499) relating to Louis XII. and his Italian War.
                    But it was the Reformation that produced the first full crop of satirical
                    ephemerae, and the heads of Luther and Alexander VI. are. therefore the direct
                    ancestors of the masks that smirk and frown from the “cartoons” of <hi
                    rend="italic">Punch</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Charivari.</hi> Fairly
                    started by Lucas Cranach, a friend of Luther, in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Passionale of Christ and Antichrist</hi> (1521), caricature was naturalized in
                    France under the League, but only to pass into the hands of the Dutch, who
                    supplied the rest of Europe with more or less satirical prints during the whole
                    of the next century. A curious reaction is visible in the work of Peter Breughel
                    (1510- 1570) towards the grotesque <hi rend="italic">diablerie</hi> and
                    macaberesque morality of mediaeval art, the last original and striking note of
                    which is caught in the compositions of Jacques Callot (1593-1635), and, in a
                    less degree, in those of his followers, Stefano della Bella (1610-1664) and
                    Salvator Rosa (1615-1673). On the other hand,however, Callot,oneof the greatest
                    masters of the grotesque that ever lived, in certain of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Caprices,</hi> and in his two famous sets of prints, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Misères</hi><hi rend="italic">de la guerre,</hi> may be said to anticipate
                    certain productions of Hogarth and Goya, and so to have founded the school of
                    ironical <hi rend="italic">genre</hi> which now-a-days does duty for
                    caricature.</p>
                <p>In England, during the 16th century, caricature can hardly be said to have
                    existed at all,—a grotesque of Mary Stuart as a mermaid, a pen and ink sketch of
                    which is yet to be seen in the Rolls Office, being the only example of it known.
                    The Great Rebellion, however, acted as the Reformation had done in Germany, and
                    Cavaliers and Roundheads caricatured each other freely. At this period satirical
                    pictures usually did duty as the title pages of scurrilous pamphlets; but one
                    instance is known of the employment during the war of a grotesque allegory as a
                    banner, while the end of the commonwealth produced a satirical pack of playing
                    cards, probably of Dutch origin. The Dutch, indeed, as already has been stated,
                    were the great purveyors of pictorial satire at this time and during the early
                    part of the next century. In England the wit of the victorious party was rather
                    vocal than pictorial; in France the spirit of caricature was sternly repressed;
                    and it was from Holland, bold in its republican freedom, and rich in painters
                    and etchers, that issued the flood of prints and medals which illustrate,
                    through cumbrous allegories and elaborate symbolization, the principal political
                    passages of both the former countries, from the Restoration (1660) to the South
                    Sea Bubble (1720). The most distinguished of the Dutch artists was Romain de
                    Hooghe (1638-1720), a follower of Callot, who, without any of the weird power of
                    his master, possessed a certain skill in grouping and faculty of grotesque
                    suggestiveness that made his point a most useful weapon to William of Orange
                    during the long struggle with Louis XIV.</p>
                <p>The 18th century, however, may be called emphatically the Age of Caricature. The
                    spirit is evident in letters as in art; in the fierce grotesques of Swift, in
                    the coarser <hi rend="italic">charges</hi> of Smollett, in the keen ironies of
                    Henry Fielding, in the Aristophanic tendency of Foote’s farces, no less than in
                    the masterly moralities of Hogarth and the truculent satires of Gillray. The
                    first event that called forth caricatures in any number was the prosecution
                    (1710) of Dr Sacheverell; most of these, however, were importations from
                    Holland, and only in the excitement attendant on the South Sea Bubble, some ten
                    years later, can the English school be said to have begun. Starting into active
                    being with the ministry of Walpole (1721), it flourished under that statesman
                    for some twenty years,—the “hieroglyphics,” as its prints were named,
                    graphically enough, often circulating on fans. It continued to increase in
                    importance and audacity till the reign of Pitt (1757-1761), when its activity
                    was somewhat abated. It rose, however, to a greater height than ever during the
                    rule of Bute (1761 — 1763), and since that time its influence has extended
                    without a single check. The artists whose combinations amused the public during
                    this earlier period are, with few exceptions, but little known and not greatly
                    esteemed. Among them were two amateurs, the countess of Burlington and General
                    Townshend; Goupy, Boitard, and Liotard were Frenchmen; Vandergucht and
                    Vanderbank were Dutchmen. But it must not be forgotten that this period
                    witnessed also the rise of William Hogarth (1697-1764). As a political
                    caricaturist this great man was not successful, save in a few isolated examples,
                    as in the portraits of Wilkes and Churchill; but as a moralist and social
                    satirist he has not yet been equalled. The publication, in 1732, of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Modern Midnight Conversation</hi> may be said to mark an epoch in
                    the history of caricature. Mention must also be made of Paul Sandby (1725-1809),
                    who was not a professional caricaturist, though he joined in the pictorial
                    hue-and-cry against Hogarth and Lord Bute, and who is best remembered as the
                    founder of the English school of water-colour; and of John Collet (1723-1788),
                    said to have been a pupil of Hogarth, a kindly and industrious humourist, rarely
                    venturing into the arena of politics. During the latter half of the century,
                    however, political caricature began to be somewhat more skilfully handled than
                    of old by James Sayer, a satirist in the pay of the younger Pitt, while social
                    grotesques were pleasantly treated by Henry William Bunbury (1750-1811) and
                    Woodward. These personalities, however, interesting as they are, are dwarfed
                    into insignificance by the great figure of James Gillray (1757-1815), in whose
                    hands political caricature became almost epic for grandeur of conception and
                    far-reaching suggestiveness. It is to the works of this man of genius, indeed,
                    and (in a less degree) to those of his contemporary, Thomas Rowlandson
                    (1756-1827), an artist of great and varied powers, that historians must turn for
                    the popular reflection of all the political notabilia of the end of the 18th and
                    the beginning of the 19th centuries. England may be said to have been the chosen
                    home of caricature during this period. In France, timid and futile under the
                    Monarchy, it had assumed an immense importance under the Revolution, and a cloud
                    of hideous pictorial libels was the result; but even the Revolution left no such
                    notes through its own artists, though Fragonard (1732-1806) himself was of the
                    number, as came from the gravers of Gillray and Rowlandson. In Germany
                    caricature did not exist. Only in Spain was there to be found an artist capable
                    of entering into competition with the masters of the satirical grotesque of whom
                    England could boast. The works of Francisco Goya y Lucientes (1746-1828) are
                    described by Théophile Gautier as “a mixture of those of Rembrandt, Watteau, and
                    the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0116-0105"/> comical dreams of Rabelais,” and Champfleury
                    discovers analogies between him and Honoré Daumier, the greatest caricaturist of
                    modern France.</p>
                <p>The satirical grotesque of the 18th century had been characterized by a sort of
                    grandiose brutality, by a certain vigorous obscenity, by a violence of
                    expression and intention, that appear monstrous in these days of reserve and
                    restraint, but that doubtless sorted well enough with the strong party feelings
                    and fierce political passions of the age. After the downfall of Napoleon (1815),
                    however, when strife was over and men were weary and satisfied, a change in
                    matter and manner came over the caricature of the period. In connection with
                    this change, the name of George Cruikshank (1792 ), an artist who stretches
                    hands on the one side towards Hogarth and Gillray, and ou the other towards
                    Leech and Tenniel, deserves honourable mention. Cruikshank’s political
                    caricatures, some of which were designed for the squibs of William Hone
                    (1779-1842), are, comparatively speaking, uninteresting; his ambition was that
                    of Hogarth—the production of “moral comedies.” Much of his work, therefore, may
                    be said to form a link in the chain of development through which has passed that
                    ironical <hi rend="italic">genre</hi> to which reference has already been made.
                    In 1829, however, began to appear the famous series of lithographs, signed H.B.,
                    the work of John Doyle (1798-1868). These apt but feeble jocularities are
                    interesting other than politically; thin and weakly as they are, they inaugurate
                    the style of political caricature which obtains, with but few and slight
                    variations, at the present date. In France, meanwhile, with the farcical designs
                    of Pigal and the realistic sketches of Henri Monnier, the admirable
                    portrait-busts of Dantan the younger, and the fine military and low-life
                    drolleries of Charlet (1792-1845) were appearing, and in these modern social
                    caricature may be said to be fairly embodied. Up to this date, though journalism
                    and caricature had sometimes joined hands (as in the case of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Craftsman</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Anti-joeobin,</hi> and
                    particularly in <hi rend="italic">Les Revolutions de France</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">de Brabant</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Actes des Apôtres),</hi> the alliance had been but brief; it was reserved for
                    Charles Philipon (1802-1862), who may be called the father of comic journalism,
                    to make it lasting. <hi rend="italic">La Caricature,</hi> founded by Philipon in
                    1831, and suppressed in 1833 after a brief but glorious career, was followed by
                    <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Charivari,</hi> which is perhaps the
                    most renowned of the innumerable enterprises of this extraordinary man. Among
                    the artists he assembled round him, the highest place is held by Honoré Daumier,
                    a draughtsman of great skill, and a caricaturist of immense vigour and audacity.
                    Another of Philipon’s band was Sulpice Paul Chevalier (1801-1866), better known
                    as Gavarni, in whose hands modern social caricature, advanced by Cruikshank and
                    Charlet, assumed its present guise, and became elegant. Mention must also be
                    made of Grandville (1803-1847), the illustrator of La Fontaine, and a modern
                    patron of the mediaeval skeleton; of Traviés, the father of the famous hunchback
                    “Mayeux;” and of Amedée de Noé, or “Cham,” the wittiest and most ephemeral of
                    pictorial satirists. In 1840, the pleasantries of “H.B.” having come to an end,
                    there was founded, in imitation of this enterprise of Philipon, a comic journal
                    which, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Punch, or the London Charivari,</hi>
                    has since become famous all over the world. Its earliest illustrators were John
                    Leech (1817-1864) and Richard Doyle, whose drawings were full of the richest
                    grotesque humour. It is in the pages of <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> that the
                    growth of modern pictorial pleasantry may best be traced. Of late years all the
                    “cartoons,” or political caricatures, have been the work of John Tenniel; they
                    exhibit few of the features of caricature as it was understood by Gillray and
                    Daumier; their object is not to excite hatred or contempt, but at most to raise
                    a smile. In social subjects, George Dumaurier a fine draughtsman, though
                    somewhat mannered and fond of a single type of face and figure, has carried the
                    ironical <hi rend="italic">genre,</hi> received by Leech from Gavarni and
                    Charlet, to the highest point of elegance it has attained.</p>
                <p>Of caricature, in the primitive sense of the word, there is but little. The fall
                    of the French Empire and the subsequent siege of Paris, together with the reign
                    of the Commune—a popular movement, though confined to a single city—produced a
                    plentiful crop of genuine caricatures, remarkable both for bitterness and for
                    ability. Among the few caricatures that now find favour may be mentioned the
                    graceful and genial caprices of Sambourne, the clever portraits of “Gill,” a
                    Parisian artist, and especially the remarkable series of portraits published in
                    London since 1862, in <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair,</hi> the work of
                    Pellegrini, which are certainly the most remarkable of their kind that have
                    appeared since the superb grotesques of Honoré Daumier.</p>
                <p>See Grose, <hi rend="italic">Rules for Drawing Caricature, with an Essay on Comic
                    Painting,</hi> London, 1788, 8vo; Malcolm, <hi rend="italic">Historical Sketch
                    oj the Art of Caricaturing,</hi> London, 1813, ,4to; Wright, <hi rend="italic"
                    >History oj Caricature and Grotesque in Literature and Art,</hi> London, 1865;
                    Jaime, <hi rend="italic">Musée</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Caricature</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> Champfleury, <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de la Caricature Antique,</hi> Paris, 8vo √ <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Caricature</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Moderne,</hi> Paris, 8vo; <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Caricature</hi><hi rend="italic">au Moyen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Age,</hi> 8vo; <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Caricature sous la République,
                    la Restauration, et</hi><hi rend="italic">ΓEmpire,</hi> Paris, 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
