<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0119-0108-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARLISLE (9th edition, volume 5, page 108)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09w45x">Celts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850410">Celts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:902429">Eden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938081">Garrisons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARLISLE</label>, a parliamentary and municipal borough, the
                    capital of Cumberland, 301 miles N.N.W. from London; 54° 54’ N. lat., 2° 55' W.
                    long. It is situated on an eminence enclosed by the three streams—the Eden, the
                    Caldew, and the Petteril. The Eden, which is the principal river, is joined by
                    the Petteril on the east side of the city; about a mile further west, as it
                    flows through fertile holms, it is joined by the Caldew, and about six miles
                    further on it falls into the Solway Firth. A handsome stone bridge, built in
                    1812-15, at a cost of £70,000, spans the Eden, midway between the mouths of the
                    Petteril and the Caldew.</p>
                <p>All the three streams are unnavigable. In the Eden there is good salmon fishing.
                    Before the Romans invaded Great Britain a Celtic town was erected on the site of
                    Carlisle; and when the Romans came they occupied and improved it. Archaeologists
                    consider it doubtful whether the Romans made it a military station to aid in the
                    defence of their newly-acquired colony against the incursions of the Picts , but
                    Roman coins, pottery, inscribed tablets, and other remains have been found in
                    such abundance that there can be no doubt Carlisle was, if not a military post,
                    a town of considerable importance in those days. The great wall of Severus,
                    extending from the Solway Firth to the German Ocean, crossed the River Eden at
                    Carlisle; and remains of this great barrier may still be seen on the outskirts
                    of the city. The Solway end of the wall, traces of which are still to be seen,
                    was about twelve miles from Carlisle, at Bowness; and there was an important
                    Roman camp, the Amboglana of the <hi rend="italic">Notitioe,</hi> about fifteen
                    miles eastward of the city, called Bird Oswald, of which interesting remains are
                    still in existence.</p>
                <p>Carlisle was the <hi rend="italic">Lniguvallum</hi> of the Romans. This name was
                    afterwards abbreviated to <hi rend="italic">Luell,</hi> and with the prefix <hi
                        rend="italic">Caer</hi> (a city), became <hi rend="italic">Caer-Luell,</hi>
                    and afterwards by easy transition, Carliol and Carlisle. After the departure of
                    the Romans in the 5th century the Picts laid the city in ruins; but in the 7th
                    century it was rebuilt by Egfrid, king of Northumberland. In 875 the town was
                    attacked by the Danes, who burned the houses, pulled down the wall, and
                    massacred the inhabitants. In this state of desolation it was left for 200
                    years, with no inhabitants but some few Celts who lodged themselves among the
                    ruins. In 1092 William Rufus, impressed with the importance of Carlisle as a
                    Border military station, ordered the town to be rebuilt and fortified, and left
                    a garrison there. It was not, however, until after the capture of the town in
                    the reign of Stephen, by David, king of Scots (who died within its walls in
                    1153), that the castle, the walls, and the citadel were completed.</p>
                <p>After undergoing two sieges the town was surrendered to the English Crown in
                    1217. Edward I. held three parliaments in Carlisle. In 1298, after the battle of
                    Falkirk, he marched to Carlisle; and nine years later it was while crossing
                    Burgh Marsh, about four miles from that city, with his army, to quell the third
                    revolt which had occurred in Scotland during his reign, that he sickened and
                    died. A monument has been erected on the spot to commemorate the event. With his
                    last breath he enjoined his son to prosecute the enterprise, and never desist
                    until he had completed the subjugation of Scotland. The nobles hastened to
                    Carlisle to pay homage to the new king, Edward IL, to whom, however, the legacy
                    of vengeance against the Scots proved but a “heritage of woe.” In 1315, after
                    the independence of Scotland had been won by the decisive battle of Bannockburn,
                    Robert Bruce, following up his success by ravaging the north of England,
                    besieged Carlisle Castle. There he met with determined resistance on the part of
                    the garrison and the inhabitants, under Sir Andrew Harcla, governor. Bruce, who
                    had his headquarters at the cathedral, made a general assault on all the gates
                    of the town on the ninth day; but the citizens defended their position with such
                    valour that the besiegers soon beat a retreat, having only killed two of the
                    besieged. Sir Andrew Harcla was created earl of Carlisle and Lord Warden of the
                    Marches for this gallant defence of the city; but he was afterwards found guilty
                    of treason and executed at Harraby Hill. In 1345 the Scots burned Carlisle and
                    Penrith. “They were very much annoyed,” says Lysons, “by small forces collected
                    by Bishop Kirkby and Sir Thomas Lacy. The bishop and Sir Robert Ogle had a sharp
                    skirmish with the enemy; the prelate was unhorsed during the encounter, but
                    having recovered his saddle continued to fight valiantly, and contrived greatly
                    to win the victory.” Nor was it only the “church militant” which did the state
                    much service in those days. In one of the sieges the women of Carlisle helped in
                    the defence of the city by pouring boiling water and rolling heavy stones from
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n120/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0120-0109"/> the walls upon the heads of the beleaguering
                    Scots below. In the 15th century Richard, duke of Gloucester, was governor of
                    Carlisle Castle, and during his governorship extensive repairs were made in the
                    old fortress, and in the course of time, during the reigns of Henry VIII. (who
                    built the citadel) and Elizabeth, it was adapted to artillery. In 1568 Mary
                    Queen of Scots, having fled from Lochleven, arrived in a fishing boat at
                    Workington, a Cumberland seaport· 32 miles from Carlisle, and was there met by
                    the deputy-governor of Carlisle, aud conducted to Carlisle Castle, where she was
                    lodged nominally as a guest but actually as a prisoner. She remained there for
                    two months. A little later in the same year a daring exploit was performed by
                    the duke of Buccleuch. William Armstrong, a redoubtable Borderer, better known
                    as “Kinmont Willie,” having been taken prisoner in disregard of a truce or
                    understanding which facilitated his capture, the “Bold Buccleuch,” with 200
                    followers, attacked Carlisle Castle, and rescued the prisoner, an achievement
                    which gave dire offence to Queen Elizabeth.</p>
                <p>During the civil wars Carlisle was harassed by frequent troubles; but the next
                    event of importance occurred in 1644, when the city and castle were besieged by
                    the Parliamentary forces under General Leslie for eight months. Sir Thomas
                    Glemham, the commander-in-chief of the royal troops, was in charge of the
                    garrison, who were reduced to great extremities before they surrendered on 25th
                    June 1645. Their valiant resistance was recognized by the besiegers, who allowed
                    them to march out “with their arms, flying colours, drums beating, matches
                    lighted at both ends, bullets in their mouths, and twelve charges of powder
                    a-piece.” The Parliamentary army pulled down some important portions of the
                    cathedral buildings, and out of the materials erected a guard-house in the
                    market-place. In 1648 Sir Philip Musgrave and Sir Thomas Glemham effected the
                    capture of Carlisle by surprise; but in October it was again surrendered to
                    Cromwell, according to treaty. At this time great distress prevailed in the
                    county, considerable families having barely the necessaries of life, while
                    numbers of the poor died on the highways.</p>
                <p>In the Scottish rebellion of 1745 Carlisle again figured in history. The
                    Pretender, Prince Charles Edward, laid siege to it, the three divisions of the
                    army with which he marched from Edinburgh having converged at the city. The
                    castle was at that time garrisoned by only two companies of invalids and some
                    disaffected militia, and Colonel Durand, who was in command, found it necessary,
                    with great reluctance, to surrender. “Bonnie Prince Charlie” rode into the town
                    on a white charger, with a hundred Highland pipers playing a triumphal march in
                    front, and made a house in English Street, which is still in existence, his
                    headquarters. But in December of the same year the duke of Cumberland arrived
                    and bombarded the castle, which his grace described as “an old hencoop, which he
                    would speedily bring down about their ears,” and on the 30th the garrison
                    surrendered. The duke quartered his soldiers in the cathedral, and thirty-one of
                    the rebels were subsequently executed at Harraby Hill. The tower in which Mary
                    Queen of Scots was imprisoned was pulled down in 1835; but a considerable
                    portion of the ancient castle still remains, and it is used as a garrison for
                    the 2d Brigade Dépôt. Only a small portion of the old city walls now exists, and
                    the city gates have entirely disappeared.</p>
                <p>Carlisle suffered in 1380 from a great fire, which destroyed 1500 houses in three
                    of the principal streets; and the plague in 1598 carried off 1076 persons,
                    one-third of the inhabitants.</p>
                <p>Carlisle is the see of a bishop. The cathedral was founded by William Rufus, and
                    completed by Henry I. The original proportions of the building have been very
                    much curtailed. A disastrous fire, in 1292, destroyed the nave, only a small
                    part of which now remains. The most interesting architectural feature of the
                    cathedral is the east window, which has been pronounced by archaeologists to be
                    one of the finest in the kingdom, the harmony of its parts and the easy flow of
                    its lines being particularly remarkable. The remains of Dr Paley are interred in
                    one of its aisles, and a stone pulpit, richly carved in Caen-stone and
                    ornamented with white alabaster, has been erected to his memory. The window in
                    the north transept has been filled with stained glass in memory of the five
                    children of Dr Tait, archbishop of Canterbury, who died of scarlet fever while
                    his grace was dean of Carlisle. The cathedral possesses many memorials of
                    interest. A large portion of the adjacent priory, founded by William Rufus, was
                    destroyed during the civil wars, but the remains may still be traced on the
                    south side of the cathedral. A convent of grey friars which existed in the city
                    was destroyed by the fire in 1292. There was also at one time a convent of black
                    friars, and a hospital founded at St Nicholas for lepers; the latter was
                    destroyed in the 17th century. According to Lyson’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >History,</hi> the bowels of Richard Coeur de Lion were buried in Carlisle
                    cathedral.</p>
                <p>In addition to the cathedral aud the castle, the chief buildings in Carlisle are
                    the court-houses—two large round towers built upon the site of the old citadel;
                    the county-jail, contiguous thereto; the news-room, the post-office, the railway
                    station, the infirmary, and two of the joint-stock banks. There is a
                    market-cross in the centre of the market-place, and two marble statues adorn the
                    principal streets. One of these, between the two court-houses (by Musgrave L.
                    Watson), is of William, earl of Lonsdale; the other, in the market-place (by
                    Woodington), is of James Steel, editor and proprietor of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Carlisle Journal,</hi> a citizen who during his lifetime took a prominent
                    part in local public affairs. In addition to the cathedral there are eight
                    established churches in Carlisle, and several places of worship for
                    Independents, Methodists, Presbyterians, Baptists, aud Roman Catholics. Its
                    literary and scientific institutions include a mechanics’ institution, a young
                    men’s Christian association, and several working men’s reading rooms, managed
                    entirely by working men themselves. Its charities consist of an infirmary with
                    100 beds, a dispensary, and a fever hospital; and in connection with the
                    infirmary there is a convalescent institution at the seaside at Silloth, to
                    which patients are admitted-upon payment of a small weekly sum. There is a
                    school-board, of nine members; a school of art; and a cathedral grammar
                    school.</p>
                <p>Carlisle is a great railway centre. The London and North-Western, the Midland,
                    the Caledonian, the North British, and the Glasgow and South-Western Railways
                    have each a terminus there; while the North-Eastern Company have access to the
                    city by their Newcastle and Carlisle section. In 1876 more than sixty passenger
                    trains left Carlisle Citadel station every week-day, and as many more entered
                    the city.</p>
                <p>The principal business of Carlisle is the manufacture of cotton goods, the
                    finishing of silesias, the printing of calicoes, and the manufacture of
                    biscuits. There are also within the city two or three large iron-works, and the
                    manufacture of felt hats is carried on upon a large scale. A dock at and railway
                    to Silloth, on the Solway Fnth, 21 miles from Carlisle, were constructed in 1855
                    to facilitate the transit of the commerce of the district, and this gradually
                    superseded Port Carlisle, which is no longer used as a harbour.</p>
                <p>Carlisle returns two members of parliament. Its municipal government is vested in
                    a mayor (unpaid), ten aidermen, and thirty councillors, who also constitute the
                    Urban Sanitary Authority. To them belong the gas-works <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n121/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0121-0110"/> and water-works, and by them a system of
                    sewerage was carried out in 1854 at a cost of about £30,000. The city has a
                    recorder and separate court of quarter sessions.</p>
                <p>The market is held on Saturdays and Wednesdays, the former being the principal
                    market. The grain is sold in the open street in bulk. Population in 1871,
                    31,074.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
