<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0594-0583-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHEQUE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 583</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37m31m">Payment</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xn18">Checks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4696zz2x">Bankers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1055703">Payment</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:852695">Checks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:884187">Crosses</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:826798">Bankers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:919522">Face</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n594/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHEQUE</label>. “A check on a banker,” says Mr Justice Byles,
                    “is in legal effect an inland bill of exchange drawn on a banker payable to
                    bearer on demand. A check is consequently subject in general to the rules which
                    regulate the rights and liabilities of parties to bills of exchange.” Commercial
                    usage has, however, imposed on cheques certain qualities which do not attach to
                    other bills of exchange.</p>
                <p>Before 1858 cheques were not subject to the stamp duties imposed on bills in
                    general, if they complied with the following conditions, viz,, to have been
                    drawn on a banker, to have specified truly the place of drawing (which must have
                    been within 75 miles from the banker’s place of business), to have been payable
                    to bearer on demand, not to have been post-dated, and not to have declared
                    payment to be made in bills or notes. Severe penalties were imposed on persons
                    making or. receiving unstamped cheques not falling under this exemption. In 1858
                    a stamp duty of a penny was imposed on all cheques, and the restrictions as to
                    place of drawing, post-dating, &amp;c., abolished. Another restriction making
                    cheques good for sums under twenty shillings is also abolished.</p>
                <p>Although a drawee of a bill is not usually liable thereon until acceptance, a
                    banker having effects belonging to his customer is bound to pay his customer’s
                    cheques within a reasonable time. There is what is called an implied contract
                    that the banker should do so, and if it is broken the customer may recover
                    damages. The rule as to presentment of bills within a reasonable time <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e,,</hi> in general the day after issue) applies to cheques,
                    but a drawer is not relieved by the holder’s negligence in presenting unless he
                    has been injured thereby, as for example by the failure of the banker in the
                    interval. The habit of crossing cheques with the name of some banker is believed
                    to have been originally intended as a direction to drawees to pay only to the
                    bankers so named, but it was held at law that such crossing amounted only to a
                    direction to pay to <hi rend="italic">some</hi> banker. The words “and Co.,” the
                    name of the particular banker being left out, have the same effect. Payment of a
                    crossed cheque otherwise than through a banker was at common law evidence of
                    negligence on the part of the drawee, rendering him responsible to the drawer.
                    The Act 19 and 20 Vict. c. 25 enacted that a cheque bearing across its face an
                    addition of the name of any banker or of the words “and Company” should be
                    payable only through some banker. Payment made otherwise than through a banker
                    hitherto indirectly and practically invalid was thus made directly and as a
                    matter of law invalid. In the construction of this statute it was held by the
                    Court of Common Pleas, in the case of Simmons <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Taylor
                    (27 <hi rend="italic">Law Journal,</hi> 45), that the crossing was no part of
                    the cheque and that its fraudulent obliteration was no forgery of the cheque,
                    and that the payment, without negligence, of a cheque with the crossing so
                    obliterated was good as against the drawer. This decision led to the Act 21 and
                    22 Vict. c. 69, which made the crossing a part of the cheque and its fraudulent
                    obliteration a felony. A holder may cross an uncrossed cheque, or prefix any
                    banker’s name to the words “and Co.,” but if a particular banker is once named
                    the cheque is henceforth payable through him alone. When a crossing has been
                    obliterated a wrong payment of the cheque in consequence, if without fraud or
                    negligence on the part of the banker, shall not be questioned. In a recent case
                    (Smith <hi rend="italic">V.</hi> Union Bank of London) the effect of these
                    enactments was explained by the Court of Appeal in a manner which startled the
                    commercial community. In that case the plaintiff had crossed a cheque received
                    by him from a customer with the name of his own bankers. The check was stolen,
                    and finally passed for full value to C who paid it into his bankers, and they in
                    turn received payment of it from the defendants. The court held that the
                    negotiability of the cheque was not affected by statute, that C had become the
                    lawful holder, and that the plaintiff had no action against the defendants. The
                    consequence of this decision was the Act 39 and 40 Vict. c. 81, which provided
                    that when a cheque bears across its face an addition of the words “and Company,”
                    or any abbreviation thereof, between two parallel transverse lines, or of two
                    parallel transverse lines simply, and either with or without the words “not
                    negotiable,” that addition shall be deemed a crossing, and the cheque shall be
                    deemed to be crossed generally. "When a cheque bears across its face an addition
                    of the name of a banker, either with or without the words “not negotiable,” that
                    addition shall be deemed a crossing, and the cheque shall be deemed to be
                    crossed specially, and to be crossed to that banker. When a cheque is uncrossed,
                    the lawful holder may cross it generally or specially; when it is crossed
                    generally, he may cross it specially, and whether crossed generally or specially
                    he may add the words “not negotiable.” When a cheque is crossed specially, the
                    banker to whom it is specially crossed may again cross it <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n595/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0595-0584"/> specially to another banker as his agent for
                    collection. If a cheque is crossed generally, the banker on whom it is drawn
                    shall not pay it otherwise than to a banker; if crossed specially, not otherwise
                    than to the banker specially named in the crossing or his agent for collection.
                    When a cheque is crossed specially to more than one banker (except when crossed
                    to an agent for collection) the banker on whom it is drawn shall refuse payment
                    thereof. When a crossed cheque has been paid, either to the special banker in
                    case of a special crossing, or to some banker in case of a general crossing, the
                    banker and (if the cheque has come to the hands of the payee) the drawer shall
                    be in the same position as if the cheque had been paid to and recovered by the
                    true owner thereof. A banker paying crossed cheques otherwise than as authorized
                    by this Act shall be liable to the true owner for any loss he may sustain. When
                    a cheque is presented for payment which does not appear at the time to be
                    crossed, or to have had a crossing which has been obliterated, or to have been
                    altered otherwise than as authorized by the Act, a banker paying the same in
                    good faith and without negligence shall not be liable by reason of the cheque
                    having been crossed, obliterated, or altered, or by reason of payment having
                    been made otherwise than to some banker, or to the banker named in the special
                    crossing. If the crossed cheque bears the words “not negotiable," the person
                    taking it takes and can give no better title to it than the person had from whom
                    he took it.</p>
                <p>A cheque is payment unless dishonoured; but on the question whether a debt has
                    been paid, it is not sufficient to produce a cheque drawn by the debtor in
                    favour of the creditor, and paid by the banker, unless it can be shown to have
                    passed through the creditor’s hands. Where a check has been fraudulently
                    altered, and a banker pays a larger sum than that originally written, he must
                    bear the loss, and cannot charge his customer unless some act of his facilitated
                    the forgery. Where a cheque was filled up in such a way as to make deception
                    easy, the customer was held responsible for the loss.</p>
                <p>A new description of draft on a banker is introduced by the Act 16 and 17 Vict.
                    c. 59, § 19.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
