<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0624-0613-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHICHESTER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 613</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100852">Royalists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n624/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHICHESTER</label>, a municipal and parliamentary borough,
                    episcopal city, and market-town of England, in Sussex, situated at the foot of a
                    small spur of the South Down Hills, on the widest part of the plain to which it
                    gives name. It is distant about 60 miles S.W. from London, and 14 N.E. from
                    Portsmouth. Chichester still retains its ancient walls, which have a circuit of
                    about a mile and a half, and probably follow the line of the Roman
                    fortifications. The town is well-built, and consists of four principal streets,
                    which meet at right angles at a central octagonal cross, fifty feet high,
                    erected by Bishop Story, and reputed to be one of the finest structures of the
                    kind in Great Britain. Of the public buildings the most remarkable are the
                    cathedral, which is 407 feet in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0625-0614"/> length and 150 in breadth, and is note-worthy as
                    having double side-aisles, the church of St Paul—a modern Gothic edifice, the
                    guild-hall, the corn-exchange, the market-house, the infirmary, and the museum
                    of the Chichester Literary Society and Mechanics’ Institute. There is also a
                    large cattle-market at the east of the city capable of accommodating several
                    thousand head of cattle. It is one of the principal cattle-markets in the south
                    of England, and was erected in 1871 by the corporation of the city at a cost of
                    £15,000. In the cathedral are a number of ancient and curious monuments, besides
                    nine by Flaxman, one of which is in memory of the poet Collins, who was a native
                    of the city, and is buried in the church of St Andrew’s. The diocese of
                    Chichester includes the whole county of Sussex except a few parishes which are
                    peculiars, and comprises nearly 300 benefices. The palace of the bishop is in
                    the city of Chichester.</p>
                <p>There is a grammar-school, founded by Bishop Story in 1497, and the bluecoat
                    school boards and educates about 30 boys. Chichester communicates with the sea
                    by means of a short canal. The borough, which returns one member to parliament,
                    had a population of 9054 in 1871.</p>
                <p>Chichester, as already mentioned, is undoubtedly built on an ancient Roman site,
                    near a line of road now known as the Stane Street; and it is usually, though
                    hardly with absolute certainty, identified with <hi rend="italic">Regnum,,</hi>
                    a town of the Belgae mentioned in the Itinerary of Antonine. A slab of grey
                    Sussex marble, now preserved at Good wood, was discovered in 1713 on the site of
                    the present council chamber, bearing an inscription which has given rise to an
                    ingenious hypothesis, which represents Chichester as the seat of the native king
                    Cogidubnus, mentioned by Tacitus as possessing independent authority, and this
                    king as the father of the Claudia to whom reference is made in the Second
                    Epistle to Timothy. The inscription proves at least that the town was the abode
                    of a considerable body of craftsmen, and that they erected a temple to Neptune
                    and Minerva under the patronage of a certain Pudens. With the conjectural
                    restoration of a few letters it reads as follows :—“A <hi rend="superscript">
                    r</hi> eptuni et Minervae templum ^ro salute dowιws divinae <hi rend="italic"
                    >ex</hi> auctoritate <hi rend="italic">Tib.</hi> Claud. Cogidubni r. leg. aug.
                    in Brit. (7oZZegium fabror. et qui in eo <hi rend="italic">a sacris</hi> sunt d.
                    s. d. donante aream 7Wente Pudentini fil.” In the early Saxon period the town
                    seems to have been destroyed by Aella, and soon afterwards restored by Cissa,
                    whose memory is preserved in the modern name, equivalent to Cissa’s Caster, or
                    Castrum. In 967 it was chosen by King Edgar as the seat of a mint, and specimens
                    of the pennies are still extant. At the time of the Conquest it had only 283
                    houses and a church; but in 1083 the bishopric was removed thither from Selsey,
                    and a cathedral was consecrated in 1108. This building having been destroyed by
                    fire, a new one was erected in the end of the 12th century by Bishops Ralph and
                    Seffrid, and this may be regarded as the basis of the present edifice. In 1213
                    the city was formally incorporated. During the civil war it was captured from
                    the Royalists by Sir William Waller, whose soldiers did great damage to the
                    cathedral. In spite of all attempts to preserve it, the tower and spire came to
                    the ground in 1861; but a restoration has since been effected under the
                    direction of Sir G. Gilbert Scott. Besides the poet Collins, Chichester numbers
                    among its worthies Bishop Juxon, Hayley the friend of Cowper, and three artists
                    of the 18th century, generally known as the</p>
                <p>Three Smiths of Chichester.” See Lower’s <hi rend="italic">Sussex,</hi> s,v.; <hi
                    rend="italic">Quarterly Review,</hi> vol. xcvii.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
