<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0048-0039-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANUTE, or Cnut (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    39)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96092x">Armaments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717w2f">Proof</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610w100">Rulers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938958">Armaments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150446">Thrones</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANUTE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cnut</hi></label> (about
                    995-1035), was the son of Sweyn or Swend, king of Denmark and England. Though
                    only nineteen years of age at his father’s death, he was elected by the Danish
                    armament to the English throne (1014). But the English, only recently subdued by
                    Sweyn, did not acquiesce in this disposal of the crown, recalled their old king
                    Ethelred from Normandy, and obliged Canute to withdraw from the country. In the
                    summer of 1015 Canute returned at the head of a vast Danish armament, and had
                    compelled the submission of most of England when Ethelred died, and his son
                    Edmund Ironside became the representative of the old English royal line. In the
                    double election which ensued, Edmund was supported almost solely by London; the
                    Witan of the rest of England decided upon Canute, who had proved himself too
                    formidable a candidate to be set aside. Nevertheless, in five pitched battles
                    fought during the year 1016, Canute found in Edmund more than an equal rival,— a
                    rival, too, that grew more dangerous, as he was recognized to be the champion of
                    the pure English nationality. At length, in the sixth battle, at Assandun in the
                    same year, the English army, weakened and disconcerted by the desertion of
                    Edric, the traitorous earl of Mercia, was completely overthrown. A division of
                    the kingdom was arranged between the two competitors, but Edmund dying soon
                    after, not without suspicion of treachery, even on Canute’s part, the latter
                    became sole ruler of England.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0049-0040"/>
                <p>His first care on attaining to undivided power was to remove all who might
                    disturb its tranquillity. The sons of Edmund Ironside were sent out of the
                    kingdom, and Edwy his brother was put to death; while Edric of Mercia soon met
                    the fate he deserved, and many other leading men were banished or slain. The
                    sternness of Canute’s early measures was, however, more the effect of policy
                    than of a cruel disposition, for in a little time he showed himself a just and
                    beneficent ruler. After exacting a dan egeld for the payment of his Danish host,
                    he sent it home, with the exception of forty ships and of the household troops
                    that attended on himself. Henceforward he put off the character of conqueror,
                    and governed England like a native Englishman, enforcing the old English laws or
                    enacting wise new ones, repressing disorder, and in every way attending to the
                    interests of his subjects. He was careful of the interests of the church, though
                    it had always been one of the great centres of resistance to Danish invasions,
                    and was not afraid to raise Englishmen, such as Earl Godwin, to the highest
                    posts in his government. A letter written to his English subjects from Rome, to
                    which he had made a pilgrimage, is the best commentary on the motives which
                    directed his reign; he is determined to make amends for the faults of his early
                    years, to persevere in a just and pious government, to repress extortion, and in
                    every way to promote the welfare of his subjects. The internal state of the
                    kingdom was one of unprecedented peace and order, during which it recovered from
                    the ravages and misgovernment of the generation preceding; and he left a happy
                    memory of himself among the people. The well-known story of the rebuke he gave
                    to his flattering courtiers, which rests on excellent authority, is a proof of
                    this; and the well-known song be composed, when rowing near the monastery of
                    Ely, is not only an example of his genial popular sympathies, but entitles him
                    to a place among the creators of English poetry.</p>
                <p>He was far more than king of England, however; he was the ruler of a vast
                    northern empire, composed of five or six monarchies though the old historians
                    differ in the enumeration of them. He succeeded to the usual overlordship over
                    Wales and Scotland, asserting it in the latter case by force of arms. Shortly
                    after his secure installation on the English throne, he superseded his brother
                    Harold on that of Denmark; he repelled an attack of the Wends on his dominions
                    there, and in those early times obtained a rectification of the Danish frontier
                    from the emperor of Germany. Though at first unsuccessful in an invasion of
                    Norway, be added that kingdom to his empire in 1028. He was now one of the most
                    powerful and respected rulers of Christendom. He died at Shaftesbury in 1035, in
                    the fortieth year of his age, and the twentieth of his reign. The best proof of
                    his energy and ability is that the heterogeneous and geographically disconnected
                    empire, which he governed so well, fell to pieces immediately after his death.
                    (Freeman’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Norman Conquest,</hi> vol. i.;
                    Palgrave’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Anglo-Saxons</hi>; Green’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Short History of the English People.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
