<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0151-0140-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARTAGENA, or Carthagena</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 140</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047551">Ores</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865087">Coal</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n151/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARTAGENA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthagena</hi></label>, a
                    fortified seaport of Spain on the Mediterranean Sea, in the province of Murcia,
                    and 29 miles S. by E. of the town of that name, in 37° 36' N. lat. and l <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> W. long. The town stands on a hill separated by a
                    little plain from the harbour; towards the N. and E. it communicates with a
                    fertile valley; on the 8. and W. it is hemmed in by high mountains. The harbour,
                    the finest on the eastern coast of Spain, is fringed by four hills; and the
                    island called La Escombrera, the ancient <hi rend="italic">Scombraria,</hi> 2£
                    miles from the narrow entrance, shelters it from the violence of wind and waves.
                    The harbour is heart-shaped and deep, except near its centre, where there is a
                    ledge of rocks only 5 feet under water. On the eastern side is a breakwater 842
                    yards in length. A tramway leads from the port to the centre of the mining
                    district, a distance of about two leagues. The streets of the town are spacious,
                    but not imposing; and the friability of the stone gives the houses a dilapidated
                    look. The barracks, arsenal, wet and dry docks, marine school, parade,
                    rope-walks, and the fortifications, are all in a neglected condition. The mines
                    near the town are very productive, and thousands of men and beasts are employed
                    in transporting ores of lead, iron, copper, zinc, and sulphur to the coast. In
                    1871 there were 150 blast-furnaces and 76 smelting furnaces at work. The profits
                    vary according to the prices of English coal and coke. Among other mineral
                    products of Cartagena may be mentioned gypsum, saltpetre, amethysts, and rubies.
                    Barley and wheat are grown in fair quantity, and there are some extensive
                    vineyards and olive yards. Esparto grass <hi rend="italic">(Stipa
                    tenacissima),</hi> a species of rush, now much used in paper manufacture, is
                    largely grown in the neighbourhood. It is the <hi rend="italic">spartum,</hi> or
                    Spanish broom, of the ancient Romans,—whence their name for Cartagena, <hi
                    rend="italic">Carthago</hi><hi rend="italic">Spartaria.</hi> It is still used
                    locally for making shoes, ship’s cables, mats, and a kind of spun cloth.
                    Barilla, earthenware, glass, and silk are also among the manufactures of
                    Cartagena. The former prevalence of fever, the abandonment of the arsenal, and
                    the prosperity of the neighbouring port of Alicante have much affected the trade
                    of the town during this century; the rail-road communication which now exists
                    with Murcia promises, however, to bring about a revival of its commerce. The
                    imports are chiefly coal and coke from Wales and the north of England. The
                    principal exports are esparto grass and metallic ores; 195,000 tons of the
                    latter were shipped in 1872, almost wholly to Great Britain. The British vessels
                    cleared in 1872 were 244, tonnage 113,015. Of foreign vessels 413 were cleared,
                    tonnage 184,933. The sanitary condition of the town is now greatly improved, as
                    the Almajar Marsh, which formerly caused much intermittent fever, has been
                    drained. The drinking-water of Cartagena is not good; house-rent and food, with
                    the exception of*bread-stuffs, are dear; and there are many paupers and
                    mendicants, to whom no public relief is afforded. The population in 1872 was
                    estimated at 26,000, exclusive of the miners and the labourers in the works of
                    the port.</p>
                <p>Cartagena was founded about the year 243 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> by
                    Hasdrubal,and was called <hi rend="italic">Carthage Nova</hi> or New Carthage,
                    to distinguish it from the African city of Carthage. It was conveniently
                    situated opposite to the Carthaginian territory in Africa, and was early noted
                    for its harbour, the best on the neighbouring coast of Spain. I ts silver and
                    gold mines were the source of great wealth both to the Carthaginians and to the
                    Romans. In 210 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> this important place, the
                    headquarters and treasure city of the Punic army, was stormed and taken with
                    great slaughter by P. Scipio. The city continued to flourish under the Romans,
                    who made it a colony, with the name <hi rend="italic">Colonia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Victrix</hi><hi rend="italic">Julia Nova Carthago.</hi> In 425 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> it was pillaged and nearly destroyed by the Goths.
                    The modern Cartagena was a bishopric till the year 1219, when the see was
                    removed to Murcia. It was rebuilt by Philip II. of Spain, for the sake of its
                    harbour. In 1706, in the war of the Spanish Succession, it was occupied by Sir
                    John Leake; and in the next year it was retaken by the duke of Berwick. On the
                    5th November 1823 the town capitulated to the French. In consequence of the
                    insurrection in Spain, Cartagena was in 1844 again the scene of warfare. On the
                    23d August 1873 it was bombarded by the Spanish fleet under Admiral Lobos; on
                    the 11th October a battle took place off the town, between the ships of the
                    Government and the Intransigentes, and on the 12th January 1874 Cartagena was
                    occupied by the Government troops.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
