<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0143-0132-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARPINI, Joannes de Plano (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    132)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc86">Bullets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208752">Mongolia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n143/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARPINI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joannes de Plano</hi></label>,
                    author of a remarkable mediaeval work on Northern Asia. He appears to have been
                    a native of Umbria, where a place formerly called Pian del Carpine, but now
                    Piano della Magione, stands near Perugia, on the road to Cortona. He was one of
                    the companions and disciples of his countryman St Francis of Assisi, and from
                    sundry indications can hardly have been younger than the latter, born in 1182.
                    John bore a high repute in the order, and took a foremost part in the
                    propagation of its teaching in Northern Europe, holding successively the offices
                    of warden <hi rend="italic">(custos)</hi> in Saxony, and of provincial <hi
                        rend="italic">(minister)</hi> of Germany, and afterwards of Spain, perhaps
                    of Barbary, and of Cologne. He was in the last post at the time of the great
                    Mongol invasion of Eastern Europe and of the disastrous battle of Liegnitz
                    (April 12, 1241), which threatened to cast European Christendom beneath the feet
                    of barbarous hordes. The dread of the Tartars was, however, still on men’s mind
                    four years later, when Pope Innocent IV. determined (1245) on sending a mission
                    to the Tartar and other Asiatic princes, the real object of which apparently was
                    to gain trustworthy information regarding the hordes and their purposes.</p>
                <p>At the head of this mission the Pope placed Friar John, at this time certainly
                    not far from 65 years of age, and to his discretion nearly everything in the
                    accomplishment of the mission seems to have been left. The legate started from
                    Lyons, where the Pope then resided, on Easter Day (16th April 1245), accompanied
                    by another friar, who speedily broke down and was left behind. After seeking the
                    counsel of an old friend, Wenceslaus, king of Bohemia, he was joined at Breslau
                    by another minorité, F. Bennet the Pole, appointed to act as interpreter. The
                    onward journey lay by Kiev; the Tartar posts were entered at Kaniev, and thence
                    the route ran across the Dnieper <hi rend="italic">(Neper)</hi> and the Don to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Ethil</hi> or Volga, on which stood the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ordu</hi> or camp of Batu, at this time the senior of the Chinghizid
                    family. Here the envoys with their presents had to pass between two fires before
                    being presented to the prince. Batu ordered them to proceed onward to the court
                    of the supreme Kaan in Mongolia, and on Easter Day once more (April 8, 1246)
                    they started on the second and most formidable part of their journey—“so ill,”
                    writes the legate, “that we could scarcely sit a horse; and throughout all that
                    Lent our food had been nought but millet with salt and water, and with only snow
                    melted in a kettle for drink.” Their bodies were tightly bandaged to enable them
                    to endure the excessive fatigue of this enormous ride, which led them across the
                        <hi rend="italic">Jaic</hi> (now called River Ural), and then north of the
                    Caspian and the Aral to the Jaxartes <hi rend="italic">(quidam fluvius magnus
                        cujus nomen ignoramus),</hi> and the Mahometan cities which then stood on
                    its banks; then along the shores of the Dzungarian lakes and so forward, till,
                    on the Feast of St Mary Magdalene (2 2d July), at last they reached the imperial
                    camp called <hi rend="italic">Sira Ordu</hi> (Yellow Pavilion), near the Orkhon
                    River,—this stout-hearted old man having thus ridden something like 3000 miles
                    in 106 days.</p>
                <p>Since the death of Okkodai the imperial authority had been in <hi rend="italic"
                        >interregnum.</hi> Kuyuk, his eldest son, had now been designated to the
                    throne; his formal election in a great <hi rend="italic">Kwmltai,</hi> or diet
                    of the tribes, took place while the friars were at Sira Ordu, numbered among
                    3000 to 4000 envoys and deputies from all parts of Asia and Eastern Europe,
                    bearing homage, tribute, and presents. They afterwards, on the 24th of August,
                    witnessed the formal enthronement at another camp in the vicinity called the
                    Golden Ordu, after which they were presented to the emperor.</p>
                <p>It was not till November that they got their dismissal, bearing a letter to the
                    Pope in Mongol, Arabic, and Latin, which was little else than a brief imperious
                    assertion of the Kaan’s office as the scourge of God. Then commenced their long
                    winter journey homeward; often they had to lie on the bare snow, or on the
                    ground scraped bare of snow with the traveller’s foot. They reached Kiev on the
                    9th of June 1247. There, and on their further journey, the Slavonic Christians
                    welcomed them as risen from the dead, with festive hospitality. Crossing the
                    Rhine at Cologne, they found the Pope still at Lyons, and there delivered their
                    report and the Kaan’s letter.</p>
                <p>Not long afterwards Friar John was rewarded with the archbishopric of Antivari in
                    Dalmatia, arid was sent as legate to St Louis. We do not know the year of his
                    death, but it would seem that his <hi rend="italic">successor</hi> in the see
                    died before April 1253; hence it is probable that John did not long survive the
                    hardships of his journey.</p>
                <p>He recorded the information that he had collected in a work, called in one MS.
                        <hi rend="italic">Liber Tartarorum,</hi> in another <hi rend="italic"
                        >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Monga-lorιιm</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >quos</hi><hi rend="italic">nos</hi><hi rend="italic">Tartaros
                        appellamus.</hi> The work is divided into eight ample chapters on the
                    country, climate, manners, religion, character, history, policy, and tactics of
                    the Tartars, and on the best way of opposing them, followed by a single chapter
                    on the regions passed through. The book thus answers to its title. Like some
                    other famous mediaeval itineraries it shows an entire absence of a traveller’s
                    or author’s egotism, and contains, even in the last chapter, scarcely any
                    personal narrative. John of Pian del Carpine was not only an old man when he
                    went cheerfully upon this mission, but was, as we know from accidental evidence
                    in the annals of his order, a fat and heavy man <hi rend="italic">(vir
                        gravis</hi><hi rend="italic">et corpulentus),</hi> insomuch that during his
                    preachings in Germany he was fain,contrary to Franciscan precedent, to ride a
                    donkey. Yet not a word approaching more nearly to complaint than those which we
                    have quoted above appears in his narrative. His book, both in its defect of
                    personal detail and in literary quality, is inferior to that written a few years
                    later by a younger brother of the order, and envoy to the Mongol, William de
                    Rubruck. But it is an excellent work, and in orrr own day an educated Mongol,
                    Galsang Gçmboyev, has borne detailed and interesting testimony to the great
                    accuracy of its statements (see <hi rend="italic">Mélanges</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Asiat,</hi><hi rend="italic">tirés du</hi><hi rend="italic">Bullet. Hist.
                        Philol. de ΓΛcad. Imp. de St Petersbourg,</hi> ii. p. 650, 1856). .</p>
                <p>The book must have been prepared immediately after the return of the traveller,
                    for the Friar Salimbene, who met him in France in the very year of his return
                    (1247), gives us these interesting particulars :—“He was a clever and
                    conversable man, well lettered, a great discourser, and full of a diversity of
                    experience. . . . He wrote a big book about the Tattars <hi rend="italic"
                        >(sic),</hi> and about other marvels that he had seen, and whenever he felt
                    weary of telling about the Tattars, he would cause that book of his to be read,
                    as I have often heard and seen” <hi rend="italic">(Chron. Fr. Salimbeni</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Parmensis</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Monum. Histor. ad
                        Prov.</hi><hi rend="italic">et Placent,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >pertinentia,</hi> Parma, 1857). .</p>
                <p>For a long time the work was but partially known, and that chiefly through an
                    abridgment in the vast compilation of Vincent of Beauvais <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Speculum</hi><hi rend="italic">Historiale)</hi> made in the generation
                    following the traveller’s own, and printed first in 1473. Hakluyt (1598) and
                    Bergeron (1634) published portions of the original work; but the complete and
                    genuine text was not printed till 1839, when it was put forth by the late Μ.
                    D’Avezac in the 4th volume of the <hi rend="italic">Recueil</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Voyages</hi><hi rend="italic">et de Mémoires</hi> of the
                    Geog. Society of Paris, a work of that great geographer which forms such a model
                    of editorial taste, learning, and sagacity, as will hardly be surpassed or
                    equalled.</p>
                <p>John"s companion, Benedictus Polonus, also left a brief narrative taken down from
                    his oral relation. This was first published by Μ. D’Avezac in the work just
                    named. (H. Y.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
