<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0400-0389-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHANCERY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 389</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:830288">Benches</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:994346">Lawyers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s296">Coke</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n400/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHANCERY</label>, the court of the Lord Chancellor, now
                    consolidated along with the other superior courts in the Supreme Court of
                    Judicature by the Act of 1873. Its origin has been briefly noticed under the
                    head of <hi rend="smallcaps">Chancellor.</hi></p>
                <p>It has been customary to say that the Court of Chancery consists of two distinct
                    tribunals—one a court of common law, the other a court of equity. From the
                    former have issued all the original writs passing under the great seal, all
                    commissions of sewers, lunacy, and the like—some of these writs being originally
                    kept in a <hi rend="italic">hanaper</hi> or hamper (whence the “hanaper
                    office”), and others in a little sack or bag (whence the “petty-bag office ”).
                    The court had likewise power to hold pleas upon <hi rend="italic">scire
                    facias</hi> for repeal of letters patent, &amp;c. “So little,” says Blackstone,
                    “is commonly done on the common law side of the court that I have met with no
                    traces of any writ of error being actually brought since the fourteenth year of
                    Queen Elizabeth.”</p>
                <p>The equitable jurisdiction of the Court of Chancery was founded on the supposed
                    superiority of conscience and equity over the strict law. The appearance of
                    equity in England is in harmony with the general course of legal history in
                    progressive societies. What is remarkable is that, instead of being incorporated
                    with or superseding the common law, it gave rise to a wholly independent set of
                    tribunals. The English dislike of the civil law, and the tendency to follow
                    precedent which has never ceased to characterize English lawyers, account for
                    this unfortunate separation. The claims of equity in its earlier stages are well
                    expressed in the little treatise called <hi rend="italic">Doctor and
                    Student,</hi> published in the reign of Henry VIIL :—“Conscience never resisteth
                    the law nor addeth to it, but only when the law is directly in itself against
                    the <hi rend="italic">law of God,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">law of reason?</hi>
                    So also King James, speaking in the Star Chamber, says, “Where the rigour of the
                    law in many cases will undo a subject, then the chancery tempers the law with
                    equity, and so mixes mercy with justice, as it preserves a man from
                    destruction.” This theory of the essential opposition between law and equity,
                    and of the natural superiority of the latter, remained long after equity had
                    ceased to found itself on natural justice, and had become as fixed and rigid as
                    the common law itself. The jealousy of the common lawyers came to a head in the
                    time of Lord Ellesmere, when Coke disputed the right of the Chancery to give
                    relief against a judgment of the Court of Queen’s Bench obtained by gross fraud
                    and imposition. J ames I., after consultation, decided in favour of the Court of
                    Equity. The substitution of lay for clerical chancellors is regarded by Mr
                    Spence <hi rend="italic">(Equitable Jurisdiction of the Court of Chancery)</hi>
                    as having at first been unfortunate, inasmuch as the laymen were ignorant of the
                    principles on which their predeeessors had acted. Lord Nottingham is usually
                    credited with the first attempt to reduce the decisions of the court to order,
                    and his work was continued by Lord Hardwicke. By the time of Lord Eldon, equity
                    had become fixed, and the judges, like their brethren in the common law courts,
                    strictly followed the precedents. Henceforward chancery and common law courts
                    have exhibited the anomaly of two co-ordinate sets of tribunals, empowered to
                    deal with the same matters, and compelled to proceed in many eases on wholly
                    different principles. The Court of Chancery could in most cases prevent a person
                    from taking advantage of a common law right, not approved of by its own system.
                    But if a suitor chose to go to a court of common law, he might claim such unjust
                    rights, and it required the special intervention of the Court of Equity to
                    prevent his enforcing them. In many cases also a special application had to be
                    made to chancery for facilities which were absolutely necessary to the
                    successful conduct of a case at common law. Another <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0401-0390"/> source of difficulty and annoyance was the
                    uncertainty in many cases whether the chancery or common law courts were the
                    proper tribunal, so that a suitor often found at the close of an expensive and
                    protracted suit that he had mistaken his court and must go elsewhere for relief.
                    Attempts more or less successful were made to lessen those evils by giving the
                    powers to both sets of courts; but down to the consolidation effected by the
                    Judicature Act, our judicial system justified the sarcasm of Lord Westbury, that
                    we set up one tribunal to do injustice and another to stop it. In one of the
                    last cases, the custody of an infant, which had been granted by the Queen’s
                    Bench to one claimant, was transferred by the Court of Chancery to another. The
                    payment of a sum of money into court for the benefit of the child made her a
                    ward of court, and enabled the judge in chancery to apply the principles of
                    equity to the case.</p>
                <p>The equitable jurisdiction of chancery was commonly divided into <hi
                    rend="italic">exclusive, concurrent,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">auxiliary.</hi>
                    Chancery had exclusive jurisdiction when there were no forms of action by which
                    relief could be obtained at law, in respect of rights, which ought to be
                    enforced. Trusts are the most conspicuous example of this class, and are, in
                    fact, the main staple of the business of the court. It also includes the rights
                    of married women, infants, and lunatics. Chancery had concurrent jurisdiction
                    when the common law did not give <hi rend="italic">adequate</hi> relief, <hi
                    rend="italic">eg.,</hi> in cases of fraud, accident, mistake, specific
                    performance of contracts, &lt;fcc. It had auxiliary jurisdiction when the
                    administrative machinery of the law courts was unable to procure the necessary
                    evidence.</p>
                <p>The Judicature Act, 1873, enacts (§24) that in every civil cause or matter
                    commenced in the High Court of Justice, law and equity shall be administered by
                    the High Court of Justice and the Court of Appeal respectively, according to the
                    rules therein contained, which provide for giving effect in all cases to
                    “equitable rights and other matters of equity.” The 25th section declares the
                    law hereafter to be administered in England on certain points, and ordains that
                    “generally in all matters not hereinbefore particularly mentioned in which there
                    is any conflict or variance between the rules of equity and the rules of the
                    common law with reference to the same matter, the rules of equity shall
                    prevail.”</p>
                <p>. Previous to being merged in the New Supreme Court of Judicature, the Court of
                    Chancery consisted of the Lord Chancellor, the Master of the Rolls, two Lords
                    Justices of Appeal, and three Vice-Chancellors. The Vice-Chancellors and Lords
                    Justices of Appeal are comparatively recent creations.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the fusion of the courts the great division between common law
                    courts and chancery is not obliterated. The chancery judges form a division by
                    themselves, to which all the pending business of the old court has been
                    transferred, and to which all causes and matters which, but for the Act, would
                    have been within the exclusive jurisdiction of that court are assigned. The
                    Chancery Division still is, and probably will for a long time be, distinguished
                    from the others by the peculiar nature of its business, by the peculiar nature
                    of its administrative arrangements, and by having a separate bar. Another
                    distinction is making itself apparent, and will assume great importance if
                    finally established. The Chancery Division seems to be unwilling to try cases by
                    jury; and in a recent case there has been a direct collision of opinion on this
                    subject between the Chancery and the Common Law Judges.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
