<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0795-0782-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CINCINNATI (9th edition, volume 5, page 782)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q67d">Costs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204604">Indiana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018703">Methodists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n795/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CINCINNATI</label>, an important city of the United States,
                    situated in the S.W. part of Ohio, on the N. bank of the Ohio River, in 39° 6'
                    N. lat and 84° 26' W. long. It is the capital of Hamilton county, and in size is
                    the first city in the State, while, according to the Federal census of 1870, it
                    is the eighth in the United States. It was first settled in 1788 by persons from
                    New Jersey, and is said to have been named in honour of the Cincinnati Society
                    of officers of the Revolutionary war. It was incorporated as a city in 1814, and
                    soon acquired a commercial importance which has steadily increased. In 1800
                    Cincinnati contained but 750 inhabitants. The population amounted to 9602 in
                    1820, 46,338 in 1840, 115,436 in 1850, 161,044 in 1860, and 216,239 in 1870. Of
                    the total population in 1870, 79,612 were foreigners, including 49,448 born in
                    Germany, 18,624 in Ireland, 3526 in England, and 2093 in France. The city is
                    chiefly built upon two terraces or plateaus, the first 60 and the second 112
                    feet above the river. Beyond these rises an amphitheatre of hills from 400 to
                    450 feet high, from which may be obtained a magnificent view of the valley of
                    the Ohio and the surrounding country. On the opposite bank of the river, in the
                    State of Kentucky, are Covington, which had 24,505 inhabitants in 1870, and
                    Newport, which had 15,087. Communication between these cities and Cincinnati is
                    afforded by two bridges and three steam ferries. The wire suspension bridge,
                    which is 1057 feet long between the towers (or, including the approaches, 2252
                    feet), with a height of 100 feet above low water, was completed in 1867 at a
                    cost of nearly $2,000,000. It has a double waggon road, and two ways for
                    pedestrians. Further up the river is a wrought iron railroad bridge built upon
                    piers; besides a railway track, it has waggon and foot ways. Cincinnati covers
                    an area of 24 square miles, extending along the river about 10 miles, with an
                    average width of 3 miles. The most important part of the city, however, is
                    comprised within a distance of 2½ miles along the river. The corporate limits
                    have been much extended in recent years by the annexation of numerous villages,
                    the most important being Columbia, Walnut Hills, Mount Auburn, and Cumminsville.
                    In these, which still retain their former names, are seen the most costly
                    residences and villas, with ornamental grounds embracing from 5 to 80 acres
                    each. The city is also noted for the beauty of its suburbs and its surrounding
                    scenery. The streets, which generally cross one another at right angles, are
                    usually from 1½ to 2½ miles long, and from 50 to 100 feet wide. Many of them are
                    lined with trees. Brick is chiefly used for buildings, with a greyish buff
                    freestone for fronts. Business buildings are usually five and often six stories
                    high. Cincinnati is well supplied with public parks, the largest of which, Eden,
                    is situated on a hill in the eastern part of the city, and contains 216 acres.
                    In Burnet Woods, recently purchased, there are 170 acres, mostly forest, on the
                    hill north of the city. Centrally situated in the city are Washington, Lincoln,
                    Hopkins, and the City parks, which together contain about 25 acres. One of the
                    most attractive objects in the city is the Tyler Davidson bronze fountain which
                    was unveiled in 1871. It was presented to the city by Mr Henry Probasco, a
                    wealthy citizen, who named it after the late Mr Tyler Davidson, the originator
                    of the proposal. Its cost was nearly $200,000. The design embraces fifteen
                    bronze figures, all cast at Munich, the chief one representing a female with
                    outstretched arms, from whose fingers the water falls in fine spray This is the
                    surmounting figure, and reaches a height of 40 feet above the ground. Among the
                    most notable buildings is that of the Federal Government, built of sawed
                    freestone in the Roman Corinthian style, with a porch of six columns; it is
                    three stories high, with a length of 150 feet and a width of 80 feet. The county
                    court-house, in the same style of architecture, is 175 feet square and three
                    stories high, and has a porch with six Corinthian stone columns. The brick
                    buildings for the city offices are 205 feet long and 52 feet wide. The city
                    workhouse, 3½ miles from the heart of the city, is a brick structure, 515 feet
                    long and 55 feet wide, erected at a cost, including 26 acres of land, of
                    $650,000. It <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n796/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0796-0783"/> has room for 700 prisoners. The Cincinnati
                    hospital, comprising eight buildings arranged around a central court and
                    connected by corridors, occupies a square of 4 acres. It cost more than
                    $1,000,000, and will accommodate 700 patients. The Masonic Temple, built in the
                    Byzantine style, 195 feet long and 100 feet wide, is four stories high, and has
                    two towers 140 feet, and a spire 1δ0 feet high. Other noticeable structures are
                    Pike’s Opera House, 170 by 134 feet, and five stories high, the Public Library,
                    St Xavier’s College, the Wesleyan Female College, and the Hughes High School.
                    The most imposing church edifices are St Peter’s Roman Catholic Cathedral, built
                    in pure Grecian style, 200 by 80 feet, with a stone spire rising to a height of
                    224 feet; St Paul’s Church (Methodist), with a spire 200 feet high; the First
                    Presbyterian Church, with an immense tower surmounted by a spire 270 feet high;
                    St John’s Episcopal Church; and two large and attractive Hebrew temples.</p>
                <p>Cincinnati is one of the most important commercial aud manufacturing centres of
                    the West. The six railroads entering the city are used by twelve companies, and
                    besides these two lines terminate at Covington on the opposite side of the
                    river. About 300 passenger and freight trains arrive and leave daily on these
                    roads. For their use are four depots near the river in different parts of the
                    city. Communication with different parts of the city and with the suburbs is
                    afforded by fourteen lines of street railroad, with about 50 miles of track, and
                    by numerous lines of omnibuses and stages. The top of the adjacent hills is
                    reached by an inclined steam passenger-railway. The position of the city on the
                    Ohio River gives it water communication with the extensive river system of the
                    Mississippi valley; while it is connected with Lake Erie by the Miami Canal,
                    whose northern terminus is at Toledo, Ohio. The Miami is connected by a branch
                    with the Wabash and Erie Canal, the largest in the United States (467 miles),
                    which extends from Toledo to Evansville, Indiana, on the Ohio river. The average
                    yearly number of steamers and barges running between Cincinnati and other ports
                    during the ten years ending with August 1875 was 338; the yearly number of
                    arrivals of steamers during this period was 2713, and of departures 2680. The
                    large steamers of the Mississippi river are enabled to reach Cincinnati by means
                    of the canal around the falls of the Ohio at Louisville, Kentucky, which was
                    opened in 1872. About three-fourths of the commerce of the city is by railroad
                    and canal, and the remainder by river transportation. The extent of the entire
                    commerce is indicated by the value of imports, which during the ten years ending
                    in 1875 averaged $314,528,009 a year, and of exports, which averaged
                    $201,236,066.</p>
                <p>Cincinnati is one of those interior ports to which, under the Act of Congress
                    passed in 1870, foreign merchandize may be transported without appraisement and
                    payment of duties at the port of first arrival. The value of such imports to
                    this city during the year ending June 30, 1875, was $566,989. The total value of
                    the products of manufacturing industry has increased from $46,995,062 in 1860 to
                    $127,459,021 in 1870 and $144,207,371 in 1874. The details for the
                    last-mentioned years are as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Industries.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>1870.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>1874.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Hands Employed.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Value of Products.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hands Employed.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Value of Products.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Iron</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10,723</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>$20,804,263</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8,713</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>$17,129,224</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Other metals .··»·················</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,809</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,873,356</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,147</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,871,362</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Wood</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,597</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,699,165</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,977</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13,776,066</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Leather ..m.... <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi>. v <hi
                                    rend="subscript"> l</hi>...∙..wn&gt;rτt</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,647</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,227,324</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,929</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,651,113</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Food</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,334</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>17,945,651</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,957</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24,071,077</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Soap, candles, and oils.·</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,122</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,455,561</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,043</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9,527,343</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cl∩tbing —</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,363</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,626,682</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,198</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13,329,914</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Beer and whisky .....∙.....∙.∙∙.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,301</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16,361,006</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,835</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24,231,273</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>cotton, wool, hemp, &amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,035</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,854,774</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>832</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,562,160</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Drugs, chemicals, &lt;fcc.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>735</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,544,195</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>560</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,937,593</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stone and earth</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,209</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,980,102</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,199</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>¾ 916,401</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Carriages, cars, &amp;c</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,175</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,794,413</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,335</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,941,396</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Paper, &amp;c.·...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>452</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>880,516</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>662</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,687,290</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Bookbinding and blank books</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>424</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>626,870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>635</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>838,800</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Printing and publishing.......</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,588</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,699,280</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,334</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,930,304</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tobacco</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,886</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,837,690</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,260</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,745,688</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fine arts ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>250</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>540,746</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>363</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>694,114</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Miscellaneous</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,177</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,697,427</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,990</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,363,253</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Total....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59,327</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>127,459,021</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60,999</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>144,207,371</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n797/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0797-0784"/>
                <p>Boat building was formerly a prominent industry, but it has recently declined.
                    Prior to 1863 Cincinnati was the chief centre in the United States for the
                    slaughtering of swine and the packing of pork. Since that year this supremacy
                    has been held by Chicago, Cincinnati taking the second rank. There are more than
                    seventy establishments in the latter city employed in this industry. The United
                    Railroads Stock-yards for the reception of live pigs occupy about 60 acres.
                    During the winter season of 1874-75 there were slaughtered 560,164 hogs,
                    weighing in the aggregate 155,864,126 B⅛, and valued at $10,897,584. The
                    production included 44,232 barrels of pork, and 23,400,157 lb of lard. During
                    the year ending August 31, 1875, pork and bacon valued at $12,645,538 were
                    exported from the city; the imports amounted to $2,580,493. The excess of
                    exports of lard over imports was $2,781,091. After this important industry the
                    brewingof lager beer ranks next, the brewers here turning out about 15,000,000
                    gallons annually. Distillation is also carried on to a very considerable extent.
                    The city contains five national banks with a capital of $4,000,000, and
                    seventeen private banks with a capital of $2,740,000. The leading commercial
                    organization is the Chamber of Commerce and Merchants’ Exchange, which has about
                    1200 members and holds daily sessions. The Board of Trade has about 900 members,
                    chiefly manufacturers. There are also a mechanics’ institute, cotton exchange,
                    and pork packers’ association. An industrial exhibition has been held in the
                    autumn of each year since 1871, and has attracted large numbers of visitors to
                    the city. The buildings are centrally situated, and occupy 3½ acres of
                    ground.</p>
                <p>The city is divided into 25 wards, and is governed by a mayor, who is elected by
                    the people for two years, and receives an annual salary of $4000, a board of 25
                    aidermen, and a board of 50 councilmen, who are also elected by the people. It
                    has a paid fire department under the control of five commissioners appointed by
                    the mayor, and a pohce force under the control of the mayor and four
                    commissioners. The efficiency of these departments is promoted by extensive
                    fire-alarm and police telegraphic lines. The city is supplied with water
                    obtained by pumping from the Ohio river by means of three immense reservoirs,
                    two of which, with a capacity of 100,000,000 gallons each, are in Eden Park.
                    Beside the usual municipal and county courts, the United States circuit and
                    district courts for the southern district of Ohio are held in the city.</p>
                <p>Cincinnati has a large number and variety of well-organized charitable
                    institutions. The Cincinnati hospital is supported by taxation, and affords free
                    treatment to all unable to pay for it; the city infirmary, besides supporting
                    pauper inmates, affords relief to outdoor poor; the Good Samaritan and St Mary’s
                    hospitals are private institutions, under the supervision of Roman Catholic
                    sisters; the Jewish hospital is maintained by persons of that faith. The
                    Longview asylum for the insane, built at Carthage, 10 miles from the city, at a
                    cost, including 110 acres of land, of $1,000,000, ranks among the first
                    institutions of the kind in the United States. It belongs to Hamilton county,
                    whose population consists chiefly of the inhabitants of Cincinnati; patients
                    are, however, sent here by the State, which contributes to its support. The
                    average daily number of inmates in 1874 was 582, nearly all of whom were
                    maintained free of charge. Besides the city orphan asylum, which has
                    accommodation for 300 children, and is supported by private charity, and the
                    German Protestant asylum, with a capacity for about 100, two large asylums are
                    maintained by the Roman Catholics and by the coloured people. There are also
                    several institutions for indigent and friendless women. The house of refuge and
                    the city workhouse are maintained by the city for the confinement of persons
                    convicted of minor offences; children are sent to the former, and adults to the
                    latter.</p>
                <p>The public schools are under the control of a superintendent and a board of 50
                    elected members, and comprise 3 high, 5 intermediate, and 30 district schools,
                    including those for coloured pupils. There are also a normal school for females
                    and evening schools. In 1874 there were 529 teachers and 28,949 pupils enrolled,
                    with an average daily attendance of 21,486. German is a prominent study in the
                    public schools, and music and drawing are taught. The Woodword and the Hughes
                    high schools have long been known for their excellence. Besides the above, there
                    are a large number of Roman Catholic parochial schools. The university of
                    Cincinnati, recently founded by means of a bequest made by Charles M <hi
                        rend="superscript"> i</hi> Micken, is designed to afford advanced and
                    technical instruction free of charge. A school of design has been in operation
                    since 1869. Besides the Cincinnati Wesleyan College for females
                    (Methodist-Episcopal), St Xavier College (Roman Catholic), and Mount St Mary’s
                    of the West, the city has 1 law, 6 medical, and 2 theological schools, 4
                    commercial colleges, and 2 schools of music. One of the theological schools is
                    connected with Mount St Mary’s of the West, the other is the widely-known Lane
                    Theological Seminary (Presbyterian), founded in 1829. It occupies a site of 7
                    acres on Walnut Hills, and has 5 professors and a library of 12,000 volumes.
                    Three of the medical schools are classified as regular, one as pharmaceutic, one
                    as homoeopathic, and one as dental. The oldest is the medical college of Ohio,
                    which was opened in 1819, and now has 10 instructors; the Cincinnati college of
                    medicine and surgery was opened in 1821, and has 14 instructors; the Miami
                    medical college, opened in 1852, has 12 instructors; and the Pulte medical
                    college, opened in 1872, has 14. There are 11 public libraries in the city, the
                    largest being the free public library, which has 81,000 bound volumes and 5500
                    pamphlets, and the young men’s mercantile with nearly 40,000 volumes. The public
                    library occupies one of the best library buildings in the country. The most
                    important literary associations are the natural history and the historical and
                    philosophical societies. There are published in the city 70 newspapers and
                    periodicals,—9 appearing daily, 1 twice a-week, 33 weekly, 3 fortnightly, 21
                    monthly, and 3 quarterly. Of these 3 daily, 9 weekly, 1 fortnightly, and 2
                    monthly are published in German. The city contains 160 churches, the largest
                    denominations being the Roman Catholic, which has 32 churches and 12 chapels,
                    the Methodist with 26 churches, the Presbyterian with 22, the Baptist with 14.
                    and the Protestant Episcopal with 11. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e.</hi> s. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">dr.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
