<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0099-0088-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARBONARI, The (9th edition, volume 5, page 88)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mf6z">Carbonari</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:846906">Carbonari</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852320">Charcoal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n99/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARBONARI, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label> (from
                    theltalian <hi rend="italic">carbonaro,</hi> charcoalmaker), were certain secret
                    societies of a liberal and even revolutionary tendency that took an active part
                    in some events of Italian and French history during the first three decades of
                    this century. Secret societies, calling themselves by this or a similar name,
                    had indeed previously existed in various parts of Europe; but it was in Italy,
                    towards the close of the Napoleonic wars, that these first began to assume an
                    historic importance. In 1808 many republicans, discontented alike with the
                    Bourbon and the Bonapartist government in Naples, had retired to the mountain
                    recesses of the Abruzzi and Calabria. At first engaged only in an isolated
                    resistance to the authorities, they began to organize themselves. They took the
                    name of Carbonari, a name suggested by the trade of charcoal-burning extensively
                    pursued in those regions, in which many of them were engaged. From this trade,
                    too, but especially from the Christian religion, and above all from the
                    crucifixion of Christ, they adopted a system of mystic rites and a symbolic
                    phraseology, by which they concealed from the uninitiated, but all the more
                    vividly expressed to the initiated, the real political aims of the society,
                    while its apparently religious character served to attract many whom its
                    revolutionary secrecy might have repelled. A lodge of Carbonari was <hi
                        rend="italic">baracca</hi> (a hut); an ordinary meeting, <hi rend="italic"
                        >vendita</hi> (a sale); a meeting of importance, <hi rend="italic">alta
                        vendita</hi><hi rend="italic">;—</hi> these terms being borrowed from the
                    trade of charcoal-burning. But for words to express the inner purpose of the
                    society they borrowed from religion. Christ, as the highest victim of tyranny,
                    was the lamb that had been put to death by the wolf; they were sworn to avenge
                    his death; and so the destruction of the wolf to avenge the slaughter of the
                    lamb became the symbolic watchword of the society. There were four grades in the
                    society; and the ceremonies of initiation were characterized by many mystic
                    rites, through which the real meaning began only gradually to appear. Many
                    efforts were made to bring about a complete organization of the Carbonari in
                    Italy, by the institution of a central power which should control the separate
                    societies of the various provinces, but they failed. Politicians soon discovered
                    how easily capital could be made of such societies, and negotiations were
                    entered into by the Bourbons to unite the Carbonari in an effort to overthrow
                    the French Government in Naples. Accordingly, for two years they carried on a
                    desultory warfare with King Murat, who at last, taking the matter thoroughly in
                    hand, drove them into the mountains, from which they had emerged, and suppressed
                    them for a time. Capobianco, their leader, was treacherously arrested and put to
                    death. Ere long, the Carbonari reappeared and helped towards the final overthrow
                    of the French power in Naples. But Ferdinand, who had courted them during his
                    misfortunes, proved false to them on his return to power, though they were
                    moderate enough in their political aims, being ready to content themselves with
                    the establishment in Naples of the constitution that had been enjoyed in Sicily
                    under English supremacy. Henceforward they began to conspire against the Bourbon
                    Government, and indeed soon spread over the whole of Italy, being more and more
                    regarded as the champions of the liberal and national cause. They were the
                    principal authors of the Neapolitan revolution of 1820, of the disturbances in
                    the Papal States of the same year, and of the Piedmontese revolution of 1821.
                    Previously recruited chiefly from the lower classes, the Carbonari now counted
                    in their ranks almost all the intelligent and patriotic population of Italy, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n100/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0100-0089"/> especially the middle classes, the officers
                    of the army, the students at the universities, the artists, and even the
                    priests,—to the number, it is said, of nearly 700,000. Unable, however, to
                    resist the military power of Austria, backed by a European congress, the
                    revolution and the Carbonari along with it were crushed, and many, such as
                    Silvio Pellico, implicated or supposed to be implicated in their conspiracies,
                    perished or languished in Austrian dungeons. They never quite revived in Italy;
                    though active again in 1830 and 1831, they were forthwith superseded by the more
                    energetic and more extreme “young Italy” of Mazzini.</p>
                <p>It was about 1820 that Carbonarism began to take root in France. There the
                    organization was more perfect, as in addition to what had been attained in
                    Italy, there was a supreme board, presided over by the veteran Lafayette, and a
                    complete hierarchy of societies, by which the will of the chief was
                    communicated, from higher to lower, to the smallest lodges in the extremities of
                    France; these were <hi rend="italic">ventes particulières, ventes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">centrales,</hi><hi rend="italic">hautes ventes, ventes
                        suprêmes.</hi> It made great progress in France, especially among the
                    students and sub-officers of the army. The example of Spain and Italy having
                    incited the French Carbonari to immediate action, attempts to raise an
                    insurrection were made in 1821 at Belfort, Thouars, La Rochelle, and other
                    towns. They were all immediately suppressed, but not without revealing to what
                    extent the Carbonari had spread over France. It was at the trial of Boriès, one
                    of those concerned in the rising at La Rochelle, that the nature and
                    organization of the Carbonari in France became publicly known, and attention was
                    drawn to the mutual fidelity prevalent among them, as none but those immediately
                    concerned in the insurrection could be brought to trial. Though completely
                    defeated in 1821, French Carbonarism did not die out, but continued to be an
                    active centre of revolutionary discontent till 1830, when, after contributing to
                    the July revolution, most of the members adhered to the government of Louis
                    Philippe For several years after, traces of it existed in some French towns, but
                    these are of no importance.</p>
                <p>Heckethorn’s <hi rend="italic">Secret Societies</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    Botta’a <hi rend="italic">History of Italy,</hi> vol. ii.; Alison’s <hi
                        rend="italic">History of Europe,</hi> vol. ii.; <hi rend="italic">Annuaire
                        Historique.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
