<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0806-0793-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CISTERCIANS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 793</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z981">Abbots</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:830322">Benedictionals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:830317">Benediction</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:794221">Abbots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n806/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CISTERCIANS</label>, a religious order of the rule of St
                    Benedict, founded in 1098, by St Robert abbot of Molesme. It was so named from
                    its original convent in the forest of Citeaux (Cistercium), about 14 miles
                    north-east of Beaune. This order became so powerful that it governed almost all
                    Europe both in temporal and spiritual concerns, and through the exertions of St
                    Bernard of Clairvaux had increased so rapidly in power, that within a century
                    from its foundation it embraced 800 rich abbeys in different countries of
                    Europe. The abbeys of LaFerté, Pontigny, Clairvaux, andMorimond were offshoots
                    of that of Citeaux, and produced in their turn a great number of separate
                    communities, all which continued under the superintendence of the abbey of
                    Citeaux. The abbey of Morimond alone possessed 700 benefices; and its supremacy
                    was acknowledged by the military orders of Ca]atrava, Alcantara, and Montesa in
                    Spain, and by those of Christ and of Avis in Portugal. But the most famous of
                    all the communities of this order was that of Clairvaux, founded in 1115 by St
                    Bernard (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bernard).</hi> Towards the end of the 12th
                    century, however, the immense wealth of Citeaux began to operate unfavourably on
                    its discipline, and led the way to great corruptions. Jean de la Barrière, abbot
                    of Notre-Dame des Feuillants, near Toulouse, succeeded in 1577 in effecting a
                    reform, which gave rise to the Fueillants in France, and likewise to the
                    Reformed Bernardines in Italy. But of all the reforms among the Cistercians, the
                    most celebrated was that effected by the abbot of La Trappe in 1664.</p>
                <p>Dependent on the abbey of Citeaux there were about 1800 monasteries and an equal
                    number of nunneries. This ancient abbey was the burial-place of all the dukes of
                    Burgundy of the original line, with the exception of the first two, who died
                    before its foundation.</p>
                <p>The Cistercians were involved in the general fate of the religious orders during
                    the period of the French Revolution of 1789, and were reduced to a few convents
                    in Spain, Poland, Austria, and the Saxon part of Upper Lusatia.</p>
                <p>The habit of the order is a white robe or cassock, with a black scapulary and a
                    woollen girdle. The nuns wear a white tunic and a black scapulary and
                    girdle.</p>
                <p>The order began by exercising more austerity than either the Benedictines of that
                    period (the 11th century) or the Cluniae monks who had emerged from the
                    Benedictine order two centuries earlier. This austerity was exhibited, not only
                    in the rude and scanty fare of the brethren (limited during a great part of the
                    year to one meal a day) and in the great amount of silence imposed, but likewise
                    in the dress, the sacred vestments, and the church furniture of the order. The
                    Cluniae monks not only possessed fine churches, but were also in the habit of
                    adorning them with pictures, jewelled crosses, and other elaborate decorations,
                    while their vestments and chalices were in keeping with this splendour. Indeed
                    one of their first men, St Hugh, a contemporary of St Bernard, strongly
                    maintained the principle that nothing could be too rich and costly for the
                    divine service. But St Stephen Harding, the English monk, who, though only the
                    second abbot, was the virtual creator of Cistercian rule and discipline,
                    impressed on the Cistercian mind a different principle, and trained up St
                    Bernard in it. Their chasubles were to be only of linen, the chalice not of gold
                    but of silver gilt, and even the white robe of the order was less voluminous in
                    its folds than that of the Cluniae brethren. In one respect, however, the sense
                    of beauty seems to have been allowed to operate. Although the material was to be
                    coarse, yet the form of a vestment might be carefully looked to; and this taste
                    for beauty of form led in due time to great advances in the architecture of
                    their buildings. This difference between the Cistercians and the Cluniacs
                    occasioned considerable rivalry and even bitterness of sentiment,—the
                    Cistercians being in danger of something like Pharisaic pride in contrasting
                    their own severer rule with the comparative luxury of their neighbours the
                    Cluniacs, who apparently afforded some ground for the charge of relaxation of
                    discipline, especially in the 12th century after the death of St Hugh.</p>
                <p>In the matter of government, the Cistercian order (as constituted by St Stephen
                    Harding at a general chapter held in 1119) differed both from the Benedictine
                    and from the Cluniae constitutions. According to the rule of St Benedict each
                    monastery was to bean independent monarchy under its own abbot; although in
                    extraordinary cases neighbouring monasteries of the order might interfere in the
                    election of an abbot. This independence had not been <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n807/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0807-0794"/> found to work well, and the Cluniae rule made
                    each daughter monastery to be subject to Cluny, and to receive its prior from
                    his appointment. Such subordination tended to greater regularity of discipline,
                    and greatly increased the power of the order, especially when abbeys were
                    assailed by laymen or unduly harassed by bishops. The abbot of Cluny became a
                    veritable prince with 314 monasteries subject to him, and with the right of
                    coining money, which was accepted as readily as that of the king of France. But
                    its concentration of power in a single hand involved the risk attendant upon all
                    such despotisms; and the Abbot Pontius, who had succeeded St Hugh about 1109
                    seems to have endangered the entire system by an extravagance which loaded Cluny
                    with debt, and by his ambition in claiming the title of Abbot of Abbots, and in
                    endeavouring to sway the oldest Benedictine house itself, the famous abbey of
                    Monte Casino. St Stephen Harding framed a constitution for the Cistercians which
                    aimed at combining the excellencies without the defects of the two systems.
                    Although in his rule the abbot of Citeaux was to be recognized as the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pater Universalis</hi><hi rend="italic">Ordinis,</hi> yet a system
                    of reciprocal visitation was to be carried on, and the four earliest houses
                    which derived their origin from Citeaux— La Ferté, Pontigny, Clairvaux, and
                    Morimond—governed the abbeys which had respectively sprung from them. The four
                    abbots of these eldest daughters of Citeaux might even in an extreme case, with
                    the consent of a general chapter, depose the head of the order, the abbot of
                    Citeaux. This constitution, known as the Chart of Charity, exercised much
                    influence upon other orders, and in some degree upon that of Cluny. But it gave
                    rise to a claim which (though not intended by its author, aud denounced by its
                    greatest <hi rend="italic">alumnus,</hi> St Bernard) was successfully urged in
                    after years by the Cistercian, as well as by other orders, viz., an exemption
                    from episcopal superintendence.</p>
                <p>With respect to intellectual culture and influence, the Cistercian order cannot
                    claim a place in the front rank among the monastic bodies. Devoted to worship,
                    to penance, to contemplation, and to culture of the soil, the order did not,
                    like some others, admit the relaxation of scholastic disputations. No doubt it
                    received learned men into its fold. It is also true that St Stephen Harding,
                    with some of his brethren, undertook a revision of the Bible, that copies of
                    many valuable works were made by the brethren (though, with less ornamentation
                    than the illuminated MSS. of some other orders), and that St Bernard was
                    solicitous to furnish all the monasteries founded by himself with good
                    libraries. Nevertheless, as an order, the Cistercians have not achieved such
                    triumphs of learning as the Benedictines, the Dominicans, or the Jesuits.</p>
                <p>But no order springing out from the Benedictine proved so popular as the
                    Cistercian. During the 11th century its houses were multiplied in every
                    direction. It touched both ends of the social scale. St Bernard and the thirty
                    novices who joined with him were all of noble birth; many similar accessions
                    were made from time to time, and in the 12th century we read of fifteen young
                    German princes entering the order. But a place was also found for the poor and
                    uneducated. Such as could not be choir brethren, might be lay brethren and till
                    the fields; and the contrast between a labourer of this sort, partaking of the
                    dignity of a great and powerful community, and the neighbouring husbandman, the
                    serf of some feudal lord, was in the eyes of many all in. favour of the monk. It
                    may have tended towards that emancipation of the labourers so largely effected
                    by the monastic orders and celebrated in a well-known sonnet by Wordsworth.</p>
                <p>The order seems to have especially thriven in England. From Waverley in Surrey,
                    the earliest Cistercian settle ment in the country, they spread over Britain,
                    especially by the rivers of Yorkshire, and extended into Scotland.</p>
                <p>The overthrow of the Cistercian houses at the time of the Reformation is a part
                    of general monastic history. While some of the dissolutions were unjust, and the
                    execution of abbots mere judicial murders, the luxury of the great Yorkshire
                    houses seems quite undeniable, and perhaps their overthrow may, on the whole, be
                    thought to favour the <hi rend="italic">dictum</hi> of Mr Carlyle,—that nothing
                    is crushed from without, until it is ripe to perish from within.</p>
                <p>For authorities see the articles already referred to. See also Manriquez, <hi
                    rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">Cister</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >denses,</hi> 4 vols, folio, Lyons, 1642, and the various biographies of St
                    Bernard by Alban Butler, Neander, De Ratisbon, Morrison, and others; and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Cistercian Saints of England,</hi> especially <hi
                    rend="italic">St Stephen Harding,</hi> edited by John Henry Newman, London,
                    1844. Dean Milman cautions his readers against the love of legend displayed in
                    these biographies, but praises “their research and exquisite charm of style,”
                    <hi rend="italic">Lot. Christianity,</hi> bk. viii. chap. 4. See also Cheruel,
                    <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Historique,</hi> Paris, 1855; and. for the
                    artistic elements, so far as regards paintings, Mrs Jamieson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Legends of the Monastic Orders,</hi> London, 1850; also Cosmo Innes’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Scotland in the Middle Ages,</hi> Edinburgh, 1860; <hi
                    rend="italic">Records of the Monastery oj Kinloss,</hi> by John Stuart, LL.D.,
                    Edinburgh, 1872; and an article “Cistercian Abbeys in Yorkshire” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Fraser's Magazine</hi> for September 1876. (J. G. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
