<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0617-0606-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHESTERFIELD, Philip Dormer Stanhope, Fourth Earl
                    of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 606</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:874582">Conducting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n617/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHESTERFIELD, <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip Dormer Stanhope,
                    Fourth Earl of</hi></label> (1694-1773), the son of Philip Stanhope, the third
                    earl, and Elizabeth Savile, daughter of the marquis of Halifax, was born in
                    London. Deprived at an early age of his mother, the care of the little Lord
                    Stanhope devolved upon his grandmother, the marchioness of Halifax, a lady of
                    culture and connection, whose house was frequented by the most distinguished
                    Whigs of the epoch. He soon began to prove himself possessed of that systematic
                    spirit of conduct and effort which appeared so much in his life and character.
                    Divined by Ruvigny, earl of Galway, who perceived in him a nascent aptitude for
                    pleasure and politics overlaid with a strong natural tendency to indolence, he
                    was advised by that nobleman, if he would become a man of mark, to rise early;
                    he acquired the habit, and kept it. His education, commenced under a private
                    tutor, was continued (1712) at Trinity Hall, Cambridge; here he seems to have
                    read hard, and to have acquired a considerable knowledge of ancient and modern
                    languages. The great orators of all times were a special object of study with
                    him, and he describes his boyish pedantry pleasantly enough, but by no means
                    without a touch of self-satisfaction in the memory. His university training was
                    supplemented (1714) by a Continental tour, untrammelled by a governor; at the
                    Hague his ambition for the applause awarded to adventure made a gamester of him,
                    and at Paris he began, from the same motive, that worship of the conventional
                    Venus, the serious inculcation of which has earned for him the largest and most
                    unenviable part of his reputation.</p>
                <p>The death of Anne and the accession of George I. opened, up a career for him and
                    brought him back to England. His relative James Stanhope, the king’s favourite
                    minister, procured for him the place of gentleman of the bedchamber to the
                    Prince of Wales. In 1715 he entered the House of Commons as member for St
                    Germans, and when the impeachment of James, duke of Ormond (June 21, 1715), came
                    before the House, he used the occasion to put to proof his old rhetorical
                    studies. His maiden speech was youthfully fluent and dogmatic; but on its
                    conclusion the orator was reminded, with many compliments, by an honourable
                    member, that he wanted six weeks of his majority, and consequently that he was
                    amenable to a heavy fine for speaking in the House. Lord Stanhope quitted the
                    Commons with a low bow, and started for the Continent. From Paris he rendered
                    the Government important service by gathering and transmitting information
                    respecting the Jacobite plot; and in 1716 he returned to England, resumed his
                    seat, and took frequent part in the debates. In that year came the quarrel
                    between the king and the heir apparent. Stanhope, whose politic instinct obliged
                    him to worship the rising rather than the setting sun, remained faithful to the
                    prince, although the ministry made several attempts to win him over. In 1723 a
                    vote for the Government got him the place of captain of the yeomen of the guard;
                    his happy reply to his predecessor, Lord Townshend, is a fine example of <hi
                    rend="italic">spirituel</hi> urbanity, and is valuable as indicating, among
                    other examples, his contempt for the money-jobbing system that obtained at
                    court. In 1725, on the revival of the Bath, the red riband was offered to him,
                    but was declined.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n618/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0618-0607"/>
                <p>In 1726 his father died, and Lord Stanhope became earl of Chesterfield. He took
                    his seat in the Upper House, and his oratory, never effective in the Commons by
                    reason of its want of force and excess of finish, at once became a power. In
                    1727, on the accession of George IL, Chesterfield was sent to the Hague as
                    ambassador. In this place his tact and temper,his dexterity and discrimination,
                    enabled him to do good service, and he was rewarded with Walpole’s friendship, a
                    Garter, and the place of Lord High Steward. In 1732 there was born to him, by a
                    certain Madame du Bouchet, the son, Philip Stanhope, for whose advice and
                    instruction were afterwards written the famous <hi rend="italic">Letters.</hi>
                    In the same year, being somewhat broken in health and fortune by his sojourn
                    abroad, he resigned his embassy and returned to England. A few months’ rest
                    enabled him to resume his seat in the Lords, of which he was one of the
                    acknowledged leaders. He supported the ministry, but his allegiance was not the
                    blind fealty Walpole exacted of his followers. The Excise Bill, the great
                    premier’s favourite measure, was vehemently opposed by him in the Lords, and by
                    his three brothers in the Commons. Walpole bent before the storm, and abandoned
                    the measure; but Chesterfield was summarily dismissed from his Stewardship. For
                    the next two years he led the opposition in the Upper House, leaving no stone
                    unturned to effect the downfall of the man who had wronged him. In 1742 Walpole
                    fell, and Carteret reigned in his stead. The new ministry, however, had not
                    Chesterfield either in its ranks or among its supporters. He remained in
                    opposition, distinguishing himself by the courtly bitterness of his attacks on
                    George II, who learned to hate him violently. In 1744 the king was compelled to
                    abandon Carteret, and the coalition or “Broad Bottom” party, led by Chesterfield
                    and Pitt, came into office. In the troublous state of European politics the
                    earl’s conduct and experience were more useful abroad than at home, and he was
                    sent to the Hague as ambassador a second time. The success of his mission was
                    complete; and on his return a few weeks afterwards he received the
                    lord-lieutenancy of Ireland, a place he had long coveted.</p>
                <p>Short as it was, Chesterfield’s Irish administration was of great service to his
                    country, and is unquestionably that part of his political life which does him
                    most honour. To have conceived and carried out a policy which, with certain
                    reservations, Burke himself might have originated and owned is indeed no small
                    title to regard. The earl showed himself finely capable in practice as in
                    theory, vigorous and tolerant, a man to be feared, and a leader to be followed;
                    he took the government entirely into his own hands, repressed the jobbery
                    traditional to the office, established schools and manufactures, and at once
                    conciliated and kept in check the Orange and Popish factions. In 1746, however,
                    he had. to exchange the lord-lieutenancy for the place of Secretary of State.
                    With a curious respect for those theories his familiarity with the secret social
                    history of France had caused him to entertain, he hoped and attempted to retain
                    a hold over the king through the influence of Lady Yarmouth, though the futility
                    of such means had already been demonstrated to him by his relations with Queen
                    Caroline’s “<hi rend="italic">ma bonne Howard.”</hi> The influence of Newcastle
                    and Sandwich, however, was too strong for him; he was thwarted and over-reached;
                    and in 1748, he resigned the seals, and returned to cards and his books with the
                    admirable composure which was one of his most striking characteristics.</p>
                <p>The dukedom offered him by George II., whose ill-will his fine tact had overcome,
                    was refused. He continued for some years to attend the Upper House, and to take
                    I&gt;art in its proceedings. In 1751, seconded by Lord Macclesfield, President
                    of the Royal Society, and Bradley, the eminent mathematician, he distinguished
                    himself greatly in the debates on the calendar, and succeeded in making the new
                    style a fact. Deafness, however, was gradually affecting him, and he withdrew
                    little by little from society and the practice of politics. In 1754 occurred the
                    famous dispute with Johnson over the dedication to the <hi rend="italic">English
                    Dictionary.</hi> This quarrel (to which are owing the doctor’s noble letter and
                    some half dozen of his roughest <hi rend="italic">mots,</hi> and the earl’s
                    clever portrait of the “intelligent Hottentot ”), with the neglect it assumed on
                    Chesterfield’s part, has been fatal to his reputation as a man of heart. During
                    the twenty years of life that followed this episode, Chesterfield wrote and read
                    a great deal, but went little into society. In 1768 died Philip Stanhope, the
                    child of so many hopes; and the earl, who had no children by his wife, Melusina
                    von Schulemberg, illegitimate daughter of George I., whom he married in 1733,
                    adopted his godson the heir to the title and estates. His famous jest (which
                    even Johnson allowed to have merit),—“Tyrawley and I have been dead these two
                    years, but we don’t choose to have it known”—is the best description possible of
                    his humour and condition during the latter part of this period of decline. To
                    the deafness was added blindness, but his memory and his fine manners only left
                    him with life; his last words (“Give Dayrolles a chair ”) prove that he had
                    neither forgotten his friend nor the way to receive him. He died on the 24th of
                    March 1773.</p>
                <p>Chesterfield was selfish, calculating, and contemptuous; he was not naturally
                    generous, and he practised dissimulation till it became part of his nature. In
                    spite of his brilliant talents, and of the admirable training he received, his
                    life, on the whole, cannot be pronounced a success. His anxiety and the pains he
                    took to become an orator have been already noticed, and Horace Walpole, who had
                    heard all the great orators, preferred a speech of Chesterfield’s to any other;
                    yet the earl’s eloquence is not to be compared with that of Pitt. Samuel
                    Johnson, who was not perhaps the best judge in the world, pronounced his manners
                    to have been “exquisitely elegant;” yet as a courtier he was utterly worsted by
                    Robert Walpole, whose manners were anything but refined, and even by Newcastle.
                    He desired to be known as a protector of letters and literary men; and his want
                    of heart or head over the <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> dedication, though
                    explained and excused by Croker, none the less inspired the famous change in a
                    famous line—“Toil, envy, want, <hi rend="italic">the patron,</hi> or the jail.”
                    His published writings have had with posterity a very indifferent success; his
                    literary reputation rests on a volume of letters never designed to appear in
                    print. The son for whom he worked so hard and thought so deeply failed
                    especially where his father had most desired he should succeed, becoming, not a
                    fine gentleman, but a commonplace book-worm. As a politician and statesman,
                    Chesterfield’s fame rests on his short but brilliant administration of Ireland.
                    As an author he stands or falls by the <hi rend="italic">Letters to his
                    Son,</hi> first published by Stanhope’s widow in 1774. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters</hi> are brilliantly written,—full of elegant wisdom, of keen wit, of
                    admirable portrait-painting, of exquisite observation and deduction. Against the
                    charge of an undue insistence on the external graces of manner Chesterfield has
                    been adequately defended by Lord Stanhope <hi rend="italic">(History,</hi> iii.
                    34). Against the often iterated accusation of immorality, it should be
                    remembered that the <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> reflected the morality of the
                    age, and that their author only systematized and reduced to writing the
                    principles of conduct by which, deliberately or unconsciously, the best and the
                    worst of his contemporaries were governed.</p>
                <p>See Chesterfield’s <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous Works,</hi> London, 1777-8, 2
                    vols. 4to; and <hi rend="italic">Letters to his Son</hi> (edited by Lord Mahon),
                    London, 1845- 51, 5 vols. See also Lord Mahon (Stanhope), <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of England from the Peace of Utrecht to the Pease of
                    Versailles.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n619/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0619-0608"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
