<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0598-0587-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHERUBIM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 587</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6497c">Wings</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mj2c">Griffin</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qq9f">Pluralism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1176014">Wings</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1141164">Synonyms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:819237">Assyrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:955402">Herders</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHERUBIM</label> (plural of cherub) were “celestial genii,·’
                    and, in Μ. de Saulcy’s opinion, little else can be positively affirmed <hi
                    rend="italic">(Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >art</hi><hi rend="italic">judaïque,</hi> p. 24). Fresh light has, however,
                    recently been thrown upon them from the cuneiform inscriptions, and we are no
                    longer reduced to admit that “le vaste champ des hypothèses restera toujours
                    ouvert.” According to the Old Testament, the cherub united the functions of
                    bearer and guardian of deity; or rather, perhaps, there was a divergence in the
                    popular beliefs on this subject. In Ps. xviii. 10, 2 Sam. xxii. 11 Yahweh (the
                    so called Jehovah) is described as “riding upon a cherub,” and in the parallel
                    line as “swooping,” the word applied in Deut, xxviii. 49 and elsewhere to the
                    flight of the eagle. Putting the two phrases together, we may conclude that,
                    according to one version of the myth— whether fully believed in or not by the
                    Psalmist need not here be discussed—the cherub was either an eagle or a
                    quadruped with eagle’s wings. This result would seem to justify connecting the
                    word with the Assyrian <hi rend="italic">kurubu,</hi> a synonym of <hi
                    rend="italic">kurukku</hi> or <hi rend="italic">karakkυ.</hi> the “circling”
                    bird, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> according to Friedrich Delitzsch, the
                    vulture. On the other hand, the prophet Ezekiel (xxviii. 13-16), though agreeing
                    with the Psalmist in mentioning but one cherub, describes him as “walking in the
                    midst of stones of fire” <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> thunderbolts), and as
                    extending his wings over “the holy mountain of Elohim,” in other words, as the
                    attendant and guard rather than as the bearer of deity. And in the fuller
                    account of Paradise in Genesis “<hi rend="italic">the</hi> cherubim” <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the entire band of cherubs) are stationed “with (or
                    near) the blade of the turning sword” (this, like the “tree of life,” has a
                    Babylonian analogue, and is a mythic phrase meaning the lightning,—see
                    references below) “to guard the way to the tree of life” (Gen. iii. 24). Now,
                    according to a talismanic inscription copied by Lenormant, <hi rend="italic"
                    >kirubu</hi> is a synonym for the steer-god, whose winged imago filled the place
                    of guardian at the entrance of the Assyrian palaces. And in the fantastic
                    description of Ezekiel penned by the River Chebar, one of the four faces of a
                    cherub was that of an ox (Ezek. i. 10, after which the corrupt passage in x. 14,
                    must, in spite of Lenormant, be corrected). We should, therefore, connect the
                    word cherub primarily with the Assyrian <hi rend="italic">kirubu,</hi> but also,
                    as proposed above, with <hi rend="italic">kumιbu.</hi> The two forms seem to be
                    co-ordinate and expressive of some quality common to the king of birds and the
                    colossal steer. Their etymology is altogether uncertain, and possibly to be
                    sought for (as Mr Sayce has suggested) outside the sphere of Semitism. Partial
                    paraUels to the cherubim in non-Semitic mythologies are not uncommon, but are
                    mostly deceptive. The most complete one is that of the winged <hi rend="italic"
                    >γpvττd</hi> (a secondary form of kerubim), who not only watched over the
                    treasures of the gods <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Herod, iv. 13, 116), but were
                    also the bearers of deity, if at least Plutarch and Eustathius may be followed
                    in identifying the <hi rend="italic">τeτpaσκeλη&lt;s</hi> οιωνός of Aesch. <hi
                    rend="italic">Prom.</hi> 395 with the griffin (see Hermann, <hi rend="italic">ad
                    loc.)</hi> Probably the griffin was imagined under more than one form. This was
                    certainly the case with the Hebrew cherub, as appears not only from the passages
                    referred to above, but from the inconsistencies of the single prophet Ezekiel
                    <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> i. 6, xli. 18). The significance of the mythical
                    cherubim has been well pointed out by C. P. Tiele. They are probably the masses
                    of clouds, which seem to guard the portals of the sky, and on which the sun-god
                    appears to issue forth at break of day. This will account for the expressions
                    used of the cherubim both of the heavenly and of the earthly “habitation” of
                    Yahweh, expressions taken up by the Biblical writers from the folklore of their
                    times.</p>
                <p>For the Assyrian authorities, see Schrader, <hi rend="italic">Jenaer</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Litteratur∙ zeitung,</hi> 1874, p. 218; Delitzsch (the younger),
                    <hi rend="italic">Assyrische Studien,</hi> pp. 107, 108; and for the Babylonian
                    lightning-myth, Lenormant, <hi rend="italic">Birose,</hi> p. 138 <hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Records of the Past,</hi> vol. iii. pp.
                    127-129. Compare also Herder, <hi rend="italic">Werke,</hi> vol. xxxiii. <hi
                    rend="italic">(Geist der</hi><hi rend="italic">Ebraïschen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Poesie),</hi> pp. 168-180; Ewald, <hi rend="italic">Antiquities of Israel,</hi>
                    Eng. transi., p. 123; Riebm, in <hi rend="italic">Theologische Studien und
                    Kritiken,</hi> 1871; Tiele, <hi rend="italic">Vergelijkende geschiedenis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der oude godsdiensten,</hi> vol. i. p. 366; and F. W. Farrar in
                    Kittos <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia of Biblical Literature,</hi> art.
                    “Cherubim. ’ (T. K. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
