<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0302-0291-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CELESTINE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 291</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c552">Nestorians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p89s">Feces</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1036176">Nestorians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1103658">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n302/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CELESTINE</label>, the name of five popes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Celestine</hi> I. was a Roman, and is supposed to have been
                    a near relative of the Emperor Valentinian. Various portions of the liturgy are
                    attributed to him, but without any certainty on the subject. He held the Council
                    of Ephesus in which the Nestorians were condemned, in 431. Four letters written
                    by him on that occasion, dated all of them lõth March 431, together with a few
                    others, to the African bishops, to those of Illyria, of Thessalonica, and of
                    Narbonne, are extant in retranslations from the Greek, the Latin originals
                    having been lost. He actively persecuted the Pelagians, and was zealous for
                    Roman orthodoxy. He sent Palladius, a Greek, to Scotland, and Patricius (St
                    Patrick) to Ireland. He raged against the Novatians in Rome, imprisoning their
                    bishop, and forbidding their worship. He was zealous in refusing to tolerate the
                    smallest innovation on the constitutions of his predecessors, and is recognized
                    by the church as a saint. He occupied the seat of St Peter eight years five
                    months and three days, and died on the 6th April 432. He was buried in the
                    cemetery of St Priscilla in the Via Salaria, but his body, subsequently moved,
                    lies now in the Church of St Prasside.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Celestine</hi> II. was elected in 1143, governed the church
                    only five mouths and thirteen days, died 9th March 1144, and was buried at the
                    Lateran. His name had been Guido di Castello, from the small town of which he
                    was a native. He had studied under Peter Abelard. The principal act of his
                    Papacy was the absolution of Louis VII. of France at the request of that
                    penitent monarch, and the removal of the interdict under which that country had
                    lain for three years.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Celestine</hi> III., Giacinto Bobone Orsini, of that noble
                    race, was elected Pope 30th March 1191, being then only a deacon, received
                    priest’s orders on the 13th of April, ruled the church six years, nine months,
                    aad nine days (though believed to have been ninety when elected), died 8th
                    January 1193, and was buried at the Lateran. He crowned the Emperor Henry VI. on
                    the day after his election with a ceremonial symbolizing his absolute supremacy,
                    as described by Roger Hoveden, who is believed (more reasonably as it would
                    seem) by Baronius, but discredited by Natalis Alexander. He subsequently
                    excommunicated the same Henry for wrongfully keeping Richard of England in
                    prison. In 1192 he confirmed the statutes of the Teutonic Order of Knights. He
                    would have resigned the Papacy, and recommended a successor shortly before his
                    death, bat was not suffered to do so by the cardinals.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Celestine</hi> IV., Godfrey Castiglioni of Milan, a nephew
                    of Urban III., became a monk at Hautecombe in Savoy, there wrote a history of
                    Scotland, and was elected Pope by seven cardinals only, in the midst of troubles
                    caused by the vicinity and violence of the Emperor Frederick IL, on the 22d
                    September 1241. He occupied the throne only seventeen days, died, before
                    consecration, on the 8th October 1241, and was buried at the Vatican.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Celestine</hi> V. was known before his election as Peter di
                    Morone. Born in 1215, the son of a peasant in the Neapolitan district, named
                    Angelario, he became a Benedictine m &gt;nk at Faifoli in the diocese of
                    Benevento when he was seventeen. He showed from the first an extraordinary
                    disposition to asceticism and solitude, and in 1239 retired to a solitary cavern
                    on the mountain Morone, whence his name. Five years later he left this retreat,
                    and betook himself, with two companions, to a similar cave on the Mountain of
                    Majella in the Abruzzi, where he lived as strictly as was possible according to
                    the example of St John the Baptist. Terrible accounts are given of the severity
                    of his penitential practices. While living in this manner he founded, in 1244,
                    the order subsequently called after him Celestines. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Celestines.)</hi> The cardinals assembled at Perugia after the death of
                    Nicholas IV., and after long dissensions and difficulties agreed as a means of
                    escaping from them to elect the hermit Pietro di Morone. When sent for he
                    obstinately refused to accept the Papacy, and even, as Petrarch says,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">De
                    Vit.</hi><hi rend="italic">Solit.,∖i∖&gt;.</hi> ii. sec. 3, ch. 18.</p></note>
                    attempted flight, till he was at length persuaded by a deputation of cardinals
                    accompanied by the kings of Naples and Hungary. Elected 7th July 1294, he was
                    crowned in the city of Aquila in the Abruzzi, 29th August. He issued two
                    decrees,—one confirming that of Gregory X., which orders the shutting of the
                    cardinals in conclave; the second declaring the right of any Pope to abdicate
                    the Papacy,—a right he, at the end of five months and eight days, proceeded
                    himself to exercise at Naples on the 13th December 1294. He did one other thing
                    which may be noted, because it seems to be the only instance known to the church
                    in which such a thing occurred. He empowered one Francis of Apt, a Franciscan
                    friar, to confer priest’s orders on Lodovico, son of Charles, king of Sicily,—a
                    fact which seems to have escaped the notice of Bingham, who says that such a
                    thing was never done.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Orig.</hi><hi rend="italic">Eccl.,</hi> liTχ, ii. cap. 3,
                    sec. 5.</p></note> In the formal instrument of his renunciation he recites as
                    the causes moving him to the step, “the desire for humility, for a purer life,
                    for a stainless conscience, the deficiencies of his own physical strength, his
                    ignorance, the perverseness of the people, his longing for the tranquillity of
                    his former life;” and having divested himself of every outward symbol of
                    dignity, he retired to his old solitude. He was not allowed to remain there,
                    however. His successor, Boniface VIII., sent for him, and finally, despite
                    desperate attempts of the late Pope to escape, got him into his hands, and
                    imprisoned him in the castle of Fumone near Ferentino in Campagna, where, after
                    languishing for ten months in that infected air, he died on the 19th May 1296.
                    He was buried at Ferentino, but his body was subsequently removed to Aquila.
                    Many Dantescan commentators and scholars have thought that the poet stigmatized
                    Celestine V. in the enigmatical verse which speaks of him “Che fece per viltate
                    il gran rifiuto.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>‘ ‘
                    Who made from cowardice the grea' refusal,” <hi rend="italic">Inferno,</hi>
                    canto iii. line 60.</p></note> Recent opinion on the point more reasonably
                    rejects this interpretation. Celestine V., like the first of the name, is
                    recognized by the church as a saint.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
