<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0798-0785-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CINNAMON (9th edition, volume 5, page 785)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:861526">Cinnamon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116836">Shooting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827573">Bark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dj58h17">Cinnamon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dj0j">Cassia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c40">Shooting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n798/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CINNAMON</label> is the inner bark of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cinnamomum</hi><hi rend="italic">Zeylani- ¢um,</hi> a small evergreen tree
                    belonging to the Natural Order <hi rend="italic">Lauroeeoe.</hi> The leaves are
                    large ovate-oblong in shape, and the flowers, which are arranged in panicles,
                    have a greenish colour and a rather disagreeable odour. Cinnamon has been known
                    from the most remote antiquity, and it was so highly prized among ancient
                    nations that in very small quantities it was regarded as a present fit for
                    monarchs and other great potentates. It is mentioned in Exod. xxx. 23, where
                    Moses is commanded to use both sweet cinnamon <hi rend="italic">(Kinnamon</hi>
                    and cassia. It is likewise alluded to by Herodotus under the name <hi
                        rend="italic">κοwαμωμov,</hi> and it is frequently mentioned by many other
                    classical writers. It is now almost exclusively a product of Ceylon, but the
                    origin of the plant and the derivation of its name are matters of considerable
                    doubt and dispute. The Arab traders, by whom the trade in this and other
                    Oriental spices was conducted in ancient times, surrounded the history and
                    production of these precious and lucrative products with grotesque tales of
                    mystery. It is contended by some that cinnamon was originally obtained from the
                    promontory of Gardafui (the <hi rend="italic">regio dnnarnomifera</hi> of
                    classical geographers), while others lean to the opinion that it was brought
                    from China, whence the chief portion of the closely allied cassia bark is still
                    derived. Although as the produce of Ceylon, cinnamon did not come prominently
                    into the market till the settlement of the Portuguese in the island, it is the
                    opinion of the best authorities that the tree yielding it is indigenous, and
                    certainly no other situation and climate have yet been found where the trees
                    flourish so well and yield a bark so fine and so delicately aromatic.</p>
                <p>The cinnamon gardens are confined to a strip of country in the neighbourhood of
                    Colombo. When the trade was at its best, five of the principal gardens measured
                    from 15 to 20 miles in circumference, but now the area of cultivation is very
                    much restricted, and plants which were at one time tended with the greatest
                    care, and guarded with inhuman jealousy, are choked with the natural profusion
                    of jungle vegetation. The bark is taken from shoots of eighteen months or two
                    years growth, in which time they attain a length of from 6 to 10 feet, and a
                    thickness of from ½ to 2 inches. The plants are managed on the coppice system,
                    and only four or five shoots are allowed to grow up from each stool. The shoots
                    are cut down twice a year after the rains, and the bark is detached in lengths
                    of about a foot. After lying in bundles as taken from the shoots for about a
                    day, each separate piece is carefully scraped to remove the outer and middle
                    layers of the bark, and the remaining portion is thereby often reduced to the
                    thickness of one-hundredth part of an inch. The pieces are then made up into
                    composite quills by placing the smaller pieces inside the larger, and thus the
                    cinnamon is often formed into straight firm rods of from 3 to 4 feet in length.
                    After drying in the sun the bark is ready to make up into bundles for
                    exportation.</p>
                <p>Cinnamon of an inferior quality is grown in Southern India at Tellicherry and
                    Tinnevelly; and in Java the cultivation was introduced by the Dutch about the
                    year 1825. The plant has also been grown in the colony of French Guiana, and in
                    other localities. The produce of none of these places, however, approaches in
                    quality to the cinnamon of Ceylon, whence also the largest proportion of the
                    entire consumption is supplied. Nearly the whole quantity prepared in Ceylon is
                    brought to the British market. The value of Ceylon cinnamon submitted to the
                    English Board of Trade, was in 1874 more than 2s. 2d. per lb, that from other
                    localities being estimated at about 10d.</p>
                <p>Ceylon cinnamon of fine quality is a very thin smooth bark, with a
                    light-yellowish brown colour, a highly fragrant odour, and a peculiarly sweet,
                    warm, and pleasing aromatic taste. Its peculiar flavour is due to an aromatic
                    oil which it contains to the extent of from 0 ’ 5 to 1 per cent. The essential
                    oil of cinnamon, as an article of commerce, is prepared chiefly in Ceylon, where
                    the coarser pieces of bark are used for its extraction. These are roughly
                    powdered and macerated in sea water for two days, when the whole is quickly
                    distilled. The oil is of a golden-yellow colour, with the peculiar odour of
                    cinnamon and a very hot aromatic taste. It consists essentially of cinnamic
                    aldehyde or the hydride of cinnamyl, and by the absorption of oxygen as it
                    becomes old it darkens in colour and develops resinous compounds with cinnamic
                    acid.</p>
                <p>Cinnamon is principally employed in cookery as a condiment and flavouring
                    material, being largely used in the preparation of some kinds of chocolate and
                    liqueurs. In medicine it acts as an aromatic stimulant and cordial; but <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n799/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0799-0786"/> it is chiefly prescribed for improving the
                    flavour of bitter substances and to correct the griping action of purgatives.
                    Being a much more costly spice than cassia, that comparatively harsh-flavoured
                    substance is frequently substituted for or added to cinnamon. The two barks when
                    whole are easily enough distinguished, and their microscopical characters are
                    also quite distinct. When powdered bark is treated with tincture of iodine,
                    little effect is visible in the case of pure cinnamon; but with cassia a
                    deep-blue tint is produced, the intensity of the coloration depending on the
                    proportion of the cassia.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
