<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0786-0773-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CID, The, Rodrigo Diaz de Bivar (9th edition, volume 5,
                    page 773)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hs61">Moslems</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bg6t">Mussulmans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819823">Asturians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955558">Heroes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n786/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CID, <hi rend="smallcaps">The, Rodrigo Diaz de
                        Bivar</hi></label>, the favourite hero of Spain, and the most prominent
                    figure in her literature, has a name so obscured by myth and fable as scarcely
                    to belong to history. So extravagant are the deeds ascribed to him, and so
                    marvellous the attributes with which he has been clothed by the fond idolatry of
                    his countrymen, that by some he has been classed with the Amadises and the
                    Orlandos whose exploits he emulated. The Jesuit Masdeu stoutly denies that he
                    had any real existence, and this heresy has not wanted followers even in Spain.
                    The truth of the matter, however, has been expressed by Cervantes, through the
                    mouth of the Canon in <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi>
                    “There is no doubt there was such a man as the Cid, but much doubt whether he
                    achieved what is attributed to him.” The recent researches of Professor Dozy, of
                    Leyden, have amply confirmed this opinion. There is a Cid of history and a Cid
                    of romance, differing very materially in character, but each filling a large
                    space in the annals of his country, and exerting a singular influence in the
                    development of the national genius.</p>
                <p>The Cid of history, though falling short of the poetical ideal which the
                    patriotism of his countrymen has for 700 years cherished, is still the foremost
                    man of the heroical period of Spain—the greatest warrior produced out of the
                    long struggle between Christian and Moslem, and the perfect type of the Spanish
                    Goth of the 12th century. Rodrigo Diaz, called de Bivar, from the place of his
                    birth, better known by the title given him by the Arabs as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cid</hi><hi rend="italic">(El Seid,</hi> the lord), and <hi rend="italic"
                        >El Campeador,</hi> the champion <hi rend="italic">par excellence,</hi> was
                    of a noble family, one of whose members in a former generation had been elected
                    judge of Castile. The •date of his birth cannot be fixed with any certainty, but
                    it was probably between 1030 and 1040. As Rodrigo Diaz •de Bivar he is first
                    mentioned in a charter of Fernando I. of the year 1064. The legends which speak
                    of the Cid as accompanying this monarch in his expeditions to France and Italy
                    must be rejected as purely apocryphal. Fernando, a great and wise prince under
                    whom the tide of Moslem conquest was first effectually stemmed, on his deathbed,
                    in 1065, divided his territories among his five children. Castile was left to
                    his eldest son Sancho, Leon to Alphonso, Galicia to Garcia, Zamora and Toro to
                    his two daughters Urraca and Elvira. The extinction of the Western Caliphate and
                    the dispersion of the once noble heritage of the Ommiades into numerous petty
                    independent states, had taken place some thirty years previously, so that
                    Castilian and Moslem were once again upon equal terms, the country being almost
                    equally divided between them. On both sides was civil war, urged as fiercely as
                    that against the common enemy, in which the parties sought allies
                    indiscriminately among Christians and Mahometans. No condition of affairs could
                    be more favour-ble to the genius of the Cid. He rose to great distinc-ation in
                    the war between Sancho of Castile and Sancho of Navarre, in which he won his
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Campeador,</hi> by slaying the enemy’s champion in
                    single combat. In the quarrel between Sancho and his brother Alphonso, Rodrigo
                    Diaz espoused the cause of the former, and it was he who suggested the
                    perfidious stratagem by which Sancho eventually obtained the victory and
                    possession of Leon. Sancho having been slain in 1072, while engaged in the siege
                    of Zamora, Alphonso was taken from his prison and raised to the vacant throne.
                    One of the most striking of the passages in the Cid’s legendary history is that
                    wherein he is represented as forcing the new king to swear that he had no part
                    in his brother’s death; but there was cause enough without this for Alphonso’s
                    animosity against the man who had helped to despoil him of his patrimony. For a
                    time the Cid, already renowned throughout Spain for his prowess in war, was even
                    advanced by the king’s favour and entrusted with high commissions of state. In
                    1074 the Cid was wedded to Ximena, daughter of the count of Oviedo, and
                    granddaughter, by the mother’s side, of Alρhonso V. The original deed of the
                    marriage-contract is still extant. Some time afterwards the Cid was sent on an
                    embassy to collect tribute from Motamid, the king of Seville, whom he found
                    engaged in a war with Abdallah, the king of Granada. On Abdallah’s side were
                    many Castilian knights, among them Count Garcia Ordoñez, a prince of the blood,
                    whom the Cid endeavoured vainly to persuade of the disloyalty of opposing their
                    master’s ally. In the battle which ensued under the walls of Seville, Abdallah
                    and his auxiliaries were routed with great slaughter, the Cid returning to
                    Burgos with many prisoners and a rich booty. There fresh proofs of his prowess
                    only served to kindle against him the rancour of his enemies and the jealousy of
                    the king. Garcia Ordoñez accused him to Alphonso of keeping back part of the
                    tribute received from Seville, and the king took advantage of the Cid’s absence
                    on a raid against the Moors to banish him from Castile. Henceforth Rodrigo Diaz
                    began to live that heroic-picaresque life which has made him famous, sometimes
                    fighting under the Christian banner, sometimes under Moorish, but always for his
                    own hand. At the head of a band of 300 free lances he offered his services first
                    to the count of Barcelona; then, failing him, to Moctadir, the Arab king of
                    Saragossa, of the race of the Beni Houd. Under Moctadir, and his successors
                    Moutamin and Mostain, the Cid remained for nearly eight years, fighting their
                    battles n ga in st Mahometan and Christian, when not engaged upon his own, and
                    being admitted almost to a share of their royal authority. He made more than one
                    attempt to be reconciled with Alphonso, but his overtures being rejected, he
                    turned his arms against the enemies of the Beni Houd, extending their dominions
                    at the expense of the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n787/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0787-0774"/> Christian states of Aragon and Barcelona, and
                    harrying even the border lands of Castile. Among the enterprizes of the Cid the
                    most famous was that against Valencia, then the richest and most flourishing
                    city of the Peninsula, and an object of cupidity to both Christian and Moslem.
                    The Cid appeared before the place at the head of an army of 7000 men, for the
                    greater part Mahometans. In vain did the Valencians implore succour from the
                    emir of Cordova, and from their co-religionists in other parts of the Peninsula.
                    In defiance of an army which marched to the relief of the beleaguered city under
                    Yussuf the Almoravide, the Cid took Valencia after a siege of nine months, on
                    the 15th of June 1094—the richest prize which up to that time had been recovered
                    from the Moors. The conditions of the surrender were all violated—the cadi Ibn
                    Djahhaff burnt alive, avast number of the citizens who had escaped death by
                    famine slaughtered, and the possessions divided among the Campeador’s
                    companions. In other respects the Cid appears to have used his victory mildly,
                    ruling his kingdom, which now embraced nearly the whole of Valencia and Murcia,
                    for four years with vigour and justice. At length the Almoravides, whom he had
                    several times beaten, marched against him in great force, inflicting a crushing
                    defeat at Cuença upon the Cid’s army, under his favourite lieutenant, Alvar
                    Fañez. The blow was a fatal one to the aged and war-worn Campeador, who died of
                    anger and grief in July 1099. His widow maintained Valencia for three years
                    longer against the Moors, but was at last compelled to evacuate the city, taking
                    with her the body of the Cid to be buried in the monastery of San Pedro at
                    Cardeña, in the neighbourhood of Burgos. Here, in the centre of a small chapel,
                    surrounded by his chief companions in arms, by Alvar Fañez Minaya, Pero
                    Bermudez, Martin Antolinez, and Pelaez the Asturian, rest, after frequent
                    disturbances from friend and foe, the bones of the mighty warrior, the truest of
                    Spanish heroes, the embodiment of all the national virtues and most of the
                    national vices. Philip II. tried to get him canonized, but Rome objected, and
                    not without reason. Whatever were his qualities as a fighter, the Cid was but
                    indifferent material out of which to make a saint,—a man who battled against
                    Christian and against Moslem with equal zeal, who burnt churches and mosques
                    with equal zest, who ravaged, plundered, and slew as much for a livelihood as
                    for any patriotic or religious purpose, and was in truth almost as much of a
                    Mussulman as a Christian in his habits and his character. His true place in
                    history is that of the greatest of the <hi rend="italic">guerrilleros</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">—</hi> the perfect type of that sort of warrior in which, from
                    the days of Sertorius to those of El Empecinado, the soil of Spain has been most
                    productive.</p>
                <p>The Cid of romance, the Cid of a thousand battles, legends, and dramas, the Cid
                    aβ apotheosized in literature, the Cid invoked by good Spaniards in every
                    national crisis, whose name is a perpetual and ever-present inspiration to
                    Spanish patriotism, is a very different character from the historical Rodrigo
                    Diaz—the freebooter, the rebel, the consorter with the infidels and the enemies
                    of Spain. He is the Perfect One, the Born in a Happy Hour, “My Cid,” the
                    invincible, the magnanimous, the all-powerful. He is the type of knightly
                    virtue, the mirror of patriotic duty, the flower of all Christian grace. He is
                    Roland and Bayard in one. In the popular literature of Spain he holds a place
                    such as has no parallel in other countries. From an almost contemporary period
                    he has been the subject of song; and he who was chanted by wandering minstrels
                    in the 12th century has survived to be hymned in revolutionary odes of the 19th.
                    In a barbarous Latin poem, written in celebration of the conquest of Almeria by
                    Alphonse VII. in the year 1147, we have the bard testifying to the supereminenco
                    of the Cid among his country’s heroes :—</p>
                <p>“Ipse Rodericus <hi rend="italic">Miο</hi> Cid semper vocatus,</p>
                <p>De quo <hi rend="italic">ct</hi> tatur quod ab hostibus haud superatus, Qui
                    domuit Mauros, comites domuit quoque nostros.”</p>
                <p>Within a hundred years of his death the Cid had become the centre of a whole
                    system of myths. The <hi rend="italic">Pοema del Cid,</hi> written in the latter
                    half of the 12th century, has scarcely any trace of a historical character.
                    Already the Cid had reached his apotheosis, and Castilian loyalty could not
                    consent to degrade him wheA banished by his sovereign :—</p>
                <p>“Dios, que buen vassalo si oviese buen señor!” cry the weeping citizens of
                    Burgos, as they speed the exile on his way.</p>
                <p>The Poem of the Cid is but a fragment of 3744 lines, written in a barbarous
                    style, in rugged assonant rhymes, and a rude Alexandrine measure, but it glows
                    with the pure fire of poetry, and is full of a noble simplicity and a true
                    epical grandeur, invaluable as a living picture of the age. The ballads relating
                    to the Cid, of which nearly two hundred are extant, are greatly inferior in
                    merit, though some of them are not unworthy to be ranked with the best in this
                    kind. Duran believes the greater part of them to have been written in the 16th
                    century. A few betray, not more by the antiquity of their language than by their
                    natural and simple tone, traces of an earlier age and a freer national life.
                    They all take great liberties with history, thus belying the opinion of Sancho
                    Panza that “the ballads are too old to tell lies.” Such of them as are not
                    genuine relics of the 12th century are either poetical versions of the leading
                    episodes in the hero’s life as contained in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chronicle,</hi> that <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> itself having been
                    doubtless composed out of still earlier legends as sung by the wandering <hi
                        rend="italic">juglαres,</hi> or pure inventions of a later time, owing their
                    inspiration to the romances of chivalry. In these last the ballad-mongers, not
                    to let their native hero be outdone by the Amadises, the Esplandians, and the
                    Felix-martes, engage him in the most extravagant adventures— making war upon the
                    king of France and upon the emperor, receiving embassies from the Soldan of
                    Persia, bearding the Pope at Rome, and performing other feats not mentioned even
                    in the Poem or the Chronicle. The last and the worst of the Cid ballads are
                    those which betray by their frigid conceits and feeble mimicry of the antique
                    the false taste and essentially unheroic spirit of the age of Philip II. As for
                    the innumerable other poems, dramas, and tales which have been founded on the
                    legend of the Cid, from the days of Guillen de Castro and Diamante to those of
                    Quintana and Trueba, they serve merely to prove the abiding popularity of. the
                    national hero in his native land.</p>
                <p>The chief sources from which the story of the Cid is to be gathered are, first,
                    the Latin chronicle discovered by Risco in the convent of San Isidro at Leon,
                    proved by internal evidence to have been written before 1258; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Gronisa General,</hi> composed by Alphonse X. in the second
                    half of the 13th century, partly (so far as relates to the Cid) from the above,
                    partly from contemporary Arabic histories, and partly from tradition; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Cronica del Gid,</hi> first published in 1512, by Juan de
                    Velorado, abbot of the monastery of San Pedro at Cardeña, which is a compilation
                    from the last, interlarded with new fictions due to the piety of the compiler;
                    lastly, various Arabic manuscripts, some of contemporary date, which are
                    examined and their claims weighed in the second volume of Professor Dozy’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Historie</hi><hi rend="italic">de la littérature</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ds Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">Espagne au moyen, âge.</hi> Huber,
                    Muller, and Ferdinand Wolf are among the leading authorities in the history and
                    literature of the Cid. Μ. Damas Hinard has published the poem, with a literal
                    French translation and notes, and John Hookham Frere has rendered it into
                    English with extraordinary spirit and fidelity. The largest collection of the
                    Cid ballads is that of Duran, in the <hi rend="italic">Romancero</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">General,</hi> in two volumes, forming part of Rivadeneyra’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Biblioteca de Λutores Españolcs.</hi> (H. E. W.) <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n788/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0788-0775"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
