<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0302-0291-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CELESTINES (9th edition, volume 5, page 291)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115271">Sharing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955538">Hermits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n302/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CELESTINES</label>, a branch of the great Benedictine
                    monastic order. At the foundation of the new rule, they were called Hermits of
                    St Damiano, or Moronites (or Murronites), and did not assume the appellation of
                    Celes tines till after the election of their founder to the Papacy as Celestine
                    V. The fame of the holy life and the austerities practised by that saintly
                    hermit (as noticed above) in his solitude on the Mountain of Majella, near
                    Sulmona, attracted many visitors, several of whom .were moved to remain and
                    share his mode of life. They built, therefore, a small convent on the spot
                    inhabited by the holy hermit, which very shortly became too small for the
                    accommodation of those who thronged thither to share their life of privations.
                    Peter of Morone, their founder, therefore built a number of other small
                    oratories in that neighbourhood. This happened about the year 1254. A new
                    religious community was thus formed, and Peter of Morone gave them a rule formed
                    in accordance with his own practices. In 1264 the new institution was approved
                    by Urban IV. But the founder, having heard that it was probable that Pope
                    Gregory X., then holding a council at Lyons, would suppress all such new orders
                    as had been founded since the Lateran Council, having commanded that such
                    institutions should not be further multiplied, betook himself to Lyons, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n303/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0303-0292"/> and there succeeded in persuading Gregory to
                    approve his new order, constituting it a branch of the Benedictines, with a rule
                    based on that of St Benedict, but adding to it many additional severities and
                    privations. Gregory further took it under the Papal protection, assured to it
                    the possession of all property it might acquire, and endowed it with that great
                    and constant, but most pernicious and fatal, object of the ambition of all
                    monastic orders, exemption from the authority of the ordinary. Nothing more was
                    needed to ensure the rapid spread of the new association; and Peter the hermit
                    of Morone lived to see himself “Superior-General” of thirty-six monasteries and
                    more than six hundred monks. Peter, however, cannot be accused of ambition or
                    the lust of power when a monastic superior, any more than when he insisted on
                    divesting himself of the Papacy, to which he was subsequently raised. As soon as
                    he had seen his new order thus consolidated he gave up the government of it to a
                    certain Robert, and retired once again to a still more remote solitude to give
                    himself up more entirely to solitary penance and prayer. Shortly afterwards, in
                    a chapter of the order held in 1293, the original monastery of Majella being
                    judged to be too desolate and exposed to too rigorous a climate, it was decided
                    that the monastery which had been founded in Sulmona should be the headquarters
                    of the order and the residence of the General-Superior, as it has continued to
                    be to the present day. The next year Peter the hermit of Morone, having been,
                    despite his reluctance, elected Pope by the name of Celestine V., the order he
                    had founded took the name of Celestines. The hermit Pope found time in the few
                    short months of his Papacy to confirm the rule of the order, which he had
                    himself composed, and to confer on the society a variety of special graces and
                    privileges. In the only creation of cardinals promoted by him, among the twelve
                    raised to the purple, there were two monks of his order. He found time also to
                    visit personally the great Benedictine monastery on Monte Casino, where he
                    succeeded in persuading the monks to accept his more rigorous rule. He sent
                    fifty monks of his order to introduce it, who remained, however, for only a few
                    months.</p>
                <p>After the death of the founder the order was favoured and privileged by Benedict
                    XI., and rapidly spread through Italy, Germany, Flanders, and France, where they
                    were received by Philip the Fair in 1300. Subsequently the French Celestines,
                    with the consent of the Italian superiors of the order, and of Pope Martin V. in
                    1427, obtained the privilege of making new constitutions for themselves, which
                    they did in the 17th century in a series of regulations accepted by the
                    provincial chapter in 1667. At that time the French congregation of the order
                    was composed of twenty-one monasteries, the head of which was that of Paris, and
                    was governed by a Provincial with the authority of General. Paul V. was a
                    notable benefactor of the order. But in consequence of later political changes
                    and events the order has been dissolved.</p>
                <p>According to their special constitutions the Celestines were bound to say matins
                    in the cfioir at two o’clock in the morning, and always to abstain from eating
                    meat, save in illness. The specialities of their rule with regard to fasting
                    would be long and tedious to recount. It cannot ba said that they are more
                    severe than those of sundry other congregations, though much more so than is
                    required by the old Benedictine rule. But in reading their minute directions for
                    divers degrees of abstinence on various days, it is impossible to avoid being
                    struck by the conviction that the great object of the framers of these rules,
                    beyond the general purpose of ensuring an ascetic mode of life, was to create a
                    speciality, to make a distinguishing difference between what “our” order does
                    and what others do.</p>
                <p>The Celestines wore a white woollen cassock bound with a linen band, and a
                    leathern girdle of the same colour, with a scapulary unattached to the body of
                    the dress, and a black hood. It was not permitted to them to wear any shirt save
                    of serge. Their dress in short was very like that of the Cistercians. But it is
                    a tradition in the order that in the time of the founder they wore a coarse
                    brown cloth. The church and monastery of St Pietro in Montorio originally
                    belonged to the Celestines in Rome; but they were turned out of it by Sixtus IV.
                    to make way for Franciscans, receiving from the Pope in exchange the Church of
                    St Eusebius with the adjacent mansion for a monastery.</p>
                <p>The order of Celestines has had its special historians, as Becquet, author of a
                    history of the Celestines of France (Paris, 1719), and in the great collection
                    of the Bollandists, vol. iii., under the month of May. But the order does not
                    seem to have been fruitful of men of much mark; nor has it ever attained in the
                    annals of Europe, or even of the church, a position of such importance as most
                    of its rival societies have reached.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
