<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0391-0380-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHAMBERS, Robert</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 380</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:875336">Connectionism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01649">Creation</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n391/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHAMBERS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>
                    (1802-1871), author and publisher, distinguished especially for his services to
                    popular literature, was born at Peebles on the 10th July 1802. His parents were
                    of the middle class, but owing to the father’s misfortunes in business the
                    family were reduced to poverty, and had to leave Peebles for Edinburgh while
                    Robert was still young. He had before that received such an education as the
                    parish and grammar schools of his native place afforded, and had shown himself
                    possessed of unusual literary taste and ability. A small circulating library in
                    the town, and a copy of the first edition of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopoedia
                    Britannica</hi> which his father had purchased, furnished him with stores of
                    reading of which he eagerly availed himself. Long afterwards he wrote of his
                    early years—“Books, not playthings, filled my hands in childhood. At twelve I
                    was deep, not only in poetry and fiction, but in encyclopaedias.”</p>
                <p>In Edinburgh the family had a somewhat hard struggle with their straitened
                    Circumstances. Robert had been destined by a sort of tacit understanding for the
                    church, and was placed for a time at a classical school with a view to his being
                    sent to the university. This design had, however, to be abandoned. After
                    enduring many hardships, and making two unsuccessful attempts to fill situations
                    in mercantile houses in Leith, he commenced business on his own account as a
                    bookstall-keeper in Leith Walk, on the advice of his elder brother and future
                    partner, William. He was then only sixteen, and his whole stock consisted of a
                    few old books belonging to his father. By slow degrees the stock was increased
                    and the business extended. A similar but distinct concern was carried on during
                    the same period with like success by William, and after a number of years the
                    two brothers were united as partners in the now well-known publishing firm of W.
                    and R. Chambers.</p>
                <p>From the commencement of his residence in Edinburgh, Robert Chambers had shown an
                    enthusiastic interest in the history and antiquities of the city. In frequent
                    rambles every feature of its ancient buildings grew familiar to him, and his
                    mind became a storehouse for all sorts of information connected with its famous
                    persons and places. He thus found a most congenial task in the publication of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Traditions of Edinburgh</hi> (1823-4), which, though not
                    his first work, was the first which brought him into general notice. It secured
                    for him the approval, and what he doubtless valued even more highly, the
                    personal friendship of Sir Walter Scott, then in the zenith of his fame. Other
                    works on kindred subjects followed in rapid succession, the most popular and
                    important being a <hi rend="italic">History of the Rebellion of</hi> 1745. He
                    also wrote from time to time a number of short poetical pieces of very
                    considerable merit, which were afterwards collected and printed for private
                    circulation (1835). For a year or two he acted as editor of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Edinburgh Advertiser,</hi> a Tory newspaper of old standing, which
                    has now ceased to appear. With commendable and characteristic prudence the
                    bookselling business was diligently prosecuted in the midst of these numerous
                    literary engagements, so that his life at this period was one of ceaseless
                    activity.</p>
                <p>In the beginning of 1832 his brother William, after consultation with him,
                    started a weekly publication under the title of <hi rend="italic">Chambers’8
                    Journal,</hi> which speedily attained an immense circulation, and still holds a
                    leading place in the cheap popular periodical literature of which it was the
                    pioneer. Robert’s connection with it was at first only that of a contributor.
                    After fourteen numbers had appeared, however, he became associated with his
                    brother as jointeditor, and from that period he wrote for it nearly all the
                    leading articles, which took the form of essays—moral, familiar, and humorous.
                    Written in an easy, graceful style, entirely free from any affectation of
                    condescension, always interesting, and carefully avoiding the debateable ground
                    of religion and politics, they contributed more perhaps than anything else to
                    the remarkable success of the <hi rend="italic">Journal.</hi> A number of them
                    were republished in 1847 in the author’s <hi rend="italic">Select Writings,</hi>
                    and are thought to be on the whole the best specimens of his original work. Of
                    the same character as his work for the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> were his
                    numerous contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Information for the People</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Miscellany of Useful and Entertaining Tracts</hi>
                    published by his firm.</p>
                <p>Among the other works of which he was in whole or in part the author, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Cyclopaedia of English Literature,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Life
                    and Writings of Burns, Ancient Sea Margins,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Domestic
                    Annals of Scotland,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Book of Days</hi> were the
                    most important. The <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia of English Literature</hi>
                    contained a series of admirably selected extracts from the best authors of every
                    period, “set in a biographical and critical history of the literature itself.”
                    The biographies were gracefully written, and the critical estimates, though
                    brief, were just and comprehensive. For the <hi rend="italic">Life of Burns</hi>
                    he made diligent and laborious original investigations, gathering many hitherto
                    unrecorded facts from the surviving acquaintances of the poet, and especially
                    from his sister, Mrs Begg, to whose benefit the whole profits of the work were
                    generously devoted. The poems are interwoven into the narrative in their proper
                    chronological order, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n392/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0392-0381"/> with a the information that could be obtained as
                    to the circumstances of their composition. In connection with the work on <hi
                    rend="italic">Ancient Sea Margins,</hi> it may be mentioned that its author
                    ranked high as a scientific geologist, and that he had availed himself of tours
                    in Scandinavia and Canada for the purpose of geological exploration. His
                    knowledge of geology was one of the principal grounds on which the authorship of
                    the celebrated anonymous work, <hi rend="italic">The Vestiges of the
                    Creation,</hi> was very generally attributed to him. As, however, neither he
                    himself nor any one entitled to speak for him ever acknowledged the work, its
                    authorship remains a mystery. The <hi rend="italic">Book of Days</hi> was his
                    last publication, and perhaps his most elaborate. Help on which he had depended
                    having failed him, he was left to do the work almost alone, and it is supposed
                    that his excessive labour in connection with it hastened his end. He died at St
                    Andrews, where he had built a pleasant residence for himself several years
                    previously, on the 17th March 1871. Two years before his death the university of
                    St Andrews had conferred upon him the degree of Doctor of Laws, in consideration
                    of his distinguished literary merit, and he was a fellow of several learned
                    societies. As a writer Chambers possessed in very harmonious combination most of
                    the qualities which form the basis of a sound and lasting popularity. Few even
                    of popular authors ever possessed in a higher degree the faculty of interesting
                    without resorting to sensation, of amusing without stooping to frivolity, and of
                    instructing without assuming superiority. Few have done more than he for the
                    illustration of Scottish life and character, and for the preservation of what
                    was curious in Scottish tradition and antiquities. But it will always be his
                    highest claim to distinction that he did as much as, if not more than, any other
                    single man to give a healthy tone and a pure moral influence to the cheap
                    popular literature which has become so important a factor in modern
                    civilization. An interesting account of the life of Robert Chambers by his
                    brother appeared in 1872, under the title, <hi rend="italic">Memoir of Robert
                    Chambers: With Autobiographic Reminiscences of William Chambers.</hi> (w. B.
                    s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
