<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0401-0390-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHÁNDÁ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 390</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9jd0w">Muhammadans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHÁNDÁ</label>, a district of British India, in the Nágpur
                    division of the Central Provinces, situated between 19° 7' and 20° 5Γ N. lat.,
                    and 78° 5Γ and 80° 5Γ E. long. It is bounded on the N. by the districts of
                    Ráipur, Bhandåra, and Wardhá, on the E. by Bastár and Ráipur, on the S. by
                    Sironchá, and on the W. by the Wardhá and Pranhítá rivers, which divide it from
                    Berar and the Hyderabad territory. Excepting in the extreme west, hills are
                    thickly dotted over the country, sometimes in detached ranges, occasionally in
                    isolated peaks rising sheer out from the plain. Towards the east they increase
                    in height, and form a broad table-land, at places 2000 feet above sea-level. The
                    Waíngaiigá River flows through the district from north to south, meeting the
                    Wardhá River at Seoní, where their streams unite to form the Pranhítá. The
                    census of 1872 returns the total area of the district at 9700 square miles, and
                    the population at 534,431 souls, residing in 2392 villages and townships, and
                    dwelling in 108,258 houses. Of the total population, 397,540, or 74 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 39 per cent., are Hindus; 8176, or 1 ’ 52 per cent.,
                    Muhammadans; 648 or ’ 12 per cent., Buddhists and Jains; 89, or O2 per cent.,
                    Christians; and 127,978, or 23 ’ 95 per cent., aboriginal tribes and people
                    returned in the census report under the heading of “others.” Two towns in the
                    district are returned as containing a population of upwards of 5000 souls; viz.,
                    Chándá, population 16,233, and Armorí, population 5271. Of the total area of the
                    district, 9700 square miles, only 988 were actually under cultivation in
                    1873-74, 5200 square miles being returned as cultivable, and 3509 as
                    uncultivable waste. The principal crops are rice, wheat, oil-seeds, sugar-cane,
                    and cotton. Within the last few years extensive coal and iron beds have been
                    discovered, and 20 mines were in operation in 1873-74. A branch line of railway
                    will shortly connect the Chándá coal-measures with the Bombay railway system.
                    Dense woods cover the country. Teak grows everywhere; and in the Government
                    forests, in the eastern part of the district, it attains a large size. The chief
                    manufacture of the district is cotton cloths, both of coarse and fine quality,
                    which are largely exported to Western India. Silkworm breeding is largely
                    carried on, and silk or silk and cotton fabrics are woven. Iron smelting is an
                    important branch of industry. The district trade is conducted at annual fairs,
                    which are held at the towns of Chándá, Bhándak, Chimur, Márkandí, and Warhá, and
                    are numerously attended by visitors from all parts of India. The sales effected
                    at these fairs in 1868-69 amounted to £152,224.</p>
                <p>Chándá is thickly studded with fine tanks, or rather artificial lakes, formed by
                    closing the outlets of small valleys, or by throwing a dam across tracts
                    intersected by streams. The broad clear sheets of water thus created are often
                    very picturesque in their surroundings of wood and rock. The chief architectural
                    objects of interest are the cave temples at Bhándak, Winjbásaní, Dewálá, and
                    Ghugus; a rock temple in the bed of the Wardhá River below Ballálpur; the
                    ancient temples at Márkandí, Ambgáon, and elsewhere; the forts of Wairágarh and
                    Ballálpur; and the old walls of the city of Chándá, its system of water-works,
                    and the tombs of the aboriginal Gond kings.</p>
                <p>The total revenue of the district in 1873-74 amounted to £38,922,10s., of which
                    £24,402 or 62 ’ 7 per cent., was derived from the land For the education of the
                    people, 67 schools, attended by 3347 pupils, were either entirely supported by
                    the state, or were subsidized under the grant-in-aid rules. For the relief of
                    the sick, 4 charitable dispensaries were maintained, at which 24,448 persons
                    were treated, at a total cost of £660, of which £439 was contributed by
                    Government. The annual rainfall at Chándá town averages 44 ’ 67 inches, but in
                    the hilly wooded region to the east it is considerably higher. The rainy season
                    lasts from the middle of June to the end of September, From the middle of
                    September to the close of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n402/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0402-0391"/> November fever of a malarious type pervails all
                    over the district. Cholera and smallpox are also common.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chăndá,</hi> the principal town in the district of the same
                    name, is situated in 19° 57' N. lat. and 79° 22' E. long., at the junction of
                    the Virái and Jharpat rivers. The town is surrounded by a wall of cut stone five
                    and a half miles in circuit, and crowned with battlements still in perfect
                    preservation. The town contains a total population of 16,233 souls, classified
                    as follows:—Hindus, 14,350; Muhammadans, 1294; Buddhists and Jains, 53;
                    Christians, 76; and “others,” 460. The municipal revenue in 1871 was £ 1120. The
                    population of the town is chiefly Marhattá and Telingá; the traders,
                    shopkeepers, and craftsmen belong to the latter. The principal manufactures are
                    coarse and fine cotton cloths, silk fabrics, brass utensils, leather slippers,
                    and bamboo work. The town is the seat of considerable external trade, the value
                    of the imports in 1868-69 being returned at £178,044, and the exports at
                    £114,342. The civil station lies a little to the north of the city, having the
                    military cantonments to the west, with the civil lines in the centre and
                    east.</p>
                <p>i CHANDARN AGAR <hi rend="italic">(popa</hi> ∖ <hi rend="italic">sx</hi> ∖ <hi
                    rend="italic">yChundernagord),</hi> aFrench settlement, with a small adjoining
                    territory, situated on the right bank of the River Húglí, 20 miles above
                    Calcutta, in 22’ 51' 40" N. lat. and 88° 24' 50" E. long. Chandarnagar has
                    played an important part in the European history of Bengal. It became a French
                    settlement towards the close of the 17th century, but did not rise to any
                    importance till the time of Dupleix, during whose administration more than two
                    thousand brick-houses were erected in the town, and a considerable maritime
                    trade was carried on. In 1757, Chandarnagar was bombarded by an English fleet
                    and captured; the fortifications and houses were afterwards demolished. On peace
                    being established, the town was restored to the French in 1763. When hostilities
                    afterwards broke out in 1794, it was again taken possession of by the English,
                    and was held by them till 1816, when it was a second time given up to the
                    French; it has ever since remained in their possession. All the former
                    commercial grandeur of Chandarnagar has now passed away, and at present it is
                    little more than a quiet suburb of Calcutta, without any external trade. The
                    European town is situated at the bottom of a beautiful reach of the Húglí, with
                    clean wide thoroughfares, and many elegant residences along the river bank. The
                    total area of the territory is only 2330 acres, including a few villages outside
                    the town. The authorities of Chandarnagar are subject to the general
                    jurisdiction of the Governor-General of Pondicherrí, to whom is confided the
                    general government of all the French possessions in India.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
