<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0788-0775-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CIDER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 775</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:861302">Cider</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1083878">Pulping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1011191">Mass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:829573">Beech</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4833mz7m">Beech</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pc8j">Cider</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s24s">Mass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7751w">Press</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n788/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CIDER</label>, an alcoholic beverage obtained by the
                    fermentation of the juice of apples. The manufacture is chiefly carried on by
                    the cultivators of the fruit, and it has been conducted from very remote times
                    in Hereford, Worcester, Gloucester, Somerset, and Devonshire in England, and in
                    Normandy in France. Cider is also largely prepared and consumed in Upper
                    Austria, Wurtemberg, in the districts of the Maine and the Moselle, and in
                    Holland; and it is besides a common beverage in the New England and Western
                    States of America. In the south-west of England the most esteemed varieties of
                    apple cultivated for cidermaking are the Royal Wilding, the Foxwhelp, White
                    Normandy Beech, Yellow Sty re, Handsome Mandy, and Skyrme’s Kernel. For a
                    superior quality of cider the large well matured apples of several varieties are
                    selected, and are ground up to a fine pulp either in an old-fashioned cider
                    mill, or in one of several newer machines which have been introduced for pulping
                    the fruit. The old form of mill consists of a circular trough around which a
                    huge heavy stone wheel or runner, weighing about a ton, is drawn by a horse.
                    Into the trough a charge of apples, to the amount of from 8 to 10 bushels, is
                    thrown, and the mill is kept in motion till the whole mass is reduced to a fine
                    uniform pulp, which is technically called “the cheese.” The old-fashioned mills
                    are now generally superseded by modem inventions, of which Coleman’s cider press
                    may be taken as the type. It consists of two pairs of rollers mounted in a
                    strong wooden frame. The first and upper pair are of hard wood, studded with
                    iron teeth or knives, set immediately under a hopper into which the fruit is
                    fed. In passing between the first pair the fruit is sliced into small pieces
                    which fall between the second pair of rollers, placed immediately below. These
                    consist of heavy cylinders of stone set quite close so that the opposing
                    surfaces press against each other, and the sliced apples in passing between them
                    are bruised to a fine pulp which is received into a trough placed directly
                    under. The pulp or cheese is, or ought to be, laid aside for at least a night to
                    allow fermentation to set in before the juice is expressed. By this means the
                    aromatic oil contained in the seeds is extracted, communicating its aroma to the
                    mass, and a richer, fuller-flavoured beverage is the result. The cheese is
                    placed in hair-cloths in a strong framed box for expressing the juice, an
                    operation which must be gently and carefully performed, so that the liquid may
                    be obtained as pure and clear as possible. The juice ought to have a specific
                    gravity of from 1O7 to 1 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 08, and should contain
                    10 or 11 per cent, of sugar and 0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 6 to 0 ’ 7 per
                    cent, of malic acid. The liquor is strained and placed for fermenting either in
                    large vats or in separate casks. In the fermentation which ensues an abundant
                    sediment is thrown to the bottom and a scum rises to the surface. In a week or
                    ten days this action should leave the liquid clear and bright if the
                    fermentation has continued steady and moderate. The liquidis then racked off
                    into casks, as free as possible from scum and sediment, and excluded from
                    atmospheric influence to stop the further action of the ferment. If in the early
                    part of the following spring it is found to be still clear, nothing further is
                    required except to cask it up for the market; but should it have become thick
                    and ropy it must be “fined” either by means of isinglass or with stewed and
                    mashed apples. It is frequently found necessary, in order effectually to stop
                    fermentation, to expose the liquor to the influence of sulphurous acid gas,
                    which is done by burning a sulphur tipped stick inside a cask half filled with
                    cider, and shaking the cask so as to make the liquor absorb the acid gas. Such
                    “matched” cider is readily detected by connoisseurs. The artificial colouring of
                    cider, when practised, is done either with burnt sugar, the juice of red beet,
                    logwood, or cochineal; and in Germany a flavour is sometimes communicated to the
                    beverage with elder flowers, cinnamon, cloves, or other aromatics. The following
                    analysis of a pint of common cider such as is supplied to agricultural labourers
                    in Somersetshire is by Dr Voelcker :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8292∙41 grs.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Alcohol</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>367 ∙69</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Grape Sugar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>31∙67</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Gum and extractive matter</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>45 05</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Albuminous compounds</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙94</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Malic Acid</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44'86</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ash</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18∙38</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8802 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                            00 grs</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Cider is very prone to undergo acetous fermentation, and develop a rough, sharp,
                    vinegary taste; and in that condition its consumption readily causes diarrhoea
                    and colic. Roughness may be much reduced by treatment with various compounds
                    prepared for the purpose which contain lime, or by the addition of a quantity of
                    hops boiled with treacle or honey to the acetified cider. When sound it is a
                    wholesome, agreeable, and refreshing stimulant beverage. In Germany a spirit,
                    apple brandy, is distilled from cider.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
