<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0290-0279-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAXTON, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 279</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:834091">Blades</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1016921">Mercerization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cs84">Mercerization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n290/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAXTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label> (1422-c.
                    1491), the introducer of printing into England, was born, as he tells us
                    himself, in “Kent in the Weide.” The date of his birth is uncertain; Oldys
                    places it in 1412, while his most recent biographer, Mr Blades, shows that it
                    could not have been much later than 1423. The latter, however, fixes upon 1422-3
                    as the approximate date; and this appears to be as near correctness as we are
                    likely to attain. 1412 seems too early; for, by the records of the Mercers’
                    Company we find that in 1438 William Caxton was apprenticed to Robert Large; and
                    it is far more likely that he was apprenticed at sixteen than at twenty-six.
                    Robert Large was a man of great wealth and of high position; in 1430 he was
                    sheriff, and in 1439 he celebrated his election to the office of Lord Mayor with
                    extraordinary splendour; and the fact that Caxton was apprenticed to a merchant
                    of such distinction makes it nearly certain that he belonged to a family of
                    considerable influence. In 1449 his master died; and it became the duty of his
                    executors to place Caxton where he could fulfil the term of his apprenticeship.
                    They sent him to Bruges; at least, we know that he was there soon after. In this
                    town he entered into business on his own account, and prospered so well that
                    before 1450 he was considered substantial security for £110, which would be
                    equivalent to £1000 at the present time; and eight years later he had become
                    governor of the Company of Merchant Adventurers. Caxton appears to have been a
                    man of considerable polish, and to have had a high reputation for sagacity; for
                    in 1465, the treaty with the duke of Burgundy concerning the wool trade being
                    about to expire, he was appointed by the king, along with Sir Richard Whitehill,
                    to negotiate its renewal; and this attempt having failed, he was again sent on a
                    similar mission three years later by the Mercers’ Company, after the marriage of
                    the duke to the sister of King Edward IV. In the next year, which is worthy of
                    note as that in which he commenced his <hi rend="italic">Recuyell</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Histoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de Troye,</hi> he was
                    considered worthy to share in the gift of the “vin d’honneur,” which was
                    presented by the authorities of Bruges only to the most important men in the
                    city. In the autumn of 1470 Caxton obtained, and availed himself of, an
                    excellent opportunity for acquiring favour and influence in the English court;
                    for Edward IV. had, with his supporters, been driven into exile, and had taken
                    refuge in Bruges, at the court of his brother-in-law, the duke of Burgundy.</p>
                <p>In 1471 Caxton, perhaps because he was beginning to find the duties of the office
                    which he held too severe for his declining strength, or it may be because the
                    interruption in the wool trade to which we have referred had diminished his
                    fortune, entered the service of the duchess of Burgundy, from whom he received a
                    yearly pension. At her command he continued the <hi rend="italic">Recuyell,</hi>
                    which was finished in September of that year.</p>
                <p>About this time Caxton learned the art of printing. Wynkyn de Worde, his
                    disciple, says that he was taught at Cologne by Ulric Zell; but Worde is often
                    inaccurate, and he seems rather to have had Colard Mansion as his master. That
                    printer was at Bruges; what need then for Caxton to go to Cologne î Besides
                    Caxton’s types are more like Mansion’s than Zell’s; and, indeed, it was long
                    before he adopted the improvements which the latter introduced.</p>
                <p>At what date Caxton brought his press to England and set it up at Westminster is
                    quite uncertain. It was probably between 1471 and 1477. 1474 is the date of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Game and Playe of Chesse</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but the
                    tradition that this work was printed in England may not be correct. He received
                    valuable patronage, being employed by Edward ΓV., Richard III., and Henry VII.,
                    by the duchess of Somerset, the earl of Arundel, Sir John Fastolf, and other
                    nobles; and he appears to have been busy writing and printing up to his death,
                    which occurred about 1492.</p>
                <p>Of Caxton’s private life and character we know very <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n291/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0291-0280"/> little. Hia temper seema to have been strongly
                    conservative; he delighted in the glories of chivalry, and declared that he
                    would rejoice in a new crusade which should prevent its decay. This disposition
                    was also displayed in his great slowness to adopt reforms in typography. He
                    appears to have been a shrewd and courtly man of business, and a scholar of
                    considerable attainments, for he was acquainted with French, Latin, and Dutch,
                    and was master of an English style which is both pleasant and vigorous.</p>
                <p>For an account of his typography, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Printing.</hi> His
                    life has been written by Oldys in the <hi rend="italic">Biographia
                    Britannica,</hi> by Lewis (1738), by Charles Knight, and by Mr Blades.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
