<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0066-0055-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAPET</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 55</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1747995">Heiresses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50fz6v">Carlovingians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4610w100">Rulers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAPET</label>, the name of a family, to which, for nearly
                    nine centuries, belonged the kings of France and many of the rulers of the most
                    powerful fiefs in that country, and which mingled with several of the other
                    royal races of Europe.</p>
                <p>The first of the Capets known in history was Robert the Strong, a Saxon who
                    received from Charles the Bald the county of Anjou, and, later, in 861, the
                    duchy of the He de France, and who gained popularity by his repulse of the
                    marauding Normans. The most distinguished of his successors were Eudes, Robert,
                    Rudolph, who succeeded to the dukedom of Burgundy in 888, 922, and 923
                    respectively, and Hugh the Great, count of Paris and Orleans, duke of France and
                    Burgundy, who held vast domains from the Loire to the frontiers of Picardy. His
                    son, Hugh Capet (987-996), being supported by the Normans and by his brother,
                    the duke of Burgundy, was, in 987, elected king by acclamation, and crowned at
                    Rheims, in place of the Carlovingians, who were hated for their German manners
                    and their desire to reconstruct the empire. The Capets, on the contrary, for
                    some time avoided all such pretensions, and carefully maintained friendship with
                    the church and the nobles, among whom they claimed to be no more than <hi
                    rend="italic">primi</hi><hi rend="italic">inter pares,</hi> and over whom they
                    scarcely attempted to exert the slightest authority. By following this policy,
                    they firmly established themselves on the throne, the influence of which they
                    greatly extended by marriages, treaties, and conquests, and which the family
                    continued to hold, after the failure of the direct royal line, at the death of
                    Charles IV. in 1322, by the accession of the indirect lines of Valois, which
                    reigned from 1322 to 1589, and of Bourbon, the last monarchical dynasty of
                    France (see <hi rend="smallcaps">France).</hi></p>
                <p>The royal house of Valois was founded by Philip VI., son of Charles de Valois,
                    second son of Philip III. (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Valois)</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">;</hi> and the house of Bourbon (whose family name was Capet)
                    was connected with the Capets by the marriage, in 1272, of Robert, the sixth son
                    of Louis IX., to Beatrice, the sole heiress of Agnes of Bourbon and the duke of
                    Burgundy (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bourbon).</hi></p>
                <p>Scarcely second in importance to the royal house is the branch to which belonged
                    the dukes of Burgundy. In the 1Oth century Burgundy fell into the hands of Hugh
                    the Great, father of Hugh Capet, who gave it, in 956, to his son Otho, and in
                    965 to his son Henry. In 1032 the second son of Robert the Pious, and grandson
                    of Hugh Capet, founded the first ducal house, which ruled till 1361. For two
                    years the duchy was in the hands of the Crown, but in 1363, the second ducal
                    house, also Capetian, was founded by Philip the Bold, son of king John (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Burgundy).</hi> * This branch of the Capets is also
                    distinguished by its union with the royal house of Austria, through the marriage
                    of Mary, daughter of Charles the Bold of Burgundy, to Maximilian, the
                    archduke.</p>
                <p>Of great importance also was the house of Anjou, which was founded by Charles,
                    brother of Louis IX., Anjou having been ceded, with other provinces, by John of
                    England to Philip Augustus, the grandfather of Charles. For an account of the
                    counts and dukes of Anjou see <hi rend="smallcaps">Anjou.</hi> Members of this
                    family sat upon the thrones of three kingdoms. The counts of Anjou were also
                    kings of Naples from 1226 to 1382; in 1309 Charles Robert of Anjou was elected
                    king of Hungary, his claim being based upon the marriage of his ancestor with
                    the daughter of Stephen IV. of Hungary; and, in 1445, Margaret,daughter of Duke
                    René, married Henry VI. of England.</p>
                <p>A third branch formed the house of Artois, which was founded, in 1226, by Robert
                    the Illustrious, grandson of Philip Augustus, who gained possession of Artois by
                    his marriage with Isabella of Hainault. This house merged in that of Valois, in
                    1383, by the marriage of Margaret of Artois with Philip the Hardy.</p>
                <p>The throne of Navarre was also filled by the Capets. In 1284 its heiress, Jane,
                    became the wife of Philip the Fair of France, and the two kingdoms were united
                    till Philip of Valois ascended the French throne, when its queen, Jane, daughter
                    of Louis X., married (1328) into the house of Evreux (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Navarre).</hi></p>
                <p>In the 13th century the throne of Constantinople was occupied by a branch of the
                    Capets,—Pierre, eighth son of Louis VI., having obtained that dignity as
                    brother-in-law of Baldwin count of Flanders (who was appointed emperor by the
                    Crusaders in 1204) and of his successor Henry. Pierre was succeeded by his two
                    sons, Robert and Baldwin de Courtenai, from the latter of whom Constantinople
                    was recovered by the Greeks in 1261.</p>
                <p>The counts of Dreux, for two centuries and a half (1132-1377), and the counts of
                    Evreux, from 1307 to 1425, also belonged to the family of the Capets,—other
                    members of which worthy of mention are the Dunois and the Longuevilles,
                    illegitimate branches of the house of Valois, which produced many famous
                    warriors and courtiers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
