<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0353-0342-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CENTRAL PROVINCES (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    342)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9jd0w">Muhammadans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n353/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CENTRAL PROVINCES</label>, a Chief-Commissionership of
                    British India, situated between 17° 50' and 24:° 30' N. lat., and between 76°
                    and 85° E. long., comprising an area of 84,078 square miles, and a population
                    returned by the census of 1872 at 8,201,519. The Chief-Commissionership was
                    constituted in 1861, when the territories previously known as the Nágpur
                    Province and the Ságar and Nerbudda Territories were united under the name of
                    the Central Provinces. This large tract, comprising almost every variety of soil
                    and of physical aspect, and inhabited by races of very diverse origin, is
                    bounded on the N. by the feudatory state of Rewah, by the small native states of
                    Bundelkhand, and by the district of Lálatpur in the North-Western Provinces; on
                    the N. and E. by the Chhotá Nágpur division, the Orissa tributary states, and
                    the northern districts of Madras; on the S. by the Godávarí district; and on the
                    S.W., W., and N.W. by the Nizám’s dominions, the Berar districts, and the states
                    comprising the Central India Agency. The Central Provinces are divided into four
                    divisions or commissionerships,—Nágpur, Jabalpur,Nerbudda,and Chhatïsgarh,
                    comprising 19 British districts. Two districts, Ságar and Damoh, lie parallel to
                    each other upon the Vindhyan table-land. To the south of them, in the valley of
                    the Nerbudda and its tributaries, are the districts of Mandlá, Jabalpur,
                    Narsinhpur, Hoshangábád, and a part of Nimár, the rest of it being in the valley
                    of the Tapti. The next range of districts continuing southwards includes Betul,
                    Chhindwárá, Seoni, and Bálághát, occupying the Sátpurá table-land, and attaining
                    a height of about 2000 feet. Still further to the south is the great Nágpur
                    plain, formed by the valleys of the Wardhá and Waingangá, and comprising the
                    districts of Nágpur, Wardhá, Bhandárá, and Chándá. To the east is the
                    Chhatísgarh plain, a low plateau of red soil, containing the districts of
                    Ráipur, Biláspur, and Sambalpur. Last of all, in the extreme south, and almost
                    cut off by forests and wild semi-independent states, is a long strip of
                    territory lining the left bank of the Godávarí, and known as the Upper Godávarí
                    district.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Physical Geography and Scenery.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    The official compiler of the statistical account of the Central Provinces thus
                    describes the physical aspects of the country :—“Within comparatively narrow
                    limits, a plateau and a plain follow each other, and again, in similar sequence,
                    a larger plateau and a larger plain, ending in a mass of hill and forest, which
                    is probably the wildest part of the whole Indian peninsula. Even the
                    continuously leveI portions of this area are broken by isolated peaks and
                    straggling hill ranges; while.its rugged formation and rapid slopes give to the
                    greatest rivers which rise in it, such as the Nerbudda and Tapti, something of
                    the character of mountain torrents. Though the scenery is on too small a scale
                    to compare in sublimity with that of the Himálayas, it is on the other hand as
                    far removed from the monotony of the plains of Hindustán. Not only is it
                    characterized by a constant variety of form and level, but it possesses a
                    diversity of colour peculiar to itself. In no other part of India are the
                    changes of soil and vegetation more rapid and marked than in theNerbudda
                    country. In the pleasant winter months, the eye may range over miles of green
                    corn lands, only broken by low, black, boundary ridges or dark twisting
                    footpaths. The horizon is bounded here and there by hill ranges, which seem to
                    rise abruptly from the plains, but on coming nearer to them, the heavy green of
                    their slopes is found to be divided from the softer hues of the young wheat by
                    broad belts of gravelly soil studded with fine trees. On the Sátpurá plateau the
                    alternations of scenery are even more frequent than in the low country. The
                    hills are higher and more abrupt, the black soil deposits are deeper, and the
                    water supply more abundant. Hence in the midst of the grim rolling plateaus of
                    basalt, there may often be found little valleys cultivated like gardens,—oases
                    of sugar-cane and opium, which, but for their inaccessibility, would tempt away
                    the best cultivators of the plains. It is thought that in some of these upland
                    basins, tea, coffee, and other delicate plants might be raised with success, but
                    the obstacles which have so long retarded the settlement of these plateaus,
                    though partially smoothed away, still exist, and can only be surmounted by
                    patient and continued energy. Much has been done to open out the country of late
                    years. Railways from both coasts now connect the plateau with the eastern and
                    western seaboards, and form the central link of communication between Calcutta
                    and Bombay.”</p>
                <p>The principal rivers of the Central Provinces are the Nerbudda, Tapti, Wardhá,
                    and Waingangá, but, owing to falls and rocky rapids, they are navigable only at
                    certain times of the year and for short distances, As a means of communication
                    they are practically useless. The chief lines of road are the following :—</p>
                <p>(1) From Jabalpur to Ságar <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Damoh, 116 miles; (2) from
                    Jabalpur to Ráipur <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Mandlá, 203 miles; (3) from Ságar
                    to Karell on the Great Indian Peninsular Railway, 76 miles; (4) from Narsinhpur
                    to Chhindwárá, 91 miles; (5) from Hoshangabad to Betul, 681 milθs; (6) from
                    Nágpur to Ráipur, J 74 miles; (7) from Nágpur to Chhindwárá, 78 miles; (8) from
                    Nágpur to Betul, 1041 miles; (9) from Nágpur to Chándá, 96 miles; (10) from
                    Ráipur to Sambalpur, 167 miles; (11) from Chándá to Sironchá, 121 miles.</p>
                <p>The country is intersected by the Great Indian Peninsular and East Indian
                    Railways. The Great Indian Peninsular Railway from Bombay enters the Central
                    Provinces near Barhanpur, and runs north-east to Jabalpur, where it joins the
                    East India line from Allahábád and Calcutta. A branch of the Great Indian
                    Peninsular Railway, which leaves the main line at Bhasáwal in Kandesh, enters
                    the Central Provinces at Wardhá, and runs to Nágpur. A state line is in course
                    of construction to connect this railway with the newly-opened coal-fields of
                    Chándá.</p>
                <p>The population of the 19 districts of the Central Provinces was returned by the
                    census of 1872 at 8,201,519, made up as follows:—Hindus 5,879,950, or 71*69 per
                    cent, of the total population; Muhammadans, 233,247, or2 <hi rend="superscript">
                        -</hi> 84 per cent; Buddhists and Jains, 36,569, or 0 ’ 45 per cent.;
                    Christians, 10,477, or 0 ’ 13 per cent.; and “others” (consisting chiefly of
                    Gonds and the original inhabitants of the country before they were driven back
                    by their Hindu conquerors), 2,041,276, or 24 ’ 89 per cent. The census report of
                    1872 returns 39 towns containing upwards of 5000 inhabitants. Of these 26 have
                    less than 10,000 inhabitants; 5 between 10,000 and 15,000; 3 between 15,000 and
                    20,000; 3 (Burhanpur, Ságar, and Kamthí) between 20,000 and 50,000; and only 2
                    (Nágpur and Jabalpur) over 50,000, the former having a population of 84,441, and
                    the latter of 55,188.</p>
                <p>Of the total surveyed and assessed area of the British territory 12,352,473 acres
                    were returned in 1873-74 as actually under cultivation, 12,220,845 acres as
                    cultivable but not under tillage, 1,365,071 acres as grazing lands, and
                    10,885,296 as uncultivable waste. Wheat, rice, and cotton are the principal
                    agricultural staples. The recently-discovered coal-fields and iron-beds in the
                    Wardhá Valley <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n354/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0354-0343"/> and the Chándá district promise to open a new
                    era of prosperity for the country.</p>
                <p>The improved means of communication afforded by the railways and roads have
                    rapidly developed the trade of the Central Provinces. In 1863-64 the imports and
                    exports were valued at about four millions sterling. In 1868-69 their value had
                    risen to six and three-quarter millions sterling. In 1873-74 the ascertained
                    imports of the Central Provinces amounted to 117,761 tons, value £4,399,134, and
                    the exports to 209,157 tons, value £3,148,598; total of imports and exports
                    326,918 tons, value £7,547,732.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The executive
                    authority at Nágpur vests in the chief-commissioner and agent to the
                    GovernorGeneral. He is assisted by a secretary and staff, a judicial
                    commissioner, a settlement commissioner, a sanitary commissioner, a commissioner
                    of customs, four commissioners of revenue and circuit, an inspector-general of
                    police, an inspector-general of public instruction, an inspector-general of
                    jails anddispensaries, a conservator of forests, and a registrargeneral of
                    assurances, who is also commissioner of excise and superintendent of stamps. A
                    commissioner presides over each of the four divisions, with a
                    deputy-commissioner and assistants in each of the nineteen districts, all
                    subordinate to the chief-commissioner at Nágpur, The total revenue of the
                    Central Provinces in 1873-74 amounted to £1,260,977, of which £1,057,021 was
                    derived from imperial, and £203,956 from provincial taxation. The civil
                    expenditure in the same year amounted to £904,670, of which £440,232 was on
                    imperial, and £464,438 on provincial account. Of the total revenue £603,056, or
                    just one-half, was derived from the land. There were 196 criminal and 119 civil
                    courts at work in 1873-74. The regular police consisted of a force of 7539
                    officers and men, besides a municipal police of 988. The total cost of the
                    regular and municipal police in 1873-74 amounted to £130,674. The troops
                    quartered in the Central Provinces are as follows Europeans—3 batteries of
                    artillery (with 18 guns), and 2 regiments and 1 company of infantry; natives—2
                    regiments of cavalry and 6∣∙ regiments of infantry. The European troops numbered
                    2462, and the native troops 5475, giving a total of 7937 officers and men, kept
                    up at a cost of £277,781. For the education of the people Government maintains,
                    or subsidizes under its grant-in-aid system, 1532 schools, attended in 1873-74
                    by 76,781 pupils, and-maintained at a total cost of £55,734, to which the state
                    contributed £31,628, or over one-half. These schools are exclusive of private
                    institutions not receiving support from the state.</p>
                <p>Besides the 19 British districts of the Central Provinces described in the
                    foregoing paragraphs, and to which alone the above statistics refer, there are
                    also 15 small feudatory states, comprising a total area of 28,834 square miles,
                    with a population of 1,049,710 souls, made up as follows :—Hindus, 638,187;
                    Muhammadans, 7718; Buddhists and Jains, 14; Christians, 5; and “others”
                    (consisting of aboriginal tribes), 403,786. The following are the details of
                    area population, revenue, &amp;c., of each of these states as officially
                    returned in 1874-5 :—(l.)Bastár: area, 13,062 square miles; population, 78,856;
                    supposed gross revenue, £9213, 10s.; annual tribute to the British Government,
                    £305, 12s. (2.) Karond: area, 3745 square miles; population, 133,483; estimated
                    revenue, £2000; tribute, £355. (3.) Kaigarh-Bargarh: area, 1486 square miles;
                    population, 63,304; estimated revenue, £750; tribute, £40. (4.) Sarangarh: area,
                    540 square miles; population, 37,091; estimated revenue, £800; tribute, £135.
                    (5.) Pátná (under British management): area, 2399 square miles; population,
                    98,636; estimated revenue, £2500; tribute, £60. (6.) Sonpur: area, 906 square
                    miles; population, 130,713; estimated revenue, £1800; tribute, £500. (7.)
                    RairáKhol: area, 833 square miles; population, 12,660; estimated revenue, £600;
                    tribute, £58. (8.) Bámrá: area, 1988 square miles; population, 53,613; estimated
                    revenue, £600; tribute, £35. (9.) Sakti: area, 115 square miles; population,
                    8394; estimated revenue, £813; tribute, £35. (10.) Kawardo: area, 887 square
                    miles; population, 75,462; estimated revenue, £5356;tribute, £1600. (11.) Kondá
                    or Chhuikhádán: area, 174 square miles; population, 29,590; estimated revenue,
                    £2203; tribute, £1100. (12.) Kánker: area, 1000 square miles; population,
                    43,552; estimated revenue, £1500; pays no tribute. (13.) Khairágarh (under
                    British management): area, 940 square miles; population, 122,264; estimated
                    revenue, £11,763; tribute, £4700. (14.) Nandgáon: area, 884 square miles;
                    population, 148,454; estimated revenue, £8595; tribute, £4600. (15.) Makrái:
                    area, 215 square miles; population, 13,648; estimated revenue, £2200; pays no
                    tribute.</p>
                <p>Including the 19 British districts and the 15 small feudatory states, the Central
                    Provinces comprise a total area of 113,797 square miles, and have a population
                    of 9,251,229 souls, made upas follows Hindus, 6,518,137, or 70 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 46 per cent; Muhammadans, 240,965, or 2 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 60 per cent.; Buddhists and Jains, 36,583, or 0
                        <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 40 per cent.; Christians, 10,482, or 0T1 per
                    cent.; and “others,” 2,445,062, or 26 ’ 43 per cent. (w. w. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
