<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0127-0116-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARMELITES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 116</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1061193">Phoca</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1041386">Nuns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:904324">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49k4610p">Phoca</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4cq9f">Elections</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kq6z">Nuns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n127/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARMELITES</label>, one of the four orders of Mendicant
                    Friars. It is perhaps difficult to say whether upon the whole the Franciscans or
                    the Carmelites have invented and propagated the more monstrous fictions
                    respecting their own commencements and subsequent story. But as regards the very
                    tender point of their first foundation, the latter must be admitted to have
                    distanced their competitors. For the history of the Franciscans at least
                    commences with a basis of solid and indubitable historical fact, whereas in the
                    case of the Carmelites we plunge at once into the region of fable, and fable of
                    the most monstrous kind. Mount Carmel is celebrated in Scripture as the abode of
                    Elijah and Elisha, the former of whom the Carmelites claim as their founder.
                    Elijah, or Elias, say the writers of the order, became a monk under the ministry
                    of angels; and his first disciples were Jonah, Micah, and Obadiah. They declare
                    further that the wife of the latter, having bound herself by a vow of chastity,
                    received the veil from the hands of Elias himself, and became the first abbess
                    of the Carmelite female order. They tell us also that Pythagoras was a member of
                    this order, and that he had on Mount Carmel several conversations with the
                    Prophet Daniel on the subject of the Trinity. They further assert that the
                    Virgin Mary and Christ himself assumed the habit and profession of
                    Carmelites.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For a full
                    account of all these absurdities, see a very curious work, printed at Paris in
                    1751, but with the date of Berlin, entitled <hi rend="italic">Ordres
                    M(mastiques, Histoire extraite de tous les Auteurs qui ont conservé à la
                    postérité ce qu'il y a de vlus curieux dans chaque Ordre.</hi></p></note> We
                    first, however, reach the solid ground of something like history in the account
                    left by Phocas, a Greek monk of the Isle of Patmos, who visited the Holy Land in
                    1185, and who concludes the narrative of his journeying by relating that the
                    cave of Elias was then visible on Mount Carmel, and that there had existed there
                    a large monastery, as might still be seen from the remains of the buildings;
                    that some years previously a monk in priest’s orders, with white hair, had
                    arrived there, coming from Calabria, and had established himself there in
                    obedience to orders given him by Elias in a vision. He made, continues Phocas, a
                    small enclosure among the ruins of the monastery, and built a bell tower and a
                    little church. He then collected about ten companions, with whom, concludes
                    Phocas, he still continues to live there. To these recluses, Albert, bishop of
                    Vercelli, who had become patriarch of Constantinople, gave a “rule” about the
                    year 1209. And this must be considered to constitute the foundation of the
                    Carmelite order.</p>
                <p>This rule consists of only sixteen articles; and it appears from it that the
                    monks on Mount Carmel were at that time eremitical, dwelling in separate little
                    houses. The lodging of the prior was placed at the entrance into the enclosure,
                    and the church was in the middle of the enclosed space. The rule contains the
                    ordinary injunctions and prohibitions as regards masses and other services to be
                    heard or said, and kinds of food to be avoided, with some unimportant
                    specialities of dates and seasons. Albert further enjoined on them to labour
                    constantly with their hands, and to practise much silence. This rule was
                    approved by Pope Honorius III. in 1226.</p>
                <p>It is related that two English crusaders, John de Vesci and Richard de Grey,
                    carried some of the recluses on Mount Carmel with them to England, and founded
                    the first Carmelite monastery in England at Alnwick. Much about the same
                    time—nearly the middle of the 13th century—Louis IX. of France, on his return
                    from the Crusades, took with him to Paris some of the Mount Carmel monks, and
                    established them under the name of Carmelites in a monastery there. Others
                    passed from Mount Carmel into Italy and Spain under the special protection of
                    the popes. The number of their establishments was very rapidly and very largely
                    increased; and they held their first European general chapter at Aylesford in
                    England in 1245.</p>
                <p>The Carmelites, however, can refer to papal briefs, bulls, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n128/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0128-0117"/> and rescripts of a much earlier time, in which
                    their existence is recognized John V. (ob 686), Stephen V. (ob. 817), Leo IV
                    (ob. 855) Adrian II. (ob. 872), Sergius ILL (ob. 911), Gregory VII. (ob. 1085),
                    and Alexander III. (ob 1181) may be cited among the early popes who conferred
                    privileges or special indulgences on the order. They further quote John XXII.
                    (ob. 1334), Sixtus IV. (ob. 1484), Julius HL (ob. 1555), Kus V. (ob. 1572),
                    Gregory XIII. (ob 1585), Sixtus V. (ob. 1590), and Clement VIII. (ob. 1605) as
                    having all, in various documents, recognized the fact of their foundation by
                    Elias. And, lastly, Benedict XIII. in 1725, permitted the order to erect in St
                    Peter’s, among the statues of the founders of the religious orders, that of
                    Elias as their founder, with the inscription,— <hi rend="italic">Universus
                    Ordo</hi><hi rend="italic">Carmxlitarum</hi><hi rend="italic">fundatori suo
                    Sancto Eliae</hi><hi rend="italic">prophxtae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >erexit!</hi></p>
                <p>The term <hi rend="italic">Universus</hi> in the above legend is intended to
                    indicate that all the different branches of the order participated in the
                    erection of the statue, although they have become entirely separate societies
                    The monks of that portion of the order which had adhered to the ancient rule,
                    modified and mitigated, however, in some respects by Innocent IV. (ob. 1254),
                    and more largely by Eugenius IV. (ob. 1447), are termed Carmelites of the
                    Ancient Observance. Shortly after the changes made in the rule by Pope Eugenius
                    IV., several local reformations were effected in the order in different
                    countries,—one in France by the general Jean Soreth of Normandy in 1451, and
                    another in the congregation at Mantua, which rapidly spread itself, and, much to
                    the disgust of the general of that portion of the order which adhered to the old
                    rule, obtained from the Pontiff the right to elect a vicar-general of their own,
                    not subject to the jurisdiction or the approbation ot the general. Various other
                    partial reformations were effected, and the members of those congregations which
                    adopted them are styled “Reformed Carmelites.” But a more important, or at least
                    a more marked and decided division into two branches was brought about by one of
                    the most noteworthy personages in all the Catholic hagiology, Saint Teresa. This
                    extraordinary woman, a native of Avila, in old Castile, became a Carmelite nun
                    in a nunnery of the order in that city in 1535. She at once determined on
                    carrying out the rule in all its primitive strictness; but finding this
                    insufficient to satisfy her abounding zeal and ambition, she obtained in 1562 a
                    brief from Pope Pius IV. authorizing her to establish a separate branch of the
                    order, the more austere observances of which should be modelled according to her
                    own views. Very shortly several nunneries of “Barefoot Carmelite Nuns” were
                    established, mainly in Spain. Her success thus far soon led her to the more
                    ambitious project of introducing a similar reform among the Carmelite body of
                    the other s⅛χ. And this also she accomplished by the assistance of two or three
                    of the leading members of the Carmelite community. The members of the
                    communities which received this reformed rule, or which were founded for the
                    observance of it, were called Barefoot Carmelites <hi rend="italic">(Carmes
                    Déchaussés,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Carmelitani Scalzi),</hi> in distinction
                    to those of the older bodies. For some time, however, the monasteries and
                    nunneries of the Barefoot Carmelites remained subject to the general of the
                    parent body; till in 1580 Pope Gregory XIII. at the instance of Philip II. of
                    Spain, permitted them to elect their own provincial generals, who were, however,
                    still subject to the general of the entire order. But Sixtus V. having regard to
                    the greatly increased and increasing number of their establishments, granted
                    them, in 1587, the privilege of electing a vicar-general of their own. Finally,
                    Clement VIII., in 1593, separated them entirely from the other Carmelites,
                    empowered them to elect a general of their body, and constituted them a separate
                    Order of Friars Mendicant,—dispositions which were subsequently confirmed by
                    Gregory XV.</p>
                <p>The Carmelites originally wore white woollen dresses. But inasmuch as the
                    Orientals among whom they dwelt deemed this colour a mark of nobility, they
                    adopted striped dresses, specimens of which may still be seen in ancient
                    paintings, the colours of such stripes being sometimes white, grey, and black,
                    and sometimes white and dark brown. After their establishment in Europe,
                    however, these striped dresses were abandoned, and by the authority of Honorius
                    IV., they began in 1287 to wear a white cape and scapulary, which was, however,
                    shortly afterwards changed for dark brown. Over this dress they now wear a white
                    cloak and hood when they quit their convent.</p>
                <p>The device, both of the original body and of the Barefoot Carmelites, consists of
                    a mountain, topped by three stars, and above this a crown, from the middle of
                    which comes forth an arm grasping a sword. The mountain represents Mount Carmel;
                    the stars symbolize theVirgin— <hi rend="italic">Stella maris—</hi> to whom the
                    order is more especially dedicated; the crown figures forth her supremacy; the
                    arm is the •arm of Elias; and the sword it grasps is the token of his zeal. A
                    ∏ne drawn across the top of the mountain differentiates the device as used by
                    the Barefoot Carmelites. The order has been, and is indeed still, a very
                    wide-spread one, in all quarters of the globe.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
