<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0253-0242-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATTACK [Cuttack]</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 242</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9jd0w">Muhammadans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sk44">Deltas</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:890004">Deltas</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n253/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATTACK <hi rend="smallcaps">[Cuttack]</hi></label>, a
                    district of British India, in the province of Orissa, under the jurisdiction of
                    the Lieutenant-Governor of Bengal, in 20° N. lat., and 85° to 87° E. long. It is
                    bounded on the N. by the district of Balasor, from which it is separated by the
                    Baitaraní and Dhámrá rivers; on the E. by the Bay of Bengal, on the S. by the
                    district of Puri, and on the W. by the Orissa Tributary States. The district
                    comprises the nucleus or middle portion of the great delta formed by the
                    Mahánadí River, and consists of three distinct tracts;—first, a marshy woodland
                    strip along the coast, from 3 to 30 miles in breadth; second, an intermediate
                    stretch of rice plains; third, a broken hilly region, which forms the western
                    boundary of the district. The marshy strip along the coast, like the Bengal
                    Sundarbans, is covered with swamps and malariabreeding jungles, but lacks their
                    forest scenery. As one approaches the sea the solid land gives place to a vast
                    network of streams and creeks, whose sluggish waters are constantly depositing
                    silt, and forming morasses or quicksands. Cultivation does not begin till the
                    limits of this dismal region are passed. The intermediate rice plains stretch
                    inland for about 40 miles, and occupy the older part of the delta between the
                    sea-coast strip and the hilly frontier. They are intersected by four large
                    rivers, which dash down from the western mountains, and then split into
                    innumerable branches on the level delta. Their distributaries, after tortuous
                    interlacings, frequently rejoin the parent stream as it approaches the sea. This
                    intermediate tract is a region of rich cultivation, dotted with great banyan
                    trees, thickets of bamboos, exquisite palm foliage, and mango groves. The hilly
                    frontier separates the delta of British Orissa from the semi-independent
                    Tributary States. It consists of a series of ranges, 10 to 15 miles in length,
                    running nearly due east and west, with densely wooded slopes and lovely valleys
                    between. The timber, however, is small, and is of little value except as fuel.
                    The political character of these three tracts is as distinct as are their
                    natural features. The first and third are still occupied by feudal chiefs, and
                    have never been subjected to a regular land-settlement, by either the Musalmán
                    or the British Government. They pay a light tribute, now permanently fixed. The
                    intermediate rice plains, known as the Mughulbandf, from their having been
                    regularly settled by the .Muhammadans, have yielded to the successive dynasties
                    and conquerors of Orissa almost the whole of the revenues derived from the
                    province. The deltaic portions are of course a dead level; and the highest hills
                    within the district in the western or frontier tract do not exceed 2500 feet.
                    They are steep, and covered with jungle, but can be climbed by men. The most
                    interesting of them are the Assa range, with its sandal trees and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n254/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0254-0243"/> Buddhist remains; Udayagirí (Sunrise-hill), with
                    its colossal image of Buddha, sacred reservoir, and ruins; and Assagiri, with
                    its mosque of 1719. The Mahávi-nayaka Peak, visible from Cattack, has been
                    consecrated for ages to Siva-worship by ascetics and pilgrims.</p>
                <p>Cattack district takes its character from its rivers. These issue in magnificent
                    streams through three gorges in the hilly frontier. On the south, the Mahánadí,
                    literally the Great River, rushes down upon the delta from a narrow gully at
                    Naráj, about seven miles west of the town of Cattack. On the extreme north of
                    the district, the sacred Baitaraní, the Styx of the Hindus, emerges from a more
                    open country, and forms the boundary line between Cattack and Balasor. The
                    Bráhmaní enters the district about half way between the two. The Cattack delta
                    is thus divided into two great valleys, one of them lying between the Baitaraní
                    and the Bráhmaní, the other between the Bráhmaní and the Mahánadí. The rivers
                    having, by the silt of ages, gradually raised their beds, now run along high
                    levels. During floods they pour over their banks upon the surrounding valleys,
                    by a thousand channels which interlace and establish communication between the
                    main streams. As the rivers enter the district by three great gorges in the
                    hills, so, after numerous bifurcations they find their way into the sea by three
                    principal mouths. On the north, the Baitaraní and Bráhmaní debouch into the Bay
                    of Bengal, under the name of the Dhámrá, at Point Palmyras; while the Mahánadí,
                    after a variety of interlacings, forms two great estuaries,—one, bearing the
                    name of the Mahánadí, at False Point, and the other, called the Devi, in the
                    south-eastern corner of the district. Siltbanks and surf-washed bars render the
                    entrance to these rivers perilous. The best harbour in Cattack district is at
                    False Point, on the north of the Mahánadí estuary. It consists of an anchorage,
                    land-locked by islands or sandbanks, and with two fair channels navigable
                    towards the land. The Famine Commissioners in 1867 reported it to be the best
                    harbour on the coast of India from the Húglí to Bombay. The dearth of the
                    preceding year (1866) had led to the discovery of its value as a port for
                    throwing supplies into the starving province. The harbour is safe and roomy, and
                    the channel properly buoyed. The Dhámrá harbour, further up the coast, although
                    not so well protected, is more resorted to by native ships. Four canals have
                    been made through Cattack since 1862 for regulating and distributing the water
                    supply by means of irrigation, and for navigation. They are—the High Level
                    Canal, the Kendrápárá Canal, the Táldandá Canal, and the Mách-hgaon Canal, with
                    their respective distributaries. The High Level Canal is designed to provide a
                    great trade-route between Cattack and Calcutta, and to irrigate the country
                    through which it passes. The other three are intended for irrigation and as
                    navigable channels within the district. The canals were undertaken by the East
                    India Irrigation Company in 1862; but the company proving unable to continue the
                    works, Government purchased them on the 31st December 1869 for £941,368. Cattack
                    district is subject to destructive floods, and from time immemorial embankments
                    have been maintained along the sides of the rivers. In 1870 their aggregate
                    length was 680 miles.</p>
                <p>The district has an area of 3178 square miles, with a total population of
                    1,494,784, 95 per cent, of whom, or 1,430,040, are Hindus. The rest consist of
                    Muhammadans, 40,013; Christians, 2314; and persons of unspecified religion,
                    22,398. The last comprise the aboriginal tribes, who here, as elsewhere, cling
                    to their mountains and jungles. They chiefly consist of the Bhumij, Tálá, Koi,
                    and Savar peoples, the Savars being by far the most numerous, numbering 16,589
                    souls. They are regarded by the orthodox Hindus as little better than the beasts
                    of the wildernesses which they inhabit. Miserably poor, they subsist for the
                    most part by selling firewood or other products of their jungle; but a few of
                    them have patches of cultivated land, and many earn wages as day labourers to
                    the Hindus. They occupy, in fact, an intermediate stage of degradation between
                    the comparatively well-off tribes in the Tributary States (the stronghold and
                    home of the race), and the Páns, Báurís, Kandrás, and other semi-aboriginal
                    peoples on the lowlands, who rank as the basest castes of the Hindu community.
                    The great bulk of the Indo-Aryan or Hindu population consists of Uriyas, with a
                    residue of immigrant Bengalis, Lálá Káyets from Behar and Northern India,
                    Telingás from the Madras coast, Marhattás from Central and Western India, a few
                    Sikhs from the Punjab, and Marwárís from Rájputáná. The Muhammadans are chiefly
                    the descendants of the Patháns who took refuge in Orissa after the subversion of
                    their kingdom in Bengal by the Mughuls in the 16th century.</p>
                <p>Only three towns in Cattack district contained in 1872 upwards of 5000
                    inhabitants, viz., Cattack, the capital, 50,878; Jájpur, 10,753; Kendrápárá,
                    10,682. Jájpur was the capital of Orissa under its Hindu kings; it is still
                    considered a sacred town, and thousands of pilgrims annually flock to it.</p>
                <p>Rice forms the staple product of the district; its three chief varieties are <hi
                    rend="italic">biáH</hi> or early rice, <hi rend="italic">sárad</hi> or winter
                    rice, and <hi rend="italic">dálua</hi> or spring rice. The other cereal crops
                    consist of <hi rend="italic">mánduá</hi> (a grass-like plant producing a coarse
                    grain resembling rice), wheat, barley, and <hi rend="italic">chiná,</hi> a
                    rice-like cereal. <hi rend="italic">Suán,</hi> another rice-like cereal, not
                    cultivated, grows spontaneously in the paddy fields. Pulses of different sorts,
                    oilseeds, fibres, sugar-cane, tobacco, spices, and vegetables also form crops of
                    the district. The cultivators consist of two classes—the resident husbandmen <hi
                    rend="italic">(Thání),</hi> and the non-resident or migratory husbandmen <hi
                    rend="italic">(Páhe).</hi> At the time of the last settlement of land revenue in
                    1837, the rights of the resident cultivators were formally recognized by
                    Government, and secured to them by palm-leaf leases. They hold their homestead
                    lands rent free, and are not liable to be ousted so long as they continue to pay
                    the rents assessed on their cultivable lands. Nor can such rents be enhanced
                    until the expiration of their leases, which run concurrently with the
                    land-settlement to 1897. The non-resident cultivators were formerly
                    tenants-at-will, but since 1859 a large proportion of them have acquired rights
                    of occupancy under the Acts of the Indian Legislature.</p>
                <p>Weekly steamers ply between Calcutta and Dhámrá. The High Level Canal, when
                    completed, will afford ample means of communication inland towards Bengal. The
                    revenues of the Cattack district have steadily increased under the British rule.
                    The total revenue in 1829-30 was £139,642, the expenditure on civil
                    administration £114,438; in 1870—71 the revenue was £243,958, the civil
                    expenditure £223,659. In the latter year the land revenue amounted to £77,629.
                    Excluding the indigenous village schools maintained by the people themselves,
                    the schools inspected by the Educational Department in 1872-73 numbered 53,
                    attended by 2435 pupils, and maintained at an outlay of £4081, to which
                    Government contributed £2699. The hot season commences in March and lasts till
                    about the middle of June; the rains continue from the middle of June till the
                    end of October, when the cold weather sets in. The average rainfall for five
                    years previous to 1870 was 63 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 18 inches, the
                    average temperature 84° Fahr. Intermittent fever, elephantiasis, smallpox, and
                    bowel complaints form the prevalent diseases. Cholera is always present among
                    the natives, and occasionally assumes the epidemic type. The district of
                    Cattack, with the rest of Orissa, passed into the hands of the English from the
                    Marhattás in 1803. (w. w. a.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n255/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0255-0244"/><hi rend="smallcaps">Cattack,</hi> the most
                    important town in the above district, and the capital of the province, is
                    situated in 20° 28' N. lat. and 85° 55' E. long, on the tongue of land where the
                    Mahánadí first bifurcates, throwing off the Kátjurí on its southern and the
                    Birúpá on its northern bank. Cattack city formed one of the five royal
                    strongholds of ancient Orissa, and was founded by a warlike prince who reigned
                    from 953 to 961. Its native kings protected it from the rivers by a masonry
                    embankment several miles long, built of enormous blocks of hewn stone, and in
                    some places 25 feet high. A fortress defended the north-west corner of the town,
                    and was captured by the English from the Mar-hattås in October 1803. It is now
                    abandoned as a place of defence. The city has long been the commercial and
                    administrative headquarters of Orissa; it is connected with False Point harbour
                    by the Kendrápårá Canal. The High Level Canal, at present in course of
                    construction, will open out inland communication between it and Calcutta. In
                    1825 the town contained 6512 houses, and a population of about 40,000.
                    Population in 1872, 50,878, viz., Hindus, 40,849; Muhammadans, 7436; Christians,
                    1968; others, 625. (w. w. <hi rend="smallcaps">h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
