<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0249-0238-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATILINA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 238</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:919364">Fabia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:846504">Capitols</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:814541">Arm</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATILINA</label>, Lucius <hi rend="smallcaps">Sergius,</hi> a
                    member of an ancient patrician family of Rome, first appears in history during
                    the proscription of Sulla, conspicuous among the ruthless band of murderers,
                    slaying his inoffensive brother-in-law with his own hand, and torturing and
                    mutilating the muchloved Gratidianus. His foul vices were unconcealed; he was
                    believed to have made away with his wife and his son to win the profligate and
                    wealthy Aurelia Orestilla; it was even suspected that he had been guilty of an
                    intrigue with the Vestal Fabia. Nevertheless, in 66 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b,c.,</hi> he found himself qualified for the consulship, and only
                    incapacitated by the impeachment brought against him by P. Clodius Pulcher for
                    extortion during his government in Africa. Catiline would not brook even delay
                    in his advance to power, and accordingly he formed a conspiracy, in which
                    Autronius, Piso, and even, according to rumour, Crassus and Caesar were
                    concerned. The new consuls were to be murdered while offering up their vows on
                    the 1st of January; and the fasces were to be seized by Catiline and Autronius.
                    The plot failed, but only because the signal was given too hastily; and the
                    discovery brought no punishment upon those implicated, for the intervention of a
                    tribune was readily obtained. Soon after, Catiline, having bribed both judges
                    and accuser, was acquitted in the trial for extortion. His scheme was forthwith
                    immensely widened. The city was to be fired, and those who opposed the
                    revolution were to be slain; all debts were to be cancelled; and there was to be
                    a proscription of all the wealthy citizens. Among the conspirators were many men
                    of the first rank and influence. Arms and money were collected, soldiers were
                    enlisted, and the assistance of the slaves was sought. But Catiline’s hopes were
                    again disappointed; once more he failed to obtain the consulship; and, moreover,
                    it soon became apparent that one of the new consuls Cicero, was mysteriously
                    able to thwart all the schemes of the conspirators. He was, in fact, informed of
                    every detail, through Fulvia, the mistress of Curius, one of the plotters, who
                    was himself soon persuaded to turn informer. Before the next <hi rend="italic"
                    >comitia consularia</hi> assembled, the orator had given so impressive a warning
                    of the danger which was impending, that Catiline was once more rejected and the
                    consuls were invested with absolute authority. The other consul, C. Autronius,
                    being absent in Macedonia, Cicero had everything in his own hands. On the 8th of
                    November, he again rose in the senate to make so vigorous an attack upon
                    Catiline that he rushed from the temple, amid the curses of the senators, and
                    fled to the army. Next day Cicero awoke the terror of the people by a second
                    declaration which he delivered in the Forum. Still not one of the rebels
                    deserted, though a free pardon and great rewards were offered to informers,—a
                    remarkable proof, it has been said, of the wretchedness and discontent of the
                    lower orders at that time. It has also, however, been suggested that there
                    existed no conspiracy of a kind concerning which any member of the lower orders
                    could give information. Legal evidence of the plot was, nevertheless, obtained
                    by the means of the Allobrogian ambassadors, implicating Lentulus, Cethegus, and
                    Statilius, who, on the nones of December, were condemned to be strangled by the
                    common executioner in the vile dungeon of the Capitol. This act of speedy
                    vengeance, which was opposed as illegal by Julius Caesar, was strenuously
                    advocated by Cato and, indirectly, by Cicero. Thus a heavy blow was dealt to the
                    cause of Catiline, who, in the beginning of 62 B.C., saw his legions, partially
                    armed and diminished by desertion, shut in between those of Metellus Celer and
                    Antony. Near Faesulae he hazarded battle with the forces of the latter,
                    commanded by Μ. Petreiuβ, for the proconsul was or pretended to be ill. So
                    terrible an engagement ensued that the bravest of the victors were slain, and of
                    the conquered not one was taken alive. Catiline’s body was found far in advance
                    of his own ranks, amidst a heap of the enemy whom he had slain.</p>
                <p>Such is the account of the conspiracy of Catiline, and such is the character of
                    its author, as we find them in the speeches of Cicero, and the histories of
                    Sallust and Dion Cassius. Though there is nothing incredible in either, it must
                    not be forgotten that our sole authorities for these statements were all members
                    of one political party, and that the aristocratical. Some of the incidents given
                    as facts by Dion Cassius are manifest absurdities; and Cicero shared the common
                    habit of ancient orators, and paid more regard to the effect than the
                    truthfulness of an accusation.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n250/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0250-0239"/>
                <p>We find him at one time admitting that Catiline had almost persuaded him of his
                    honesty and merit, nay, even seeking a political union with him; at another,
                    when his alliance had been rejected and an election was at hand, declaiming
                    against him as a murderer, and as a profligate horribly conspicuous among
                    profligates. And, lastly, though Sallust’s vivid narrative is consistent
                    throughout, it is not hard to see that he cherished very bitter feelings against
                    the democratical party. Nevertheless, we have certainly no ground for accepting
                    the view which makes Catiline a worthy successor of the Gracchi, an honest enemy
                    of the hateful oligarchy, and a disinterested champion of the provincials. The
                    following is probably as accurate a statement of the case as can now be given.
                    There was at the time on the part of many of the Roman nobles a determination to
                    raise themselves to power, despite the opposition of the senate, while the
                    bolder among them were quite prepared to resort to force, if that appeared
                    likely to be for their advantage. When, therefore, the senatorial party
                    successfully assumed the aggressive, and its leader, Cicero, ventured on the
                    bold course which we have described, they at once took up arms. Among them
                    Catiline stands out conspicuous, and receives all the attacks of their enemies.
                    Whether he was morally worse than the rest we cannot say with confidence; it was
                    enough that he was far the foremost in force of body and of mind.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
