<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0905-0248-0237-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATHOLIC APOSTOLIC CHURCH (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    237)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nx59">Gifts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888378">Deacons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808921">Anglicans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATHOLIC APOSTOLIC CHURCH</label>, a religious community
                    often called “Irvingites,” but not itself acknowledging any other name than that
                    of “the Catholic Apostolic Church,” which, the members say, belongs to them in
                    common with the whole of baptized Christendom. The relation of the celebrated
                    preacher Edward Irving to this community was, as they state it, somewhat similar
                    to that of John Baptist to the early Christian church, <hi rend="italic"
                        >ι.e.,</hi> he w as the forerunner and prophet of the coming dispensation,
                    not the founder of a new sect; and indeed the only connection which Irving seems
                    to have had with the existing organization of the Catholic Apostolic body was in
                    “fostering spiritual persons who had been driven out of other congregations for
                    the exercise of their spiritual gifts.” Shortly after Irving’s trial and
                    deposition, certain persons were at some meetings held for prayer designated as
                    “called to be apostles of the Lord” by certain others claiming prophetic gifts.
                    In the year 1835, six months after Irving’s death, six others were similarly
                    designated as “called” to complete the number of the “twelve,” who were then
                    formally “separated” by the pastors of the local congregations to which they
                    belonged to their higher office in the universal church on the 14th July 1835.
                    This separation is understood by the community not as “in any sense being a
                    schism or separation from the one Catholic Church, but a separation to a special
                    work of blessing and intercession on behalf of it.” The twelve were afterwards
                    guided to ordain others,—twelve prophets, twelve evangelists, and twelve
                    pastors, “sharing equally with them the one Catholic Episcopate,” and also seven
                    deacons for administering the temporal affairs of the Church Catholic. The
                    central episcopacy of eight-and-forty was regarded as “indicated by prophecy,”
                    being foreshown in the forty-eight boards of the Mosaic Tabernacle. For
                    ecclesiastical purposes the church universal is under their charge in twelve
                    tribes; for Christendom is considered <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0905-0249-0238"/> to be divided into twelve portions or tribes,
                    each tribe being under the special charge of an apostle and his coministers, and
                    the seat of the Apostolic College being at Albury in England.</p>
                <p>For the service of the church a comprehensive book of liturgies and offices was
                    provided by the “apostles ;” and lights, incense, vestments, holy oil, water,
                    chrism, and other adjuncts of worship have been appointed by their authority.
                    The ceremonial in its completeness may be seen in the church in Gordon Square,
                    London, and elsewhere. The daily worship consists of “matins” with <hi
                        rend="superscript"> t</hi> proposition” (or exposition) of the sacrament at
                    6 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.m.,</hi> prayers at 9 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.m.</hi>
                    and 3 <hi rend="smallcaps">p.m.,</hi> and “vespers” with “proposition” at 5 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">p.m.</hi> On all Sundays and holy days there is a “solemn
                    celebration of the Eucharist” at the high altar; on Sundays this is at 10 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.m.</hi> On other days “low celebrations” are held in the
                    side-chapels, which with the chancel in all churches correctly built after
                    apostolic directions are separated or marked off from the nave by open screens
                    with gates.</p>
                <p>Each congregation is presided over by its “angel” or bishop (who ranks as pastor
                    in the Universal Church); under him are four-and-twenty priests, divided into
                    the four ministries of “elders, prophets, evangelists, and pastors,” and with
                    these are the deacons, seven of whom regulate the temporal affairs of the
                    church—besides whom there are also “sub-deacons, acolytes, singers, and
                    doorkeepers.” The understanding is that each elder, with his co-presbyters and
                    deacons, shall have charge of 500 adult communicants in his district; but this
                    has been but partially carried into practice. This is the full constitution of
                    each particular church or congregation as founded by the “restored apostles,”
                    each local church thus “reflecting in its government the government of the
                    Church Catholic by the angel or high priest Jesus Christ, and His forty-eight
                    presbyters in their fourfold ministry (in which apostles and elders always rank
                    first), and under these the deacons of the Church Catholic.” The priesthood is
                    supported by tithes; it being deemed a duty on the part of all members of the
                    church who receive yearly incomes to offer a tithe of their increase every week,
                    besides the free-will offering for the support of the place of worship, and for
                    the relief of distress. Each local church sends “a tithe of its tithes” to the
                    “Temple,” by which the ministers of the Universal Church are supported; by these
                    offerings, too, the needs of poorer churches are supplied, and other expenses
                    connected with the administration of the Church Catholic. From recent statements
                    made by members of this community it appears to be making steady progress. It
                    claims to have among its clergy many of the Roman, Anglican, and other churches,
                    the orders of those ordained by Greek, Roman, and Anglican bishops being
                    recognized by it with the simple confirmation of an “apostolic act.'*</p>
                <p>For further details of doctrines, ritual, ⅛c., see <hi rend="italic">Restoration
                        of Apostles and Prophets,</hi> by R. N. Bosworth; also his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Readings on the Liturgy,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Church and
                        Tabernacle.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
