<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0251-0240-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 5, page 240</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205534">Libya</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dj16">Stoics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wq2m">Temperance</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jr84">Tempering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133750">Stoics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1147289">Temper</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1147375">Tempering</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n251/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATO</label>, Μ. <hi rend="smallcaps">Porcius</hi> (commonly
                    distinguished from his great-grandfather, Cato the Censor, by the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Uticensis,</hi> from the place of his death and the renown
                    attending upon it),- furnishes a remarkable specimen of the effect of Hellenic
                    training upon the hard and narrow but determined spirit of the old Latin race.
                    While he inherited from his illustrious ancestor, and from the general
                    discipline of his family through many generations, a sour and severe temper, a
                    pedantic adherence to form and usage, aud an utter lack of sympathy with any
                    temper or habits alien from his own, his feelings had been deepened, if not
                    expanded, by the study of the Greek philosophy. As a devoted follower of the
                    Stoic teaching he had attained to very lofty principles, and made them, with
                    almost undeviating consistency, the rule of his life and conduct. He became a
                    fanatic in the pursuit of holiness and pureness of living, in the highest sense
                    in which such graces could be acquired by a pagan, with a view to himself and
                    his own perfection only, but with no love of man and no faith in Providence. He
                    waged a brave but hopeless war against the evil tendencies of his age; but he
                    attached to himself no party, gave strength to no cause, effected no good in his
                    generation, and at the last critical moment betrayed his trust to humanity by
                    fleeing from immediate evil by an unreflecting suicide. But his aims were, for
                    the times in which he lived, generous and noble, and his career well deserves to
                    be studied by succeeding generations. It is only in a very slight outline that
                    it can be here presented.</p>
                <p>Cato was born in the year 95 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and on the death of
                    his parents was brought up in the house of his uncle, Livius Drusus, who was
                    just then beginning to incite the Italians to claim a share in the Roman
                    franchise and its privileges. This was the commencement of the intestine
                    troubles of the Republic, and the whole of Cato’s after-life was passed amidst
                    domestic dissensions and civil wars. In his early years he expressed with
                    striking boldness his disgust at the cruelties of Sulla. The priesthood of
                    Apollo, to which he early consecrated himself, commended him to a life of rigid
                    observances, and gave a great impulse to his fervid imagination. He learned the
                    principles of the Stoics under a Greek teacher named Antipater, but his oratory
                    in the Forum represented only the harsh, vehement, and caustic type of his Roman
                    countrymen. After fighting in the ranks against Spartacus he became a military
                    tribune, 67 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and served a campaign in Macedonia.
                    On his return he obtained the quaestorship, and distinguished himself for his
                    zeal and integrity in the management of the public accounts, which recommended
                    him for a provincial appointment in Asia. Again he acquitted himself with marked
                    disinterestedness, and conceived a disgust equal to that of his great ancestor
                    at the corruption of the public men with whom ho came in contact. He saw,
                    however, much to admire in the discipline which Lucullus had enforced in his own
                    Eastern command, and he supported his claims to a triumph, while he opposed the
                    inordinate pretensions of Pompeius. When the favour of the nobles gained him the
                    tribuneship he exerted himself to convict Murena, one of their chief men, of
                    bribery. Cicero, more pliant than himself, defended the culprit and obtained his
                    acquittal; but Cioero was glad to avail himself of the firmness and stern
                    justice of his recent adversary, when he urged the execution of Catilina’s
                    associates. By this time Cato had become a great power in the state. Though
                    possessed of little wealth and no family influence, his <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n252/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0252-0241"/> character for unflinching resolution in the cause
                    of the ancient free state rendered him a valuable instrument in the hands of the
                    nobles, perplexed as they were by the open hostility of Caesar and the
                    oppressive patronage of Pompeius and Crassus. They were the better disposed,
                    perhaps, to make use of him from the oddity of his unpractical temper, which
                    made it the easier for them occasionally to disclaim and repudiate his
                    assistance. They did not, indeed, find him so complacent a dupe as Cicero, nor
                    did they treat him more faithfully. They thrust him into the snare prepared for
                    him by the triumvirs, and let him be sent on a mission of gross injustice
                    towards the king of Cyprus, which his pedantic loyalty to the state forbade him
                    to refuse. He continued to struggle against the combined powers of the triumvirs
                    in the city, and became involved in scenes of violence and riot, while
                    desperately resisting the superior force of their turbulent adherents. He
                    succeeded, however, in obtaining the praetorship in 54, in which office he
                    strenuously exerted himself in the hopeless and thankless task of suppressing
                    bribery, in which all parties were equally interested. Resolved not to stoop to
                    such practices himself, he failed to attain the consulship; and he had made up
                    his mind to retire from the arena of civic ambition when the civil war broke out
                    in 49.</p>
                <p>Cato had now persuaded himself that the sole chance for the free state lay in
                    conceding an actual supremacy to Pompeius. Accordingly he did not scruple to
                    support the unjust measures of the nobles against Caesar, which gave too fair a
                    colour to the invasion of Italy. Cato was, indeed, little prepared for his
                    commander’s flight across the Adriatic, and the surrender of the city, the
                    government, and therewith the ostensible right, to the victorious rebel. Though
                    he followed Pompeius to Epirus he found little satisfaction in his camp, where
                    the fugitives were loudly threatening a bloody vengeance on their enemies. He
                    excused himself from accompanying the forces of the Senate into Thessaly, by
                    which he escaped being present at the battle of Pharsalia. After that great
                    disaster, when his chief had abandoned his party and provided only for himself,
                    he too felt at liberty to separate himself from the main body of the
                    republicans, and conducted a small remnant of their forces into Africa. His
                    march through the deserts of Libya gained him immortal glory. The struggle
                    between the senate and Caesar was renewed in the African province. Cato shut
                    himself up in Utica, and prepared to defend it as the most important post for
                    communication with Italy. The battle of Thapsus, and the total rout of the
                    senatorial forces, now threw upon him the whole weight of maintaining a cause
                    which had become evidently desperate. The people of the place were anxious to
                    make terms with the victor; but he would not trust the Roman citizens and
                    soldiers to the clemency of the heir of Marius. Hitherto the civil wars of Rome
                    had been continually marked by bloody retaliation; even if Caesar himself were
                    disposed to mercy he might not be able to restrain the violence of his allies;
                    and it was rumoured that terrible execution had been inflicted upon the captives
                    of the last battle. Accordingly Cato determined to keep the gates closed till he
                    had sent his adherents off by sea. While the embarkation was in progress his own
                    demeanour continued calm and dignified. He supped familiarly with his friends,
                    discoursing with them, as was his wont, on philosophical topics. On being
                    informed that the last of the transports had left the port he cheerfully
                    dismissed his attendants, and soon afterwards stabbed himself on his couch.
                    Assistance was promptly offered, but he refused to avail himself of it, and so
                    perished, much, it may be said, to his own fame, but with little advantage to
                    his country (46 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi></p>
                <p>Cato had been reading, we are told, in his last moments Plato’s dialogue on <hi
                    rend="italic">The Immortality of the Soul,</hi> but it is not likely that the
                    Stoic, with his keen and rigid logic, put much faith in the vague aspirations of
                    the idealist of Academus. His own philosophy had taught him to act upon a narrow
                    sense of immediate duty without regard to future contingencies. He conceived
                    that he was placed in the world to play an active part, marked out by
                    circumstances, and when disabled from carrying out his principles, to retire
                    gravely from it. He had lived for the free state, and it now seemed his duty to
                    perish with it. Caesar had slain the commonwealth; it never occurred to him that
                    Caesar himself was mortal, and that the commonwealth might live again. Had he
                    condescended to ask his life, the conquerors would have been proud to grant it;
                    in two years more he might have been the survivor, for he was hardly yet fifty
                    years of age, and might have formed a rallying point for the few devoted
                    spirits, though few indeed they were, who really cared for freedom. Cato has
                    left perhaps, from the circumstances of his life and of his death, the most
                    marked name in the history of Roman philosophy, but he was a student, possibly a
                    dreamer only, composed no works, and bequeathed to posterity no other
                    instruction than that of his example. The memory of his career proved indeed
                    fruitful. The school of the Stoics, which took a leading part in the history of
                    Rome under the earlier emperors, looked to him as its saint and patron. It
                    continued to wage war against the empire, hardly less openly than Cato himself,
                    for two centuries, till at last it became actually seated on the imperial throne
                    in the person of Marcus Aurelius, (c. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
