<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0193-0175-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">TEMPLE, Sir William</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 175</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:912601">Enteritis</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4610vv86">Enteritis</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=193" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">TEMPLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William</hi></label>, was
                    born in London in the year 1628. The family from which he sprung was ancient,
                    and is said to have assumed its surname from the manor of Temple, in the hundred
                    of Sparken Hall, in Leicestershire. He was first sent to school at Penshurst, in
                    Kent, under the care of his uncle, the celebrated Dr Hammond, then minister of
                    that parish; but at the age of ten he was removed to a school at
                    Bishop-Stortford, in Hertfordshire. When he had acquired a sufficient knowledge
                    of Greek and Latin, he returned home at the age of fifteen; and two years
                    afterwards he went to Cambridge, where he was placed under the tuition of the
                    learned Dr Cudworth, then fellow of Emanuel College. His father, Sir John
                    Temple, being a statesman, seems to have designed him for the same mode of life;
                    and on this account, after residing at Cambridge two years, which were
                    principally spent in acquiring a competency of French and Spanish, both
                    languages exceedingly useful for his intended pursuits, he was sent abroad to
                    finish his education.</p><p>He began his travels by visiting France in 1648. As he chose to pass through the
                    Isle of Wight, where his majesty was detained a prisoner, he there accidentally
                    met with the second daughter of Sir Peter Osborne of Chicksand, in Bedfordshire,
                    then governor of Guernsey for the king; and his lady being on a journey with her
                    brother to St Maloes, where their father then was, the young traveller joined
                    their party. This gave rise to an honourable attachment, which, at the end of
                    seven years, concluded in a happy marriage. Having resided two years in France,
                    and perfectly learned the French language, Temple made a tour through Holland,
                    Flanders, and Germany, during which he became completely master of the Spanish.
                    In 1654 he returned from the continent, and, marrying Miss Osborne, passed his
                    time in retirement with his father, his two brothers, and a sister, then in
                    Ireland, happy in that perfect harmony which has been so often remarked in their
                    family. As he rejected all offers of employment under Cromwell, the five years
                    which he lived in Ireland were spent chiefly in improving himself in history and
                    philosophy; but at the restoration, in 1660, being there chosen a member of the
                    convention, while others were trying to make their court to the king, Mr Temple
                    opposed the poll-bill with so much spirit, that his conduct soon attracted the
                    attention of the public, and brought him into notice. In the succeeding
                    parliament, in 1661, he was elected with his father for the county of Carlow;
                    and in the year following he was chosen one of the commissioners to be sent from
                    that parliament to the king, which gave him an opportunity of waiting on the
                    duke of Ormond, the new lord lieutenant, then at London. He soon afterwards
                    returned to Ireland, but with a resolution of quitting that kingdom, and of
                    removing with his family to England.</p><p>On his return he met with a very favourable reception from the duke of Ormond;
                    and soon acquired such a share in his esteem, that the duke complained of him as
                    the only man in Ireland that had never asked any thing from him. When he
                    mentioned his design of carrying his family to England, his grace said, that he
                    hoped he would at least give him leave to write in his favour to the two great
                    ministers, Clarendon, then lord chancellor, and the earl of Arlington, who was
                    secretary of state. This the duke did in such strong terms, as procured him the
                    friendship of these two noblemen, as well as the good opinion of the king.
                    Temple, however, made no other use of this advantage than to tell Lord
                    Arlington, that if his majesty had any employment abroad, which he was fit for,
                    he should be happy to undertake it; but, at the same time, he requested that he
                    might not be sent into any of the northern climates, to which he had a very
                    great aversion. The secretary replied, he was very sorry he had made such an
                    objection, as there was no other employment then undisposed of except that of
                    going envoy to Sweden. However, in 1665, about the beginning of the first Dutch
                    war, Arlington sent a messenger to acquaint him that he must immediately come to
                    his house. He found that his lordship’s business was to tell him, that the king
                    had occasion to send some person abroad upon an affair of the utmost importance,
                    and that he had resolved to make him the first offer; but that he must know,
                    without delay, and without telling him what it was, whether he would accept of
                    it, and that he must be ready to set out in two or three days, without
                    mentioning it to any of his friends. After a little consideration, Temple told
                    his lordship, that as he took him to be his friend, and as he had advised him
                    not to refuse, as it would be an entrance into his majesty’s service, he should
                    consult no further. This business was to carry a secret commission to the bishop
                    of Munster. He accordingly set out on the second of August, and executed it so
                    much to the satisfaction of Charles II. that, on his return to Brussels, his
                    majesty appointed him resident there, and created him a baronet. As Brussels was
                    a place where he had long wished to reside, he sent for his family in April
                    1666; but before their arrival, he had again been obliged to depart upon
                    business to the prelate’s court. The bishop having listened to terms of
                    accommodation with France, Sir William wrote two letters to dissuade him from
                    that alliance; and these not having the desired effect, he went in disguise to
                    Munster, where, though he arrived too late to secure the prince in his first
                    engagement, yet he prevailed on him to permit five or six thousand of his best
                    troops to enter into the Spanish service. In this journey he passed for a
                    Spanish envoy, having twenty Spanish guards to attend him. In this manner he
                    first went to Dusseldorp, where the duke of Neuburg, though in the French
                    interest, gave him a guard to Dortmund; but when he reached that place, finding
                    the gates shut, he was forced to proceed to a village at the distance of a
                    league, which being full of Brandenburg troops, he was under the necessity of
                    lodging in a barn, upon a straw bed, with his page for a pillow. Next day he was
                    entertained at a castle belonging to the bishop of Munster, by one Gorges, a
                    Scotish lieutenant-general in that prelate’s service, with what he calls a very
                    episcopal way of drinking. The general coming to the large hall, in which stood
                    a great many flaggons ready charged, called for wine to drink the king’s health.
                    A silver bell*</p><pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=194" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0194-0176"/><p>which might hold about two quarts, was presented to him; and, as soon as he
                    received it, he pulled out the clapper, and giving it to Sir William, to whom he
                    intended to drink, ordered the bell to be filled. He drank off the contents to
                    his majesty’s health; and asking Sir William for the clapper, put it on, and
                    turning down the bell, rang it, to show that he bad drunk fair, and left nothing
                    in it. He then took out the clapper, desired Sir William to give it to
                    whomsoever he pleased; and, ordering the bell to be filled again, presented it
                    to Sir William: but as the latter seldom used to drink, he had generally some
                    gentleman with him to supply his place in this respect whenever it might be
                    necessary. Having finished his business at Munster, he returned to Brussels,
                    where he passed a year with great pleasure and satisfaction.</p><p>Two months after the conclusion of the peace with the Dutch at Breda, Sir
                    William’s sister, who resided with him at Brussels, being very desirous of
                    seeing Holland, he went thither incognito to gratify her desire; but while he
                    was at the Hague, he paid a private visit to De Witt, in which he laid the
                    foundation of that close intimacy which afterwards subsisted between them. In
                    the spring of 1667, a new war breaking out between France and Spain, which
                    exposed Brussels to the danger of falling into the hands of the former, Sir
                    William sent his lady and family to England; but he himself remained there with
                    his sister till the Christmas following, when he was ordered by the king to come
                    over privately to London. Taking the Hague in his way, he paid another visit to
                    De Witt, and, pursuant to his instructions, proposed those overtures to him
                    which produced the triple alliance. Soon after his arrival at the British court,
                    he returned, on the 16th of January 1668, with the character of envoy
                    extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Holland; where a conference being opened,
                    he brought that treaty to a perfect conclusion in the short space of five days.
                    The ratifications of this alliance being exchanged on the 15th of February, he
                    repaired to Brussels; and a treaty being set on foot between France and Spain at
                    Aix-la-Chapelle, he proceeded for that place on the 24th of April in quality of
                    his majesty’s ambassador extraordinary and mediator. Here he arrived on the
                    27th; and it was chiefly owing to his assistance that the Spaniards were brought
                    to sign the articles of that peace on the second of May. This service being
                    completed, he returned to Brussels, with a view of remaining there in his former
                    station of resident; but he received letters from the earl of Arlington, with
                    the king’s order to continue as ambassador, and to serve his country in that
                    quality in Holland, as, on account of the late alliances, his majesty was
                    resolved to renew a character which the crown of England had discontinued there
                    since the time of King James. Sir William being now left at liberty to return to
                    England, embraced the opportunity; and upon his arrival at London he was
                    received with every possible demonstration of favour, both by the king and the
                    court.</p><p>Setting out again for Holland, with his new character of the king’s ambassador,
                    he arrived at the Hague in the end of August 1668. Here he enjoyed the
                    confidence of that great minister De Witt, and lived in great intimacy with the
                    prince of Orange, who was then only eighteen years of age; but, in September
                    1669, he was hurried back to England by Lord Arlington, who ordered him to put
                    his foot in the stirrup as soon as he should receive his letter. When Sir
                    William waited on the earl, he found that he had not one word to say to him;
                    for, after making him attend a long time, he only asked a few indifferent
                    questions respecting his journey. Next day he was received as coolly by the
                    king; but the secret soon came out, and he was urged to return to the Hague, and
                    pave the way for a war with Holland. In this, however, he excused himself from
                    having any concern; which so much provoked the lord-treasurer Clifford, that he
                    refused to him an arrear of two thousand pounds due from his embassy. Disgusted
                    with Arlington’s behaviour, which was so unlike the friendship he had formerly
                    professed, Sir William now retired to his house at Sheen, near Richmond, in
                    Surrey; and in his retreat, when free from the hurry of business, he wrote his
                    Observations on the United Provinces, and one part of his Miscellanies, in the
                    time of the second Dutch war. But about the end of summer 1673, the king wishing
                    to put an end to the war, sent for Sir William, and desired him to go to Holland
                    to negociate a peace; but powers having been sent from thence at this time to
                    the Marquis de Fresno, the Spanish ambassador at London, Sir William was ordered
                    to confer with him; and a treaty was accordingly concluded in three days, and
                    the point carried respecting the superiority of the British flag, which had been
                    so long contested. In June 1674 he was again sent ambassador to Holland to offer
                    the king’s mediation between France and the confederates, then at war, and it
                    was accepted not long after; Lord Berkeley, Sir William Temple, and Sir Leoline
                    Jenkins, being declared ambassadors and mediators. Nimeguen, which Sir William
                    had proposed, was at length agreed upon by all parties to be the place of
                    treaty. During his stay at the Hague, the prince of Orange, who was fond of the
                    English language, and of the plain English way of eating, constantly dined and
                    supped once or twice a week at his house; and by this familiarity he so much
                    gained the prince’s confidence and esteem, that he had a considerable hand in
                    his marriage with the princess Mary, daughter of James II.</p><p>In July 1676 he removed his family to Nimeguen, where he spent the remainder of
                    that year without making any progress in the treaty; and the year following his
                    son was sent over with letters from the lord-treasurer, ordering him to return,
                    and succeed Mr Coventry as secretary of state. In consequence of this order, Sir
                    William came over to England in the spring of 1677; and though the affair of the
                    secretary’s place was dropped at his desire, he did not return to Nimeguen that
                    year. About this time, the prince having the king’s leave to come over, he soon
                    after married the princess Mary; and this gave occasion for a new coolness
                    between Lord Arlington and Sir William, as he and the lord-treasurer Osborne,
                    who was related to Sir William’s lady, were only privy to that affair. After the
                    prince and princess were gone to Holland, as the court always seemed inclined to
                    favour France, the king wished to engage Sir William in some negociations with
                    that crown; but he was so ill satisfied with this proposal, that he offered to
                    give up all pretensions to the office of secretary; and desiring the
                    lord-treasurer to acquaint his majesty with his intentions, retired to Sheen, in
                    hopes of being taken at his word. Upon a discovery, however, of the French
                    designs not to evacuate the Spanish towns agreed by the treaty to be delivered
                    up, the king commanded him to undertake a third embassy to the states. With them
                    he concluded a treaty, by which England engaged, in case France refused to
                    evacuate the towns in forty days, to declare war immediately against that
                    nation; but before half that time was elapsed, one Du Cros was sent from the
                    English court to Holland upon a business which there damped all the good humour
                    excited by the treaty, and which produced such sudden and astonishing changes in
                    this country, as gave Sir William a distaste for all public employments.</p><p>In 1679 he returned to Nimeguen, where the French delayed to sign the treaty till
                    the last hour; but having concluded it, he returned to the Hague, whence he was
                    soon after sent for to enter upon the secretary’s office, which Mr Coventry at
                    length resolved to resign. He accordingly came over, and went to court, as all
                    his friends hoped, with a full intention of assuming his office; but he started
                    some difficulty, because he had not a seat in the House of Commons, thinking
                    that, by his not being a member, the public <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=195" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0195-0177"/>business would suffer at such a critical time, when the contests between the
                    two parties ran so high, that the king thought fit to send the duke of York into
                    Flanders, and the parliament to commit the lord-treasurer Danby to the Tower.
                    After this his majesty still pressed Sir William to be secretary of state; using
                    as an argument for his compliance, that he had nobody to consult with at a time
                    when he had the greatest need of the best advice. Notwithstanding all this, Sir
                    William declined the king’s offer, advising him to choose a council in whom he
                    could confide, and upon whose abilities he could depend. This advice the king
                    followed; and the choice of the persons being concerted between his majesty and
                    Sir William, the old council was dissolved four days after, and the new one
                    established, of which the latter was a member.</p><p>In 1680 the councils began again to be changed, on the king’s illness, at the end
                    of summer, and the duke of York’s return to court. At this juncture Sir William,
                    endeavouring to bring to the king’s favour and business some persons to whom his
                    majesty had taken a dislike, if not an aversion, he met with such treatment from
                    them as gave him a fresh distaste to the court, at which he seldom made his
                    appearance; so that he resided principally at Sheen. Soon after this the king
                    sent for him again; and having proposed that he should go as ambassador into
                    Spain, Sir William consented; but when his equipage was almost ready, and part
                    of the money paid down for it, the king changed his mind, and told him that he
                    would have him defer his journey till the end of the session of parliament, in
                    which he was chosen a member for the university of Cambridge. In this session
                    the spirit of party ran so high that it was impossible to bring the house to any
                    kind of temper. The duke was sent into Scotland; but this would not satisfy
                    them, nor any thing but a bill of exclusion, which Sir William strenuously
                    opposed, saying that “his endeavour ever should be to unite the royal family,
                    and that he would never enter into any councils to divide them.” Not long after
                    this period, the parliament being dissolved by his majesty, without the advice
                    of his privy council, and contrary to what he bad promised, Sir William made a
                    bold speech against that measure; for which he was very ill used by some of
                    those friends who had been most earnest in promoting the last change in the
                    ministry. Upon this he grew quite tired of public business, declined the offer
                    he had of again serving for the university in the next parliament, which was
                    soon after called, and met at Oxford; and seeing his majesty resolved to govern
                    without his parliament, and to supply his treasury through another channel, he
                    retired to Sheen a few days after, whence he sent word by his son, that “he
                    would pass the rest of his days like a good subject, but would never more meddle
                    with public affairs.” From that time Sir William lived at this place till the
                    end of that reign and for some time in the next; when, having purchased a small
                    seat called Moor Park, near Farnham in Surrey, for which he conceived a great
                    fondness, on account of its solitude and retirement, and its healthy and
                    pleasant situation, and being much afflicted with the gout, and broken with age
                    and infirmities, he resolved to spend the remainder of his life in this
                    agreeable retreat. In his way thither he waited on King James, who was then at
                    Windsor, and begged his favour and protection to one “that would always live as
                    a good subject, but, whatever might happen, never again enter upon any public
                    employment desiring his majesty to give no credit to any thing he might hear to
                    the contrary. The king, who used to say that Sir William Temple’s character was
                    always to be believed, promised him whatever he desired, gently reproached him
                    for not entering into his service, which, he said, was his own fault; and kept
                    his word as faithfully to Sir William as Sir William did to his majesty, during
                    the surprising turn of affairs that soon after followed by the arrival of the
                    prince of Orange. At the time of this happy revolution, in 1688, Moor Park
                    becoming unsafe, as it lay in the way of both armies, he retired to the house at
                    Sheen, which he had given up to his son; to whom he refused leave, though
                    importunately begged, to go and meet the prince of Orange at his landing; but
                    after King James’s abdication, when the prince reached Windsor, he went thither
                    to wait upon his highness, and carried his son along with him. The prince
                    pressed him to enter into his service, and to be secretary of state; but his age
                    and infirmities confirming him in the resolution which he had made not to meddle
                    any more with public affairs, he was satisfied that his son alone should enjoy
                    his majesty’s favour. Mr John Temple was upon this appointed secretary at war;
                    but he had hardly been a week in that office, when he resolved to put an end to
                    his own life. This resolution he carried into effect on the 14th of April 1689,
                    by throwing himself out of a boat, hired for that purpose, in shooting London
                    bridge; having first put stones into his pocket to make him sink speedily.</p><p>In 1694 Sir William had the additional affliction to lose his lady, who was a
                    very extraordinary woman, as well as an affectionate wife. He was then
                    considerably turned of sixty; at which age he practised what he had so often
                    declared to be his opinion, that “an old man ought then to consider himself of
                    no farther use in the world, except to himself and his friends.” After this he
                    lived four years very much afflicted with the gout; and his strength and spirits
                    being worn out, he expired in the month of January 1698, in the seventieth year
                    of his age. He died at Moor Park, where his heart was buried in a silver box
                    under the sun-dial in his garden, opposite to a window from which he used to
                    contemplate and admire the works of nature, with his sister, the ingenious Lady
                    Gifford. This was according to his will, in pursuance of which his body was
                    privately interred in Westminster Abbey. There a marble monument was erected in
                    1722, after the death of his sister Lady Gifford. She resembled him in genius as
                    well as in person, and left behind her the character of one of the best and most
                    constant friends.</p><p>Sir William Temple’s principal works are, 1. Memoirs from 1672 to 1691. They are
                    very useful for those who wish to be acquainted with the affairs of that period.
                    2. Remarks upon the State of the United Provinces. 3. An Introduction to the
                    History of England. 4. Letters written during his last embassies. <hi rend="italic">5.</hi> Miscellanies. He is a pleasing and popular writer; and his
                    style was long regarded as a model of grace and elegance.</p></div></body></text></TEI>