<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0085-0067-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TABRIZ, or Tabreez</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 67</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df9q">Tiles</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw7t">Porter</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1150910">Tiles</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:838614">Bricks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1072068">Porters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1072067">Porter</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=85" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TABRIZ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Tabreez</hi></label>, a city
                    of Persia, and capital of the province of Azerbijan, and for a considerable time
                    the residence of Abbas Mirza, the heir-apparent of the Persian crown. It is
                    seated in an immense plain at the foot of a mountain, on the banks of a small
                    river whose waters are applied to the cultivation of the land. Tabriz was
                    formerly a magnificent city, and, according to Chardin’s account, contained,
                    when he visited it in 1686, 15,000 houses, as many shops, 300 caravanserais, 250
                    mosques, magnificent domed bazaars, and 550,000 inhabitants, though this last
                    appears rather an exaggerated estimate. At present, Morier does not consider it
                    to be more than one tenth of its former magnitude. All the large buildings have
                    been destroyed by earthquakes. Two of these occurred during the last century,
                    and were particularly fatal: 100,000 inhabitants perished, having been swallowed
                    up in the yawning abyss of the earth, with their houses; and others crushed
                    under masses of falling ruins. Notwithstanding these calamities, a new city has
                    arisen amid the desolation of the old; and on all sides are to be seen the ruins
                    of houses, streets, &amp;c., which afford some idea of the extent and
                    magnificence of the former city. Tabriz is at this day three miles and a quarter
                    in circumference. Morier, who visited this place in 1809, mentions that it is
                    surrounded by walls built of sun-burnt bricks, and by towers of kiln-burnt
                    bricks placed at irregular distances from each other. After his second visit in
                    1811, he mentions that, four years before, Abbas Mirza had made Tabriz his
                    capital, and that he had repaired and beautified the walls, and otherwise
                    improved the city. Sir R. K. Porter, by whom Tabriz was visited in 1817, also
                    says that it had been lately re-fortified by order of the prince Abbas Mirza,
                    who then resided in it. It is now surrounded with a thick wall, protected by
                    towers and bastions, with the addition of a very deep dry ditch, the whole
                    embracing a circumference of 6000 yards. The object of the prince is not so much
                    to adorn as to strengthen the city; and, besides the fortifications, a maidan or
                    square has been laid out by him, and surrounded with barracks for the troops
                    which he is organizing according to European tactics. He was also building a
                    palace for his own residence, which possessed, however, none of that pomp which
                    distinguished the royal residences of former days. Beyond this boundary to the
                    north and east extend the suburbs, which rise amid the ruins and broken ground
                    which formerly composed the city. Four gates of no very imposing appearance open
                    into the new city. They are surmounted by turrets, and ornamented with slight
                    minarets covered with chequer-work of blue and green tiles, collected from the
                    remains of the ancient vaulted mosques. Out of the 250 mosques mentioned by
                    Chardin, the ruins of only three are visible. The most considerable is that of
                    Ali Shah, erected nearly 600 years ago by Ali Koja, which still presents lofty
                    arches and the mouldering vaulted work of splendid domes. This building, both
                    within and without, has been cased over its whole surface with lackered tiles of
                    porcelain, adjusted with singular taste and ingenuity into a variety of
                    intricate and elaborate figures of green, dark, and light blue, interspersed
                    with Arabic sentences in letters of gold; and a broad band of rich legends
                    formed in white upon this beautifully varied ground, and interwoven with flowers
                    in green and gold, winds round the whole extent of the building. This fine ruin
                    is within the new fortifications of the city, where are also the remains of the
                    ark or citadel. The latter building comprehends within its limits the remains of
                    a mosque, which is a very finely constructed mass of brick-work, about eighty
                    feet in height; at the top of which three small chambers have been constructed,
                    whence the town and the surrounding country are seen as if laid out on a chart.
                    The prince at one time intended to reside in this place; but it was sub <pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=86"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0086-0068"/> sequently converted into an arsenal and
                    manufactory of arms, which was visited by Morier, and in which he saw stores of
                    guns, artillery, and the other materiel of war, and numerous carpenters,
                    wheelwrights, and others, with European tools, and a blacksmith’s forge at work.
                    To the south-east of the city, at the foot of a sloping hill, is a powder-mill,
                    worked by water, and erected entirely by a Persian. It is, says Morier, by far
                    the best structure at Tabriz, being built of brick, stone, and marble. The
                    remains of this structure that still exist, after repeated shocks of
                    earthquakes, prove the original solidity and excellence of the workmanship.
                    About two miles to the south-west of the new walls of the town, but far within
                    the remnants of the old boundaries, stand the magnificent remains of the
                    sepulchre of Sultan Kazan. The intervening ground is marked with shapeless
                    ruins, even stretching beyond the sepulchre to a great extent. The tomb itself
                    has the appearance of a huge mound of mingled lime, dust, tiles, and bricks,
                    surrounded, however, with spacious arches of stone, the remains of its former
                    grandeur. Beyond the eastern gate of the town, the ruins of the ancient city
                    reach for more than three miles over the valley, and on the adjoining heights
                    which skirt the base of the hills. On one of the most commanding of these
                    subordinate acclivities stands the vast and venerable structure of an ancient
                    fortress, which from its position and strength must have commanded the whole
                    valley. At what period this vast structure was first built, is entirely unknown;
                    but the thickness of the walls, the massy towers, and the splendid materials of
                    its interior parts, plainly show the great labour and cost at which it must have
                    been reared. No sun-dried bricks have been employed in this building, which
                    consists of huge masses of loose stones and mortar thrown together, and
                    afterwards closely faced with large stones. A very large tower, looking towards
                    the town and the valley, flanks the south-west front of the castle, which seems
                    in a less impaired state than any of the other quarters. In the interior of
                    these ruins are found several vaulted and spacious underground apartments, and
                    near them the remains of a magnificent mosque. The shattered walls are filled up
                    with heaps of tiles, dust, and furnace-made bricks, interspersed with the pieces
                    of white transparent marble called Tabriz marble, which is dug up in immense
                    blocks from the mountains on the banks of Lake Ooroomia. Sir R. K. Porter also
                    marked the foundations of other considerable buildings, and the site where baths
                    had been constructed. He ascribes the destruction of these edifices on the
                    heights more to the devastations of war than to earthquakes, as the ruins that
                    still remain mark out very clearly the plan and architectural dispositions of
                    the edifice. The plain in which Tabriz is situated is bounded to the north-east,
                    the east, and south-east, by a chain of barren mountains, conspicuous for their
                    red and ochreous appearance. These mountains rise immediately behind Tabriz, and
                    recede into a deep vale, which, being watered by a plentiful stream, is perhaps
                    more highly cultivated than any tract of its size in Persia, and is remarkable
                    for beautiful and picturesque scenery.</p>
                <p>It is generally understood that the ancient name of Tabriz was Ganzaca; and no
                    notice is found of it as the capital of Azerbijan until the fourth century of
                    the Christian era. From that period, under the names of Ganzaca, Tauris, Tabriz
                    or Tabreez, it has been esteemed the capital of the province. But it must have
                    subsequently declined in consequence, as the houses of the city only amounted to
                    3000 when Heraclius took possession of it 300 years after. It was not till after
                    the accession of the Sefi race of kings that Tabriz regained its former
                    importance. It must have been a great city when it was visited by Chardin in
                    1686, who rates its population at 550,000. But in 1727 it was nearly destroyed
                    by an earthquake, in which 70,000 people are said to have perished; and in a
                    succeeding shock, which took place in 1787, only 40,000 remained to be
                    engulphed; a proof that the population had in the mean time greatly declined.
                    Longitude, according to the observations of the unfortunate traveller Brown, 47.
                    17. 46. E. Latitude, according to Major Monteith, 38. 4. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
