<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-8811-0250-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANTIGONUS I</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193098811?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ANTIGONUS I</label>., one of the captains of
                    Alexander the Great, was the son of Philip, a Macedonian nobleman. After
                    Alexander’s death, a division of the provinces taking place, Pamphylia, Lycia,
                    and Phrygia Major fell tohis share. But Perdiccas, well acquainted with his
                    ambitious spirit and great abilities, determined to divest him of his
                    government, and laid plans for his life, by bringing various accusations against
                    him. Antigonus, aware of the danger, retired with his son Demetrius into Greece,
                    where he obtained the favour and protection of Antipater; and in a short time
                    Perdiccas dying, a new division took place, when he was invested not only with
                    the government of the former provinces, but also with that of Lycaonia. He was
                    likewise intrusted with the command of the Macedonian household troops; and upon
                    Eumenes being declared a public enemy, he received orders to prosecute the war
                    against him with the utmost vigour. On the commencement of this war, Eumenes
                    suffered a total overthrow, and was obliged to retire with only 600 brave
                    followers to a castle situated on an inaccessible rock, where he might rest in
                    safety from all the assaults of Antigonus. In the interval, his friends
                    assembled a new army for his relief, which was routed by Antigonus, who now
                    began to exhibit the great projects of his ambition. Polyperchon succeeding to
                    the tutorship of the young king of Macedon after Antipater’s death, Antigonus
                    resolved to set himself up as lord of all Asia. On account of the great power of
                    Eumenes, he greatly desired to gain him over to his interest; but that faithful
                    commander, effecting his escape from the fortress where he was closely
                    blockaded, raised an army, and was appointed the royal general in Asia. The
                    governors in Upper Asia co-operating with him, he succeeded in several
                    engagements against Antigonus; but was at last delivered up to him through
                    treachery, and put to death. Upon this the governor of Upper Asia yielded to
                    Antigonus. Those whom he suspected, he either sacrificed to his resentment or
                    displaced from their offices. Then seizing upon all the treasures at Susa, he
                    directed his march towards Babylon, of which city Seleucus was governor.
                    Seleucus fled to Ptolemy, and entered into a league with him, together with
                    Lysimachus and Cassander, with the intention of giving a check to the exorbitant
                    power of Antigonus, who, notwithstanding this, made a successful attempt upon
                    the provinces of Syria and Phoenicia. But these provinces were soon after
                    recovered by Ptolemy, who defeated his son Demetrius, while he himself was
                    employed in repelling Cassander, who had made rapid progress in Lesser Asia.
                    They were again taken by Antigonus, who, being flushed with his success, planned
                    an expedi·ion against the Nabathaean Arabs, dwelling in the deserts adjacent to
                    Judea; but on the first enterprise against the town of Petra, his general
                    Athenaeus, with almost all his troops, was cut to pieces by the Arabs. Antigonus
                    then sent his son against them, who returned after forcing them to reasonable
                    terms. Demetrius then expelled Şeleucus from Babylon; and success attending his
                    arms wherever he went, the confederates were obliged to make a treaty with
                    Antigonus, in which it was stipulated that he should remain in possession of all
                    Asia, but that the Greek cities should continue in possession of their liberty.
                    This agreement was soon violated, under the pretęnce that garrisons had been
                    placed in some of these cities by Antigonus. At first Ptolemy made a successful
                    descent into Lesser Asia, and on several of the islands of the Archipelago; but
                    he was at length defeated by the successful arms of Demetrius in a sea-fight,
                    who also took the island of Cyprus, with many prisoners. On this victory
                    Antigonus was so elated that he assumed the title of king, and bestowed the same
                    upon his son; and from that time, B. c. 306, his reign in Asia, and that of
                    Ptolemy in Egypt, and of the other captains of Alexander in their respective
                    governments, properly commence.</p>
                <p part="N">Irritated at the hostile conduct of Ptolemy, Antigonus prepared a
                    numerous army and a formidable fleet; and having taken the command of the army,
                    he gave the com· mand of the fleet to Demetrius, and hastened to attack him in
                    his own dominions. After enduring the severest hardships, they met in the
                    vicinity <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> of Mount Cassius; but Ptolemy acted with
                    such valour and address that Demetrius could gain no advantage over him; and
                    after several fruitless attempts, he abandoned the undertaking. He next
                    attempted the reduction of Rhodes; but meeting with obstinate resistance, he was
                    obliged to make a treaty upon the best terms that he could, having been called
                    to join Antigonus against Cassander, who at this time had formed a confederacy
                    with Seleucus and Lysimachus. When Demetrius united his forces with those of
                    Antigonus, they advanced to Phrygia, and having met the enemy at Ipsus, a
                    decisive battle was fought, in which Antigonus fell, in the 84th year of his
                    age, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 301.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Antigonus</hi><hi rend="italic">Gonatas,</hi> son
                    of Demetrius Poliorcetes, was the grandson of the former Antigonus. His
                    character was eminently distinguished by humanity and mildness of disposition.
                    When he besieged Thebes under the command of his father, he strongly
                    remonstrated against the loss of so many lives for such an insignificant object.
                    Filial affection was so powerful in his mind, that when his father was taken
                    prisoner by Seleucus, he generously offered himself in his stead; and being
                    rejected, he wore deep mourning, and refrained from all festivals and amusements
                    during his father’s imprisonment. Informed of his death, all the floods of
                    sorrow burst from his tender heart, and sailing with a fleet to meet his ashes,
                    he received them with all the demonstrations of filial sensibility and dutiful
                    respect. By the death of his father he became master of all the European
                    dominions of Demetrius, together with the kingdom of Macedon, and various other
                    cities in Greece. The Gauls invading his country, he defeated and expelled them;
                    but was soon after routed by Pyrrhus, king of Epirus. Some time after, however,
                    Pyrrhus was slain at Argos; and when his head was brought to him by his son, he
                    expressed the highest displeasure, and throwing his robe over it, he gave orders
                    to search for his body, and to inter the same with all funeral honours. ∙</p>
                <p part="N">In the evening of his reign he so cultivated the arts of peace, and so
                    conciliated the minds of his subjects, that he secured their affections both to
                    himself and his descendants. The taking of the citadel of Corinth by intrigue
                    was the meanest action of his reign; but he improved that event in maintaining
                    the freedom of the small estates of Greece, and in increasing his own dominions.
                    The Achaeans, and Aratus their famous chief, vigorously opposed his measures,
                    and at length recovered Corinth; but Antigonus was so inclined to peace, that
                    notwithstanding this event, he pursued his wonted plan, and left his kingdom in
                    peace about the 80th year of his life and the 44th of his reign, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 243; and Demetrius II. his son, next ascended
                    the throne.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
