<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0998-0958-15" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028641">Mud</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937852">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=998" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YARKUND</label>, a city of Cashgar, in that part of Chinese
                    Tartary which commonly goes by the name of Little Bucharia. It is situated on a
                    river of the same name, on the eastern side of that great range of mountains
                    which extends northwards from the Himalaya range, and divides Chinese from
                    Independent Tartary. This city, after enjoying a high degree of celebrity in
                    that part of Asia, was destroyed by Meerza Abubekr, grandson of Timour, who
                    however restored it to prosperity, when its population increased; and the air
                    being salubrious, he made it his residence, adorning it with splendid edifices,
                    bringing water into the streets, and in other ways rendering it fit for a royal
                    abode. Its walls are about 1200 feet high; and numerous gardens, the finest in
                    the world, were planted around it. It is at present defended by a wall of stone
                    cemented with mud, in which there are five gates. The houses are mean, being
                    built of stone and mud, and have all balconies. The bazaar runs from east to
                    west, and is described as consisting of a range of seats upon a platform, behind
                    which there are handsome shops, chiefly occupied by Chinese. It contains more
                    than ten large colleges, for the support of which lands are assigned, and plenty
                    of caravanserais for the accommodation of travellers. The town is watered by
                    canals from the river, from which are filled certain reservoirs, of mud and
                    stone, which supply the inhabitants with water when the canals are frozen and
                    the river low. The water of the river is also employed in irrigating the
                    surrounding cultivation and gardens. The inhabitants of this and the other towns
                    in this part of Asia are chiefly mechanics, merchants, and teachers or priests.
                    Many of them are afflicted with the glandular swelling in the throat called
                    goitre. The women of the country, whether high or low, do not wear veils. The
                    Russians carry on a commercial intercourse with Yarkund, which is a great
                    emporium of inland trade. It is within the dominion of the Chinese, under whose
                    government it has been for the last eighty years. Long. 78. 27. 45. E. Lat. 38.
                    19. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
