<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1000-0960-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kb2c">Lead</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994553">Lead</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1000" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YETHOLM</label>, a parish on the confines of England, in the
                    county of Roxburgh, containing two villages of the same name. One of these, Town
                    Yetholm, is the place where the largest colony of Gipsys in Scotland is to be
                    found. The strolling habits and vagabond life which they lead are too well known
                    to require any description here; but it may be stated, that in consequence of
                    the operation of the new police act for Scotland and England, there is every
                    probability of a change taking place in their erratic mode of life, by their
                    being compelled to settle to steady occupations in a fixed place of abode, or
                    otherwise being liable to be imprisoned as vagrants. Their number is at present
                    about 100. The village is situate in a valley about one mile in length and <pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1001"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-1001-0961"/> a quarter of a mile in breadth, through which
                    the Bowmont flows. The parish church is situated in Kirk Yetholm, whilst in Town
                    Yetholm there are two dissenting places of worship. The population of the parish
                    in 1831 was 1289.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
