<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1007-0967-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:878973">Cork</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130935">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150792">Tides</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq8b">Tides</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1007" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YOUGHAL</label>, a town in the county of Cork, is situated
                    about 140 statute miles from Dublin, and lies on the shore of a harbour of the
                    same name, into which, at spring-tides, vessels of 400 or 500 tons burthen can
                    enter. It is of great antiquity, and was formerly a place of strength. The old
                    walls in great part remain, and still form, on the summit of the hill to the
                    westward, the boundary of the town. Owing to the very abrupt rise of this hill,
                    the town is confined between it and the water, and can only extend itself in the
                    direction of its length from north to south; but in both these directions it has
                    outgrown its ancient limits, which are there only to be traced by partial
                    remains of the walls. Youghal, notwithstanding its vicinity to Cork, which will
                    probably prevent its ever rising into any great commercial importance, has yet a
                    considerable trade with England, particularly in the export of agricultural
                    produce. It contained, according to the census of 1831, about 9600 inhabitants,
                    and 1200 houses, being, on an average, exactly eight to a house. The increase of
                    population in ten years is supposed to have been about 1000, but is not very
                    accurately known. When the census was taken, there were only six houses
                    building. The greater part of the town belongs to the duke of Devonshire.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
