<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0999-0959-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120819">Sleep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888601">Deals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15r77">Sleep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=999" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YAWNING</label>, an involuntary opening of the mouth,
                    generally produced by weariness or an inclination to sleep. Yawning, according
                    to Boerhaave, is performed by expanding at one and the same time all the muscles
                    capable of spontaneous motion, by greatly extending the lungs; by drawing in
                    gradually and slowly a large quantity of air, and gradually and slowly breathing
                    it out after it has been retained for some time and rarefied, and then restoring
                    the muscles to their natural state. Hence the effect of yawning is to move,
                    accelerate, and equally distribute all the humours through all the vessels of
                    the body, and consequently to qualify the muscles and organs of sensation for
                    their various functions. Sanctorius observes, that a great deal is insensibly
                    discharged, when nature endeavours to get rid of the retained perspirable
                    matter, by yawning and stretching the limbs. To these a person is most inclined
                    just after sleep, because a greater quantity going off by the pores of the skin
                    than at other times, whenever a person wakes, the increasing contraction that
                    then happens closes a great deal of the perspirable matter in the cutaneous
                    passages, which will continually give such irritations as excite yawning and
                    stretching; and such motions, by shaking the membranes of the whole body, and
                    shifting the contact of their fibres, and the enclosed matter, by degrees throw
                    it off. Hence we see the reason why healthful strong people are most inclined to
                    such motions, because they perspire most in time of sleep, and therefore have
                    more of the perspirable matter to lodge in the pores, and greater irritations.
                    The advantages of some little exercise just after waking in a morning are
                    considerable, as it throws off all the perspirable matter that is ready for its
                    exit from the body. When yawning is troublesome, Hippocrates says that it is
                    cured by long, deep respiration, or drawing in the air at long intervals.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
