<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0998-0958-17" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=998" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YARMOUTH</label>, a seaport town and borough of the county of
                    Norfolk and hundred of East Flegg, 124 miles from London. The old town is
                    situated on the eastern bank of the Yare, and is connected with the new town,
                    called Little Yarmouth, by means of a bridge over that river. The old town,
                    which is still surrounded by walls, consists of four principal lines of streets
                    running nearly parallel with the river, and of about 150 narrow lanes called
                    rows, which are impassable for wheel-carriages. The principal streets are well
                    built and wide, opening in some places to the spacious quay, market-places, and
                    squares. The best dwelling-houses arc situated along the quay, which is
                    considered the finest in the kingdom, having in the centre a noble promenade,
                    planted on each side with trees, and resembling<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=999" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0999-0959"
                    /> those on the banks of the Seine at Paris. The part of the town beyond the
                    walls consists of extensive warehouse premises, and inferior dwelling-houses.
                    The new town principally consists of substantial private residences; and the
                    space between them and the river is occupied by docks, timber-wharfs,
                    building-yards, and other premises connected with the trade of the port. The
                    streets are well lighted with gas, and well supplied with water. The town-hall,
                    church, and theatre, are hand-some buildings. In addition to the church, there
                    are other two chapels connected with the establishment, and places of worship
                    for the various bodies of dissenters. There is an extensive manufactory for
                    crapes and other silk goods, which is said to be in a thriving condition, and
                    which gives employment to about 500 persons, principally women. Ship-building,
                    and the various trades connected with it, are also carried on to some extent in
                    Yarmouth; nevertheless it cannot be considered as a manufacturing town, but
                    derives its importance and prosperity from the trade and commerce which it owes
                    to its situation and port. The rivers Yare, Waveney, and Bure, which unite in
                    Braydon Water, contiguous to the town, are navigable; the first to Norwich, the
                    second to Bungay, and the third to Aylsham; and secure to Yarmouth an extensive
                    inland trade in the exportation of the agricultural produce of the districts
                    that are traversed by these rivers, and in supplying them with coals and other
                    heavy goods. The exportation of grain and malt from this port is considcrable;
                    but the principal business of Yarmouth is the herring and mackarel fisheries,
                    and the curing and exportation of this staple commodity to foreign countries,
                    particularly to the states bordering the Mediterranean. An extensive timber
                    trade with the Baltic is also carried on; and there are at present nearly 400
                    square-rigged vessels belonging to the port Yarmouth Roads have long been the
                    principal rendezvous for the collier trade; and the town derives some advantages
                    from the supply of fresh provisions to the numerous shipping employed in this
                    trade. The harbour of Yarmouth, formed by the river Yare, has an awkward
                    entrance, which, as is always the case in harbours of this description, is
                    obstructed by a bar. Great attention, however, is bestowed on the remedying of
                    these defects, and on the general improvement of the port. Vessels drawing about
                    twelve feet of water, or of about 200 tons burden, can cross the bar, and
                    proceed to the town at spring-tides. Yarmouth has two weekly markets, and that
                    held on Saturday is much frequented. An annual fair is held on the Friday after
                    Good Friday, but is neither of importance to the town nor its neighbourhood. The
                    town is divided into six wards, and is governed by a mayor, twelve aldermen, and
                    thirty-five councillors. It returns two members to the House of Commons. The
                    duties collected here in 1837 amounted to L.66,l69, and in 1838 to L.70,775. The
                    population amounted in 1821 to 18,040, and in 1831 to 21,448.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Yλrmouth,</hi> a small market-town of the Isle of Wight and
                    the county of Hants, a part of the parish of Medina, 100 miles from London. It
                    stands on a rising ground facing the sea, and retains traces of having been much
                    larger at some former period than it is at present. In its present state it
                    consists of several well-built streets. There is but little trade carried on.
                    The population amounted in 1821 to 564, and in 1831 to 586.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
