<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1014-0974-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j75q">Sick</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1014" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZALEUCUS</label>, a famous legislator of the Locrians, and
                    the disciple of Pythagoras, flourished 500 years <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c.
                    He made a law, by which he punished adulterers with the loss of both their eyes;
                    and his son offending, was not absolved from this punishment; yet, to shew the
                    father as well as the just lawgiver, he put out his own right, and his son’s
                    left eye. This example of justice and severity made so strong an impression on
                    the minds of his subjects, that no instance was found of the commission of that
                    crime during the reign of the legislator. It is added, that Zaleucus forbade any
                    wine being given to the sick, on pain of death, unless it was prescribed by the
                    physicians; and that he was so jealous of his laws, that he ordered, that
                    whoever was desirous of changing them, should be obliged, when he made the
                    proposal, to have a cord about his neck, in order that he might be immediately
                    strangled if those alterations were esteemed no better than the laws already
                    established. Diodorus Siculus attributes the same thing to Charondas, legislator
                    of the Sybarites.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
