<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1075-1025-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wf2d">Militia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1021608">Militia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1075" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZUG</label>, a canton of Switzerland, the smallest of the
                    whole confederacy. It is bounded on the north by Zürich, on the east and
                    south-east by Schwytz, on the south-west by Lucerne, and on the west by Aargau.
                    It is only 110 square miles in extent; and is divided into two parts, the inner
                    and the outer amt or bailiwick. It contains 1876 dwellings, with 14,710
                    inhabitants. They are all of the German race, and speak that language. The
                    religion is that of the Romish church, and the canton contains nine parish
                    churches, with three monasteries, all under the bishop of Constance. The
                    constitution is a pure democracy. All the males who have completed the age of
                    nineteen must become soldiers, and must be regimented in the militia. An
                    assembly of the whole inhabitants is held on the first Sunday in May, when the
                    several officers are chosen for the year. The chief, called the Landamann, is
                    elected for two years, and from the two bailiwicks alternately. The officers of
                    the militia are nominated for life. The council consists of thirty-four members,
                    and in ordinary times assembles three times in the year, and at such other
                    periods as the chief may deem it necessary; but a committee of that body is
                    permanent, and superintends the police, and forms à court of appeal from the
                    ordinary tribunals. There are inferior authorities in each of the two
                    bailiwicks, who rule in local affairs. The taxes are collected on liquids
                    consumed, whether wine, beer, or spirits; besides which there are stamp-taxes,
                    and payments for licenses to carry on trade; but the whole burdens are very
                    light. The contribution of the canton to the general confederacy is 1250 francs,
                    and the contingent of men 250.</p>
                <p>The face of the country is alpine, but the highest mountain, the Ruffi, does not
                    exceed 4830 feet. The other mountains, as the Rossberg, the Zugerberg, the
                    Morgarten, and the Dreilanderstein, are lower. The river Reuss is the principal
                    stream, which runs to the lake of Zug, and receives the smaller brooks. It forms
                    the boundary with the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1076"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-1076-1026"/>canton of Aargau. The lake of Zug, one of
                    peculiar beauty, is about nine miles in length and two and a half in breadth.
                    The road by its side presents points of view and striking objects which charm
                    the eye, and leave a lasting impression on the mind of the traveller. This lake
                    is dangerous to navigate with a strong southerly wind, on account of the sudden
                    violent gusts. It has however some trade on it, and is abundantly stocked with
                    fish of various kinds. The lake of Eger, and that of Fenster, have their
                    peculiar beauties, and, like that of Zug, abound in fish. The climate is that of
                    the Alps, but rather milder than in some other parts. The soil is good, and
                    yields corn and wine, much fruit, especially plums, and great quantities of
                    walnuts and chestnuts. There are no manufactures except two paper-mills. The
                    trade consists in the export of butter, cheese, cattle, wool, hides, dried
                    fruits, and chestnuts. These are sufficient to pay for the few foreign
                    necessaries and luxuries that are wanted. The chief profit is however derived
                    from the very numerous foreigners who visit the country in the summer months,
                    and who find good accommodations, but at no very cheap rate.</p>
                <p>The capital of this canton likewise bears the name of Zug. It stands on the lake
                    at the foot of a mountain. It is fortified, contains two churches, a Capuchin
                    monastery, a hospital, a council-house, a workhouse, and 2800 inhabitants. It is
                    a poor place, except at the time of the annual fair, which continues fourteen
                    days, when there is an appearance of activity.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
