<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1024-0984-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:895648">Ditches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1024" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZELLE</label>, a city of the kingdom of Hanover, in the
                    province of Lüneburg, in Germany. It stands on the river Aller, at the point
                    where the Fuse falls into that stream. It is surrounded with walls and ditches,
                    is the seat of the supreme courts of law, and of the Lutheran superintendent
                    general. It has a gymnasium, and several other establishments for education, and
                    contains three Lutheran, one reformed, and one catholic church, 1460 houses, and
                    10,300 inhabitants, including those of the suburb. There are various
                    manufactures, but mostly on a small scale; but a considerable trade arises from
                    the city being the great thoroughfare for the goods conveyed by waggons between
                    Hamburg, Bremen, and the middle and south of Germany. Adjoining to the city is
                    the ancient palace of the dukes of Zelle. It is not in very good condition, none
                    of the royal family having lived in it since the death of the unfortunate queen
                    of Denmark, Caroline Matilda, who held her court in it till her death. Long. 9.
                    57. 4. E. Lat. 52. 37. 3. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
