<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1024-0984-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936105">Functionals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm13w80">Patents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1024" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZEMINDAR</label>, in its original meaning, signifies a great
                    landholder of Bengal; but it is now more strictly applicable to those who have
                    their title constituted or confirmed by a patent or charter from government, by
                    which they hold their lands or zemindaries upon certain conditions. It appears
                    from history, that in times prior to the irruption of the Mahommedans, the
                    rajahs who held their residence at Delhi, and possessed the sovereignty of
                    Hindustan, deputed officers to collect their revenues. The word <hi
                        rend="italic">zemindar</hi> is Persian, and that language could have had no
                    currency in the countries of India, until it was introduced by the people of
                    Persia. When the emperor Shehab-ul-Dien Ghory conquered the empire of Hindustan
                    at the end of the 12th century, he left Sultan Cutub-ul-Dien to be his viceroy
                    at Delhi, and administer the government of Hindustan. From that time the customs
                    and practices of the Mahommedans began gradually to be established in India:
                    their armies were sent into the countries of the reduced rajahs, under the
                    command of omrahs, in order to preserve the conquest; and lands were allotted to
                    them to defray the expense. From hence arose the system of jaghiredary in
                    Hindustan. But when these omrah jaghiredars had established their own strength,
                    several of them rebelled against the imperial authority, and aspired to the
                    crown. Thus circumstanced, the emperors, in order to obviate these mischiefs,
                    thought it would be more politic to commit the management of the country to the
                    native Hindus, who had most distinguished themselves by the readiness and
                    constancy of their obedience to the sovereign power.</p>
                <p>In pursuance of this plan, districts were allotted to num.</p>
                <p>bers of them under a reasonable revenue (Jummah Monâsib), which they were
                    required to pay in money to the governors of the provinces, deputed from the
                    emperor; and in case any one of the omrahs or provincial governors should swerve
                    from his allegiance, the zemindars of that country were to exert themselves in
                    such a manner as should check rebellion, and restore good government. For this
                    purpose, grants of zemindary were severally conferred upon such of the Hindus as
                    were obedient, describing their apportionment of the country; and every person
                    who had received a grant under the authority of the crown, was thereby fully
                    invested with the functions of zemindar.</p>
                <p>The functions of a zemindar are, 1st, the preservation and defence of their
                    respective boundaries from traitors and insurgents; 2dly, the tranquillity of
                    the subjects, the abundance of cultivators, and increase of his revenue; 3dly,
                    the punishment of thieves and robbers, the prevention of crimes, and the
                    destruction of highwaymen. The accomplishment of these objects is considered in
                    the royal grant as the discharge of office to the sovereign; and on that account
                    the word <hi rend="italic">office</hi> (khidmut) is employed in the Dewanny
                    Sunnud for a zemindary. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hindustan.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
