<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0867-0834-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KÁNARA, or Canara, North (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    834)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837525">Brahmanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40000538">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n867/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KÁNARA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Canara, North</hi></label>,
                    the most southerly of the coast districts of Bombay, India, lying between 13°
                    52' and 15° 31' N. lat., and between 74° 10' and 75° 7' E. long., bounded on the
                    N. by Belgaum, E. by Dhârwâr and Mysore, S. by South Kânara, W. by the Arabian
                    sea and N. W. by the Portuguese territory of Goa, with an area of 4235 square
                    miles. The chief town is Kârwâr. The main feature in the physical geography of
                    the district is the Sahyâdri range of the Western Ghâts, which, running from
                    north to south, divides it into two parts, a lowland or coast strip (Payanghât),
                    and an upland plateau (Bâlâghât). The coast-line is only broken by the Kârwâr
                    headland in the north, and by the estuaries of four rivers and the mouths of
                    many smaller streams, through which the salt water finds an entrance into
                    numerous lagoons winding several miles inland. The breadth of the lowlands
                    varies from 5 to 15 miles. From this narrow belt rise a few smooth, flat-backed
                    hills, from 200 to 300 feet high; and at places it is crossed by lofty, rugged,
                    densely wooded spurs, which, starting from the main range of the Sahyâdri hills,
                    maintain almost to the coast a height of not less than 1000 feet. Among these
                    hills lie well-tilled valleys of garden and rice land. The plateau of the
                    Bâlâghât is irregular, varying from 1500 to 2000 feet in height. In some parts
                    the country rises into well-wooded knolls, in others it is studded by small,
                    isolated, steep hills. Except on the banks of streams and in the more open
                    glades, the whole is one broad waste of woodland and forest. The open spaces are
                    dotted with hamlets or parcelled out into rice clearings.</p>
                <p>Of the rivers flowing eastward from the watershed of the Sahyâdri hills the only
                    one of importance is the Wardha, a tributary of the Tungabhadra. Of those that
                    flow westwards, the four principal ones, proceeding from north to south, are the
                    Kâli, Gungawâli, Tadri, and Sharavati. The last of these, plunging over a cliff
                    825 feet in height, about 35 miles from Honâwar town, forms the famous Gersoppa
                    falls. The mineral products of the district consist of iron, limestone, and
                    building stone. Extensive forests clothe the Sahyâdri hills, and are conserved
                    under the rules of the forest department. During the ten years 1866-76 they
                    yielded an average annual revenue of £39,307 to the state. Tigers, leopards,
                    bears, deer, and wild hogs are numerous, and small game is plentiful. North
                    Kânara formed part of Madras till 1861, when it was transferred to Bombay
                    presidency.</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 returned a population of 398,406 (206,417 males and 191,989
                    females), 94 to the square mile. The Hindus numbered 364,402; Mahometans,
                    21,755; Pârsis, 25; Christians, 12,189; and Jews, 34. The most noteworthy class
                    among the Hindus are the Havik Brahmans, who make their livelihood from spice
                    and areca nut gardens. Besides the regular Mahometan population
                        (de-scenιlants<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n868/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0868-0835"/> from Hindu converts to Islam), there are two
                    special classes of foreign Mahometans,—the Navâyâtas or seamen, representatives
                    of early colonies of Arab merchants, and the Sidis or descendants of African
                    slaves formerly owned by the Portuguese. The Christians are nearly all Roman
                    Catholics, a few families of whom are of Portuguese extraction, though much
                    mixed by intermarriage with the natives; the remainder consist of local converts
                    or their descendants.</p>
                <p>The area under cultivation is returned at 333,175 acres, or about 12 per cent, of
                    the total area. Rice forms the staple crop, but <hi rend="italic">rdgi,</hi>
                    sugar-cane, and safflower are also grown to a considerable extent; and
                    cocoa-nuts, areca-nuts, cardamoms, and pepper are produced in gardens in large
                    quantities for home consumption and for export. Cochineal is largely exported.
                    Coffee is grown only to a small extent. Kârwâr, Kumpta, Ankola, Bhatkal, and
                    Honâwar are the most important seaports. The total value of the trade at these
                    in 1876 was £1,841,173, viz., £1,199,077 exports and £642,096 imports. Carving
                    in sandal wood and ebony forms an important industrial art. Salt is largely
                    manufactured under Government supervision. The total revenue of the district in
                    1876-77 was £165,597, of which the land tax yielded £82,862, and forests
                    £34,281. There were, in 1875-76, 83 schools, attended by 4425 pupils. Fever of a
                    severe type is the prevalent disease, and occasionally rages in an epidemic
                    form. The average annual rainfall on the coast varies from 100 inches at Kârwâr
                    to 163 at Kumpta ;. in the uplands it averages about 72 inches.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
