<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0763-0718-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">XENOCRATES (9th edition, volume 24, page 718)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882287">Crates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915833">Ethics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nq7b">Ethics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n763/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XENOCRATES</label> of Chalcedon, scholarch or rector of the
                    Academy from 339 to 314 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> was born in 396.
                    Removing to Athens in early youth, he became the pupil of the Socratic
                    Aeschines, but presently joined himself to Plato, whom he attended to Sicily in
                    361. Upon his master’s death (347 B.c.), in company with Aristotle he paid a
                    visit to Hermias at Atarneus. In 339, Aristotle being then in Macedonia,
                    Xenocrates succeeded Speusippus in the presidency of the school, defeating his
                    competitors Menedemus and Heracleides by a few votes. On three occasions he was
                    member of an Athenian legation, once to Philip, twice to Antipater. Soon after
                    the death of Demosthenes in 322, resenting the Macedonian influence then
                    dominant at Athens, Xenocrates declined the citizenship offered to him at the
                    instance of Phocion, and, being unable to pay the tax levied upon resident
                    aliens, was, it is said, sold, or on the point of being sold, into slavery. He
                    died in 314, and was succeeded as scholarch by Polemon, whom he had reclaimed
                    from a life of profligacy. Besides Polemon, the statesman Phocion, Chaeron
                    tyrant of Pellene, the Academic Crantor, the Stoic Zeno, and Epicurus are
                    alleged to have frequented his lectures.</p>
                <p>Xenocrates’s earnestness and strength of character won for him universal respect,
                    and stories were remembered in proof of his purity, integrity, and benevolence.
                    Wanting in quickness of apprehension and in native grace, he made up for these
                    deficiencies by a conscientious love of truth and an untiring industry. Less
                    original than Speusippus, he adhered more closely to the letter of Platonic
                    doctrine, and is accounted the typical representative of the Old Academy. In his
                    writings, which were numerous, he seems to have covered nearly the whole of the
                    Academic programme; but metaphysics and ethics were the subjects which
                    principally engaged his thoughts. He is said to have invented, or at least to
                    have emphasized, the tripartition of philosophy under the heads of physic,
                    dialectic, and ethic.</p>
                <p>In his ontology Xenocrates built upon Plato’s foundations: that is to say, with
                    Plato he postulated ideas or numbers to be the causes of nature’s organic
                    products, and derived these ideas or numbers from unity (which is active) and
                    plurality (which is passive). But he put upon this fundamental dogma a new
                    interpretation. According to Plato, existence is mind pluralized: mind as a
                    unity, <hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., universal mind, apprehends its own plurality
                    as eternal, immutable, intelligible ideas; and mind as a plurality, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, particular mind, perceives its own plurality as
                    transitory, mutable, sensible things. The idea, inasmuch as it is a law of
                    universal mind, which in particular minds produces aggregates of sensations
                    called things, is a “determinant” <hi rend="italic">(πέρας</hi> ἔ <hi
                    rend="italic">χον),</hi> and as such is styled “quantity” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(ποσόv)</hi> and perhaps “number” (<hi rend="italic">άριθμόs)</hi>; but the
                    ideal numbers are distinct from arithmetical numbers, and the elements of ideal
                    numbers from the elements of arithmetical numbers. Xenocrates, however, failing,
                    as it would seem, to grasp the idealism which was the metaphysical foundation of
                    Plato’s theory <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n764/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0764-0719"/> of natural kinds, took for his principles
                    arithmetical unity and plurality, and accordingly identified ideal numbers with
                    arithmetical numbers. In thus reverting to the crudities of certain Pythagoreans
                    he laid himself open to the criticisms of Aristotle, who, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Metaphysics,</hi> recognizing amongst contemporary Platonists
                    three principal groups—(1) those who, like Plato, distinguished mathematical and
                    ideal numbers; (2) those who, like Xenocrates, identified them; and (3) those
                    who, like Speusippus, postulated mathematical numbers only—has much to say
                    against the Xenocratean interpretation of the theory, and in particular points
                    out that, if the ideas are numbers made up of arithmetical units, they not only
                    cease to be principles but also become subject to arithmetical operations.
                    Xenocrates’s theory of inorganic nature was substantially identical with the
                    theory of the elements which is propounded in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Timaeus,</hi> 53 C <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> Nevertheless, holding that every
                    dimension has a principle of its own, he rejected the derivation of the
                    elemental solids—pyramid, octahedron, icosahedron, aud cube— from triangular
                    surfaces, and in so far approximated to atomism. Moreover, to the tetrad of
                    simple elements—namely, fire, air, water, earth—he added the <hi rend="italic"
                    >πέμπτη οὑσία,</hi> ether.</p>
                <p>His cosmology, which is drawn almost entirely from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Timaeus,</hi> and, as he intimated, is not to be regarded as a cosmogony,
                    should be studied in connexion with his psychology. Soul is a self-moving
                    number, derived from the two fundamental principles, unity (<hi rend="italic"
                    >ἕv</hi>) and plurality (<hi rend="italic">δυάs</hi> ά <hi rend="italic"
                    >όριστοs),</hi> whence it obtains its powers of rest and motion. It is
                    incorporeal, and may exist apart from body. The irrational soul, as well as the
                    rational soul, is immortal. The universe, the heavenly bodies, man, animals, and
                    presumably plants, are each of them endowed with a soul, which is more or less
                    perfect according to the position which it occupies in the descending scale of
                    creation. With this Platonic philosopheme Xenocrates combines the current
                    theology, identifying the universe and the heavenly bodies with the greater
                    gods, and reserving a place between them and mortals for the lesser
                    divinities.</p>
                <p>If the extant authorities are to be trusted, Xenocrates recognized three grades
                    of cognition, each appropriated to a region of its own, —namely, knowledge,
                    opinion, and sensation, having for their respective objects supra-celestials or
                    ideas, celestials or stars, and infracelestials or things. Even here the
                    mythological tendency displays itself,— <hi rend="italic">νοητά, δοξαστά,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">aίσθητά</hi> being severally committed to Atropos,
                    Lachesis, and Clotho. Of Xenocrates’s logic we know only that with Plato he
                    distinguished <hi rend="italic">τò καθ’ αὑτό</hi> and <hi rend="italic">τò πρόs
                    τι,</hi> rejecting the Aristotelian list of ten categories as a superfluity.</p>
                <p>Valuing philosophy chiefly for its influence upon conduct, Xenocrates bestowed
                    especial attention upon ethics. The catalogue of his works shows that he had
                    written largely upon this subject; but the indications of doctrine which have
                    survived are scanty, and may be summed up in a few sentences. Things are goods,
                    ills, or neutrals. Goods are of three sorts—mental, bodily, external; but of all
                    goods virtue is incomparably the greatest. Happiness consists in the practice of
                    virtue, the requisite powers and opportunities being presupposed. Hence the
                    virtuous man is always happy, though his happiness cannot be perfect unless he
                    is adequately provided with personal aud extraneous advantages. The virtuous man
                    is pure, not in act only, but also in heart. To the attainment of virtue the
                    best help is philosophy; for the philosopher does of his own accord what others
                    do under the compulsion of law. Speculative wisdom and practical wisdom are to
                    be distinguished. Meagre as these statements are, they suflice to show that in
                    ethics, as elsewhere, Xenocrates worked upon Platonic lines, and that in his
                    theory of the relations of external advantages to happiness, as well as in the
                    technicalities of his exposition, he closely resembled Aristotle.</p>
                <p>Xenocrates was not in any sense a great thinker. His metaphysic was a travesty
                    rather than a reproduction of that of his master. His ethic had little which was
                    distinctive. But his austere life and commanding personality made him an
                    effective teacher, and his influence, kept alive by his pupils Polemon and
                    Crates, ceased only when Arcesilaus, the founder of the so-called Second
                    Academy, gave a new direction to the studies of the school.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> D. Van de Wynpersse, <hi rend="italic">De
                    Xenocrate Chalcedonio,</hi> Leyden, 1822; C. A. Brandis, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gesch. d. Griechisch-Römischen Philosophie,</hi> Berlin, 1853, ii. 2, 1, 19-37;
                    E. Zeller, <hi rend="italic">Philosophie d. Griechen,</hi> Leipsic, 1875, ii.,
                    1, 840-842, 862-883; F. W. A. Mullach, <hi rend="italic">Fragmenta Philosophorum
                    Graecorum,</hi> Paris, 1881, iii. 100-130. (H. JA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
