<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-6489-0258-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUMBARTON (7th edition, volume 8, page 258)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1094658">Rent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100781">Rowing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90227c">Rent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b75c">Rowing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193326489?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUMBARTON</label>, a county in Scotland, situated between 55.
                    53. and 56. 25. north latitude, and between 3. 55. and 4. 53. west longitude
                    from Greenwich, consists of two districts, six miles distant from each other,
                    part of Lanarkshire running between them. The western, which is much the larger,
                    is about forty miles long and twelve broad, and is bounded by Perthshire on the
                    north; by Argyleshire, from which it is separated by an arm of the sea called
                    Loch Long, on the west; by the river Clyde and Lanarkshire on the south-west and
                    south; and by Stirlingshire on the east. The eastern district is completely
                    enclosed by Stirlingshire and Lanarkshire. The whole county contains 298 square
                    miles, or 190,848 English acres, of which the smaller division contains about
                    forty-two miles, or 28,000 acres. It is divided into twelve parishes, of which
                    there are only two in the eastern district, Kirkintilloch and Cumbernauld. This
                    last belonged to Stirlingshire. till the Earl of Wigton, whose property it was,
                    became heritable sheriff of Dumbartonshire, when he procured it to be annexed to
                    this county.</p>
                <p>The prevailing winds are from the west and south-west, but easterly winds are
                    frequent in the spring months. Showers are very common, but heavy and continued
                    rains of rare occurrence. Frosts are seldom severe, and, except on the
                    mountains, snow never lies long. The climate is upon the whole salubrious. The
                    range of the barometer is about 2∙80, and of the thermometer from 6° to 80°. The
                    soils of the lower grounds are schistoze clay mixed with small stones, rich
                    black loam on the banks of the Clyde, and gravelly soil on the river Leven; but
                    about two thirds of the county consist of lofty mountains, some of them 3000
                    feet high, part of the ridge which crosses the island from Forfarshire to the
                    Frith of Clyde, known in the districts to the eastward by the names of the
                    Siedlaw, Ochil, and Campsie Hills.</p>
                <p>Coal, iron ore, limestone, freestone, and slate, are its most valuable fossil
                    productions. There are pits for working coals at Langfauld and Lawmuir in East
                    Kilpatrick, and at Duntocher in West Kilpatrick, where great quantities are
                    raised for the consumption of the cotton works at Duntocher, and for calcining
                    lime at the neighbouringlime works. Ironstone is raised in considerable
                    quantities in the parishes of Kirkintilloch and Cumbernauld, which meets with a
                    ready market at Carron foundery.</p>
                <p>Limestone is found in the higher grounds at Kilpatrick, Dumbarton, and Row; but
                    it is only wrought at Langfauld, Lawmuir, and Duntocher, where coal is quarried
                    along with it, and also at Row, Netherwood, and Cumbernauld. White and red
                    freestone are met with in several places; the finest quarries are at Garscube,
                    on the banke of the Forth and Clyde Canal; and at Levengrove and Dalreoch, in
                    the immediate neighbourhood of Dumbarton.</p>
                <p>Several slate quarries have been wrought with success, at Luss and Camstradden on
                    the estates of Sir James Colquhoun, and at Roseneath on the estates of the Duke
                    of Argyll. The principal markets are at Glasgow, Greenock, &amp;c. to which the
                    slates are conveyed in lighters by the Leven and the Clyde.</p>
                <p>The only river of any note which can be said to belong to this county is the
                    Leven, the outlet of Lochlomond, which, flowing for about five miles through a
                    fine valley, joins the Clyde at Dumbarton Castle. Its waters, which are
                    singularly pure and soft, are well adapted to the business of bleaching and
                    printing cottons, branches which are established to a great extent along its
                    course. The other streams are Luss, Froon, Finlays, Douglas, Falloch, and
                    Luggie. Clyde, Endrick, and Kelvin, flow along its borders. Lochlong and
                    Gareloch are arms of the sea, the first of which separates this county from
                    Argyleshire; and the other, penetrating the land for about seven miles, nearly
                    detaches the peninsula of Roseneath from the mainland. W’hilst this extent of
                    sea-coast affords the benefit of water carriage to so large a portion of the
                    county, the inland tracts are benefited in almost an equal degree by the Forth
                    and Clyde Canal, which passes through it for more than sixteen miles. This canal
                    is about thirty-five miles in length, and it rises and falls about 160 feet, by
                    means of forty locks. It is carried over the valley where the Kelvin flows, by
                    an aqueduct sixty-five feet in height and 420 feet in length. The only
                    remarkable lake is Lochlomond, which is about twenty-four miles long, and in its
                    greatest breadth, towards the south, above six. About two thirds of the shore,
                    and most of its islands, thirty in all, are in Dumbartonshire; the rest belong
                    to Stirlingshire. It is probably not to be equalled by any lake in Britain for
                    the variety and magnificence of its scenery; the picturesque beauty of its
                    wooded banks and islands affording a striking contrast to the rugged and lofty
                    nιoun-tains<pb break="no" facs="nls:193326502?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0708-6502-0259"/> that rise in its vicinity. It covers about 20,000
                    acres, and its surface is supposed to be increasing. The best view of the lake
                    is from a promontory above Luss, a village on the western shore.</p>
                <p>The landed property of this county is divided among about a hundred and fifty
                    individuals, exclusive of feuars in towns and villages. One third of the estates
                    are of considerable extent, and the remainder are small. The valued rent is
                    L.33,327. 19s. Scots, of which about a third is held under the fetters of strict
                    entails. In 1811 the actual rent of the lands was L.56,972. 15s., and of the
                    houses L.5791. l5s., total L.62,764. 10s.; and the annual value of real property
                    in 1815 λvas L.71,587 sterling. There are a number of beautiful seats belonging
                    to the larger proprietors, among which Roseneath, the splendid mansion of the
                    Duke of Argyll, and Garscubc, the residence of Sir Archibald Campbell of
                    Succoth, are by far the finest specimens of architecture. There are also a great
                    many fine villas, the property of manufacturers and merchants.</p>
                <p>The county sends one member to parliament, who, prior to the passing of the
                    reform act in 1832, was elected by about seventy voters upon superiorities; but
                    by the reform measure the constituency has been increased to 924.</p>
                <p>The arable lands of Dumbartonshire are divided into farms ranging in extent from
                    50 to 250 acres: and of late years great improvements have been made in
                    agriculture, and in the breed of all kinds of stock. The land is generally
                    laboured and manured according to the improved system of husbandry; two crops of
                    grain seldom or never being taken without the intervention of a green crop
                    properly tilled and manured. The usual rotation is, first, oats; secondly,
                    potatoes or other green crop; thirdly, wheat or barley sown with rye-grass and
                    clover; fourthly, hay; and, lastly, pasture. Wheat, oats, and potatoes, are the
                    principal crops. The land is well inclosed and subdivided, principally by hedge
                    and ditch, and partially by stone-walls. The tenants generally hold leases for
                    nineteen years. Within the last twelve or fifteen years the breed of draught or
                    farm horses has been greatly improved; a circumstance which is ascribed partly
                    to the emulation excited among the tenantry to ride good horses at the yeomanry
                    drills, and partly to the annual competition for prizes given by the landlords
                    of this district. The dairy stock is principally of the Ayrshire breed; and
                    great improvements have also been made in this department, which is a source of
                    much profit to the farmers nearest to the city of Glasgow. The accommodation to
                    the tenantry has kept pace with these improvements. Many excellent steadings
                    have been erected, generally in the form of a square, having in front the
                    dwelling-house, which communicates with the offices, forming the other three
                    sides of a square.</p>
                <p>There arc in this county many excellent tracts of pasture land. Sheep of the
                    black-faced breed, and a limited number of black cattle, are reared with great
                    success. The shccp are disposed of in Glasgow, where there is a weekly sale; and
                    the cattle are sold at the Carman market, held in the Moor of Carman on the
                    first Tuesday of June. From 12,000 to 17,000 head of cattle, principally of the
                    Argylcshire breed, arc generally disposed of at that market, for the purpose of
                    being fattened on the rich pastures of the south. In the highland district,
                    farms for grazing arc necessarily of great extent. But it is not uncommon for
                    fishermen and mechanics to hold pendicles, or “poffles” as they arc called,
                    below L.12 of rent; and the cottars, who are usually employed as labourers on
                    the larger farms, possess small patches of arable ground for raising potatoes,
                    with hill pasture for a cow, at a rent of L.5, and sometimes less.</p>
                <p>Great improvements have been made on the roads intersecting this county. A new
                    road along the upper part of Lochlomond, and passing through Glenfalloch,
                    communicates with the great military road through Perthshire, Argyleshire,
                    &amp;c. and renders all parts of this county of easy access.</p>
                <p>The woods and plantations of this county are extensive and valuable. According to
                    the agricultural survey in 1810, their extent appears to be near 7000 English
                    acres, of which about the half is coppice; yielding to the proprietors a yearly
                    income almost equal to the rent of the arable lands. On spots unfavourable to
                    oak, these coppice woods consist of ash, yew, holly, mountain-ash, birch, hazel,
                    aspen, alder, crab, thorn, and willow. The age at which they are cut is from
                    twenty-two to twenty-four years, when they are worth from L.40 to L.45 an acre;
                    but there are instances of woods, of considerable extent, selling at much more,
                    where proper attention has been paid to inclosing them, and afterwards
                    thickening them by means of layers, or thinning them, as may be necessary. It is
                    the usual practice to reserve a certain number of young trees at each cutting,
                    the greater part of which are cut down at the second fall, when they are nearly
                    fifty years old, and the rest left to grow up to timber trees. The soil and
                    climate of this county are particularly favourable to plantations, which begin
                    to make a return to their owner in ten or twelve years, and.in thirty years
                    afford supplies to the carpenter. The most extensive plantations are on the
                    estates of Luss and Bonhill. There is a very fine ash in Bonhill church-yard,
                    the branches of which cover an area one hundred feet in diameter. Its trunk is
                    about nine feet high, the smallest diameter is six feet, and its three principal
                    branches are from ten to twelve feet in circumference. On the banks and islands
                    of Lochlomond there is a considerable number of yew trees, some of them of great
                    size.</p>
                <p>The manufactures of this county are various and extensive. The cotton works at
                    Duntocher, belonging to Mr Dunn of Duntocher, are the most extensive works oí
                    that description in Scotland. He gives employment to a population of 2500, and
                    he is the second landed proprietor in the county. There are two paper-mills at
                    Dalmuir; two extensive ship-building yards, three large glass manufactories, and
                    two tan-works, at Dumbarton; a manufacture of alkali at Burnfoot of Dalmuir; and
                    a distillery of pyroligneous acid at Milburn. On the short course of the river
                    Leven, not much exceeding three miles in a direct line, there are twelve large
                    print-fields and bleachfields. The extent of the whole, in 1810, is thus
                    stated:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ground occupied, about (Scotch
                            acres)</p><p>Value of buildings and machinery</p><p>Coals consumed
                            annually, tons</p><p>Yearly expense in fuel</p><p>Number of persons
                            employed, of both sexes am</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>350</p><p>L.250,000</p><p>32,000</p><p>..L.19,000 d</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>all ages</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Average earnings about 2s. a
                            day.</p><p>Total yearly wages, allowing for interruptions from sickness
                            and other causes</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>..L.90,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Excise duties annually</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>.L. 140,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Besides these large establishments, there is a number of lint-mills, two
                    woollen-mills, chiefly employed in carding, and several fulling-mills.</p>
                <p>The gross produce of the salmon-fisheries of this county may be about L.1000 a
                    year; the principal are upon the rivers Leven and Clyde. Those on Lochlomond are
                    comparatively of little importance. About fifty boats are employed in the
                    herring fishery, of which the annual value may be about L.4500.</p>
                <p>The rates of wages are higher in this than in most of the Scottish counties. In
                    1810, farm servants, who are for the most part unmarried, had from L.35 to L.42
                    a year; and when manufactures are prosperous, many of the workmen<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193326515?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-6515-0260"/> in them earn
                    nearly twice as much. Provisions are also dear; and fuel, which consists
                    principally of coal, the greater part of it brought from the adjoining counties,
                    is in many parts higher priced than in our largest cities. There were about 274
                    paupers in the county in 1811; but few of them were maintained solely on
                    parochial charity. Such as are able to gain their subsistence in part by their
                    own industry, receive only what is necessary to support them in addition to
                    their own earnings; and those who are altogether incapable of work are in most
                    cases relieved by the charity of individuals, the parish paying only for clothes
                    and house rent. The whole sum expended by the parishes does not much exceed
                    L.1000 a year, of which a small part is raised by assessment. The rent of land
                    and interest of capital amount to L.200, incidental funds to L.120, and the
                    collections at the churches to L.390.</p>
                <p>The following is a tabular view of the population of this county :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Arrochar parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1801.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1811.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>470</p><p>2,460</p><p>2,549</p><p>1,795</p><p>2,541</p><p>879</p><p>1,404</p><p>2,844</p><p>3,210</p><p>953</p><p>632</p><p>970</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>420</p><p>2,791</p><p>2,859</p><p>2,334</p><p>3,121</p><p>898</p><p>1,643</p><p>3,428</p><p>3,740</p><p>965</p><p>747</p><p>1,243</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>376 3,003 3,105 2,864 3,481 1,008
                            1,545 3,692 4,580 1,150</p><p>754</p><p>1,759</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>559</p><p>3,874</p><p>3,596</p><p>3,080</p><p>3,623</p><p>999</p><p>1,675</p><p>5,879</p><p>5,888</p><p>1,181</p><p>825
                            2,032</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bonhill ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cardross ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cumbernauld ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Dumbarton burgh and parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kilmaronock parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kilpatrick, New or East,
                            parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kilpatrick, Old or West,
                            parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kirkintilloch parish</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Luss ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>R∩seneat,h ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Row ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>County of Dumbarton</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20,710</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24,189</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27,317</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>33,200</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dumbarton,</hi> the capital of Dumbartonshire, in Scotland,
                    is situated at the confluence of the rivers Clyde and Leven. It is a very
                    ancient place, and is said to have been once the capital of a kingdom of the
                    Britons, established in the vale of the Clyde. Alcluyd was the name of this
                    ancient capital of the Strathclydenses; but whether it was situated on the site
                    of the present town, or confined within the precincts of the castle, cannot be
                    exactly ascertained. Dumbarton is built upon the eastern bank of the Leven,
                    which almost encircles it. The greater part of the town is composed of one main
                    street, lying in a semicircular form round the head or west end of the
                    peninsula. At the height of the tides it is flooded by the waters of the Leven.
                    It was erected into a royal burgh by Alexander II. in the year 1221, and
                    declared to be free of all imposts and burgh taxes; it afterwards received other
                    charters front succeeding monarchs; and, finally, it obtained a confirmation of
                    the whole from James VI. The subsequent history of the burgh is destitute of
                    interest. It naturally partook of the fortunes and misfortunes of the adjacent
                    part, of which it was in reality a dependency. Besides the main street, there
                    are some bye thoroughfares, lanes, and detached houses, and a suburb on the
                    western side of the Leven, leading to Renton. It is connected with the latter by
                    a good stone bridge of five arches, 300 feet long. The waters of the Leven form
                    a commodious harbour, and, for the benefit of trade, an excellent quay and
                    capacious dock have been formed. Ship-building is carried on to some extent. The
                    principal article of manufacture and export is glass. The glass-works, which are
                    situated to the north-west of the town, give employment to a great number of
                    individuals; and the article made is considered as equal to any manufactured in
                    Britain. The other and inferior manufactures of Dumbarton are leather, glue,
                    some linen, beer, &amp;c. with a considerable quantity of goods for the Glasgow
                    market. In recent years the intercourse and trade with Glasgow have been much
                    extended by means of steam navigation. Dumbarton has an important cattle market
                    every year on the 4th of June. There are two other fairs throughout the year,
                    and the town has a large weekly market on Tuesdays. The burgal government of the
                    town consists of a provost, an elder and younger bailie, a dean of guild, a
                    treasurer, five merchant councillors, and five trades councillors from the same
                    number of incorporated trades. The town has an excellent grammar-school, and a
                    good subscription library. A branch of the Commercial Bank is settled here, and
                    there are a number of agents of insurance offices. A very excellent jail has
                    recently been erected. The church of the burgh and parish is a handsome modern
                    structure with a spire and clock. There are also in the town and its vicinity a
                    burgher and relief meeting house, and a Roman Catholic chapel. The town is the
                    seat of a presbytery in the synod of Glasgow. By the late reform act Dumbarton
                    joins with Kilmarnock, Rutherglcn, Renfrew, and Port Glasgow in returning a
                    member to parliament. The situation of Dumbarton Castle is eminently
                    picturesque. The buildings composing the fort are perched on the summit of a
                    rocky mount, shooting up to the height of 206 feet sheer out of the alluvial
                    plain on the east side of the débouché of the river Leven. To the west of the
                    castle there are rocky eminences on the verge of the Clyde, of a similar fabric,
                    though less detached. The rock of Dumbarton measures a mile in circumference at
                    the base. It diminishes in breadth near the top, which is cloven into two
                    summits, of different heights. The rock is basalt, and has a tendency to the
                    columnar formation. Some parts of it have a magnetic quality. The fortress,
                    naturally strong, possesses several batteries, which command a most extensive
                    range. The defences arc kept in constant repair, and it is garrisoned by a
                    limited body of soldiers and functionaries. The rock of Dumbarton has been
                    occupied by works of a warlike character during the successive dynasties of 1800
                    years, and, as such, it is the most ancient stronghold in the country of which
                    any record or tradition is preserved; nor is it necessary to observe, that it
                    was the scene of many a gallant exploit to be found recorded in the annals of
                    the country. Dumbarton is fifteen miles north-west of Glasgow, and fifty-nine
                    west of Edinburgh. The population of the burgh and parish amounted in 1821 to
                    3481, and in 1831 to 3623.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
