<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-4435-0100-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DOMESTIC (7th edition, volume 8, page 100)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193324435?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DOMESTIC</label>, any man who acts under another, and serves
                    to compose part of his family. Sometimes the term domestics is applied to the
                    wife and children, but most frequently to servants, such as footmen, lacqueys,
                    porters, and the like.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Domestic,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> is sometimes
                    opposed to foreign. Thus <hi rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic">domestic</hi>
                    occurrences” signify those events which happen in our own country, in
                    contradistinction to those of which we receive intelligence from abroad.</p>
                <p>In its more usual acceptation, the term implies something peculiar to <hi
                    rend="italic">home</hi> or <hi rend="italic">household.</hi> Thus we speak of
                    <hi rend="italic">domestic</hi> happiness or pleasures, meaning the pleasures
                    enjoyed in the bosom of one’s family; in opposition to those which are found in
                    the bustle of public life, or delusively sought for in the haunts of
                    dissipation.</p>
                <p>The solace of domestic enjoyment has been coveted by the wisest and greatest of
                    men. Senators and heroes have shut out the acclamations of an applauding world,
                    in order to enjoy the society of their little ones, and to partake the
                    endearments of family conversation. They knew that even their best friends, in
                    the common intercourse of life, were in some degree actuated by interested
                    motives in displaying their affection; that many of their followers applauded
                    them in hopes of reward; and that the giddy multitude, however zealous, were not
                    always judicious in their approbation. But the attentions paid them at their
                    fire-side, and the smiles which exhilarated their own table, were the genuine
                    result of undissembled love.</p>
                <p>“The nursery has often alleviated the fatigues of the bar and the senate-house,”
                    says an excellent essayist, (Knox). “Nothing contributes more to raise the
                    gently pleasing emotions than the view of infant innocence enjoying the raptures
                    of a game at play. All the sentiments of uncontrolled nature display themselves
                    to the view, and furnish matter for agreeable reflection to the mind of the
                    philosophical observer. To partake with children in their little pleasures is by
                    no means unmanly. It is one of the purest sources of mirth. It has an influence
                    in amending the heart, which necessarily takes a tincture from the company that
                    surrounds us. Innocence as well as guilt is communicated and increased by the
                    contagion of example. And the great Author of evangelical philosophy has taught
                    us to emulate the simplicity of the infantine age. He seems indeed himself to
                    have been delighted with young children, and found in them what he in vain
                    sought among those who judged themselves their superiors, unpolluted purity of
                    heart.</p>
                <p>“Among the great variety of pictures which the vivid imagination of Homer has
                    displayed throughout the Iliad, there is not one more pleasing than the
                    family-piece which represents the parting interview between Hector and
                    Andromache. It deeply interests the heart, while it delights the imagination.
                    The hero ceases to be terrible, that he may become amiable. We admire him while
                    he stands completely armed in the field of battle; but we love him more while he
                    is taking off his helmet, that he may not frighten his little boy with its
                    nodding plumes. We are refreshed with the tender scene of domestic love, while
                    all around breathes rage and discord. We are pleased to see the arm, which is
                    shortly to deal death and destruction among an host of foes, employed in
                    caressing an infant son with the embraces of paternal love. A professed critic
                    would attribute the pleasing effect entirely to contrast; but the heart has
                    declared, previously to the inquiries of criticism, that it is chiefly derived
                    from the satisfaction which we naturally take in beholding great characters
                    engaged in tender and amiable employments.</p>
                <p>“But after all that is said of the purity and the solidity of domestic pleasures,
                    they unfortunately appear to a great part of mankind insipid, unmanly, and
                    capable of satisfying none but the weak, the spiritless, the inexperienced, and
                    the effeminate. The pretenders to wit and modern philosophy are often found to
                    renounce the received opinions of prudential conduct, and, while they affect a
                    superior liberality, to regulate their lives by the most selfish principles.
                    Whatever appears to have little tendency to promote personal pleasure and
                    advantage, they leave to be performed by those simple individuals who are dull
                    enough, as they say, to pursue the journey of life by the straight road of
                    common sense. It is true, they will allow that the world must be replenished by
                    a perpetual succession; and it is no less true, that an offspring once
                    introduced into the world requires all the care of painful attention. But let
                    the task be reserved for meaner spirits. If the passions can be gratified
                    without the painful consequences of supporting a family, they eagerly seize the
                    indulgence; but the toil of education they leave to those whom they deem fools
                    enough to take a pleasure in it. There will always be a sufficient number, say
                    they, whose folly will lead them, for the sake of a silly passion called
                    virtuous love, to engage in a life of perpetual anxiety. The fool’s paradise,
                    they add with derision, will never be deserted.</p>
                <p>“Presumptuous as are all such pretenders to newly-invented systems of life and
                    conduct, it is not to be supposed<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193324448?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-4448-0101"/> they will
                    think themselves superior to Cicero. Yet Cicero, with all his liberality of
                    mind, felt the tenderness of conjugal and parental attachment, and acknowledged
                    that at one time he received no satisfaction in any company but that of his
                    wife, his little daughter, and, to use his own epithet, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >honied</hi> young Cicero. The great Sir Thomas More, whom nobody will suspect
                    of narrowness of mind, who, by a very singular treatise, evinced that he was
                    capable of thinking and of choosing for himself, has left it çn record that he
                    devoted a great share of his time, from the united motives of duty and delight,
                    to the amusement of his children.</p>
                <p>“It will be objected by those who pretend to have formed their ideas of life from
                    actual observation, that domestic happiness, however pleasing in description,
                    like many a poetic dream, is but an alluring picture, designed by a good heart,
                    and painted in glowing colours by a lively fancy. The constant company, they
                    urge, even of those we love, occasions an insipidity. Insipidity grows into
                    disgust. Disgust long continued sours the temper. Peevishness is the natural
                    consequence. The domestic circle becomes the scene of dispute. Mutual antipathy
                    is ingenious in devising mutual torment. Sullen silence or malignant remarks
                    fill up every hour, till the arrival of a stranger causes a temporary restraint,
                    and excites that good humour which ought to be displayed among those whom the
                    bonds of affection and blood have already united.</p>
                <p>“Experience, indeed, proves that these remarks are sometimes verified. But that
                    there is much domestic misery is no argument that there is no domestic
                    happiness, or that the evil may not be removed. Natural stupidity, natural ill
                    temper, acquired ill habits, want of education, illiberal manners, and a neglect
                    of the common rules of discretion, will render every species of intercourse
                    disagreeable. When those are united by connubial ties who were separated by
                    natural and inherent diversity, no wonder if that degree of happiness which can
                    only result from a proper union is unknown. In the forced alliance which the
                    poet of Venusium mentions, of the serpent with the dove, of the tiger with the
                    lamb, there can be no love. When we expatiate on the happiness of the domestic
                    group, we presuppose that all who compose it are originally assimilated by
                    affection, and are still kept in union by discreet friendship. When this is not
                    the case, the censure must fall on the discordant disposition of the parties,
                    and not on the essential nature of family intercourse.</p>
                <p>“To form under the direction of prudence, and by the impulse of virtuous love, an
                    early conjugal attachment, is one of the best securities of virtue, as well as
                    the most probable means of happiness. The duties which are powerfully called
                    forth by the relations of husband and father, are of that tender kind which
                    inspires goodness and humanity. He who beholds a woman whom he loves, and a
                    helpless infant looking up to him for support, will not easily be induced to
                    indulge in unbecoming extravagance, or devote himself to indolence. He who has a
                    rising family to introduce into a vicious world, will be cautious of setting a
                    bad example, the contagion of which, when it proceeds from parental authority,
                    must be irresistibly malignant. Thus many who, in their individual and
                    unconnected state, would probably have spent a life not only useless to others,
                    but profligate and careless in itself, have become valuable members of the
                    community, and have arrived at a degree of moral improvement to which .they
                    would not otherwise have attained.</p>
                <p>“The contempt in which domestic pleasures have in modern times been held, is a
                    mark of profligacy. It is also a proof of a prevailing ignorance of real
                    enjoyment. It argues a defect in taste and judgment as well as in morals; for
                    the general voice of the experienced has in all ages declared, that the truest
                    happiness is to be found at home.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
