<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-1941-0202-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AURUNGABAD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q80j">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1043442">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193191941?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">AURUNGABAD</label>, a large province of Hindostan,
                    in the Deccan, about 300 miles in length by 160 in average breadth. It is
                    situated principally between the 18th and 19th degrees of north latitude, and is
                    bounded on the north by Gujerat, Khandeish, and Berar; on the east by Beeder; on
                    the south by Bejapoor, from which it is separated by the Neera and Beema rivers;
                    and on the west by the Indian Ocean. The great chain of the Ghauts runs through
                    this province in a direction north and south, at the distance of about 100 miles
                    from the Indian Ocean, and rises to a very considerable elevation; and the
                    surface of the country, particularly in their neighbourhood, is irregular, and
                    in general mountainous. The rivers which rise on the western declivity of these
                    mountains, and flow into the Indian Ocean, have necessarily a short course, and
                    are inconsiderable in size; while those again which have their sources on the
                    eastern declivity of the mountains, and flow eastward into the Bay of Bengal,
                    such as the Beema, the Neera, and the Godavery, do not attain any considerable
                    size until they are beyond the limits of this province. Rice is the great staple
                    of agriculture, especially in the lower districts, which are in general fertile,
                    and, besides supplying the wants of the inhabitants, yield a surplus for
                    exportation. A different mode of agriculture is however followed in the higher
                    districts. The other vegetable productions, besides rice, are the same as in
                    other parts of Ĥindostan. Horses of a hardy breed are reared in great numbers
                    for the Mahratta caValry; but they are neither strong nor handsome, though they
                    suit the light weight of the riders for whom they are intended. A great
                    proportion oí this province, and almost all the sea-coast, were long in
                    possession of the Mahrattas, who were pirates by sea as well as robbers by land:
                    they seldom ventured on the ocean except as pirates, and they continued their
                    predatory habits by sea and by land until they were restrained by the strong arm
                    of British power. Three-fourths or the province were formerly subject to the
                    Peishwa, and the remainder to the Nizam; with the exception of the islands of
                    Bombay, Salsette, and a few tracts on the main land. 1he inhabitants are not
                    supposed to exceed six millions, of whom not above one-twentieth are of the
                    Mahometan persuasion. The language commonly used is the Mahratta, but there are
                    besides various provincial dialects.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Aurungλbad,</hi> the capital of the above province,
                    which <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191954?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0704-1954-0203"/> was formerly named Guřka. It was the capital
                    of the Mogul conquests; and having become the favourite residence of Aurungzebe
                    during his viceroyalty of the Deccan, it received the name of Aurungabad, from
                    which the name of the province was derived. The city contained the capital of
                    the modern Nizams after they became independent of Delhi, until they quitted it
                    for Hyderabad. The city has fallen from its ancient grandeur. The interior is
                    but half peopled and in ruins, and presents all the appearances of desertion and
                    decay. The population is, however, still considerable; and in the bazaar, which
                    is very extensive, are exposed for sale various kinds of commodities, European
                    and Indian, particularly silks and shawls. The walls are similar in their
                    construction to those of all the other cities in this quarter in India, being
                    rather low, with round towers. The travelling distance from Poona is 186 miles,
                    from Bombay by Poona 284, from Hyderabad 295, from Madras 647, from Delhi 750,
                    and from Calcutta 1022 miles. Long. 75. 33. E. Lat. 19. 54. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
