<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0897-0860-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">UPSALA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 860</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1144248">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937845">Gardeners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n897/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">UPSALA</label>, a city of Sweden, the seat of its oldest
                    university and residence of the archbishop of Sweden, is situated on the small
                    river Fyris, 42 miles north of Stockholm. In spite of its position in a vast and
                    fertile plain, Upsala was a rather insignificant little town till the opening of
                    railway communication in 1866. The population, which in 1840 was only 5100, had
                    at the end of 1885 increased to more than 20,000 (with students, scholars, and
                    others, 23,000). The industries of the place are still unimportant, but its
                    trade by sea (navigation being open for six or seven months of the year) and by
                    rail is somewhat livelier. Upsala owes its fame to its university, which was
                    founded in 1477. In 1624 Gustavus Adolphus endowed it with 300 farms, the
                    revenue of which formed its entire income for more than two hundred years.
                    Parliament now contributes nearly the half of its whole revenue (393,300 crowns,
                    or about £21,800, in 1885). The professors numbered 58 in 1887, with 61
                    “docents” and assistant teachers, and there were 1928 students. The last-named
                    are divided into 13 “nations” (based on the old ecclesiastical division of the
                    country), almost every one of which possesses a house of its own, with a hall,
                    readingrooms, and library. About £7200 is distributed yearly in “stipendia” or
                    scholarships. The new university house, above the cathedral, on the site of the
                    former archbishop’s castle, is in the Renaissance style, and was built in
                    1879-87. It has a great hall capable of holding 2000 persons, eleven
                    lecture-rooms, &amp;c. The vestibule, lighted from above by three large cupolas,
                    and surrounded by open galleries, is particularly fine. The library building
                    (called Carolina Rediviva, in remembrance of the Carolina which formerly existed
                    near the cathedral) was erected in 1819-41. The library, which has a right to a
                    copy of every book printed in Sweden, at present (1887) contains 250,000 volumes
                    and 11,000 MSS., among which is the famous <hi rend="italic">Codex</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Argenteus</hi> of Ulfilas’s translation of the Gospels. The
                    “Gustavianum,” built by order of Gustavus Adolphus for a university house, is
                    now wholly occupied by the zoological institution. The botanical garden (which
                    formerly belonged to the castle) was presented by Gustavus III. to the
                    university in 1787,—the former garden (in the northern part of the city), where
                    Rudbeck and Linnaeus worked, and where the residence of the latter is still to
                    be seen, having been found too small and inconvenient. The medical faculty
                    possesses a hospital and anatomical, chemical, and pathologico-physiological
                    institutions; and about a mile from the town there is a magnificent lunatic
                    asylum. The astronomical and meteorological institutions, as well as those of
                    chemistry and physics, have also special buildings, all of recent date. The
                    Royal Society of Sciences, established in 1710 by Eric Benzelius, the younger,
                    occupies a house of its own, and has a valuable library. Of the buildings the
                    cathedral, founded in the latter part of the 13th century and completed in 1435,
                    is the most remarkable. The material is brick, but the proportions are
                    uncommonly noble and harmonious; the length is 390 feet, and the height inside
                    88. It has suffered considerably from repeated fires, but since 1886 an
                    extensive restoration has been going on. The castle, on the summit of a long
                    ridge above the town, was founded in 1548 by Gustavus I., but not finished till
                    a century later, when it was often used as a royal residence. It was destroyed
                    by fire in 1702, and for more than forty years remained a ruin. At present only
                    a small part of it is habitable, and that part is chiefly used by the provincial
                    government, and as a residence of the governor. Apart from the cathedral and a
                    few insignificant houses, there are no remains from the mediaeval period, the
                    city formerly having consisted almost entirely of wooden houses.</p>
                <p>The name of Upsala originally belonged to a place nearly 2 miles to the north of
                    the present city, which is still called Old Upsala. This Upsala, mentioned as
                    early as the 9th century, was famous throughout Scandinavia for its splendid
                    heathen temple, which, gleaming with gold, made it the centre of Svithiod, then
                    divided into a great number of kingdoms; three huge grave mounds or barrows
                    still commemorate old times. In the same place the first cathédral of the
                    bishops of Upsala was also erected (about 1100). On the destruction of this
                    building by fire, the inconvenient situation caused the removal in 1273 of the
                    archiépiscopal see to the present city, then called Ostra Aros,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The name first occurs in
                    Snorro Sturluson in connexion with the events of the year 1018; it signifies
                    “the mouth of the eastern river.”</p></note> but within a comparatively short
                    time it came to be generally called Upsala. During the Middle Ages the cathedral
                    and the see of the archbishop made Upsala a kind of ecclesiastical capital.
                    There the kings were crowned, after the election had taken place at the Mora
                    stones, 10 miles south-east of Upsala. As early as the 14th century, however,
                    Stockholm became the proper residence of the king. In 1567 Erik XIV. murdered in
                    the castle five of the most eminent men of the kingdom, three of them belonging
                    to the family of Sture. In 1593 was held the great synod which marks the final
                    victory of Protestantism in Sweden; in the same year the university was restored
                    by Charles IX. In the castle Christina, daughter of Gustavus Adolphus, resigned
                    her crown to Charles X. in 1654. In 1702 nearly the whole city, with the castle
                    and the cathedral, was burnt down. Among the teachers of the university who have
                    carried its name beyond the boundaries of their own country, the following
                    (besides Linnaeus) deserve to be mentioned :—Olof Rudbeck the elder, the author
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Atlantica</hi> (1630-1702); Torbem Bergman (1735-1784),
                    the celebrated chemist; and Erik Gustaf Geijer (1783-1847), the historian.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
