<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-1420-0474-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FABROT, Charles-Annibal</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 474</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:828176">Basilicas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:862898">Civilization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110280">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45s7h">Basilicas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46m3337r">Civilization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nj3s">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193751420" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FABROT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles-Annibal</hi></label>,
                    one of the most celebrated jurisconsults of his time, was born in 1580, at Aix
                    in I ιovence, whither his father, originally of Nismes, had gone to establish
                    himself during the civil wars. His earlv studies were successfully prosecuted,
                    and he made great progress in the ancient languages and in the civil and the
                    canon law. In 1606 he took the degree of doctor, and was soon afterwards
                    admitted as advocate before the parliament of Aix. As this court then reckoned
                    amongst its members men of distinguished merit, such as the celebrated Peiresc
                    and William Duvair, who was its first president, their common taste for letters
                    naturally united them with Fabrot, for whom, in 1609, Duvair procured a
                    professorship in the university of Aix. Having become keeper of the seals, the
                    latter carried his young friend with him to Paris, where Fabrot remained until
                    after the death of his benefactor, when he returned to resume his peaceful
                    functions as professor. But these did not absorb the whole of his time, and he
                    employed his leisure in other labours, which, however, had all a relation to
                    jurisprudence. The great interpreters whom the sixteenth century produced had
                    left almost nothing to be added in regard to the books of this science written
                    in Latin. But Fabrot opened for himself a different path. The successors of
                    Justinian on the throne of Constantinople had caused to be executed in Greek an
                    abridgment of his compilations, to which were added articles taken from the
                    fathers and the councils; and to this abridgment Leo the Philosopher gave the
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Basilica,</hi> which, in fact, formed the code of the
                    eastern empire until its destruction. The <hi rend="italic">Basilica,</hi> long
                    unknown, were in some sort discovered by Cujas, who made great use of them in
                    his writings, but did not publish them. Fabrot, however, undertook this task,
                    and, about 1639, extracted from this collection, and published in Greek and
                    Latin, fourteen laws, which are wanting in the Digest. These, with some other
                    productions of Fabrot, were inserted by Everard Otton in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thesaurus Juris</hi><hi rend="italic">Civilis.</hi> Of the sixty books of which
                    the <hi rend="italic">Basilica</hi> were composed, thirteen have been lost.
                    Those which remain Fabrot translated; and he supplied, by means of summaries,
                    the place of those which are lost. This work, consisting of seven volumes in
                    folio, was published in 1647 at Paris, where Fabrot had now established himself,
                    and was dedicated to the Chancellor Seguier, through whose influence, exerted in
                    his favour, he obtained a considerable pension, by means of which he was enabled
                    to continue his useful labours. Matthieu Mole, at first procureur-général, then
                    first president anti keeper of the seals, a man whose heroic firmness is so well
                    known, and Jerome Bignon, a magistrate distinguished for his knowledge and
                    integrity, likewise gave Fabrot proofs of the estimation in which they held his
                    talents. Besides the <hi rend="italic">Basilica,</hi> the latter also translated
                    into Latin the Greek paraphrase which Theophilus had made of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutions</hi> of Justinian (Paris, 1638 and 1657, in 4to)∙ The
                    particular nature of his pursuits having rendered him familiar with the
                    Byzantine historians, Fabrot published several of their works, such as those of
                    Cedrenus, Nicetas, Anastasius the Librarian, and others, enriched wit <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> notes and dissertations. And as he was not only
                    acquainted with the civil, but also with the canon law of t e lower empire,
                    which in fact form but one whole; whet Justel and William Voet compiled their
                    Library of Canot Law, which appeared in 1661, they inserted in that compilation
                    the constitutions of Theodorus Balsamon, wuc were found amongst the papers of
                    Fabrot, with notes in '&gt;s peculiar manner. But one of the undertakings ¶ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ιc</hi> have done the greatest honour to this learned
                    juriscon suit, is his edition of the works of Cujas, which he co^ rected
                    according to several manuscripts, and enriche' <hi rend="superscript"> w</hi>
                    notes and several treatises of Cujas, which had not f viously seen the light.
                    Before the appearance o t of Naples and of Venice, this was the best of all t
                    <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193751433"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-1433-0475"/>tions of Cujas. Fabrot commenced it in 1652, and
                    completed it in 1658. It is believed that the continued and intense application
                    which he bestowed on this work caused the malady of which he died on the 16th of
                    January 1659. His reputation was so extensive, that the most celebrated
                    universities of France desired to have the benefit of his services as professor
                    of law; but he refused every offer of the kind which was made to him, however
                    advantageous, that his attention might not be diverted from the great
                    undertakings in which he had embarked. Fabrot wrote, 1. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epistola</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Mutuo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">cum</hi><hi rend="italic">responsione</hi><hi rend="italic">Cl.
                    Salmasii ad Mena- (jinrn,</hi> Leyden, 1645, in 8vo; 2. <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Antiquités</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Ville de Marseille,</hi> translated from
                    the Latin of J. Raymond de Solier, Marseilles, 1615, and Lyons, 1632, in 8vo; 3.
                    <hi rend="italic">Exercitationes duce</hi><hi rend="italic">de tempore
                    partus</hi><hi rend="italic">humani</hi><hi rend="italic">£t de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">numero puerperii,</hi> Aix, 1629, in 4to; 4. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proelectio in</hi><hi rend="italic">titulum Decretalium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >“</hi><hi rend="italic">De vita</hi><hi rend="italic">et honestate
                    Clericoum,</hi>” Paris, 1651, in 4to; 5. <hi rend="italic">Notae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">at titulum Codicis Theodosiani “De papariis sacrificiis et
                    templis,</hi>” Paris, 1648, in 4to.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
