<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-3331-0621-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLEURY, Claude</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 621</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:981348">Jansenists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1112660">Sentimentalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193753331" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FLEURY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude</hi></label>,
                    sub-prcceptor of the young princes of France, was the son of an advocate before
                    the council, originally from Rouen, and born at Paris on the 6th of December
                    1640. He studied under the Jesuits, in the College of Clermont, where he passed
                    six years; and he ever afterwards cherished sentiments of the liveliest
                    gratitude towards his kind and able masters. Being intended by his father for
                    the bar, he now applied himself to the study of the civil law and of history, to
                    which he added the belles-lettres, for which he had a strong predilection, and
                    he was admitted as an advocate before the parliament of Paris in 1658. He
                    remained at the bar nine years, during which time the peaceable life he led, a
                    natural taste for solitude, and religious sentiments, the fruits of his early
                    education, insensibly produced in his mind an inclination for the church. As
                    soon as his resolution was fixed, he made a corresponding change in his
                    pursuits, and the works which had hitherto been the objects of his study were
                    replaced by theology, the fathers, ecclesiastical history, and the canon law, in
                    all which he became very learned. He had already been some time in priest’s
                    orders, when, in 1672, he was chosen, on account of his merit, as preceptor to
                    the sons of the Prince of Conti, who were educated along with the dauphin. At
                    the expiration of this engagement, the king, who had occasion to observe and
                    appreciate his merit, entrusted him with the education of the Count of
                    Vermandois, which, however, he did not complete, as this young prince died in
                    1683. In 1684, the king conferred on him the abbey of Loc-Dieu, belonging to the
                    order of Citeaux; and in 1689, appointed him sub-preceptor to the Dukes of
                    Burgundy, Anjou, and Berry. The Abbé Fleury having thus found himself associated
                    with Fénélon, shared the labour which that illustrious prelate bestowed on the
                    education of his august pupils, and contributed essentially to its success. It
                    was in 1696, whilst he was still occupied with the instruction of the princes,
                    that he was named one of the forty of the French Academy to fill the place of La
                    Bruyère. In other respects he led as retired a life at court as he could have
                    done in the most profound solitude. Entirely occupied with the duties of his
                    office, to which he devoted himself without reserve, he had but few moments of
                    leisure; but these, when he could command them, were given to useful pursuits.
                    When the education of the princes was completed, Louis, who not only knew howto
                    distinguish talents, but also how to reward them, conferred on Fleury the rich
                    priory of Argenteuil; upon which the abbe, faithful to the discipline
                    established by the canons, resigned his abbey into the hands of the king. It was
                    then that, free from all care, he devoted himself entirely to pursuits worthy a
                    man of his station; but Louis XIV. having died, in 1716, he was recalled to the
                    court by the regent, to become confessor to the young king. In appointing him to
                    this office the regent is reported to have said, “I have chosen you because you
                    are neither Jansenist, nor M&lt; linist, nor Ultramontanist.” Fleury discharged
                    with zeal and sagacity the delicate functions of his new situation, which,
                    however, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193753344" xml:id="kp-eb0709-3344-0622"/>he
                    resigned in 1722, by reason of his great age. He died on the 14th of July 1723,
                    in his eighty-third year. Fleury was alike remarkable for his great learning and
                    extreme simplicity of manners; in him Christian humility was blended with true
                    dignity, and the gentlest disposition with the loftiest spirit. He was mild,
                    affable, benign, charitable; an ardent lover of truth, and a bright pattern of
                    those virtues which he inculcated on others. His understanding, naturally
                    excellent, was cultivated with infinite labour; and his heart was as carefully
                    disciplined as his understanding. Profound knowledge, sterling rectitude of
                    principle, innocent manners, a simple, laborious, and edifying life, sincere
                    modesty, admirable disinterestedness, unfailing regularity, and the utmost
                    fidelity in the discharge of all his duties; such are the traits of the
                    character of Fleury as delineated by his contemporaries; a character which, in
                    their judgment, exhibited an assemblage of all the talents and virtues which
                    form the profound scholar, the honest man, and the devout Christian. The
                    following is a list of the numerous works which he left behind him, part of
                    which were composed during brief snatches of leisure, whilst occupied with the
                    education of his different royal and noble pupils: 1. <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    du Droit Français,</hi> 1674, in 12mo; 2. <hi rend="italic">Catéchisme
                    Historique,</hi> Paris, 1679, in 12mo; 3. <hi rend="italic">Les Moeurs</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Israelites,</hi> Paris, 1681, in 12mo; 4. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les Moeurs</hi><hi rend="italic">des Chrétiens,</hi> 1682, in 12mo; 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">La</hi><hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                    vénérable</hi><hi rend="italic">mere Marguerite d’Arbouze,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >abbesse et reformatrice du Val-de-</hi><hi rend="italic">Grace,</hi> Paris,
                    1684, in 8vo; 6. <hi rend="italic">Traite du choix et de la méthode des
                    Etudes,</hi> Paris, 1686, in 12mo; 7. <hi rend="italic">Institution au Droit
                    Ecclesiastique,</hi> Paris, 1687, in 2 vols. 12mo; 8. <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Devoirs des Maitres et des Domestiques,</hi> Paris, 1688, in 12mo; 9. <hi
                    rend="italic">La Traduction Latine de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Exposition de la Doctrine de</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Eglise Catholique par Bossuet,</hi> Antwerp, 1678, in 12mo; 10.
                    <hi rend="italic">Histoire Ecclésiastique,</hi> Paris, 1691 and the following
                    years, in 20 vols. 4to, continued by Père Fabre, of the Oratory, Paris, 1726 and
                    the following years, in 16 vols. 4to, making in all 36 vols. 4to; 11. <hi
                    rend="italic">Discours sur</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire Ecclésiastique,</hi> Paris, 1802, in 8vo; 12. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discours sur les Libertés de l’Eglise Gallicane,</hi> 1724. Besides these
                    works, the Abbé Fleury was also the author of the following, viz. 1. <hi
                    rend="italic">Discours sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la Predication,</hi> 1773, in
                    12mo; 2. <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">du Droit</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">publique de France,</hi> 1769, in 4 vols. 12mo; 3. <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Soldat Chrétien,</hi> 1772, in 12mo; 3. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lettres a Santeul, et deux Lettres en vers Latins;</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discours sur la Poésie et notamment sur celle des Hébreux;</hi> 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">Portrait du Duc dc Bourgogne, et Avis pour ce Prince;</hi> 6. <hi
                    rend="italic">Réflexions sur Machiavel;</hi> 7. <hi rend="italic">Lettres sur la
                    Justice;</hi> 8. <hi rend="italic">Pensées tirées de Saint-Augustin;</hi> 9. <hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires pour le Roi d’Espagne;</hi> 10. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discours Académiques.</hi> All the works of the Abbé Fleury, with the exception
                    of the Ecclesiastical History, were collected by Rondet, under the titles of <hi
                    rend="italic">Opuscules,</hi> Nismes, 1780, in 5 γols. 8vo; but Μ. Emery,
                    superiorgeneral of the Congregation of Saint-Sulpice, published a volume
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux</hi><hi rend="italic">Opuscules,</hi> Paris,
                    1807, in 12mo, containing several unedited pieces, some of them possessing
                    considerable merit.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
