<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-4930-0744-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FORFAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 744</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139579">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:999328">Lions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193754930" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FORFAR</label>, a county in Scotland, bounded by the shires
                    of Aberdeen and Kincardine on the north, the German Ocean on the east, the Frith
                    of Tay, which separates it from Fife, on the south, and the county of Perth on
                    the west. It is situated between 56° 27' and 57° north latitude, and between 2°
                    28' and 3° 22 ’ west longitude from Greenwich, and extends from north to south
                    from twenty-six to thirty-four miles, and twenty-three to thirty from west to
                    east. It contains, by the lowest computation, 832 square miles, or 532,480
                    English acres, without including portions of the parishes of Lundie, Cupar, and
                    Alyth, the greater part of which belongs to the county of Perth.</p>
                <p>More than a third of its area is occupied by the Grampians, here called the
                    Binchinnin Hills, on which it meets the Braes of Mar in Aberdeenshire. The
                    surface of this northern division of the county, or the Braes of Angus, with the
                    exception of the mountains at the head of Glen Clova, is not in general so bold
                    and abrupt as many other alpine districts of Scotland; the hills are for the
                    most part rounded, and rather tame, and covered with a thin coat of moorish
                    soil, carrying stunted heath. Catlaw, the highest, is 2264 feet above the level
                    of the sea. There are several considerable valleys in this district, the
                    principal of which are Glen Isla, Glen Prosen, Clova, Lethnot, and Glen Esk,
                    which are watered by streams that rise in the west and north, and commonly flow
                    south-east, receiving innumerable torrents from the mountains in their progress.
                    South from the Grampians, and parallel to them, is another but lower range,
                    called the Siedlaw Hills, supposed to be a continuation of the Ochils; some of
                    these hills are 1400 feet in height. Between these two grand divisions lies
                    Strathmore, the Great Valley, as the name denotes in Gaelic, or, as it is
                    commonly called, the How of Angus, extending about thirty-three miles in length,
                    and from six to eight in breadth; a district beautifully diversified by gentle
                    eminences, fertile fields, plantations, villages, and gentlemen’s seats, very
                    little of it being 200 feet above sea level. It was at one time proposed to
                    carry a canal through this valley, which might be extended to Dumbarton, and
                    thus connect the three great rivers of Scotland, the Clyde, the Forth, and the
                    Tay; another from Arbroath ts Forfar was also in contemplation; but neither of
                    them has been carried into effect. The fourth, and remaining division, extends
                    from the Siedlaw Hills to the German Ocean on the east, and the Frith of Tay on
                    the south, and is, with a few exceptions, a rich and well-cultivated tract,
                    varying in breadth from three to eight miles, and comprehending about a fourth
                    part of the whole county.</p>
                <p>The woods and plantations have been computed to extend to 35,000 acres, of which
                    about 5000 consist of coppice and natural wood. Several of the Grampian glens
                    are sprinkled with birches, oak, and hazels. The botany and zoology of the
                    county were explored with great industry some years ago by Mr George Don of
                    Forfar, who presented a very ample enumeration in both departments, in a paper
                    subjoined to Mr Headrick’s <hi rend="italic">Survey for the Board, of
                    Agriculture,</hi><hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> The general colour of the soils is
                    red, but often inclining <pb break="no" facs="nls:193754943"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-4943-0745"/>to dark brown or black. In the Grampians the soil
                    is often moorish, over whitish retentive clay, but loose and friable in the
                    glens. Over the puddingstone or gravelstone rock in the lower grounds, it is
                    sometimes thin, mossy, and encumbered with stones; and over the sandstone a
                    tenacious clay occurs. The soil above whinstone is fertile, though sometimes
                    shallow. In Strathmore it is often gravelly, in other parts a dead sand. There
                    is no great extent of moss; but what exists is of much value for fuel.</p>
                <p>The mineralogy of a considerable portion of Forfarshire was examined by Colonel
                    Imrie, who has given a minute description of it in a paper published in the
                    sixth volume of the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Society of
                    Edinburgh.</hi> In the Grampian district, towards the summit of the county, on
                    the confines of Aberdeenshire, the prevailing rock is granite, some of it very
                    beautiful, with topazes or rock-crystals in its cavities or fissures, known by
                    the name of <hi rend="italic">cairngorums,</hi> from a mountain of that name in
                    Aberdeenshire; also micaceous schistus, and porphyry dykes of the latter in some
                    places intersecting the former. Laminated talc or mica, called by the shepherds
                    <hi rend="italic">sheep’s siller,</hi> from its silvery lustre, which is
                    sometimes thickly studded with small garnets, is found in irregular veins, and
                    siliceous spar in jutting or detached hills. Lead was wrought at Gilfianan,
                    above the old castle of Innermark, in the upper part of the parish of Lochlee,
                    and also at Ardoch, near Mill-den, on the Esk. At the former place, according to
                    Edward, in his <hi rend="italic">Description of Angus,</hi> published in 1678,
                    it yielded one sixty-fourth part of silver; but both mines have long since been
                    abandoned. Limestone in small quantities frequently occurs, and is wrought in
                    several parts; there are also broad veins of slate, but which, it is said, does
                    not come off in plates of sufficient size for use. In descending the Grampians
                    to Strathmore, gravelstone prevails, and afterwards, on the lower grounds,
                    sandstone. Clay marl is found both in Strathmore and the Siedlaw Hills, but is
                    little used. Shell marl is in greater request, and abounds in different parts,
                    particularly in the lochs of Kin-ordie, near the bottom of the Grampians, Lundie
                    in the Siedlaw Hills, Logie in the parish of Kirriemuir, and Restennet near
                    Forfar. These lochs have been drained and rendered of easy access. It is also
                    found in the lochs of Forfar, Rescobie, and Balgavies, where it is raised by
                    scoops, and conveyed to the shore in boats. The Siedlaw Hills are chiefly
                    composed of sandstone of various colours, some of it susceptible of a high
                    polish. Sandstone flags, which are much used instead of slate for covering
                    roofs, are raised in great quantities on the hill of Balmashanner, and in the
                    moor to the south of Forfar; but the most extensive range of these flags is in
                    the parish of Carmylie, and along the southern declivity of the Siedlaw Hills.
                    The principal lime-works are in the maritime division, at Hedderwick near
                    Montrose, and at Boddin in the parish of Craig, upon the sea-shore. The only*
                    mineral springs are chalybeate, one of which is near Montrose, another to the
                    west of Arbroath, two in the side of a rivulet about a mile farther west, and
                    one in the north-west corner of Dumbarrow in the parish ofDunichen.</p>
                <p>The heaviest rains are from the east and south-east, and the heaviest snows from
                    the north and north-east. At Crescent, half a mile westward of Dundee, the
                    quantity of rain that fell during six years, from 1790 to 1795 inclusive, varied
                    from 22∙27 to 34∙12 inches; but at Belmont, in the centre of Strathmore, during
                    the same years, it was from 31∙45 to 39∙55 inches. The mean height of the
                    barometer at Belmont, during the first three of these years, was 29∙60, and that
                    of the thermometer 42°. At Crescent, the mean degree of cold during winter, for
                    the whole period, was from 32ģ°.to 39J <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>, and of
                    heat during summer, from 60+ to 66°. The south-east wind blows at Crescent
                    twenty-one, and the south-west one hundred and nine days annually; whereas at
                    Belmont the former prevails eighty-five and the latter one hundred and
                    thirty-eight days.</p>
                <p>The principal lochs or lakes have been already mentioned as containing
                    shell-marl. To these may be added Lochlee among the Grampians, from which the
                    North Esk issues, and Lentrathan near their base. None of the streams are so
                    considerable as to have the name of rivers, but are called waters. The <hi
                    rend="italic">North Esk,</hi> after leaving Lochlee, flows towards the east, and
                    then the south-east, where it forms the boundary between this county and
                    Kincardineshire, and falls into the sea about three miles north-east of
                    Montrose, having received the Mark, the Tarf, the Westwater, and the Cruick in
                    its course. The <hi rend="italic">South Esk</hi> rises in the north-western part
                    of the county, among the Grampian summits of Clova, and passing by Brechin,
                    discharges itself into the basin of Montrose, five miles from the mouth of the
                    North Esk, after being joined by the waters of Prosen, Carritty, and other
                    mountain streams. Its general course is from north-west to south-east. <hi
                    rend="italic">Isla,</hi> the last stream of any note, has also its source in the
                    Grampians, flowing from the summit of the glen which bears its name, in a
                    direction from north to south, until, at Ruthven, it bends to the westward, and
                    joins the Tay in Perthshire. Below the bridge of Craig it has cut a chasm, in
                    some places more than a hundred feet in depth, through a barrier of porphyry and
                    gravelstone rocks, where it forms cascades of singular beauty. The Dean, the
                    Lunan, the Dighty, and a few others, are inconsiderable streams.</p>
                <p>Much of the landed property of Forfarshire has changed its owners within the last
                    century; and of the forty barons mentioned by Edward, in the work already
                    referred to, the descendants of not more than a third of them now possess
                    estates in it. It is in general divided into estates of a moderate size. In 1811
                    a large proportion were from L.100 to L.1000 a year, some from L.2000 to L.6000;
                    but only one or perhaps two worth L.12,000 a year. About a third part of the
                    county is now held under entail. The valued rent is L.17L,239. 16s. 8d. Scots,
                    which is divided amongst two hundred and sixty-six estates, three fourths of
                    which are below L.500 Scots. The real rent of the lands in 1811 was L.260,196.
                    15s., which is less than 10s. an acre; and of the houses, L.64,108 sterling.
                    There are more than sixty gentlemen’s seats, some of them venerable for their
                    extent and antiquity, such as the Castles of Glammis, Brechin, and Airly, the
                    house of Panmure, and others, distinguished for elegance and the beauty of their
                    situation. Amongst the latter, Kinnaird Castle, the seat of Sir James Carnegie,
                    is the most magnificent.</p>
                <p>Farms are of every size, but in general not large, the average size of such as
                    are arable being from 100 to 250 acres. There is a greater number below than
                    above 100 acres. According to the <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Survey,</hi>
                    the whole number of farms in 1808 was 3222, of which about the half were under
                    L.20 of yearly rent, and only eighty-six above L.300. In the western division of
                    the Grampian district, the arable land is still held in runrig or intermixed,
                    and the mountains in common, either without leases, or on leases not exceeding
                    nine years. Throughout the rest of the county the leases are commonly for
                    nineteen or twenty-one years. The farm-houses lately erected in the lower parts
                    of the county are in general convenient and comfortable, but in the Grampians
                    they are still miserable huts, with «'alls of stone and turf alternately, five
                    feet high, and covered with thatch fastened with ropes in the form of a hay
                    rick. In some parts where stones are scarce, cottages and even small farm-houses
                    are built with clay, wrought up and mixed with straw, but in general the
                    cottages are built with stone and clay, with clay floors and thatched roofs, one
                    of which may be constructed for about L.15. Their number has been much
                    diminished of late.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193754956" xml:id="kp-eb0709-4956-0746"/>
                <p>The agriculture of Forfarshire is for the most part respectable, though modern
                    improvements are not so general as in the Lothians and border counties of
                    Scotland. Wheat, which, according to Pennant, was a rare crop in 1775, is now
                    cultivated to a great extent upon almost every variety of soil, to the height of
                    800 feet above the level of the sea; also barley, and all the other farm crops
                    common in Scotland. In reaping the corn crops there is a practice peculiar to
                    this and one or two of the contiguous counties, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >threaving</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the reaper is paid for his work not by
                    the acre or by day-wages, but according to the number of sheaves he cuts down,
                    or by the <hi rend="italic">threave,</hi> which contains twenty-four or
                    twenty-eight sheaves, the girth of which is specified. The advantages of this
                    practice are, that women and children, who cannot perform full labour, find
                    employment, working in families, on different parts of a field; whilst the
                    farmer gets his crops cut low and clean, from its being their interest to fill
                    the sheaf with the thickest part of the straw, which is always that nearest the
                    ground. The unmarried men-servants, instead of boarding in the farmer’s own
                    house, often live apart in a place called the <hi rend="italic">bothy,</hi>
                    where they cook their own victuals.</p>
                <p>No great progress has been made here in the improvement of live stock. The <hi
                    rend="italic">garron,</hi> a small breed of horses, keeps its ground in the
                    Grampians, where the number employed is much too considerable for the work they
                    have to perform. The Lanarkshire or west-country breed is common in the lower
                    districts. There is supposed to be more than .9000 horses of all kinds and ages
                    in the county, which were valued in 1811 at L.220,270. The cattle in the
                    cultivated parts, when fat, weigh from forty to sixty stones, and in some
                    instances a great deal more; and many more are fattened than reared, the
                    practice on the grazing lands being to purchase them from the counties of
                    Kincardine, Aberdeen, and Moray, and after making them fat, or nearly so, to
                    sell them for the markets in the south. They are accordingly of a variety of
                    breeds. Many of the permanent or stationary stock are without horns, and seem to
                    be allied to the Galloways. Oxen were formerly employed in labour; but they are
                    now rarely used except in turning up soils overrun with broom and other shrubs.
                    The permanent stock of cattle is said to be about 37,400, worth L.261,800. There
                    are few flocks of sheep, except in the Grampians and the highest of the Siedlaw
                    Hills, though almost every residing proprietor, and many of the farmers, keep a
                    small number. The original breed is the small white or yellowfaced; but the
                    Linton, or black-faced, is the most numerous. The number is computed at 60,000,
                    and the value at L.42,000. A herd of fallow-deer is kept in the park at
                    Panmure.</p>
                <p>Forfarshire contains five royal burghs, with a number of villages and hamlets;
                    and a pretty large proportion of its inhabitants are employed in manufactures
                    and commerce. The royal burghs are, 1. Forfar, the county town; 2. Dundee; 3.
                    Aberbrothick, or Arbroath; 4. Montrose; and 5. Brechin. To these may be added
                    Kirriemuir, a considerable village; Cupar Angus, of which, however, only a small
                    part is in this county, most of it being in Perthshire; Glammis, Douglastown,
                    and Letham. In 1808, 11,269,867∣ yards of linen were stamped for sale in the
                    county, the value of which was nearly half a million sterling. About half as
                    much more, which was not stamped, might be made for domestic use and private
                    sale.</p>
                <p>There are two customhouses in Forfarshire; one at Dundee, and another at
                    Montrose. For an account of the Dundee shipping trade, see the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Dundee.</hi> That at Montrose, including Johnshaven and
                    Gourdon, amounts to 108 vessels, about 11,000 tons.</p>
                <p>The fisheries on the coast of this county have not been prosecuted with great
                    success. The boats employed are generally small, requiring only four hands. For
                    some years considerable quantities of herrings have been caught in the months of
                    June, July, and August. But the river fisheries have become of great value since
                    the plan was adopted, at the suggestion of the late Mr Dempster of Dunichen, of
                    conveying fresh salmon to London packed in ice. Mr Headrick estimates the
                    produce of six of these fisheries in 1810 at L.7450. The greatest salmon
                    fisheries are in the Frith of Tay, and were carried on chiefly by stake-nets, a
                    practice which was objected to by the proprietors higher up the river, and which
                    has been since declared illegal <hi rend="italic">intra fauces terra,</hi> or
                    within the estuary.</p>
                <p>Many religious and military ruins are to be found in Forfarshire. Near the
                    cathedral of Brechin is a curious round tower, of which, though such be common
                    in Ireland, only two, it is said, have been observed in Britain; this, and
                    another similar to it at Abernethy, in Perthshire. (See the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Brechin.)</hi> At Arbroath are the remains of an abbey, founded
                    by William the Lion in 1178, and very richly endowed, where was held the
                    parliament of Robert Bruce which addressed the celebrated remonstrance to the
                    Pope, asserting the independence of the kingdom. A hill fort called <hi
                    rend="italic">Cater-thun,</hi> in the parish of Menmuir, north-west. of Brechin,
                    is worthy of notice. Pennant thinks it was one of the posts occupied by the
                    Caledonians before their engagement with Agricoa, at the foot of the
                    Grampians.</p>
                <p>The county of Forfar sends one member to Parliament; the burgh of Dundee one; and
                    Inverbervie, Montrose, Arbroath, Brechin, and Forfar one, Montrose being the
                    returning burgh. It contains fifty-three entire parishes, besides portions of
                    three others, which belong to presbyteries that meet at Forfar, Dundee, Brechin,
                    Meigle, and Arbroath, and which, with the presbytery of Fórdtm, compose the
                    synod of Angus and Mearns. There is no assessment for the poor in the
                    county.</p>
                <p>See Edward’s <hi rend="italic">Description of Angus,</hi> reprinted in 1791, and
                    Colonel Imrie⅛ <hi rend="italic">Section of the Grampians,</hi> already referred
                    to; <hi rend="italic">Beauties of Scotland,</hi> vol. iv.; Headrick’s <hi
                    rend="italic">General View of the Agriculture of Angus or Forfarshire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Wernerian Society,</hi>
                    vol. ii.; <hi rend="italic">The General Report &lt;y Scotland</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and Playfair’s <hi rend="italic">Description of
                    Scotland,</hi> vol. i.</p>
                <p>The following are the returns of the population for the years ending 1811, 1821,
                    and 1831.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>YEAR.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many Families
                            occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ï</p><p>3</p><p>P</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agricul-</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, or Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1811</p><p>1821</p><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16,13o</p><p>16,812</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24,750</p><p>26,718</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>505</p><p>576</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4980</p><p>5114</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13,616</p><p>15,348</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6154</p><p>6256</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>48,151</p><p>52,071</p><p>65,093</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>59,113</p><p>61,359</p><p>74,513</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>107,264</p><p>113,430</p><p>139,606</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193754969" xml:id="kp-eb0709-4969-0747"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Forfar,</hi> a royal burgh of Scotland, and capital of the
                    county of Forfar, is situated in the lowest part of the <hi rend="subscript">
                    l</hi> county, which declines to it on all sides, and has rather a pleasant
                    appearance. The streets are by no means regular, but many of the houses are well
                    built and neat; an improvement, however, which has taken place within the last
                    few years. At the beginning of the present century its streets were chiefly
                    composed of old thatched houses, and its church was in a state of decay. But the
                    town is now ornamented with a handsome suit of county buildings, situated in a
                    good street. A new church with a steeple has likewise been erected, and an
                    Episcopal chapel was opened in 1823. Besides these places of worship, some sects
                    of dissenters have meeting-houses here. Forfar being the seat of the county
                    courts of the sheriff, possesses a number of public offices and legal
                    practitioners. There is a parish school, and an academy, where the languages,
                    mathematics, and geography are taught. It has also an excellent news-room and
                    library. The chief trade of Forfar is the weaving of oβnaburgs and coarse
                    linens. From time immemorial however it has been celebrated for the manufacture
                    of <hi rend="italic">brogues</hi> or strong shoes, such as are fitted for the
                    rugged soil of the Highlands, where they are principally used by the
                    inhabitants.</p>
                <p>Forfar is a royal burgh of unknown antiquity, the privileges of which were
                    confirmed in 1669, in virtue of which it is governed by a provost, two bailies,
                    and nineteen counsellors, who are elected annually. The revenue of the burgh may
                    be averaged at L.1000. On the west side of the town there is a beautiful sheet
                    of water, which, although considerably reduced by draining, is still about a
                    mile in length by half a mile in breadth. In former times Forfar was protected
                    by a castle, which stood on a mound to the north of the town. Its origin is
                    uncertain, but it is believed to have been the place where the first parliament
                    of Malcolm Ceanmore assembled, after the destruction of Macbeth. The site of
                    this ancient fortress is now marked by the town cross, which was removed by the
                    magistrates some years ago, for the purpose of pointing out where the royal
                    residence had been. Forfar has shared in the general advancement of population,
                    trade, and agricultural improvement, and it is now one of the most comfortable
                    little towns in the county. It lies fourteen miles north from Dundee, and
                    fifty-six from Edinburgh. In 1821 the population, including the parish, amounted
                    to 5897, and in 1831 to 7944.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
