<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-2187-0533-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main"/>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 533</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193752187" type="entry">
                <p>FICHTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Theophilus,</hi> an eminent German
                    metaphysician, was born at Rammenau, a village of Lusatia, on the 19th of May
                    1762. His father was a ribbon manufacturer, and carried on a small trade in
                    haberdashery. A wealthy person in the neighbourhood having been struck with the
                    extraordinary genius which young Fichte displayed, put him to school, in order
                    to give him an opportunity of cultivating his talents; but the boy becoming
                    impatient of restraint, ran off, and was found sitting on the banks of the
                    Saale, with a map, on which he was endeavouring to trace the way to America.
                    From this period he seems to have prosecuted his studies in an extremely
                    desultory manner; occasionally attending the lectures of the professors of
                    Wittemberg and Leipsic, without devoting his attention exclusively to any
                    particular science. Theology, however, appears to have been his favourite study;
                    and this predilection is conspicuous in many of his subsequent writings, which
                    are distinguished by a singular mixture of philosophical and religious
                    mysticism. When he left the university, his situation was by no means enviable.
                    He possessed no fortune to enable him to indulge in the luxury of philosophical
                    speculation; and, in spite of his decided aversion to every kind of constraint,
                    he was compelled, by the necessity of his circumstances, to accept the situation
                    of tutor in the family of a Prussian gentleman. But his residence in Prussia
                    enabled him to cultivate the acquaintance of the celebrated philosopher of
                    Königsberg, to whose judgment he submitted his first work, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Critical Review of all Revelations,</hi> which was published anonymously in
                    1792. In the literary journals, this production, which had attracted
                    considerable attention, was ascribed to the pen of Kant, until the real author
                    made himself known.</p>
                <p>Having received fifty ducats from a Polish nobleman, in whose family he had been
                    tutor, Fichte set out on a course of travels through Germany and Switzerland,
                    and afterwards married a niece of Klopstock’s at Zurich. In 1793, he published
                    the first part of his <hi rend="italic">Contributions towards rectifying the
                    Opinions of the Public respecting the French Revolution.</hi> This book, which
                    is written with considerable force and originality, created a great sensation in
                    Germany, and was violently attacked, in consequence of a new and apparently
                    dangerous theory which the author advanced relative to the social contract. The
                    book, however, was perused with great avidity; but the attacks to which we have
                    alluded probably prevented him from publishing the continuation.</p>
                <p>The reputation of Fichte was now so well established, that he soon afterwards
                    obtained an appointment to the philosophical chair at Jena, as successor to
                    Reinhold, who had been called to the university of Kiel. Here he commenced his
                    lectures by a programme, in which he endeavoured to give an idea of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Doctrine of Science (</hi><hi rend="italic">Wissenschaf</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">tslxhre),</hi> the name by which he distinguished the principles
                    of that system of transcendental idealism, which he afterwards more fully
                    developed. In 1794, besides the ordinary duties of his professorship, he every
                    Sunday gave a regular course of lectures, in the form of sermons, <hi
                    rend="italic">On the Literary Calling,</hi> which was numerously attended.
                    Having established the principles of his doctrine of science, he endeavoured to
                    extend their application to the several departments of philosophy; and with this
                    view he published in 1796 his <hi rend="italic">Fundamental Principles of the
                    Law of Nature,</hi> and two years afterwards his <hi rend="italic">System of
                    Morals·</hi> In conjunction with Niethammer, he also published a philosophical
                    journal, in which some articles were inserted, containing certain philosophical
                    views of religion, which were considered by many as tending directly to atheism.
                    Amongst a number of objectionable propositions, it was maintained <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193752200" xml:id="kp-eb0709-2200-0534"/>that God was nothing else
                    than the moral order of the ' universe; and that, to worship God as a being who
                    could only be represented as existing in time and space, was a species of
                    idolatry. One of Fichte’s colleagues called the attention of the Saxon minister
                    Burgsdorf to these heretical propositions; and the consequence was, the rigorous
                    confiscation of the work throughout the whole of Saxony. Fichte and his friend
                    Forberg wrote an <hi rend="italic">Appeal to the Public,</hi> and several <hi
                    rend="italic">Apologies,</hi> in order to exculpate themselves from the
                    imputation of atheism. The government of Weimar behaved on this occasion with
                    prudence and moderation; but the celebrated Herder, vice-president of the
                    consistory, took part against Fichte. Eberhard, on the other hand, although
                    hostile to the metaphysical system of Fichte, undertook his defence. The
                    controversy was carried on with great violence, and excited considerable ferment
                    throughout the whole of Germany.</p>
                <p>In the mean time Fichte resigned his professorship at Jena, and repaired to
                    Berlin, where he met with a very flattering reception. Here his time was
                    occupied in giving private lectures, and in composing his various writings. In
                    1800 he published a short treatise, entitled <hi rend="italic">The Exclusive
                    Commercial State,</hi> containing one of those philosophical systems of
                    political economy from which the praise of ingenuity cannot be withheld; whilst,
                    at the same time, the most cursory view of the general principles on which it is
                    founded must be sufficient to convince us that it could never be advantageously
                    reduced to practice.</p>
                <p>About this period Fichte met with a formidable rival in Schelling, who had
                    formerly been a warm partisan of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Science,</hi> but who now separated from his master, and
                    propounded a new metaphysical theory of his own, which soon acquired a large
                    share of popularity at the German universities, especially at Jena. Fichte
                    indeed endeavoured to modify his theory of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of
                    Science,</hi> and to present it to the world in a new and more attractive form;
                    but he never again recovered the sway which he had formerly exercised over the
                    public mind. Meanwhile, his ardent wish to be again placed in an academical
                    chair was at length gratified by Μ. de Hardenberg, who in</p>
                <p>1805 procured for him the appointment of ordinary professor of philosophy in the
                    university of Erlangen. This appointment was accompanied with the especial
                    favour of being permitted to pass the winter at Berlin, in order to continue his
                    lectures there. But this state of amphibious professorship, as his friends used
                    to call it in jest, did not last long. During the summer of 1805 he delivered at
                    Erlangen his celebrated lectures <hi rend="italic">On the Essence of the
                    Literary Character (uber</hi><hi rend="italic">das Wesen des Gelehrten).</hi>
                    The following winter he delivered to a numerous audience the course which he
                    afterwards published under the title of <hi rend="italic">Guide to a Happy
                    Life.</hi> This was one of those publications in which he attempted to present
                    his metaphysical doctrines to the public in all their sublimity, and, at the
                    same time, with such clearness, as should render them intelligible to common
                    readers.</p>
                <p>The disasters which assailed the Prussian monarchy in</p>
                <p>1806 were attended with serious consequences to Fichte. Erlangen having ceased to
                    be a Prussian university, he did not await the entry of the French into Berlin,
                    but fled to Königsberg, and thence proceeded to Riga. In the summer of 1807 he
                    delivered a course of philosophical lectures at Königsberg. The peace which
                    ensued enabled him to return to Berlin, where he pronounced his famous <hi
                    rend="italic">Orations to the German Nation,</hi> which were enthusiastically
                    read and applauded throughout all Germany. When the university of Berlin was
                    founded, he obtained, through the interest of Μ. de Humboldt, the situation of
                    rector, which secured to him an honourable revenue, whilst his rank, as first
                    professor of philosophy, gave him great academical influence. His health,
                    however, had suffered considerably from the shocks he had for some time
                    experienced, and he found it necessary to have recourse to the waters of
                    Bohemia, from which he derived great benefit. But his wife was attacked with a
                    nervous fever, in consequence of her attendance on the deserted sick; and
                    although she recovered, Fichte, whose affection would not allow him to leave her
                    for a moment, caught the infection, and died on the 29th of January 1814.</p>
                <p>Fichte was small in stature, but stout and well formed; his countenance was
                    expressive of thoughtfulness and determination. In his intellectual character,
                    genius was combined with inflexible firmness; and these qualities enabled him to
                    surmount difficulties which would have overwhelmed a man of less vigorous
                    temperament. In other respects his dispositions were amiable and his morals
                    correct. It was in the academical chair that the genius of Fichte was manifested
                    in its greatest splendour. It was said of him that he was born a professor; and
                    there was indeed a charm in his manner of lecturing which had a pow erful
                    influence on the minds of his pupils, several of whom we have heard talk of him
                    with enthusiasm. His fervid and brilliant eloquence, the clearness of his
                    reasoning, and the simplicity and correctness of his language, seemed to diffuse
                    a magic light and colouring over the darkest and most abstruse metaphysical
                    problems. Those who were charmed with his eloquence were easily convinced by his
                    reasoning, and became willing converts to his doctrines. His writings,
                    especially those works in which his peculiar doctrines are propounded in a
                    systematic form, are by no means so attractive as his lectures appear to have
                    been. On the contrary, notwithstanding a constant affectation of strict and
                    simple reasoning, his propositions are enveloped in such a degree of
                    transcendental obscurity, as renders it extremely difficult to comprehend either
                    the basis or the scope of that system of doctrines which he laboured to
                    establish.</p>
                <p>Hence it is far from being an easy matter to give an intelligible abstract of the
                    principles of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of Science,</hi> especially as we
                    must necessarily presuppose some acquaintance, on the part of our readers, with
                    the previous metaphysical labours of Kant. Fichte commenced his philosophical
                    career precisely at that period when the writings of Kant had nearly obtained a
                    paramount influence in the German schools, and when men even of superior talents
                    thought it no mean glory to be able to comprehend and illustrate his doctrines.
                    The Kantian theory was confessedly idealistic. Its celebrated author set out
                    with an analysis of the cognitive faculty, and endeavoured to describe its
                    various functions, as well as to ascertain the scope and limits of its
                    legitimate exercise. All our knowledge, according to the critical philosophy,
                    must have a reference to possible experience. Of external objects, or things in
                    themselves <hi rend="italic">(noumena),</hi> we can have no absolute knowledge;
                    for we can know nothing but what is perceived by the senses, and cognized (if we
                    may be allowed the expression) by our intellectual faculties, according to the
                    laws peculiar to our constitution. These intellectual laws, or subjective forms,
                    tend to combine our knowledge, and to render the field of experience a
                    comprehensible whole. As we can have no knowledge of objects in themselves, but
                    only of their <hi rend="italic">phenomena,</hi> neither can we have any
                    knowledge of things beyond the sphere of our experience, because these can
                    neither be perceived by our senses nor subjected to the laws of the
                    understanding. All reasoning, therefore, from mere ideas must necessarily be
                    futile, because it has no reference to any corresponding object within the
                    limits of experience. And although we can have no absolute knowledge of objects
                    as they really exist, yet our knowledge of them possesses a subjective reality
                    (that is, a reality with reference to t <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> thinking
                    subject), and may be said to correspond with t⅛ <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193752213" xml:id="kp-eb0709-2213-0535"/>objects, because, from the
                    nature of our intellectual constitution, we are incapable of receiving any other
                    impression from them.</p>
                <p>Reinhold was one of the earliest partisans of Kant, and one of the most ingenious
                    and most popular commentators on the critical philosophy. But his talents were
                    better adapted for explaining and illustrating the doctrines of others, than for
                    discovering new truths, or inventing any original system of his own; and
                    although an indefatigable student of philosophy, he seems to have never arrived
                    at any settled conviction in metaphysical matters, but to have alternately
                    adopted and abandoned every new theory which was successively presented to his
                    view. After having been for some time enthusiastically devoted to the-doctrines
                    promulgated in the <hi rend="italic">Critical Review of Pure Reason,</hi> which
                    he esteemed the greatest masterpiece of philosophical genius, he at length
                    discovered that Kant had neglected to secure the foundations of the edifice he
                    had raised, and this defect he attempted to supply by his own <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theory of the Faculty of Perception</hi><hi rend="italic">{Theorie des Vor
                    Stellung</hi><hi rend="italic">sver-mogens).</hi> The main proposition laid down
                    and illustrated in this work is nothing more nor less than this: We are
                    compelled by consciousness to admit that every perception presupposes a
                    percipient subject and an object perceived, both of which must be distinguished
                    from the perception to which they relate; thus referring all our knowledge to
                    consciousness as its ultimate principle. In the enunciation of this proposition
                    there is nothing very new or original; but the illustration of this elementary
                    doctrine, which, as a late reviewer of the German metaphysical theories
                    observes, might have formed an excellent subject for a short philosophical
                    dissertation of two or three sheets, is dilated into a work nearly as large as
                    that to which it was intended to serve as a mere introduction; nor is the
                    unnecessary length of the treatise in any measure compensated by the importance
                    of the truths developed, or the ingenuity displayed in the research.</p>
                <p>With greater talents and consistency, Fichte, who announced himself as a strict
                    Kantian, attempted to resolve the same problem, and to develope a system which,
                    by deducing all our knowledge from one simple principle, should give unity and
                    stability to the critical theory. In his <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of Science
                    (</hi><hi rend="italic">Wissenschaftslehre),</hi> accordingly, he derives all
                    our knowledge from the original act of the tDinking subject in reflecting upon
                    itself. <hi rend="italic">I am I</hi> (which he expresses by the formula A = A),
                    or the absolute position of the I by the I, is in itself the certain principle
                    of ill philosophy and of all our knowledge. But the creative energy of the I, in
                    the course of this reflective process, goes still farther. By its own act, also,
                    the I places the <hi rend="italic">not-I</hi> (objects) as opposed to itself. In
                    reflecting upon itself, as the absolutely active principle, it finds itself
                    either determined by or determining the <hi rend="italic">not-I.</hi> In the
                    former case, it appears as the <hi rend="italic">intelligent I</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> in the latter, as the <hi rend="italic">absolutely free,
                    practical I.</hi> Hence the distinction between theoretical and practical
                    philosophy. The idea, then, which pervades the whole theory of Fichte is this:
                    The I, θr the thinking subject, is the absolutely active principle, which <hi
                    rend="italic">constructs</hi> the consciousness, and produces all that exists,
                    by position, contraposition, and juxtaposition. The y hole universe, in short,
                    is the product of the I, or think- <hi rend="superscript"> ιn</hi> g
                    subject.</p>
                <p>We have thus endeavoured to give a very concise sketch . <hi rend="superscript">
                    0 a</hi> +θory which we shall not think of pursuing through ζ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> s</hi> various ramifications, as we should despair of making
                    intelligible to our readers by any length of exposition, ιchte has been praised
                    by his countrymen for his logical ŋ consistent reasoning; but to us it appears
                    that his eory proceeds entirely upon arbitrary assumptions, rest-g upon no solid
                    foundation. That he displays considerable ingenuity in the development of his
                    ideas we are willing to admit; but we are quite at a loss to perceive the '
                    merit of the theory he has advanced, when considered as a system of
                    philosophical truths. The parade of scientific deduction which his reasoning
                    exhibits may impose upon the incautious student; but a careful examination will
                    undoubtedly convince him that the whole is a mere tissue of empty notions,
                    derived from arbitrary and assumed principles.</p>
                <p>In attempting to apply the principles of his doctrine of science to the theory of
                    morals and the law of nature, Fichte exhibited many original and paradoxical
                    opinions, along with some very just and ingenious philosophical observations. In
                    his later writings he considerably modified his original theory of the doctrine
                    of science, and produced a system of philosophical and religious mysticism,
                    which appears to have given birth to the transcendental idealism of Schelling,
                    an author who seems to have carried the extravagance of speculative reasoning to
                    its utmost limits.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of the works of Fichte.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Versuch einer Kritik aller Offenbarung.</hi> (Critical
                    Review of all Revelation.) Königsberg, 1792, 1793, 8vo.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Ueber den Begriff der Wissenschaftslehre.</hi> (On the
                    notion of a Doctrine of Science.) Jena, 1794, 8vo.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Grundlage der</hi><hi rend="italic">gesammten</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Wissenschaftslehre.</hi> (Foundation of the whole Doctrine of
                    Science.) Ibid. 1794, 8vo.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Grundriss des eigentümlichen der Wissenschaftslehre.</hi>
                    (Sketch of the peculiarity of the Doctrine of Science.) Weimar, 1794.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Vorlesungen</hi><hi rend="italic">ueber die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Bestimmung des Gelehrten.</hi> (Lectures on the Literary Calling.)
                    Jena, 1794.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">System</hi><hi rend="italic">der Sittenlehre.</hi> (System
                    of the Doctrine of Morals.) Jena and Leipsic, 1795.</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Beytrage</hi><hi rend="italic">zur Berichtigung der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Urtheile</hi><hi rend="italic">des Publi-cums ueber die
                    Französische Revolution.</hi> (Materials for Rectifying the Opinions of the
                    Public respecting the French Revolution.)</p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Grundlage des Naturrechts.</hi> (Foundation of the Law of
                    Nature.) Jena, 1796, 1797. 2 vols. 8vo.</p>
                <p>9. <hi rend="italic">Appellation an das Publicum ueber die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ihm</hi><hi rend="italic">beygem-essenen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >atheistischen</hi><hi rend="italic">Aeusserungen.</hi> (Appeal to the Public
                    respecting the atheistical expressions imputed to him.) Jena and Leipsic,
                    1799.</p>
                <p>10. <hi rend="italic">Ueber die</hi><hi rend="italic">Bestimmung des
                    Menschen.</hi> (On the Destiny of Man.)</p>
                <p>11. <hi rend="italic">Der geschlossene Handlesstaat.</hi> (The exclusive
                    Commercial State.)</p>
                <p>12. <hi rend="italic">Sonnenklarer Bericht</hi><hi rend="italic">an</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">das grossere</hi><hi rend="italic">Publicum ueber</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">das eigentliche Wesen der neuesten Philosophie.</hi> (Luminous
                    Report to the greater public on the peculiar Character of the modern
                    Philosophy.) Berlin, 1801.</p>
                <p>13. <hi rend="italic">Wissenschaftslehre.</hi> (Doctrine of Science.) Tübingen,
                    1802, 8vo.</p>
                <p>14. <hi rend="italic">Vorlesungen</hi><hi rend="italic">ueber</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">das Wesen der Gelehrten.</hi> (Lectures on the Literary
                    Character.) Berlin, 1806.</p>
                <p>15. <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Grundzuge des gegenwartigen
                    Zeitalters.</hi> (The Characteristics of the present age.) Ibid. 1806.</p>
                <p>16. <hi rend="italic">Anweisung zum seligen Leben.</hi> (Guide to a Happy Life.)
                    Ibid. 1806.</p>
                <p>17. <hi rend="italic">Reden an die Deutsche Nation.</hi> (Discourses to the
                    German nation.) Ibid. 1806.</p>
                <p>18. <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Wissenschaftslehre</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">ihrem allgemeinsten Umrisse
                    dargestellt.</hi> (The Doctrine of Science exhibited in its most general
                    outline.) Ibid. 1810.</p>
                <p>19. <hi rend="italic">Freidrich Nicoai's</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben und
                    Sonderbare Meinun</hi><hi rend="italic">gen, herausgegeben von Schlegel.</hi>
                    (Life and singular opinions of Frederic Nicoai, edited by Schlegel.) Tübingen,
                    1801. .</p>
                <p>20. <hi rend="italic">Antwortschrieben</hi><hi rend="italic">an K. L. Reinhold,
                    auj</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">lfff</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> η</hi><hi rend="italic">Beytrage zur
                    leichtern</hi><hi rend="italic">Uebersicht</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Zastandes</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Philo·</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193752226" xml:id="kp-eb0709-2226-0536"
                    /><hi rend="italic">Sophie,</hi> &amp;c. (Answer to K. L. Reinhold, on his
                    Materials for acquiring a more easy View of the State of Philosophy, &amp;c.)
                    Tübingen, 1801.</p>
                <p>21. <hi rend="italic">Ueber die</hi><hi rend="italic">einzig mogliche Storung
                    der</hi><hi rend="italic">acadernischen</hi><hi rend="italic">Freyheit.</hi> (On
                    the only possible disturbance of Academical Freedom.) Berlin, 1812.</p>
                <p>22. <hi rend="italic">Ueber</hi><hi rend="italic">den Begriff des
                    wahrhaften</hi><hi rend="italic">Kriegs, in</hi><hi rend="italic">Bezug
                    auf</hi><hi rend="italic">den Krieg in jahre,</hi> 1813. (On the notion of real
                    war, with reference to the war in 1813.) Tübingen, 1815.</p>
                <p>Fichte is also the author of several essays in periodical publications, and
                    particularly in a philosophical journal edited by himself, with the assistance
                    of Niethammer.</p>
                <p>Those who are desirous of obtaining more minute information respecting Fichte’s
                    philosophical theory, may consult the following works; Tennemann’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Grundriss der Geschichte der Philosophie;</hi> Degerando, <hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">Comparce,</hi> &amp;c. W. T. Krug,
                    <hi rend="italic">Briefe ueber die Wissenschaftslehre.</hi> F. W. J. Schelling,
                    <hi rend="italic">Darlegung des wahren Verhaltnisses</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >der</hi><hi rend="italic">Naturphilosophie zu der verbesserten Fichtischen
                    Lehre.</hi> J. Fries, <hi rend="italic">Peinhold, Fichte und Schelling.</hi> C.
                    F. Bachmann, <hi rend="italic">Ueber die Philosophie meiner Zeit.</hi> Ancillon,
                    <hi rend="italic">Essai</hi><hi rend="italic">sur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >le</hi><hi rend="italic">premier</hi><hi rend="italic">problème de la
                    philosophie;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Essai sur l’exist</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ence et sur les</hi><hi rend="italic">derniers systèmes de métaphysique qui ont
                    paru</hi><hi rend="italic">en Allemagne.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(k.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
