<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-5619-0797-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOX</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 797</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:933481">Foxes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1084913">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193755619" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOX</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Zoology.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mammalia.</hi></p>
                <p>Fox, <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> the martyrologist, was born at Boston in
                    Lincolnshire, in the year 1517. At the age of sixteen he was entered a student
                    of Brazen-Nose College in Oxford; and in 1543 he took his degree of master of
                    arts, and was chosen fellow of Magdalen College. He discovered an early genius
                    for poetry, and, conformably to the taste of his age, wrote several Latin
                    comedies upon subjects taken from Scripture. Of these, one still remains,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">De Christo</hi><hi rend="italic">Triumphante,</hi>
                    printed at London in 1551, and at Bale in 1556, 8vo, and reprinted in 1672. But
                    having forsaken the muses, he applied himself with great assiduity to the study
                    of theology, including church history; and having manifested an inclination,
                    which he took no pains to conceal, for the doctrines of the reformation, he was,
                    ip the year 1545, expelled from his college as a heretic, happy, it is said, to
                    have fared no worse. He had lost his father early in life, and, as his mother
                    had married again, his stepfather availed himself of this occurrence to retain
                    the whole of his patrimony, knowing that Fox would not venture to sue him for
                    restitution. This rascality on the part of his mother’s husband reduced him to
                    the greatest distress; but he soon afterwards found an asylum in the house of
                    Sir Thomas Lucy, Warwickshire, who employed him as tutor to his children. When
                    this engagement expired, Fox, who had in the meanwhile married the daughter of a
                    citizen of Coventry, proceeded to London; but finding no immediate means of
                    subsistence, he was again reduced to absolute want. Relief, however, at length
                    came, and in a manner which is described as almost miraculous. As he was one day
                    sitting in St Paul’s church, emaciated with hunger, a stranger accosted him
                    familiarly, and, bidding him be of good cheer, put a sum of money into his hand;
                    telling him, at the same time, that new hopes were at hand. And, in fact, he
                    was, three days thereafter, received into the family of the Duchess of Richmond,
                    as tutor to the Earl of Surrey’s children, who, upon their father being sent to
                    the Tower, were committed to her care. In this family he lived at Ryegate in
                    Surrey, during the latter part of the reign of Henry VIII., the entire reign of
                    Edward VI., and part of that of Queen Mary; but he could never discover the
                    generous person who had at once relieved his distress and predicted his good
                    fortune. At length, however, being persecuted by his implacable enemy Bishop
                    Gardiner, he was obliged to seek refuge abroad; and he selected as the place of
                    his retreat Basil in Switzerland, where he subsisted by correcting for the
                    press. But on the death of Queen Mary he returned to England, where he was
                    graciously received by his former pupil the Duke of Norfolk, who retained him
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:193755632" xml:id="kp-eb0709-5632-0798"/>in his family
                    as long as he lived, and bequeathed him a pen- ’ sion at his death, which took
                    place in 1S63. Mr Secretary Cecil also bestowed on him a rectory near Salisbury;
                    and, in point of fact, he might have obtained considerable church preferment,
                    had it not been for his unwillingness to subscribe to the canons. He died in the
                    year 1587, in the seventieth year of his age, and was buried in the chancel of
                    St Giles’s, Cripplegate. Fox was a man of great industry, and considerable
                    learning; a zealous, but not a violent reformer; a nonconformist, but not an
                    enemy to the Church of England. The most celebrated of his works is that which
                    is entitled <hi rend="italic">Acts and Monuments of the Church,</hi> and
                    commonly called <hi rend="italic">Martyrology,</hi> containing a history of the
                    troubles in the church of Rome since the tenth century, particularly in England
                    and Scotland. It was published at London, 1563, in folio, but afterwards
                    augmented, and printed for the fourth time in 1583, two vols. folio, and in
                    1632, three vols. folio. He relates in detail the history of the martyrs of the
                    Protestant religion, but embellishes his narrative with so many marvellous
                    circumstances, that his enemies, it must be confessed, had some reason in
                    applying to it the name of Legend. The Catholics, in particular, reproached him
                    with passion and with grossness; and, what was far more serious, accused him of
                    having often altered the truth in order to swell the number of martyrs to his
                    creed. Nor can it be denied that, in the first edition, he had enrolled amongst
                    the number of those who had sealed their testimony with their blood, persons
                    still living, and who remonstrated against the honour intended for them. But
                    notwithstanding all these and many other objections, some of which are
                    undoubtedly well founded, the <hi rend="italic">Martyrology</hi> met with
                    prodigious success in England, where, amidst all the changes which have taken
                    place in taste and opinion, it still maintains its ground. The other writings of
                    Fox, which were very numerous, consist of works on theology, and particularly
                    controversy; and some of his letters which have been preserved reflect honour on
                    his character as a man of sense and humanity.</p>
                <p>Fox, <hi rend="italic">George,</hi> the founder of the sect of Quakers, was born
                    at Drayton, Leicestershire, in the year 1624. His father, a zealous
                    Presbyterian, was a weaver. Young Fox, from his earliest years, showed uncommon
                    gravity, and participated in none of the diversions natural to his age; he
                    courted solitude, and when he spoke it was in a melancholy tone. His parents
                    were unable to give him any education beyond reading and writing, but they early
                    inspired him with sentiments of religion and virtue. Fox was at first placed
                    with a wool-merchant, and sent to tend sheep in the woods; a circumstance which
                    seems to have confirmed his inclination for a solitary and contemplative life.
                    He was then put as an apprentice to a shoemaker at Nottingham; and from the
                    accounts of the times we learn, that as he wrought at his trade, he used to
                    meditate much on the Scriptures, which, with his solitary course of life,
                    improving his natural melancholy, induced him at length to fancy himself
                    inspired; and in consequence he set up as a preacher. He proposed but few
                    articles of faith, insisting chiefly on moral virtue, mutual charity, the love
                    of God, and a deep attention to the inward motions and secret operations of the
                    Spirit; he required a plain, simple worship, and a religion without ceremonies,
                    making it a principal point to wait in profound silence for the directions of
                    the Holy Spirit. Fox met with much rough treatment on account of his zeal, was
                    often imprisoned, and several times in danger of being put to death. But, in
                    spite of all discouragements, his sect, which received the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Quakers,</hi> prevailed, and many considerable men were led to
                    join them; amongst whom were Barclay and Penn. Fox died on the 16th of January
                    1690. He was comparatively an uneducated man, as we have already seen; but he
                    possessed in an eminent degree the talent of persuasion, since, although born in
                    an inferior grade of society, and devoid of any but the simplest instruction, he
                    succeeded in recommending his doctrine to men of a superior rank in society. It
                    was undoubtedly owing to this circumstance that the society of Quakers, or, as
                    they call themselves, Friends, was enabled to outlast so many other sects,
                    founded by enthusiasts, which have generally disappeared immediately after the
                    death of their authors; whereas Quakerism acquired every day new force, and the
                    laws which at first persecuted, ended by tolerating, and even protecting it.
                    Fox, however, only laid the foundation; it was reserved for Barclay and Penn to
                    raise the superstructure. The writings of Fox have been collected in three
                    volumes folio; the first containing his Journal, which is eminently curious; the
                    second, his Correspondence; and the third, all that he has written on his
                    Doctrine. Some persons have indeed pretended that he is not really the author of
                    these different productions; but his followers, on the other hand, maintain that
                    whatever is most admirable in this collection really proceeded from the pen of
                    their patriarch.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
