<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-2863-0585-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FINCH, Heneage</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 585</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm43155">Finches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:924818">Finches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193752863" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FINCH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Heneage</hi></label>, first Earl
                    of Nottingham, and Lord High Chancellor of England, was the son of Sir Heneage
                    Finch, recorder of London, and born in December 1621. He received his education
                    at Westminster school, and at Christ Church College, Oxford, of which he was a
                    gentleman commoner; and he studied law in the Inner Temple, where, by his
                    talents and diligence, he became remarkable for great legal acquirements. On the
                    restoration of Charles II. he was made solicitor-general, and created a baronet.
                    He was also appointed reader of the Inner Temple, and chose as his subject the
                    statute of the 39th Elizabeth, concerning the payment and recovery of debts of
                    the crown, which he treated with great force of reason and depth of legal
                    erudition. As solicitor-general, he took an active part in the trials of the
                    regicides; and, in 1661, he was chosen member of parliament for the university
                    of Oxford, by the recommendation of Lord Clarendon; but, according to the author
                    of <hi rend="italic">Athence Oxonienses,</hi> he did his constituents no good,
                    when they wanted his assistance for taking off the tax upon hearths. In 1665,
                    after the prorogation of the parliament which then sat at Oxford, he was created
                    doctor of civil law in full convocation; but after the ceremony had terminated,
                    the public orator, being called upon to do his duty, stood up, and, in allusion
                    to the tax above mentioned, observed, “that the university wished they had more
                    colleges to entertain the parliament men, and more chambers, but by no means
                    more chimneys ;” an expression of academical opinion which, however undignified
                    in itself, startled the new-made doctor of laws, who changed colour, and seemed
                    by no means to relish the quaint remark of the orator. In 1667, i when Lord
                    Clarendon was impeached for certain alleged high crimes and misdemeanours, Sir
                    Heneage, mindful of his old friend, stoutly defended him against the charges
                    preferred by his enemies. In 1670 he was appointed attorney-general, and, some
                    years afterwards, lord keeper. He was then raised to the peerage by the style
                    and title °f Baron Finch of Daventry, in the county of Northampton; and, in
                    1675, appointed lord high chancellor of Eng-officiated as high steward at the
                    trial of Lord ōtanord, who, in the madness of that time, was found guilty of
                    high treason by his peers, on a charge of being concerned in the Popish plot. In
                    1681 he was created arl of Nottingham, and died, the following year, at his
                    ∣ouse in Queen Street, Lincoln’s-Inn-Fields, from the exhaustion produced by
                    long-continued exertion. Lord Nottingham was distinguished for both sagacity and
                    eloquence; and though he lived in times when it was difficult to pursue a steady
                    and consistent course, he conducted himself <hi rend="superscript"> in such
                    a</hi> manner as to retain the favour of the court without forfeiting the
                    approbation of the people. “He was a person,” says Mr Justice Blackstone, “of
                    the greatest abilities, and most incorrupted integrity; <hi rend="subscript">
                    a</hi> thorough master and zealous defender of the laws and constitution of his
                    country; and endued with a pervading genius that enabled him to discover and
                    pursue the true spirit of justice, notwithstanding the embarrassments raised by
                    the narrow and technical notions which then prevailed in the courts of law, and
                    the imperfect ideas of redress which had possessed the courts of equity. The
                    reason and necessities of mankind arising from the great change in property, by
                    the extension of trade, and the abolition of military tenures, co-operated in
                    establishing his plan, and enabled him, in the course of nine years, to build a
                    system of jurisprudence and jurisdiction upon wide and rational foundations,
                    which have also been extended and improved by many great men who have since
                    presided in Chancery; and from that time to this, the power and business of the
                    court have increased to an amazing degree.” In the name of the Earl of
                    Nottingham have been published, 1. Several Speeches and Discourses on the trials
                    of the Regicides; 2. Speeches delivered in both Houses of Parliament; 3. Speech
                    at the Sentence of William Viscount Stafford, 7th December 1680; 4. Answers to
                    his Majesty’s command upon several Addresses presented to his Majesty at Hampton
                    Court, 19th May 1681; 5. The Arguments upon which he made the Decree in the
                    cause between the Honourable Charles Howard, plaintiff, Henry Duke of Norfolk,
                    Henry Lord Mowbray his son, Henry Marquis of Dorchester, and Richard Marriot,
                    Esq. defendants, folio; 6. An Argument on the claim of the Crown to pardon on
                    Impeachment, folio. He also left in manuscript, <hi rend="italic">Chancery
                    Reports,</hi> and notes on Coke’s <hi rend="italic">Institute,</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
