<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-1758-0500-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FENCING</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 9, page 500</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:814541">Arm</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:899347">Dueling</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44746v0f">Dueling</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kx8h">Wrist</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sn82">Combat</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193751758" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FENCING</label>, is the proper use of the small-sword or
                    foil· The small-sword is a light court-dress sword, made to taper gradually from
                    the hilt to the point, and of a size regulated by the judgment of the wearer, if
                    he understand the use of the weapon. The foil, with which the art o fencing is
                    practised, is a small quadrangular blade, about the length of a small sword, and
                    mounted in nearly the same manner; but, for the convenience of the exercise, it
                    is made lighter, blunted, and covered with leather a the point, to prevent
                    accidents in practice.</p>
                <p>The first weapon in use amongst mankind, whether or offensive or defensive
                    purposes, appears to have been sword, and combat with this weapon is perhaps
                    near y old as the world. The most ancient book extant makes frequent mention of
                    the sword, and the same thing may be <pb break="no" facs="nls:193751771"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-1771-0501"/>said of Homer, who is full of continual allusions
                    to this wea- ’ pon. The earliest swords were probably made of wood, like those
                    used by the natives of Mexicowhen first visited by the Spaniards; but after the
                    discovery of metals, copper swords were introduced, of which kind many have at
                    different times been found in Ireland. As soon, however, as the art of tempering
                    steel had been discovered, that metal superseded all other substances in the
                    fabrication of arms; nor is it probable that any change in this respect will
                    take place, or that any further improvement is attainable. The form of the
                    sword, however, has varied at different times and in different countries. Those
                    used by the Roman legions were short and strong, with a blade seldom exceeding
                    nineteen inches in length, but two-edged, and calculated both for the cut and
                    the thrust. The British swords, called <hi rend="italic">spathae,</hi> were
                    large, long, and heavy; and the Saxon and the Norman partook of the same
                    character. The ancient practice of the weapon was probably carried to its
                    greatest perfection amongst the Romans, whose partiality for gladiatorial
                    exhibitions formed a remarkable feature of their character. The various and
                    complicated methods of combat in which this celebrated people took delight are
                    either alluded to or described by most of'their writers, particularly by Livy,
                    Juvenal, Seneca, and Suetonius.</p>
                <p>The history of the modern small-sword or rapier is involved in some obscurity.
                    The latter term, though now considered as synonymous with the former, properly
                    denotes a long, ordinary, old-fashioned, cutting sword. But modern usage has
                    identified the expressions, and by a rapier is now always meant a sword for the
                    thrust, in contradistinction to one constructed for cutting. The smallsword or
                    rapier is undoubtedly very ancient, although there is reason to believe that it
                    was not brought into general use until armour began to wear out of fashion.
                    Since that time the art of fencing has always been considered as a gentlemanly
                    accomplishment, and in many parts of the Jontinent it is cultivated with the
                    greatest zeal and assiduity. Shakspeare, indeed, makes Hamlet, who lived at the
                    court of Florwendillus, a fencer; but as our great dramatist has not been very
                    careful in avoiding anachronisms, it may reasonably be doubted whether the
                    small-sword has any claim to such antiquity. Some have maintained that the
                    weapon was not used in England before the reign of Elizabeth; and Darcie <hi
                    rend="italic">{Annals of Elizabeth)</hi> informs us that one Rowland York, who
                    appears to have betrayed Deventer to the Spaniards in the year 1587, was the
                    first who brought into England “that wicked, pernicious fashion to fight in the
                    fields in duels with a rapier called a tucke only for the thrust.” Stowe also
                    mentions that long tucks and long rapiers began about the twelfth or thirteenth
                    year of Elizabeth, and that “he was held the greatest gallant that had the
                    deepest ruffe and largest rapier. The offence,” he adds, “to the eye of the one,
                    and the hurt unto the life of the subject that came by the other, caused her
                    majesty to make proclamation against them both, and to place selected grave
                    citizens at every gate to cut the ruffes and breake the rapier’s points of all
                    passengers that exceeded a yard in length of their rapiers, and a nayle of a
                    yard in depth of their ruffes.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In <hi rend="italic">The Two Angry Women of Abingdon,</hi> a
                    comedy printed in 1599, we find the following pathetic complaint. "Sword and
                    buckler fights begin to grow out of use. I am sorry for it; í shall never see
                    good manhood again. If it be once g'one, this poking fight of rapier and dagger
                    will come up; then a tall man, and a good sword-and-buckler man, will be spitted
                    like a cat or a rabbit."</p></note></p>
                <p>But at what time soever the small-sword came into use m this country, it is not
                    surprising that, when once introduced, it should have been cultivated as the
                    fairest and most equitable instrument of duelling. Before this period meetings
                    for the purpose of single combat were utterly revolting to human nature. No
                    regard was paid to equality of arms or numbers; advantages, however unfair, were
                    seized whenever an opportunity offered; and the ferocious passions, instead of
                    being curbed, had fuller scope given or their gratification, “The duellist of
                    former times,” says Sir Walter Scott, in a note to <hi rend="italic">The Lady of
                    the Lake,</hi> did not always stand upon those punctilios respecting equality
                    <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> f arms, which are now judged essential to fair
                    combat. It is true that in formal combats in the lists, parties were, by the
                    judges of the field, put as nearly as possible in the same circumstances. But in
                    private duels it was often otherwise.” In the desperate combat which was fought
                    between Quelus, a minion of Henry III. of F i ance, and Antraqnet, with two
                    seconds on each side, and from which only two persons escaped alive, Q,uelus
                    complained that his antagonist had the advantage of a poniard which he used in
                    parrying, whilst his own left hand, which he was obliged to use for the same
                    purpose, had been cruelly mangled. When he charged Antraquet with this odds,
                    “Thou hast done wrong,” answered the latter, “to forget thy dagger at home; we
                    are here to fight, not to settle punctilios of arms.” In another duel of a
                    similar kind, however, a younger brother of the house of Aubange in Angouleme
                    behaved more generously, and at once threw away his dagger when his antagonist
                    challenged it as an undue advantage. Nevertheless, it would be difficult to
                    conceive any thing more brutal and savage than the mode in which private
                    quarrels were at this time conducted in France. Those who were most jealous on
                    the point of honour, and who thence acquired the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >raffines,</hi> did not scruple to avail themselves of every advantage of
                    strength, numbers, surprise, and arms, in order to accom plish their
                    revenge.</p>
                <p>Brantôme, in his discourse on duels, informs us that the Italian masters of the
                    science of defence made a great mystery of their art and mode of instruction;
                    that they never suffered any person to be present except the scholar who was to
                    betaught, and even examined beds, closets·, and other places of probable
                    concealment. The lessons of these teachers often gave the most treacherous
                    advantages to their pupils; for the challenger having by usage a right to choose
                    his weapons, frequently selected some strange and inconvenient kind of arms, the
                    use of which he had practised under his instructor, and thus killed at his ease
                    an antagonist, to whom, perchance, the weapon was presented for the first time
                    on the field of battle. Nor can we doubt that the same, or even still more
                    treacherous advantages, are taught by some Italian masters of the present day,
                    especially when we learn, from an authentic publication of the life of a late
                    pope, that in Rome upwards of a thousand persons annually fall victims to the
                    stiletto, either by the hands of hired assassins, or in private quarrels. Dr
                    Moore estimates the number of murders perpetrated by the dagger in Naples alone
                    at not less than four hundred annually. Such are the cowardly and ferocious
                    modes in which vengeance usually seeks its gratification amidst an enslaved and
                    degraded people.</p>
                <p>The practice of deciding duels with the sword, however, may be considered as now
                    extinct in this country. When the rapier was looked upon as an indispensable
                    part of a gentleman’s dress, the facility of immediate rencounter which it
                    offered gave occasion to frequent and dangerous brawls, by which the public
                    tranquillity was disturbed, and the lives of peaceable citizens sometimes
                    sacrificed. But. still it may reasonably be doubted, whether the comparatively
                    rare occurrence of duels since the introduction of the pistol, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193751784" xml:id="kp-eb0709-1784-0502"/>be not fearfully overbalanced
                    by a long list of fatal results, not to mention amputated limbs and distressing
                    mutilations. Be this as it may, however, the discontinuance of sword duels in
                    England has, in a great measure, removed one of the chief objections against
                    fencing; namely, that adroitness in the use of weapons creates a fondness for
                    contention, and a disposition to indulge in violence and insult. Since arms have
                    ceased to be worn, such an objection can no longer be urged against the art of
                    defence; and it may perhaps be questioned whether it had much weight, even when
                    arms formed part of the equipment of every one who called himself a gentleman.
                    All parties were thus placed upon nearly an equal footing; and if turbulent
                    characters went about armed, there was nothing to prevent the peaceably disposed
                    from being as well provided as the brawlers, and also on a par with them in
                    respect of skill in the use of weapons. If the thief makes use of a crowbar, the
                    honest housekeeper has the protection of an iron bolt. The primary intention of
                    fencing is the security of one’s own person; and where the weapons and the art
                    of using them skilfully were equally accessible to all, the evil disposed had no
                    advantage, and therefore small temptation to indidge their turbulent
                    propensities.</p>
                <p>The practice of the foil in England, however, is now confined to the most
                    laudable purposes, namely, the enjoyment of salutary recreation, and the
                    acquisition of a graceful and unconstrained deportment. The beneficial effects
                    of moderate fencing to persons of weak constitutions, or of studious and
                    sedentary habits, have been attested by medical practitioners of the first
                    eminence. On this subject the suffrages of the most distinguished members of the
                    British schools of medicine and of surgery, which Mr Angelo has annexed to his
                    engravings, illustrative of the fencing attitudes, seem completely
                    decisive.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>"Perhaps there
                    is no exercise whatever,” says Mr Roland, “more calculated for these purposes
                    (developing and cultivating bodily strength and activity) than fencing. Riding,
                    walking, sparring, wrestling, running, and pitching the bar, are all of them
                    cer-ι nly highly beneficial; but, beyond all question, there is no single
                    exercise which combines so many advantages as fencing-Bythe muscles of every
                    part of the body are brought into play; it expands the chest, and occasions an
                    equal distribution of the bl°o(and other circulating fluids, through the whole
                    system. More than one case has fallen under the author’s own observation, in
                    whic a ections of the lungs, and a tendency to consumption, have been entirely
                    removed by occasional practice with the foil; and he can state, upon very high
                    medical authority, that since the institution of a <hi rend="italic">Salle
                    d’Armes</hi> at Geneva, scrofula, which was long lamentably prevalent there, has
                    been gradually disappearing.” <hi rend="italic">(Theory and Practice of
                    Fencing,</hi> p. 163.)</p></note> To the public speaker, also, the practice of
                    the fencing-room has been found to impart an ease and freedom of gesture
                    attainable perhaps by no other exercise, not excepting even the discipline of
                    the ballet-master. A modern writer on the subject of delivery or elocution,
                    gives it as his opinion that the use of the foil and the broadsword diffuses
                    ease, elegance, and grace all over the body, and imparts to the look and gesture
                    an appearance of intellectual vigour. It does more; it teaches invaluable
                    lessons of patience and self-command, and contributes to discipline the temper,
                    whilst it serves to develope the corporeal powers, and to strengthen them by
                    unconstrained and salutary exercise. We may add here, that several works of
                    merit have appeared on this subject; but the most valuable and complete one yet
                    published is Roland’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Theory and Practice of
                    the Art of Fencing,</hi> Edinburgh, 1823; nearly all the others we have met with
                    being deficient either in explanation or in practical utility.</p>
                <p>Having already described the weapons used in fencing, we shall now proceed to
                    give such definitions as appear to be requisite for conveying a general idea of
                    the subject, referring the reader for the necessary details to the excellent
                    work of Mr Roland, which will be found equally clear in its explanations, and
                    comprehensive in its views of every branch of the art.</p>
                <p>After the first positions have been acquired, the different modes of attack come
                    to be considered. <hi rend="italic">Attacks</hi> are made in three ways: first,
                    by a quick thrust proceeding merely from the wrist, the arm at the same time
                    being elevated and advanced, with the point directed towards the adversary’s
                    breast; secondly, by what is technically called an extension; and, lastly, by
                    longeing and recovering. The <hi rend="italic">parades,</hi> in which consists
                    the defensive part of the art, naturally follow the attack. A parade is a
                    defence of the body, made by an opposition of one’s blade to that of an
                    adversary, in such a situation as, upon his attack, to prevent the point of his
                    sword hitting. The parades are eight in number, viz. six simple, and two round
                    or counter parades, and they are called <hi rend="italic">quarte,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">tierce, circle, octave, prime,</hi><hi rend="italic">quinte,</hi>
                    and round or counter in quarte and tierce. When and how these parades are made
                    in fencing may be learned by consulting Mr Roland’s work (p. 32 et seqq.).</p>
                <p>The next division of the subject includes <hi rend="italic">straight thrusts,
                    simple disengagements,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bindings of the blade.</hi> A
                    <hi rend="italic">straight thrust</hi> is used as an attack, when an antagonist,
                    from his position on guard, leaves sufficient opening to enable him to be
                    touched upon that side of the body on which blades are joined. When such an
                    opportunity offers, the wrist must be suddenly raised, so as to bring the <hi
                    rend="italic">forte</hi> of one’s sword to the <hi rend="italic">foible of</hi>
                    the adversary’s; after which <hi rend="italic">longe</hi> immediately on the
                    same line to his breast, observing, however, to preserve a correct opposition.
                    In fencing, <hi rend="italic">opposition</hi> signifies the art of covering the
                    body at the time of delivering a thrust, on that side where the foils happen to
                    cross, in order to prevent an antagonist exchanging hits. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >disengagement</hi> is made either as an attack, or as a return after defending
                    one’s-self from a thrust, and is executed both under and over the wrist or
                    foils. A disengagement over the arm may be parried with tierce or prime, and, if
                    made low, by the parade of circle; from the position of octave, by quarte, or,
                    if the thrust be delivered low, by circle; from the position of quinte, by prime
                    as the readiest defence, but quarte and tierce are also correct parades against
                    this thrust. There are three different ways of <hi rend="italic">binding the
                    blade.</hi> Of these, <hi rend="italic">βanconnade</hi> is the principal, as it
                    is sometimes a safe attack when any other mode would be attended with
                    considerable danger; it is also made as a <hi rend="italic">riposte.</hi> The
                    attack of flanconnade is commenced when the bladeá are joined in quarte, and it
                    is parried either by octave or quinte, or by the parade of quarte. The return
                    over the arm, after the parade of circle, is parried by prime or tierce, or by
                    changing quickly to the counter in quarte. The return over the arm, after the
                    parade of prime, is parried by prime or tierce, or, if made at a considerable
                    distance, by the counter in quarte.</p>
                <p>In fencing there are a great variety <hi rend="italic">of feints,</hi> which it
                    is not easy to describe intelligibly without figures, <hi rend="italic">Å.
                    feint</hi> is an intentional movement made to deceive an adversary. All thrusts,
                    therefore, may, strictly speaking, come under the definition of feints, as the
                    fencer’s object, in all his attacks, is to deceive his antagonist. For the sake
                    of convenience, however, straight thrusts and simple disengagements have been
                    arranged under a separate head. In executing the feint called <hi rend="italic"
                    >one, two,</hi> inside of the arm, supposing the adversary’s body to be covered
                    in quarte, the parade oı tierce is deceived; commencing from the outside, that
                    of quarte is deceived; from the position of the circle the octave, and from that
                    of the octave the circle is deceived-This<pb break="no" facs="nls:193751797"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-1797-0503"/> feint, if made inside the arm, is parried by the
                    parade of quarte, or by the counter in tierce, made upon an opponent’s second
                    disengagement; upon the outside of the arm, by tierce, prime, or the counter in
                    quarte; and from the position of the octave, by octave or quinte. The feint <hi
                    rend="italic">one, two,</hi> is likewise made as a return after the parade of
                    quarte or tierce, or sometimes after that of circle or octave. The <hi
                    rend="italic">cut and disengage</hi> is a species of <hi rend="italic">one,
                    two,</hi> in making which from the position of quarte, an adversary’s parade of
                    tierce is deceived, and from the position of tierce his parade of parte. <hi
                    rend="italic">Cat and disengage,</hi> if made inside of the arm, is parried by
                    quarte, or the counter in tierce; if outside, by tierce or counter in quarte.
                    <hi rend="italic">Feint</hi><hi rend="italic">seconde</hi> is another feint very
                    nearly resembling <hi rend="italic">one, two,</hi> and is generally made as a
                    return after the parades of tierce, prime, or quinte. In this feint the octave
                    or quinte is deceived; and it is parried by tierce, prime, or quarte, the two
                    former being the readiest where quinte is the parade deceived, but if the feint
                    has been answered with octave, the thrust must then be parried with quarte. The
                    feint <hi rend="italic">one, two, three,</hi> is made on either side of the
                    blade, upon precisely the same principles as <hi rend="italic">one, two</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> the only difference between them consisting in making one
                    disengagement more in the latter than in the former movement. The <hi
                    rend="italic">cut and one two</hi> is a species of <hi rend="italic">one, two,
                    three.</hi> These feints, if made over the arm, are parried with the simple
                    parade of tierce; if on the inside, with simple quarte. The other feints are,
                    <hi rend="italic">doubling,</hi> which, <hi rend="italic">mutatis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">mutandis,</hi> is executed upon precisely the same principles; <hi
                    rend="italic">one two and deceive the circle,</hi> executed from the inside
                    position of quarto; <hi rend="italic">one two and deceive the coτιnter,</hi>
                    which may be made from either side of the blade, but is most frequently used
                    commencing from the position of tierce; <hi rend="italic">feint
                    flan-connade,</hi> which can be commenced only from the engagement of quarte;
                    <hi rend="italic">feint one two and deceive octave,</hi> which is commenced
                    either from the outside or inside engagement; <hi rend="italic">feint</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">seconde</hi><hi rend="italic">and deceive</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >quarte,</hi> which is always commenced from the outside engagement, whether
                    made as an attack or a return; <hi rend="italic">feint</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >seconde</hi><hi rend="italic">and deceive</hi><hi rend="italic">tierce,</hi>
                    which differs from the preceding only in the last disengagement; <hi
                    rend="italic">one tipο and deceive</hi><hi rend="italic">quarte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">from the position of the circle,</hi> when the first disengagement
                    is made over the adversary’s wrist towards the body under the arm, and the
                    second over the wrist towards the inside of the body; and <hi rend="italic"
                    >doubling on both sides of the arm,</hi> which is too complicated a feint to be
                    frequently used in actual fencing, because it is difficult to fol-ow the
                    adversary’s sword with certainty through many different parades, and there is
                    much danger of <hi rend="italic">time thrusts</hi> upon feints which consist of
                    so many disengagements.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Time thrusts</hi> are so called because the success of these
                    movements depends entirely upon their being executed at the exact moment of time
                    employed by the adversary in planning or in executing his attack; and, when made
                    correctly, they are by far the most scientific movements in fencing. There are
                    two sorts of time thrusts, in the execution of one of which it is necessary that
                    the blades should cross each other, but for the completion of the other it is
                    not absolutely necessary that the blades should even meet. Those time thrusts in
                    the execution of which the blades cross are more scientific, and expose the
                    fencer less to exchanged hits. There are two time thrusts <hi rend="italic">in
                    opposition;</hi> one the <hi rend="italic">time over the αrm</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> and the other the <hi rend="italic">time in
                    octave.</hi> he former is applicable to all thrusts, however simple or mmplex
                    the feint may be, provided the longe is made upon the outside; whereas all
                    longes directed to the inside of the body, or under the arm, are exposed to the
                    time in oc- <hi rend="superscript"> lve</hi>; and thus almost every thrust made
                    in fencing affords ŋ‘opportunity for one or other of these two movements, hose
                    time thrusts in which the opposition is not essential ≡re made upon incorrect
                    movements of the adversary, when exposes himself by the wideness of his attacks,
                    or by quitting the blade in a dangerous position, or by making too many
                    disengagements in his feints, or by giving a variety of openings which the
                    judgment of the fencer must determine how he is to take advantage of. This
                    thrust is practised almost entirely upon irregular attacks, and requires gι eat
                    caution to be observed. It has been already stated, that time thrusts in
                    opposition, when correctly made upon good attacks, are, perhaps, the finest
                    movements in fencing; but young fencers should nevertheless attempt them very
                    seldom, from the danger of misjudging the attack, and thus exposing themselves
                    to the certainty of being hit. And the time out of opposition is attended with
                    still greater hazard, as its success depends rather upon the wideness and
                    irrcgularity of an adversary’s movements, than on the security of one’s own
                    situation afforded by the opposition in the former species of time thrust.</p>
                <p>When fencing was comparatively little known, it was thought necessary that there
                    should be some intermediate practice for the pupil between the lesson of the
                    master and his making the assault; for which purpose, it appears, he was taught
                    to longe, at a proper distance, at the wall. This was called by the French <hi
                    rend="italic">tirer au mur,</hi> and was considered as useful for planting the
                    learner well upon his legs, accustoming him to measure distance correctly, and
                    causing his motions, in making his extension and longe, to follow one another in
                    the proper succession. But as the art became better understood, observation
                    induced masters to place pupils together for their mutual advantage, the one to
                    attack by simple disengagements, the other to parry by quarte and tierce
                    alternately; and this practice, from its origin, was for a considerable time
                    called <hi rend="italic">tirer au mur,</hi> a denomination which it still
                    retains amongst fencers of the old school. It is now, however, generally known
                    by the denomination of <hi rend="italic">quarte</hi><hi rend="italic">and
                    tierce,</hi> and, in its improved state, is not merely intended as an exercise
                    for the scholar, but also as a graceful display of the principal motions of
                    fencing; for which reason it should be invariably practised before commencing
                    the assault, and in fencing before company it is never dispensed with. Quarte
                    and tierce appears very simple in its execution, yet it is exceedingly useful to
                    fencers in all stages of their progress, and difficult to acquire with such
                    correctness that all its movements shall take place in their proper succession,
                    and be made with the grace and precision characteristic of a good fencer. For a
                    description of the method of thrusting quarte and tierce, we must refer the
                    reader to the fifth chapter of Mr Roland’s work, section first. The <hi
                    rend="italic">counters</hi> is also a practice of importance to young fencers,
                    and should consequently be attended to by them.</p>
                <p>In the language of the fencing-room, making the <hi rend="italic">assault</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">playing loose</hi> are synonymous, signifying the practice
                    of attackand defence, or, in otherwords,.a just application of the lessons
                    received, which, in fact, ought to be done as correctly as if with sword in
                    hand. In the assault, the mere movements should be almost mechanical; for the
                    mind being wholly employed in discovering and counteracting the designs of the
                    adversary, as well as in concealing its own, the hand should, on the proper
                    opportunity being given, instantly execute that which the mind conceives,
                    without any consideration of the manner in which the particular motion is to be
                    made, as loss of time would most probably prove fatal to its success. The rules
                    to be observed are few and distinct. The first thing which the attention of a
                    young fencer should naturally be directed to is, the most secure manner in which
                    he can come into the position of the guard, when opposed to an adversary ready
                    to take every advantage of his inexperience. Whilst advancing into distance, it
                    is also an object of importance to have one side of the body secured by the
                    position, particularly that side to which the antagonist’s blade is opposed; so
                    that, if he commence an attack during this movement, he must quit the blade in
                    order<pb break="no" facs="nls:193751810" xml:id="kp-eb0709-1810-0504"/> to
                    direct his thrust or feint at any opening afforded him by the position of his
                    opponent; and the opportunities of attack being few, his designs will thus be
                    the more easily discovered. In short, the commanding an opponent’s blade almost
                    obliges him to effect some change in the relative situations of the contending
                    parties, before he advances into distance; and as the necessity of such previous
                    movement must be foreseen, any attempt of this kind is favourable for making an
                    attack on him. And, generally, whilst standing in the position of the guard, it
                    is an advantage to have one side of the body covered, and to command the foible
                    of the adversary’s blade. Straight thrusts and simple disengagements, executed
                    with quickness and vigour, should frequently be attempted, even though they do
                    not succeed in hitting; and this counsel should be particularly attended to in
                    fencing with a stranger. Quick simple thrusts are almost the only certain way of
                    ascertaining his favourite parades, and consequently of knowing by what feints
                    to attack him with a probability of success. The suddenness and rapidity of the
                    attack will inevitably extort from him the secret of his favourite defence.</p>
                <p>Many masters of the old school, and some, too, of the present day, have treated
                    <hi rend="italic">disarming</hi> as a matter of importance in the art; but, from
                    its inutility, not to mention danger, in the field, it is now considered by the
                    highest authorities on the subject as incompatible with good fencing. Mr Roland,
                    in the work already referred to, shows by what methods this may be accomplished,
                    and at the same time demonstrates the utter uselessness of the trick, for it is
                    no better. The only advantage of disarming indeed is that of annoying the person
                    disarmed; for, sword in hand, it is rendered nugatory by the use of a
                    sword-knot, with which, it may be presumed, every person at all acquainted with
                    the weapon will take especial care to fasten it to his wrist in a serious
                    affair. As the manoeuvre of disarming may therefore be defeated by the most
                    ordinary precaution, attempting it can serve no other purpose than to make one
                    play heavily and unpleasantly; whilst, from the strength it requires for the
                    execution of its movements, it takes from the necessary quickness, and affords
                    an adversary favourable moments of attack during the time an attempt is being
                    made to bind his blade. In short, disarming is considered as characteristic of
                    unskilful fencing; since perfection in the trick can only tend to render fencing
                    disagreeable with the foil and ineffectual with the sword. We may add, that <hi
                    rend="italic">volting, demi-volting, pirouetting,</hi> parrying with and
                    opposing the left hand, are manoeuvres now totally disused in fencing.</p>
                <p>As far back as 1692 a very curious book on the subject of fencing was published
                    by Sir William Hope; it is now very scarce. In 1780 a Lieutenant M‘Arthur
                    published a work on fencing, which he dedicated to the Duke of Argyll, and
                    which, we believe, is considered as a respectable performance. But since the
                    latter period nothing worth noticing appears to have been written on the
                    subject, with the exception of Angelo’s book, illustrated by engravings, and the
                    works of the two Rolands; of these, the most complete and satisfactory is Mr
                    George Roland’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Theory and Practice of
                    Fencing</hi> above referred to. The only standard French works on the subject
                    are, a Treatise by Μ. Danet, director of the royal academy of privileged
                    fencing-masters; and one by Μ. Laboissier; both works of great merit, and highly
                    esteemed in France.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
