<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-8701-0722-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOCCACIO, or Boccace, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 722</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1059232">Petrarchism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jj0k">Merchants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n873131">Carthusians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193198701" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOCCACIO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Boccace, John</hi></label>,
                    one of the most gifted and learned writers of his age, whose name alone,
                    according to Mazzuchelli, is worth a thousand eulogiums, was born in 1313. His
                    father was a merchant at Florence, where the pursuits of commerce were held in
                    the highest estimation; and his family came originally from Certaldo, a village
                    situated about twenty miles from the capital of Tuscany; for which reason he
                    generally subjoined to his name the words <hi rend="italic">da Certaldo.</hi>
                    Boccacio was not, therefore, the son of a peasant, as has been asserted in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Historique.</hi> He appears to have been the
                    illegitimate offspring of a connection which his father had formed while at
                    Paris, having been called thither by some commercial affairs; and it was also in
                    the French capital that the illustrious author of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Decameron</hi> first saw the light. Conveyed at an early period to Florence, he
                    commenced his studies, and, from his tenderest years, evinced a decided taste
                    for poetry; but he had scarcely attained <pb break="no" facs="nls:193198714"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-8714-0723"/>the age of ten when his father placed him in the
                    house of another merchant, with the view of training him up to commerce. Several
                    years afterwards this merchant took him to Paris, and kept him in all six years
                    in his house; but failing to inspire his charge with a taste for the mercantile
                    profession, to which the latter gave only a reluctant and compulsory attention,
                    he sent the youth back to his father. At Florence, as at Paris, Boccacio was
                    divided between occupations for which he felt nothing but repugnance, and a
                    taste for letters which went on increasing daily. And this taste received a
                    fresh stimulus at Naples, to which he had been sent with the view of withdrawing
                    him from such pursuits, and attaching him definitively to the mercantile
                    profession. He remained there eight years, and instead of associating only with
                    merchants, he established an intimacy with several learned men, Florentine as
                    well as Neapolitan, whom the favour of King Robert, the friend and patron of
                    letters, had drawn to his capital. There is no evidence whatever of Boccacio
                    having personally experienced the kindness of Robert; but he appears to have
                    excited a tender interest in the bosom of the king’s natural daughter, for whom
                    he composed several works both in prose and verse, and whom he often designates
                    by the name of Fiammetta. Endowed with all exterior advantages, of a lively and
                    joyous disposition, possessing an amiable and yielding character, and the
                    favoured lover of the daughter of a king, it is not surprising that he should
                    have then felt less inclination than ever for mercantile occupations and
                    pursuits. The sprightly taste of the princess, the intimate companionship of men
                    of letters, the impression made upon him in a walk near Naples by the tomb of
                    Virgil, the presence of Petrarch, who was treated with the most marked
                    distinction by the court, being then about to proceed to Rome, there to receive
                    the laurel crown, and probably, also, his first intercourse with this celebrated
                    man, whose intimate friend and associate he was afterwards to become,—all
                    contributed to strengthen his natural inclination, and to decide his vocation as
                    a literary man and a poet.</p>
                <p>After a residence of two years with his father at Florence, he returned to
                    Naples, and was favourably received by the queen, Jane; and it is believed that
                    it was as much to gratify the young queen as his dear Fiammetta, that he began
                    the Decameron, or collection of a hundred tales, which places him, without a
                    rival, in the first rank of Italian prose-writers. Having lost his father, and
                    being thus at liberty to follow his own inclination, he went to settle at
                    Florence, where his studies suffered no interruption except what was occasioned
                    by pleasure, and some honourable missions with which he was charged by his
                    fellow-citizens. Among other offices of this kind, he was the person selected to
                    go to Padua, and carry to Petrarch the intelligence of his recall, and of the
                    restitution that had been made of the property of his father, who, formerly
                    banished from Florence, had since died in exile; and it was in the execution of
                    this mission that he formed with his illustrious contemporary that close and
                    intimate friendship which only ceased with their lives. Some years afterwards,
                    having involved himself in embarrassments by his expenditure in the purchase of
                    books and his taste for pleasure, he was generously relieved by Petrarch, who
                    not only afforded him pecuniary aid, but gave him good counsel both as to his
                    works and his conduct, and was mainly instrumental in bringing about the change
                    which subsequently took place in his habits and character. A coürse of pleasure
                    or dissipation is sure, sooner or later, to terminate in satiety, ennui,
                    heart-sickness, and remorse; and when this crisis actually comes on, the
                    presence and counsels of a tender and judicious friend may not only serve to
                    check the moral re-action before it proceeds too far, but may also give a new
                    and salutary direction to the mind and feelings of the penitent. Petrarch
                    performed this important office to his friend. The exhortations of a Carthusian
                    monk had at first inspired the latter with an extravagant scheme of reform,
                    being nothing less than an entire renunciation of the world, and of those
                    studies which are denominated profane; but Petrarch brought him back to better
                    views, and kept him steadily in that just medium which is the position
                    recommended by true wisdom.</p>
                <p>Some new troubles having about this time broken out in Florence, Boccacio
                    withdrew to Certaldo, where he possessed a small territory, in order to continue
                    his pursuits in tranquillity. Hitherto he had only written in the vulgar tongue,
                    and produced works of mere amusement; but now he composed several, which he
                    wrote in Latin, on subjects of erudition and history; and one of these treatises
                    is the first modern work in which a collection was made of all the mythological
                    notions which are scattered throughout the writings of the ancients. He knew
                    Greek very well, having brought, at his own expense, from Venice to Florence,
                    Leontius Pilatus of Thessalonica, and entertained him for three years, in order
                    to learn of him that language, to read with the learned refugee the Iliad and
                    the Odyssey, and to translate both from beginning to end into Latin. He had also
                    the glory of procuring from Greece, at his own expense, copies of these immortal
                    works; nor did his zeal in the cause of classical learning stop here; for he
                    spared neither pains nor expense in order to obtain good Greek and Latin
                    manuscripts, and employed all his influence to induce his contemporaries to
                    lcarn Greek, and to substitute the study of antiquity for that of the scholastic
                    sciences,'which alone had hitherto been encouraged. Auspicious for the cause of
                    true learning, these efforts added to the reputation and authority of Boccacio.
                    He was twice charged with important embassies from the republic of Florence to
                    Pope Urban V., and executed them in a manner creditable to himself and
                    satisfactory to his countrymen. He then returned to Certaldo, and resumed his
                    favourite studies; but a long and grievous malady, with which he was now
                    attacked, reduced him to a state of languor and depression more painful than
                    even the disease itself. On recovering somewhat, he undertook a difficult, but
                    to him most agreeable, task. He had always been an ardent admirer of Dante; he
                    knew by heart nearly the whole of his poem, and had copied it several times with
                    his own hand. The Florentines, who had persecuted and exiled this great poet,
                    wishing now to honour and vindicate his memory, instituted, by a decree of the
                    senate, a public chair for the explication of this poem, which, although it
                    contained many sublime things, was nevertheless filled with obscurities and
                    difficulties, certain to increase with the progress of time, and in proportion
                    as we are removed from the period in which the author wrote; and it was on
                    Boccacio that they conferred the new professorship. But the efforts which he
                    made to fulfil the expectations of his countrymen retarded his convalescence;
                    the death of Petrarch, his master and friend, which took place at this time, and
                    was suddenly communicated to him, proved a stunning blow; he became daily weaker
                    and weaker; and in little more than a year he died at Certaldo, on the 21st
                    December 1375, in the sixty-second year of his age.</p>
                <p>Boccacio was indeed born a poet; he was so in all his works of imagination, at
                    least in invention if not in style. All that he has written in verse is
                    mediocre; several of his Italian works in prose are also poor enough. He is only
                    superior and inimitable in his novels, of which nevertheless he made small
                    account. Like his master Petrarch, he believed that his serious works, written
                    in Latin, formed his best title to fame; yet his reputation rests exclusively<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193198727" xml:id="kp-eb0704-8727-0724"/> on a simple
                    collection of tales, as that of Petrarch does on his amatory verses. Every thing
                    lie has written in Latin bears a character of crude precipitation, which,
                    however, is less the effect of negligence in the author, than of those
                    difficulties and obstacles which were then opposed to the composition of such
                    works. In his youth he had flattered himself with the idea of obtaining the
                    second place in poetry by his verses; his admiration of Dante did not allow him
                    to aspire to the first; and the Italian poems of Petrarch were as yet unknown to
                    him. But as soon as he became acquainted with the latter, he threw into the fire
                    the greater part of his lyric verses, sonnets, canzoni, and other amatory poems;
                    and those which’have since been published are merely such as, in spite of
                    himself, escaped this act of severity. But the fortunate result of his disgust
                    with his poetical productions was to induce Boccacio to write with greater care
                    in prose, and to give to his language a perfection, rhythm, harmony, and
                    elegance in the <hi rend="italic">tournure</hi> of expression, which it had
                    hitherto wanted, and which Italian, with all its capabilities, has never
                    attained to the same degree in the hands of any other writer. His style may be
                    characterized in two words; it is <hi rend="italic">simplex munditiis;</hi>
                    grace, elegance, and simplicity combined are its peculiar attributes; and so
                    skilfully is the art of the writer concealed in the very perfection of his work,
                    that while the charm diffused over it proves irresistible to readers of every
                    class, it seems a spontaneous emanation of his mind, the result of mere
                    volition, without labour, without effort, and without premeditation. The
                    following is a tolerably correct list of Boccacio’s different works:</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">De Genealogia Deorum libri</hi> xv. <hi rend="italic">De
                    Montium, Syl-varum, Lacuum, Fluviorum, et Marium nominibus, liber.</hi> The
                    first edition of these two works united is in folio, without date, but it is
                    supposed to have been printed at Venice prior to 1472, which is the date of the
                    second edition. A third was printed the following year, and there have since
                    been several at Venice, Paris, and Basel. The treatise on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Genealogy of the Gods</hi> was the fruit of immense reading; and as there
                    existed at that time no similar work in which information might be obtained
                    respecting the mythology of the ancients, its success was prodigious. In this
                    production Boccacio cites several authors no longer extant, and derives from
                    them particulars which are only to be found in his book. This work, translated
                    into Italian by Joseph Betusi, has gone through twelve or thirteen editions, the
                    first being that of Venice, 1574, in 4to. There are also two French
                    translations; the first at Paris in 1498, in folio, reprinted in 1531, also in
                    folio, and the second at Paris in 1578, in 8vo. The little <hi rend="italic"
                    >Treatise on Mountains, Forests, Lakes, Fivers, and Seas,</hi> has also been
                    translated into Italian; it is in quarto, but without date or name of place.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">De Casibus Virorum et Fceminarum Illustrium, libri</hi> ix.
                    The Paris edition of this treatise is in folio, and dated 1535, 1544. It was
                    translated into Italian by Betusi, Venice, 1545, 8vo; into English by John
                    Ludgate, London, 1494, folio, reprinted in the same form in 1527; into Spanish
                    by D. Pedro Lopez de Ayala, and D. Juan de Zamora, Seville, 1495, Toledo, 151Ĩ,
                    folio; into German by Jerome Ziegler, Augsburg, 1545, folio; and several times
                    into French, first by an anonymous translator, Bruges, 1476, folio; next by
                    Laurens du Premier-fait, Paris, 1483, folio, and at Lyons the same year; and,
                    lastly, by Claude Witard, Paris, 1578, 8vo.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">De Claris Mulicribus.</hi> The first edition is without date
                    or name of place; the second was published at Ulm in 1473, and, like the first,
                    is in folio. The work was translated into Italian∙by Vincent Bagli, a
                    Florentine, Venice, 1506, 4to, and by Joseph Betusi, who made several additions,
                    and prefixed a life of Boccacio, Venice, 1545 and 1547,8vo. There are also
                    Spanish, French, and German versions.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Eclogae.</hi> These eclogues, sixteen in number, were
                    printed, along with those of Virgil, Calphurnius, Nemesianus, Petrarch, and
                    Gauricus, at Florence in 1504, and again at Basel in 1546, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bucolicorum Autores.</hi></p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">La Tescide,</hi> the first Italian poem which presents a
                    specimen of the epopee. It is written in the <hi rend="italic">ottava rima,</hi>
                    of which Boccacio is usually considered as the inventor. Ferrara, 1475, folio;
                    Venice, 1528, 4to; Paris, 1597, 12mo, a French translation.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Amorosa Visione,</hi> Milan 1520 and 1521, in 4to, with
                    grammatical observations, and a defence of Boccacio by Claricio d’Imola, Venice,
                    1531, 8vo.</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Il Filostrato,</hi> a romantic poem in <hi rend="italic"
                    >ottava rima,</hi> the hero of which is the young Troilus, son of Priam, and the
                    subject his amours with Chryseis, whom the poet makes the daughter of Chalcas,
                    Bologna, 1498, 4to; Milan, 1499, 4to; Venice, 1501 and 1528, 4to.</p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Nimfale Fiesolano,</hi> a poem also in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >ottava rima,</hi> in which, under the veil of pastoral fiction, Boccacio is
                    supposed to give an account of a gallant adventure which occurred at Florence in
                    his time. Venice, 1477, 4to; Paris, Molini, 1778, 8vo.</p>
                <p>9. <hi rend="italic">Fime,</hi> or poems on various subjects, being such as
                    escaped the flames when the author resolved to bum all his verses. They have
                    been several times collected; but Baldelli’s edition, printed at Leghorn in
                    1802, is the best.</p>
                <p>10. <hi rend="italic">Il Filocopo, owero Amorosa Fatica,</hi> &amp;c. a romance,
                    written by the author when very young, and wholly devoid of interest. It is
                    unconscionably long, and desperately tedious; and the style, which is sometimes
                    flat and at other times bombastical, gives no promise of that purity of diction
                    which Boccacio afterwards attained. Venice, 1472, folio; Milan, 1476 and 1478,
                    folio; Venice, 1514, 4to; Paris, 1542, folio, and 1555, 8vo.</p>
                <p>11. <hi rend="italic">L’Amorosa Fiammetta,</hi> another romance, in no degree
                    superior to <hi rend="italic">11 Filostrato.</hi> Padua, 1472, 4to; Venice,
                    1481, 4to; Paris, 1585, 1609, 12mo.</p>
                <p>12. <hi rend="italic">Ľ Urbano,</hi> Florence, 1598, 8vo; translated into French
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Urbain le Mescogneu,</hi> Lyons, without
                    date.</p>
                <p>13. <hi rend="italic">Ameto</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Nimfalc d’ Ameto,</hi> a
                    work written in prose, intermixed with verse, and the earliest specimen of this
                    kind of composition. Rome and Venice, 1478, 4to; Treviso, 1479, 4to; Venice,
                    1503, folio; Florence, 1521, 8vo.</p>
                <p>14. <hi rend="italic">Il Corbaccio, o sia Laberinto d’Amore,</hi> a bitter and
                    coarse invective against some female who had displeased him after his return to
                    Florence. The indecency of this production is abominable, but the purity and
                    beauty of the style have caused it to be sought after. Florence, 1487, 4to;
                    Venice, 1516, 24to, and 1528, 8vo; Paris, 1569, 8vo.</p>
                <p>15. <hi rend="italic">Origine, Vita et Costumi di Dante Alighieri,</hi> Rome,
                    1544, 8vo; Florence, 1576, 8vo. In this life of Dante Boccacio shows himself
                    more of a romancer than a biographer; but it is nevertheless interesting on
                    account of several curious anecdotes it contains, and also by reason of the
                    style, which is every way worthy of Boccacio.</p>
                <p>16. <hi rend="italic">Commento sopra la Commedia di Dante Alighieri,</hi>
                    invaluable work, containing a great number of explications of difficult passages
                    in Dante, although almost suffocated by a multitude of details foreign to the
                    intelligence of the text. This commentary, which embodies the lessons delivered
                    publicly by Boccacio at Florence, when he was attacked with the malady of which
                    he died, was not printed till the eighteenth century. It extends only to the
                    17th chapter of the <hi rend="italic">Inferno,</hi> and occupies the two last
                    volumes of the collection of Boccacio’s works in Italian prose, published at
                    Naples, with the false imprint of Florence, in θ vols. 8vo, 1724.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193198740" xml:id="kp-eb0704-8740-0725"/>
                <p>17. Lastly, <hi rend="italic">Il Decamerone,</hi> Boccacio’s principal title to
                    immortality, and of all works extant, that, perhaps, of which it is the most
                    difficult to convey a tolerably accurate idea in few words. To regard it merely
                    as a collection of gallant and licentious tales, is to entertain a very false
                    notion indeed of this extraordinary work. The greater part of the poets, it is
                    true, who have borrowed from this source, have indeed taken little else from it
                    than licentiousness; but it is their fault more than that of the author, if
                    their draughts have been so confined. In the Decameron, Boccacio has painted, as
                    on an immense canvass, men of all conditions, of all characters, of all ages;
                    and described events of every kind, from the freest and the gayest to the most
                    touching and the most tragical. He has also given models of all sorts of
                    eloquence, and carried his language to a pitch of perfection unknown before his
                    time, and unrivalled since. For three centuries after it appeared it was
                    constantly reprinted, and more than a hundred different editions might be
                    enumerated; to say nothing of translations into every language of Europe which
                    is connected with an independent literature. At the same time it has experienced
                    singular vicissitudes. From the date of the first edition in 1470, liberties of
                    every kind were taken with the text, particularly in the more licentious parts,
                    which led to its prohibition by two popes, Paul IV. and Pius IV.; some
                    academicians also undertook to reform the Decameron; important corrections as
                    well as suppressions were made; and several editions, thus amended, appeared.
                    But in order to judge of the work as it proceeded from the hand of Boccacio, we
                    must revert to the older editions, or to those which have followed them. The
                    rarestand dearest is that of Florence, 1527, in 4to. Of this, however, an exact
                    copy was printed at Venice in 1729, but bearing at the end the name of Florence
                    and the date of 1527. It is nevertheless easily distinguishable by those marks
                    which are known to bibliographers. The curious ought to have, also, for
                    comparison, the edition amended by the Florentine academicians, conformably to
                    the orders of the grand duke of Tuscany, and approved by Gregory XIII. It will
                    show, on the one hand, to what a state the master-piece of Boccacio had been
                    reduced; and, on the other, excite surprise at the remnants of the old
                    interpolations which are preserved, and invested with the pontifical sanction.
                    This edition was printed at Florence in 1573, in 4to. The edition of Salviati,
                    who undertook a new reform, appeared at Venice in 1584, in 4to. In both these
                    reformed editions the portion of the text respected and left untouched is of
                    extreme purity. It would be endless to attempt an enumeration of other editions,
                    or of the translations which have been made into different languages. <hi
                    rend="italic">(Biographie Universelle, Creseembeni.')</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
