<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-3033-0286-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAILLIE, Robert</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 286</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193193033" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAILLIE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, one of the
                    most learned men among the Scotish presbyterians of the seventeenth century, was
                    born at Glasgow in the year 1599. His father, who is described as a citizen, was
                    a son of Baillie of Jerviston, who belonged to the family of Carphin, a branch
                    of the ancient family of Lamington, in the county of Lanark; his mother was
                    Helen Gibson, connected with the Gibsons of Durie, one of whom was an eminent
                    judge in the supreme court. In the year 1617 he was matriculated in the
                    university of Glasgow, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Robertus
                    Baillize;</hi> and here it may be remarked that, according to the careless
                    practice of the age, he afterwards exhibited no small variety in the orthography
                    of his surname, writing it Baylie, Baily, Bailie, and Baillie. His studies were
                    partly conducted under the superintendence of John Cameron, a man of great
                    learning and reputation, who had been a professor in the protestant university
                    of Saumur, and who in 1622 was appointed principal of the university of Glasgow.
                    From him Baillie imbibed the doctrine of passive obedience; and, in consequence
                    of this prejudice of education, he only gave a tardy assent to the strenuous
                    measures which were afterwards adopted against Charles the First. Having taken
                    the degree of A. M. he applied himself to the study of divinity, and in due time
                    received ordination from Archbishop Law.</p>
                <p>On the 16th of August 1626 he was admitted one of the regents of the university;
                    and, on taking his chair, he delivered an inaugural oration <hi rend="italic">De
                    Mente agent</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> e</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> Dr
                    Strang, a man of talents and learning, had been appointed principal a few months
                    before. About the same period,</p>
                <p>Baillie appears to have prosecuted the study of the oriental languages, in which
                    he is allowed to have attained to no mean proficiency. He was anxious to promote
                    similar studies in the university; and in the year 1629 he delivered an oration
                    <hi rend="italic">In Laudern Linguoe Hebraeae.</hi></p>
                <p>One of the pupils intrusted to his charge was Lord Montgomery, eldest son to the
                    earl of Eglintoun, by whom he was presented to the living of Kilwinning in
                    Ayrshire. His induction must have taken place between 1630 and 1632. With this
                    noble family he continued to live on terms of intimacy; and as he was a person
                    of excellent character, he equally enjoyed the approbation of his own
                    parishioners, and the confidence of his ordinary the archbishop of Glasgow. In
                    1633 he declined the offer of a living in Edinburgh. Between 1634 and 1636 he
                    was much employed in discussing, by means of private correspondence with his
                    brethren, certain questions respecting Arminianism, and the ceremonies obtruded
                    on the church by the partisans of Laud. In 1638 the presbytery of Irvine elected
                    him a member of the assembly which was held at Glasgow, and which laid the
                    foundation of material changes in church and state. During the ensuing year his
                    countrymen raised a considerable army, which was placed under the command of
                    Alexander Leslie, an old and experienced officer; and Baillie appears to have
                    caught some portion of the military ardour which now prevailed in this cause of
                    religion and liberty. “It would have done you good,” he remarks in one of his
                    letters, “to have cast your eyes athortour brave and rich hills as oft as I did,
                    with greater contentment and joy; for I was there among the rest, being chosen
                    preacher by the gentlemen of our shire, who came late with Lord Eglinton. I
                    furnished to half a dozen of good fellows, muskets andpikes, and to my boy a
                    broad sword. I carried myself, as the fashion was, a sword, and a couple of
                    Dutch pistols at my saddle; but, I promise, for the offence of no man, except a
                    robber in the -way; for it was our part alone to pray and preach for the
                    encouragement of our countrymen, which I did to my power most chearfully.” <hi
                    rend="italic">{Letters,</hi> vol. i. p. 174.) He afterwards states, “Our
                    soldiers grew in experience of arms, in courage, in favour, daily. Every one
                    encouraged another. The sight of the nobles, and their beloved pastors, daily
                    raised their hearts. The good sermons and prayers, morning and evening, under
                    the roof of heaven, to which their drums did call them for bells; the
                    remonstrances very frequent of the goodness of their cause; of their conduct
                    hitherto, by a hand clearly divine; also Lesly’s skill, and prudence, and
                    fortune, made them as resolute for battle as could be wished. We were feared
                    that emulation among our nobles might have done harm, when they should be met in
                    the field; but such was the wisdom and authority of that old, little, crooked
                    soldier, that all, with an incredible submission, from the beginning to the end,
                    gave over themselves to be guided by him, as if he had been great
                    Solyman....Hadyou lent your ear in the morning, or especially at even, and heard
                    in the tents the sound of some singing psalms, some praying, and some reading
                    Scripture, ye would have been refreshed. True, there was swearing, and cursing,
                    and brawling, in some quarters, whereat we were grieved; but we hoped, if our
                    camp had been a little settled, to have gotten some way for these misorders; for
                    all of any fashion did regret, and all promised to do their best endeavours for
                    helping all abuses. For myself, I never found my mind in better temper than it
                    was all that time since I came from home, till my head was again homeward; for I
                    was as a man who had taken my leave from the world, and was resolved tn die in
                    that service without return.” This enthusiastic army had advanced to the borders
                    of the kingdom, and had pitched its -camp on Dunse Law; the royal forces were
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:193193046" xml:id="kp-eb0704-3046-0287"/> within a very
                    short distance; and the adverse parties were on the eve of a general engagement,
                    when the treaty of Berwick, negotiated with Charles in person, produced a
                    temporary cessation of open hostilities. But the seeds of dissension were too
                    widely scattered, and had taken too deep root, to be so speedily checked in
                    their growth: the notions of the king, sufficiently arbitrary in themselves,
                    were at variance with the elastic spirit of the age; and his subjects, in both
                    divisions of the island, were gradually impressed with a deep conviction of his
                    insincerity. In the year 1640 the Covenanters again had recourse to arms; and
                    having invaded England, they took the town of Newcastle. Baillie now resumed his
                    attendance in the camp; and before the close of the year he was employed in
                    London, along with other commissioners, in preparing charges against Archbishop
                    Laud, for the innovations which he had obtruded on the church of Scotland. He
                    had very recently published <hi rend="italic">The Canterburiarì's
                    Self-Conviction,</hi> which seems to have been industriously circulated, and
                    which arrived at a fourth edition. About this period of his life he composed
                    various other works of a controversial nature, and was regarded as one of the
                    most strenuous defenders of the presbyterian cause.</p>
                <p>His merit was now so conspicuous that he was offered a professorship in each of
                    the four universities. Having been appointed one of the professors of divinity
                    at Glasgow, he delivered, on the 6th of July 1642, an inaugural oration <hi
                    rend="italic">De Hoereticoum Autocatacrisi.</hi> About this period he must have
                    taken the degree of D. D.; for the records of the university describe him as
                    “Doctor et Professor SS. Theologiae.” His colleague David Dickson, who had been
                    appointed in 1640, is described in the same manner; but neither of them assumed
                    the title of doctor in his printed works. Both professors discharged the
                    functions of clergymen in the city; and in such of his publications as bear the
                    author’s name, Baillie styles himself minister at Glasgow, or minister of the
                    gospel at Glasgow, without any addition. While he filled this chair, it is to be
                    inferred that his chief employment consisted in teaching the oriental languages.
                    Dr Dickson having been removed to the university of Edinburgh, he was admitted
                    to the higher professorship of divinity on the 17th of January 1651. His labours
                    were various and extensive. He was much engaged in the public affairs of the
                    church, and was a member of all the general assemblies from 1638 to 1653, with
                    the exception of those which were held during his attendance at Westminster. In
                    1642 the assembly appointed him to visit and preach in the north of Ireland
                    during four months. To the assembly of Westminster, which commenced its sittings
                    in the year 1643, the church of Scotland sent Alexander Henderson, Robert
                    Douglas, Samuel Rutherford, Robert Baillie, and George Gillespie, together with
                    three ruling elders, the Earl of Cassilis, Lord Maitland, and Sir Archibald
                    Johnston of Warriston. Of the proceedings of this ecclesiastical coun-cd,
                    Baillie has given an interesting account in his correspondence. His modest
                    opinion of himself, and his high estimate of his colleagues, are equally
                    conspicuous. “These things are so high, and of so great concernment,” he remarks
                    in a letter to Robert Blair, “that no living man can think Mr Henderson may be
                    away; and to put ' him to go and return, it were very hard to venture such a
                    jewel, that is so necessary to the well-being both of church and state of all
                    these dominions. Mr Samuel, for the great parts God has given him, and special
                    acquaintance with the question in hand, is very necessary to be here. ...Mr G.
                    Gillespie, however I had a good opinion of his gifts, yet I profess he has much
                    deceived me. Of a truth there is no man whose parts in a publick dispute I do so
                    admire. He has studied so accurately all the points ever yet came to our
                    assembly, he has gotten so ready, so assured, so solid a way of publick
                    debating, that however there be in the assembly divers very excellent men, yet,
                    in my poor judgement, there is not one who speaks more rationally, and to the
                    point, than that brave youth has done ever; so that his absence would be
                    prejudicial to our whole cause, and unpleasant to all here that wishes it well.”
                    <hi rend="italic">(Letters,</hi> vol. i. p. 451.) In 1645 he returned from
                    England, in order to give to the general assembly an account of the proceedings
                    at Westminster; and having resumed his station among the assembled divines, he
                    continued to reside for some time longer in the English metropolis.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The following passage occurs
                    in a letter, dated at Glasgow on the 22d of August 1654, and addressed to the
                    famous Dr Fuller: ‘ Haveing lately, and but lately, gone through your Holy Warr
                    and Description of Palestine, I am fallen so in love with your pen, that I am
                    sorie I wes not before acquaint with it. and with yourself, when from the 1643
                    to 1647 I lived at Worcester house, and preached in the Savov, that then, when I
                    had some credite there, I might have used my best endeavours to have done yow
                    pleasure.” (Baillie’s <hi rend="italic">MS. Letters,</hi> vol. iv. p. 423.) Of
                    the pulpit-oratory, and of the general talents of the Scotish divines who
                    visited London, the Earl of Clarendon and Mr Hume have given the same
                    unfavourable account; but on this subject, as well as on many others, their
                    opinion is strongly contested by Mr Brodie. “These famous divines preached as
                    chaplains, by turns, in one of the lecture-rooms; and, as was to have been
                    expected at such a juncture from ņien of their reputation, capacity, and
                    profound as well as varied erudition, they drew immense crowds. If we may form
                    an estimate of their pulpit-oratory from their works, we may safely pronounce
                    that the English did not discredit themselves by flocking to hear such
                    preachers.” <hi rend="italic">{History of the Biitish Empire,</hi> vol. iii. p.
                    41.) </p></note> He now stood very high in the esteem and confidence of his
                    countrymen; and in 1649 he was one of the commissioners sent to Holland for the
                    purpose of inviting Charles IL, and of settling the terms of his admission to
                    the government. In the controversy which prevailed among the presbyterians
                    between 1650 and 1660, he adhered to the party of the Resolutioners against that
                    of the Protesters. The commission of the general assembly had adopted two <hi
                    rend="italic">resolutions,</hi> by which they consented to the repeal of the act
                    for reforming the army, and the act by which certain classes of persons were
                    excluded from places of power and tru9t, on account of their immoral conduct, or
                    of the opposition which they had evinced towards the cause of civil and
                    religious reform; and the resolutions having been approved by two subsequent
                    assemblies, a formal <hi rend="italic">protest</hi> against the constitution and
                    proceedings of those assemblies was entered by various ministers and elders.</p>
                <p>After the restoration, Patrick Gillespie, who had enjoyed the special favour of
                    Cromwell, was ejected from his office; and on the 23d of January 1661 Baillie
                    was admitted as principal of the university of Glasgow. For this promotion he
                    was indebted to Lauderdale, who had not yet appeared in his true and hideous
                    colours. According to some writers, he might have exchanged his academical
                    office for a bishopric; but he was deeply grieved at the establishment of
                    episcopacy, and would not accept of preferment in the church. When the new
                    archbishop or Glasgow, Andrew Fairfoul, arrived at his metropolitan seat, he did
                    not fail to pay his respects to the learned principal. Baillie admits that “he
                    preached on the Sunday, soberly and well.” “The chancellor, my noble kind
                    scholar,” he afterwards states, “brought all in to see me in my chamber, where I
                    gave them sack and ale the best of the town. The bishop was very courteous to
                    me. I excused my not using of his styles, and professed my <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193193059" xml:id="kp-eb0704-3059-0288"/>utter difference from his
                    way, yet behoved to intreat his favour for our affairs of the college; wherein
                    he promised liberally. What he will perform, time will try.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Letters,</hi> vol. ii. p. 461.) According to another account, the archbishop
                    visited him during his illness, and was accosted in the following terms:—“Mr
                    Andrew, I will not call you my Lord. King Charles would have made me one of
                    these lords; but I do not find in the New Testament that Christ has any lords in
                    his house.” In other respects he is said to have treated the prelate very
                    courteously; and it may not be superfluous to remark, that this mode of using
                    the Christian name instead of the surname was not unusual at that period.
                    Baillie died in the month of July 1662, at the age of sixty-thřee.</p>
                <p>His first wife was Lilias Fleming, of the family of Car-darroch, in the parish of
                    Cadder, near Glasgow. Of this marriage there were many children, but only five
                    survived him. 1. Henry, a clergyman, who was never beneficed. His posterity
                    inherited the estate of Cárnbroe, which was recently sold by General Baillie. 2.
                    Lilias, married to Eccles of Kildonan in Ayrshire. 3. Helen, married to a bailie
                    of Glasgow, named Colquhoun. 4. Elizabeth, married to Mr Hamilton, a gentleman
                    of Strathbane in the kingdom of Ireland. 5. Mary, married to Walter Buchanan of
                    Orchard. The mother of .these children died on the 7th of June 1653, after a
                    lingering illness. She is mentioned by her husband in terms of much respect and
                    affection. On the 1st of October 1656 he married Mrs Wilkie, who was a widow,
                    and the daughter of Dr Strang. The issue of this marriage was Margaret, who
                    became the wife of Walkingshaw of Borrowfield.</p>
                <p>Wodrow, the zealous and faithful historian of the persecuted church of Scotland,
                    has formed a very high estimate of Baillie’s literary character. “Mr Robert
                    Bailie may most justly be reckoned among the great men of this time, and was an
                    honour to his country, for his profound and universal learning, his exact and
                    solid judgement, that vast variety of languages he understood, to the number of
                    twelve or thirteen, and his writing a Latin style which might have become the
                    Augustan age.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Wodrofs
                    History of the Sufferings of the Church of Scotland, <hi rend="italic">vol. i.
                    p. 128. Edinb. 1721-2, 2 vols. fol See the same author’s</hi> Lift of James
                    lVodro∙w, Α.M. Professor of Divinity in the University of Glasgow, <hi
                    rend="italic">p. 30. Edinb. 1828, 12mo.</hi></p></note> This commendation of his
                    Latinity may admit of some abatement; for although he evidently possessed a very
                    familiar knowledge of the language, his Latin style cannot safely be said to
                    reach the standard of ancient purity and elegance. An episcopalian writer, the
                    author of the Appendix to Spotswood, has commemorated Baillie as “a learned and
                    modest man: though he published some very violent writings, yet those flowed
                    rather from the instigation of other persons, than his own inclinations.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">T.
                    Middleton’s</hi> Appendix to the History of the Church of Scotland, <hi
                    rend="italic">p. 23. Lond. 1G77, fol.</hi></p></note> Mr Brodie, a recent
                    historian of much ability and research, bestows the following commendation on
                    Baillie and his associates. “The clergy, on whom they greatly depended, were
                    profound scholars, and no despicable politicians. Nothing can be more misplaced
                    than the ridicule which has been so profusely levelled at that body. They proved
                    themselves ambitious; but, to be satisfied of their talents, and to admire their
                    knowledge, it is only necessary to peruse their works. The writings of Baillie,
                    even his familiar letters, breathe a manliness of spirit, and evince
                    intelligence and erudition, that must for ever rescue from contempt a class of
                    which he did not conceive himself entitled to rank at the head.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Brodie’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hist, of the British Empire,</hi> vol. ii. p. 506.</p></note></p>
                <p>Baillie had devoted much attention to the study of the oriental languages, and
                    was skilled in Hebrew, Chaldee, Syriac, Samaritan, Arabic, and Ethiopic. In his
                    correspondence with the scholars of the continent, he urged Golius, Buxtorf, and
                    other learned men, to compose elementary works on such of these languages as
                    were not already provided wjth them. In an unpublished letter, dated at Glasgow
                    on the 27th of August 1656, and addressed to Mr Crawford, a minister of London,
                    he remarks, “The reason of my calling to you at this tyme is my desyre to know
                    the condition of that excellent book, the best to me that ever was printed, Dr
                    Walton’s Polyglott Bible.” He was solicitous that the learned protestants should
                    undertake an Encyclopaedia of arts and sciences; and urged his correspondents
                    not to permit the education of youth, and the composition of books for
                    elementary instruction, to be so generally engrossed by the Jesuits.</p>
                <p>Of Baillie’s publications, the following is as complete a list as we have been
                    able to furnish.</p>
                <p>1. Ladensium Auro%αrακwΛς, the Canterbvrians SelfConviction; or, an evident
                    Demonstration of the avowed Arminianisme, Poperie, and Tyrannie of that Faction,
                    by their owne confessions: with a postscript to the personat Jesuite Lysimachus
                    Nicanor,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Epistle
                    congratvlatorie of Lysimachus Nicanor, of the Societie of Jesu, to the
                    Covenanters in Scotland; wherein is parallelled our sweet harmony and
                    correspondency in divers materiali points of Doctrine and Practice. <hi
                    rend="italic">Anno Domini</hi> 1640, 4to.— The author or this Epistle was John
                    Corbet, a Scotish clergyman, who having taken refuge in Ireland, was “hewed in
                    pieces in the very armes of Ins poore wife. (Baillie s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historical Vindication,</hi> p. 2.) Some notices of him mav be found in
                    Burnet’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Bishop Bedell,</hi> p. 140. Lond. 1685, 8vo.
                    ^ <hi rend="smallcaps">√ j</hi></p></note> a prime Canterburian. <hi
                    rend="italic">Written in March, and printed in Aprile,</hi> 1640,4to.—This book
                    was speedily reprinted at Amsterdam; and a “third edition, augmented by the
                    author, with a large Supplement,” was <hi rend="italic">printed for Nathaniel
                    Better,</hi> 1641, 4to. The additional part was likewise published in a separate
                    form, under the title of “A large Supplement of the Canter-bvrian
                    Self-Conviction.” <hi rend="italic">Imprinted</hi> 1641, 4to. A fourth edition
                    of the work bears the title of “The Life of William now Lord Arch-bishop of
                    Canterbvry, examined.” Lond. 1643, 4to.</p>
                <p>2. A Parallel or briefe Comparison of the Liturgie with the Masse-Book, the
                    Breviarie, the Ceremoniall, and other Romish Ritualls.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Some animadversions on this work are
                    subjoined to L. Womock’s <hi rend="italic">Beaten Ogle for the Lamps of the
                    Sanctvarie.</hi> Lond. 1641, 4to.</p></note> Lond. 1641, 4to. Reprinted in
                    1661.</p>
                <p>3. Queries anent the Service-Book.</p>
                <p>4. An Antidote against Arminianism.</p>
                <p>5. The Unlawfulnesse and Danger of limited Episcopacie; whereunto is subjoined a
                    short Reply to the modest Advertiser and calm Examinator of that Treatise: as
                    also the Question of Episcopacie discussed from Scripture and the Fathers. Lond.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">1(j41,</hi> 4to.</p>
                <p>6. Satan the Leader in chief to all who resist the Reparation of Sion; as it was
                    cleared in a Sermon to the Honourable House of Commons at their late solemn
                    Fast, Fehr. 28, 1643. Lond. 1643, 4to.</p>
                <p>7. Errours and Induration are the great Sins and the great Judgements of the
                    Time: preached in a Sermon before the Right Honourable House of Peers, in the
                    Abbey-Church at Westminster, July 30, 1645, the day of the moncthly Fast. Lond.
                    1645, 4to.</p>
                <p>8. A Dissvasive from the Errours of the Time: wherein the Tenets of the
                    principall Sects, especially of the Independents, are drawn together in one Map,
                    &amp;c. Lond. 1645, 4to. Lond. 1646, 4to.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193193072" xml:id="kp-eb0704-3072-0289"/>
                <p>9. An Historical Vindication of the Government of the Church of Scotland, from
                    the manifold base Calumnies which the most malignant of the Prélats did invent
                    of old, and now lately have been published with great industry in two pamphlets
                    at London; the one intituled <hi rend="italic">Issachars Burden,</hi> &amp;c.,
                    written and published at Oxford by John Maxwell,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>John Maxwell, D.D., was the son of Maxwell of
                    Cavons in Nithsdale; and after having been beneficed at Murthlack and in
                    Edinburgh, he became bishop of Ross in the year 1633. He was deposed and
                    excommunicated by the assembly of 1638, and took refuge in England. In 1640 he
                    was appointed bishop of Killala in Ireland; but the rebellion speedily ensued,
                    and after being stript flaked and severely wounded, he was again compelled to
                    seek a place of refuge in England, and for some time he attended the king at
                    )xford. In 1645 he was appointed archbishop of Tuam, and died on the 14th of
                    February 1646. The work which Baillie answered <hi rend="superscript"> ls</hi>
                    entitled “The Burthen of Issachar: or, the Tyranical Power and Practises of the
                    Presbyteriall Government in Scotland.” <hi rend="italic">Pruned</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> w</hi><hi rend="italic">the yeare</hi> 1646, 4to. Dr
                    Maxwell is the author of another work, which was answered by Rutherford: “<hi
                    rend="italic">Sacrosancta Regum Majesti</hi> or, the sacred and royall
                    Prerogative of Christian Kings.” Oxford, 1644, 4to∙ According to Bishop Burnet,
                    he was “a man o eminent parts, and an excellent preacher; but by his forwardness
                    and aspiring he was the unhappy instrument of that which fought on all the
                    disorders in Scotland.” <hi rend="italic">{Life of Bishop Bedell,</hi> p. 141.)
                    He is mentioned and described in the Life, Diary and Correspondence of Sir
                    William Dugdale, p. 437. Lond. 1827, 4to.</p></note> a Scottish Prelate, &amp;c.
                    Lond. 1646, 4to.</p>
                <p>10. Anabaptism, the trve Fovntaine of Independency, Brownisme, Antinomy,
                    Familisme, &amp;c. in a Second Part of the Disswasive from the Errors of the
                    Time. Lond. 1647, 4to.</p>
                <p>11. A Review of Doctor Bramble, late Bishop of Londonderry, his Faire Warning
                    against the Scotes Disciplin. Delf, 1649, 4to.—This tract was afterwards
                    incorporated, without being reprinted, in a collection entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Three Treatises concerning the Scotish Discipline.</hi> Hagh,
                    1661, 4to. The other two treatises are Bramhall’s Fair Warning and Watson’s
                    Second Fair Warning, in answer to Baillie; and the volume likewise includes a
                    virulent epistle by another Scotish writer, Dr Creyghton, afterwards bishop of
                    Bath and Wells. Baillie’s Review was reprinted at Edinburgh; and having been
                    translated into Dutch, it was published at Utrecht under the inspection of
                    Gisbert Voet.</p>
                <p>12. A Scotch Antidote against the English Infection of Arminianism. Lond. 1652,
                    12mo.</p>
                <p>13. Appendix practica ad Joannis Buxtorfii Epitomen Grammaticae Hebraeae. Edinb.
                    1653, 8vo.</p>
                <p>14. Catechesis elenctica Errorum qui hodie vexant Ecclesiam; ex nudis sacrae
                    Scripturae Testimoniis, in brevibus et claris Quaestionibus ac Responsionibus
                    proposita, in gratiam studiosae Juventutis Academiae Glasguensis. Lond. 1654,
                    12mo.</p>
                <p>15. A Reply to the Modest Inquirer.—Perhaps relating to the dispute between the
                    Resolutioners and Protesters. This tract, together with numbers 3 and 4, we have
                    not seen. They are all mentioned in Baillie’s papers, in the possession of Dr
                    M‘Crie.</p>
                <p>16. The Disswasive from the Errors of the Time, vindicated from the Exceptions of
                    Mr Cotton and Mr Tombes. Lond. 1655, 4to.</p>
                <p>17. Operis Historici et Chronologici libri duo; in quibus Historia sacra et
                    profana compendiose deducitur ex ipsis Fontibus, a Creatione Mundi ad
                    Constantinum Magnum. Amstelodami, 1663, fol.—Some copies have the addition of an
                    index, with a new title bearing the date of 1668.</p>
                <p>18. Letters and Journals; containing an impartial Account of public Transactions,
                    civil, ecclesiastical, and military, in England and Scotland, from the beginning
                    of the Civil Wars in 1637, to the year 1662; a period, perhaps, the most
                    remarkable and interes,ting in the British History; now first published from the
                    manuscripts of Robert Baillie, D. D. Principal of the University of Glasgow.
                    Edinb. 1775, 2 vols. 8vo.—Some copies, bearing the same date, have a different
                    title, which states that the Letters were “carefully transcribed by Robert
                    Aiken.” Many of them are addressed to the author’s cousin-german William Spang,
                    minister of the Scotish staple at Campvere, and afterwards of the English
                    congregation at Middelburg in Zecland. It was chiefly from the materials thus
                    communicated that Spang prepared two different publications. The first is
                    entitled “Brevis et fidelis Narratio Motuum in Regno et Ecclesia Scoticana,
                    excerpta ex scriptis Utriusque partis scitu dignissimis, per Irenaeum
                    Philalethen.” Dantisci, 1640, 4to. This -work only prosecutes the narrative till
                    the first of October 1638; but he speedily reprinted it, and added a
                    continuation to the year 1640. “Rerum nuper . ìņ Regno Scotiae gestarum
                    Historia.” Dantisci, 1641, 8vo.-r-These letters were published from a copy
                    belonging to Matthew Baillic of Carnbroe, Esq.; and the editor likewise
                    consulted the copy preserved among the archives of the church of Scotland. The
                    copy which belonged to the author’s family is now in the possession of Dr
                    M‘Crie, to whose kindness we are indebted for the use of it, as well as for
                    several biographical notices. This manuscript consists of four volumes in folio,
                    and is in a tolerably good state of preservation. Baillie’s Letters and Journals
                    arc of great historical value; and as the editor, besides omitting many detached
                    passages, -has suppressed a considerable number of entire letters, we beg
                    leave-to suggest, and even to urge, the expediency of a new and complete
                    edition.</p>
                <p>Baillie had apparently some concern in the publication of a posthumous work of
                    hl’s learned predecessor Robert Boyd, principal of the university of Glasgow:
                    <hi rend="italic">'In Epistolam Pauli Apostoli ad Ephesios Proelectiones supra
                    cc.</hi> Lond. 1652, fol. Prefixed is a life of the author by Rivet, with whom
                    Boyd had been intimately acquainted; but the preface is subscribed with the
                    initials R. B. A biographical notice, bearing the same signature, is prefixed to
                    the work of his father-in-laŵ Dr Strang, <hi rend="italic">De Interpretatione et
                    Perfectione Scripturae.</hi> Roter. 1663, 4to∕ (x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
