<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-4619-0408-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARROW, Isaac</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 408</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cn8b">Grangerism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:852538">Charters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193194619" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARROW, <hi rend="smallcaps">Isaac</hi></label>, an eminent
                    mathematician and divine, was the son of Mr Thomas Barrow, a linen-draper in
                    London, where he was born in 1630. He was at first placed for two or three years
                    at the Charter-house School. There, however, his conduct gave but little hopes
                    of success in the profession of scholar; for he was extremely fond of fighting,
                    and of promoting pugnacity among his school-fellows. But being removed from this
                    establishment, his disposition took a happier turn; and having soon made
                    considerable progress in learning, he was admitted a pensioner of Peter-house,
                    in Cambridge, where he applied himself with great diligence to the study of
                    literature and science, especially of natural philosophy. He afterwards turned
                    his thoughts to the profession of physic, and made some progress in anatomy,
                    botany, and chemistry; after which he studied chronology, geometry, and
                    astronomy. He then travelled into France and Italy, and in a voyage from Leghorn
                    to Smyrna gave proofs of great personal bravery; for the ship having been
                    attacked by an Algerine pirate, Mr Barrow remained upon deck, and fought with
                    the utmost intrepidity, until the pirate, unprepared for the stout resistance
                    made by the ship, sheered off and left her to pursue her voyage unmolested.</p>
                <p>At Smyrna he met with a most kind reception from Mr Bretton, the English consul,
                    upon whose death he afterwards wrote a Latin elegy. From this place he proceeded
                    to Constantinople, where he received similar civilities from Sir Thomas Bendish,
                    the English ambassador, and Sir Jonathan Dawes, with whom he afterwards
                    contracted an intimate friendship. While at Constantinople he read and studied
                    the works of Chrysostom, once bishop of that see, whom he preferred to all the
                    other fathers. He resided· in Turkey somewhat more than a year, after which he
                    proceeded to Venice, and thence returned home through Germany and Holland in
                    1659. Immediately on his return he received episcopal ordination from Bishop
                    Brownrig? and in 1660 he was appointed to the Greek professorship at Cambridge.
                    When he entered upon this office, he intended to have prelected upon the
                    tragedies of Sophocles; but he altered his intention, and made choice of
                    Aristotle s rhetoric. His lectures on this subject, however, having been lent to
                    a friend who never returned them, are irrecoverably lost. In July 1662 he was
                    elected professor of geometry in Gresham College, on the recommendation of <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193194632" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4632-0409"/> J)r Wilkins,
                    master of Trinity College, and afterwards bishop of Chester; and in May 1663 he
                    was chosen a fellow of the Royal Society, at the first election made by the
                    council after obtaining their charter. The same year the executors of Mr Lucas,
                    who, according to the will of that individual, had founded a mathematical chair
                    at Cambridge, fixed upon Mr Barrow as the first professor; and although his two
                    professorships were not inconsistent with each other, he chose to resign that of
                    Gresham College, which he did on the 20th May 1664. In 1669 he resigned his
                    mathematical chair to his illustrious friend Mr Isaac Newton, having now
                    determined to renounce the study of mathematics for that of divinity. Upon
                    quitting his professorship, Mr Barrow was only a fellow of Trinity College; but
                    his uncle gave him a small sinecure in Wales, and Dr Seth Ward, bishop of
                    Salisbury, conferred upon him a prebend in that church. In the year 1670 he was
                    created doctor in divinity by mandate; and, upon the promotion of Dr Pearson,
                    master of Trinity College, to the see of Chester, he was appointed to succeed
                    him by the king’s patent, bearing date the 13th February 1672. When the king
                    advanced Barrow to this dignity, he was pleased to say, “he had given it to the
                    best scholar in England.” His majesty did not speak from report, but from his
                    own knowledge; for the doctor being then his chaplain, his majesty frequently
                    conversed with him, and in his humorous way used to call him an “unfair
                    preacher,” as he exhausted every subject he discussed, and left no room for
                    others to comeafter him. In 1675 Dr Barrow was chosen vice-chancellor of the
                    university. His works are very numerous, and such as do honour to the science
                    and literature of the English nation. They are, 1. Euclid’s Elements; 2.
                    Euclid’s Data; 3. Optical Lectures, read in the public school of Cambridge; 4.
                    Thirteen Geometrical Lectures; 5. The Works of Archimedes, the four Books of
                    Apollonius’s Conic Sections, and Theodosius’s Spherics explained in a new
                    Method; 6. A Lecture, in which Archimedes’s Theorems of the Sphere and Cylinder
                    are investigated and briefly demonstrated; 7. Mathematical Lectures, read in the
                    public schools of the university of Cambridge. The above were all written in
                    Latin; and as to his English works, they have been collected, and printed
                    together in four volumes folio. “The name of Dr Barrow,” says Mr Granger, “will
                    ever be illustrious for a strength of mind and a compass of knowledge that did
                    honour to his country. He was unrivalled in mathematical learning, and
                    especially in the sublime geometry; in which he has been excelled only by one
                    man, and that man was his pupil, the great Sir Isaac Newton. The same genius
                    that seemed to be born only to bring hidden truths to light, to rise to the
                    heights or descend to the depths of science, would sometimes amuse itself in the
                    flowery paths of poetry; and he composed verses both in Greek and Latin. He at
                    length gave himself up entirely to divinity; and particularly to the most useful
                    part of it, that which has a tendency to make men wiser and better. He has, in
                    his excellent sermons on the creed, solved every difficulty and removed every
                    obstacle that opposed itself to our faith, and made divine revelation as clear
                    as the demonstrations m his own Euclid. In his sermons he knew not how to leave
                    off writing till he had exhausted his subject; and his admirable discourse on
                    the duty and reward of bounty to the poor took him up three hours and a half in
                    preaching.” This excellent person, who was a bright example of Christian virtue,
                    as well as a prodigy of learning, died on the 4th of May 1677, in the
                    forty-seventh year <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> his age; and was interred in
                    Westminster Abbey, where <hi rend="superscript"> a rn</hi> ° <hi
                    rend="superscript"> n</hi> ument, surmounted with his bust, was soon after
                    erected, by the contributions of his friends.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">&gt;arrow,</hi> a river of Ireland, which rises in Queen’s
                    County, and being joined by the Nore and the Suìr, falls into the sea at
                    λVaterford Bay.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
