<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-9221-0762-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOMBAY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 762</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1017057">Merchants</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh7s">Arminianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80q31">Arminians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193199221" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOMBAY</label>. This island, which is the seat of government
                    for the western part of India, is situated in lat. 18. 56. N. and long. 72. 56.
                    E. Its length from north to south is six and a half miles, and its breadth, near
                    the fort, is about a mile. It is separated from the mainland by an arm of the
                    sea, and it forms, in conjunction with the adjacent islands of Colabah,
                    Salsette, Butcher’s Island, Elephants, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193199234"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-9234-0763"/>and Caranjah, a large, commodious, and
                    well-sheltered harbour. The north side of the harbour is partly formed by the
                    island of Colabah, which is separated from Bombay by a small creek, fordable at
                    low water, and is about two and a half miles long. Near its southern extremity
                    stands the light-house, a building of a circular form, rising from the sea to
                    the height of 150 feet, and showing its light at the distance of twenty-one
                    miles. The island of Salsette, which is about twenty miles long and fifteen
                    broad, is separated from Bombay by a narrow arm of the sea. Over this strait a
                    causeway was constructed in 1805, which, by improving the communication with the
                    mainland, is of infinite service to the surrounding country, with the produce of
                    which Bombay is supplied; but it is said to have had a prejudicial effect on the
                    harbour. Butcher’s Island is nearly opposite to Bombay Castle, at the distance
                    of three miles; and about two miles from this, and still fronting the fort, is
                    the inconsiderable but celebrated island of Elephanta. The two small islands of
                    Henery and Kenery lie at the entrance of the harbour.</p>
                <p>The town of Bombay is nearly a mile in length, from the Apollo Gate to that of
                    the Bazar, and about a quarter of a mile broad in the widest part, from the
                    custom-house across the Green to Church Gate, which is nearly in the centre
                    between the Apollo and the Bazar Gates. There are likewise two gates towards the
                    sea, having commodious wharfs and cranes built out from each, with a
                    landing-place for passengers. Between these gates is Bombay Castle, a regular
                    quadrangle, built of hard and durable stone, and having the advantage, in one of
                    the bastions, of a large reservoir of water. The fortifications are numerous,
                    and they have been improved in proportion as the place has risen into greater
                    importance from its increasing trade. They have lately received a considerable
                    accession of strength from Dungance Hill, which commanded the town, having been
                    included within the fort; and towards the sea they are extremely strong, the
                    harbour being completely commanded by ranges of batteries placed one above
                    another. But on the land side its means of resistance are not so formidable; nor
                    is this of much moment, as an enemy, once landed, would find no difficulty in
                    possessing himself of the place. A bombardment would in a few hours lay the town
                    in ashes; and were the houses, which are lofty and made of combustible
                    materials, once on fire, the troops could no longer preserve their station on
                    the ramparts. Indeed it is probable that the destruction of the magazines would
                    be the consequence of the conflagration of the adjacent buildings.</p>
                <p>In the centre of the town is a large open space called the Green, around which
                    are many large, well-built, and handsome houses. Here is also the church, which
                    has an extremely neat and light appearance; and on the left of the Church Gate
                    is the government-house, which is a showy edifice, but liable to the
                    inconvenience of having the largest apartments in both floors a passage-room to
                    the others. On the right of the Church Gate is the Bazar, which is crowded and
                    populous. Here the native merchants reside; and at the entrance to the street
                    stands the theatre, which is a handsome building. In the year 1803 this part of
                    the town was greatly injured by a destructive fire, which destroyed nearly three
                    fourths of the Bazar, together with the barracks, custom-house, and many other
                    public buildings, besides property of immense value belonging to native
                    merchants. The flames spread with such rapidity that the magazine was
                    endangered; and, in order to preserve the town from total destruction, many
                    houses in the neighbourhood of the castle were battered down with artillery.
                    Since this period the town has been rebuilt on an improved plan, at the expense
                    of the company.</p>
                <p>Bombay is the only principal settlement in India where the rise of the tides is
                    sufficient to admit the construction of docks on a great scale. The highest
                    spring tides rise to the height of seventeen feet, and the height of the
                    ordinary tides is fourteen feet. In consequence of these natural advantages, the
                    dry dock of Bombay has scarcely its equal for size and convenience; having three
                    divisions, with a pair of strong gates to each, so that it is capable of
                    receiving three ships of the line at a time. Near this dock is a convenient
                    place to heave down several ships at once; and this operation is well executed,
                    and with great expedition, by the Persees, who are generally accounted excellent
                    ship-carpenters. Here is a rope-walk, equal to any in England, with the single
                    exception of the king’s yard at Portsmouth, where cables and all sorts of lesser
                    cordage are manufactured. It has also a covering to protect the workmen from the
                    heat or inclemency of the weather. The dock-yard is large and well contrived,
                    having ample supplies of naval stores deposited in the warehouses, together with
                    large quantities of timber, for repairing and building ships, and forges for all
                    kinds of smith’s work. With these advantages, Bombay claims a distinguished rank
                    as a naval arsenal; while, within these few years, many merchant ships of from
                    600 to 1300 tons, partly for the country trade and partly for the service of the
                    company, have been built in its docks, and, in beauty of construction, good
                    workmanship, and durability, are superior to any other class of merchant ships
                    in the world. Bombay is the only port in any of the British possessions out of
                    Europe at which a ship of the line was ever built; and it deserves to be
                    recorded that the Minden, a seventy-four gun ship, was launched from its
                    dockyards in 1810. It has also added several frigates to the British navy. All
                    these vessels are built of Malabar teak, which is esteemed superior to any in
                    India. The teak forests, from which supplies of wood are derived, he along the
                    western side of the Ghaut Mountains, and other con-tinguous ridges to the north
                    and east of Basseen; the numerous streams which descend from them affording
                    water-carriage for the timber. The docks belong to the company, and the king’s
                    ships pay a monthly rent for repairs. They are entirely occupied by Persees, who
                    are esteemed remarkably skilful and assiduous. Bombay, thus possessing, in the
                    skill of its workmen, the excellence of its timber, and the superiority of its
                    docks, all that is necessary for a naval arsenal, may be considered as a station
                    of the first importance to the British power in India.</p>
                <p>From its position, Bombay commands an extensive commerce with the countries
                    situated in the Persian and Arabian Gulfs, and with the western coast of India.
                    It also carries on a valuable trade with the eastern parts of India, the islands
                    in the-Eastern Ocean, and with China. Of the trade with China the staple
                    commodity is cottonwool. The other articles consist of sandal-wood and pepper,
                    the produce of Malabar and other adjacent countries; gums, drugs, and pearls,
                    from Arabia, Abyssinia, and Persia; elephants’ teeth, cornelians, and other
                    produce of Cambay; sharks’ fins, birds’ nests, and other articles from the
                    Maldive and Laccadive islands. The ships generally arrive at Canton in June or
                    July, and he there until December or January. In 1808 the quantity of cotton
                    brought to Bombay for re-exportation amounted to 85,000 bales, of 375 pounds
                    each, which were partly procured from the country on the Nerbuddah, and from
                    Gujerat and Cutch. The quantity, however, is not usually so large; and in this
                    trade Bombay has been lately rivalled by the competition of the merchants of
                    Bengal and Madras, who, having adopted a different method of cleaning their
                    cotton, have sold it to greater advantage in the market<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193199247" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9247-0764"/> of Canton than the merchants
                    of Bombay; and unless the latter adopt the same method of preparing their
                    commodity, it is probable that this lucrative branch of trade will decline. It
                    is about fifty or sixty years since the cotton trade from Bombay to China was
                    first established. At that period a great scarcity of provisions having occurred
                    in China, the cultivation of cotton was restricted by an edict of the
                    government, and grain was ordered to be raised in its stead. Hence a great
                    demand arose in the Chinese market for cotton, which has continued ever since to
                    increase. But the general inattention of the Bombay merchants to the quality of
                    the commodity, and the many frauds which have been practised upon the Chinese,
                    have induced them to resume the cultivation of cotton, for the purpose of having
                    within themselves the necessary supply of this useful article. On this account
                    the demand from China may be rather considered as precarious. In stowing and
                    packing the cotton, great dexterity is displayed. It is pressed down by means of
                    a screw, worked by a capstan, to each bar of which there arc thirty men,
                    amounting on the whole to 240 to each screw. Hemp is packed in the same manner,
                    but it requires to be carefully laid in the press, its fibres being liable to be
                    broken if they are bent.</p>
                <p>Bombay carries on a considerable trade with Europe, and with different parts of
                    America. The imports from Europe are principally articles for the use of the
                    natives and Europeans, consisting mostly of the finer articles of European
                    manufacture, the produce of other countries for re-exportation, piece goods, and
                    treasure.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"> The following is a Table of the
                            estimated Value in Rupees<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                            type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">A lack is 100,000, which, at 2ş.
                            3d. per rupee, is L.11,250 sterling. When any sum amounts to more than
                            100,000 rupees, the usual mode of numeration is to·divide the lacks from
                            the remaining part of the sum, thus, 15,18,400, which is 15 lacks,
                            eighteen thousand tour hundred rupees.</hi></p></note> of the Exports
                            and Imports to and from other places: </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Imports. S </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ucca Rupees. </cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> Exports. Sicca Rupees. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>From Madeira</p><p>From Brazils (of
                            which there was treasure to the amount of 13,57,650)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>70,360</p><p>15,18,400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Brasils </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 43,334 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From the Isle of France, of which
                            cloves composed two thirds) </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 5,34,183 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To the Isle of France </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,63,403 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From China, consisting of articles for
                            the use of the natives and Europeans, manufactures, piece-goods,
                            treasure </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 40,64,654 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To China </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 37,17,522 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Manilla, half of which consisted
                            of sugar </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,29,350 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Manilla </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>78,837</p><p>6,458</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Pegu </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Pegu </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Prince of Wales Island, and the
                            islands to the eastward </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 4,99,886 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Prince of Wales Island </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 7,54,560 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>From Bengal, consisting of raw silk,
                            piecegoods, sugar, groceries, grain</p><p>From the coast of
                            Coromandel</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 27,70,051 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Bengal </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 4,25,615 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 80,771 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To coast of Coromandel </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1,87,464 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Ceylon </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1,14,331 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Ceylon </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 67,048 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Malabar and Canara, grain,
                            manufactures, piece-goods </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 30,01,139 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Malabar </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 17,66,193 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Goa and the Concan, grain,
                            manufactures, piece-goods </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 20,40,364 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Goa and Concan, consisting generally
                            of the produce imported from other countries </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 51,29,222 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Bassein and adjacent villages </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3,63,682 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Tò Bassein, &amp;c </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,96,179 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Cutch and Sinde </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3,26,668 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Cutch and Sinde, consisting chiefly
                            of Chinese goods </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 11,11,227 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Persian Gulf, grain, manufactures,
                            piecegoods, treasure, horses </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 21,40,740 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To the Persian Gulf, merchandise
                            imported from other countries </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 19,48,205 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Arabian Gulf, merchandise,
                            treasure, horses </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 9,44,292 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To the Arabian Gulf, merchandise and
                            European goods </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3,64,731 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From east coast of Africa </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1,37,386 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To the East coast of Africa </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 46,449 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Surat, grain, manufactures,
                            piece-goods, treasure </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 10,30,336 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Surat, manufactures of other
                            countries, treasure </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 19,07,032 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From Gujcrat, &amp;c. piece-goods,
                            treasure </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 51,11,636 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> To Gujerat </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 39,53,572 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> The whole value of the imports for
                            1811-12 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">: amounted </cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> The whole value of exports, for
                            1811-12, </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> to </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 169,70,626 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Merchandise </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 145,50,642 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Treasure </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 37,37,084 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Treasure </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 30,27,963 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Horses </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,39,875 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Horses </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,29,473 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Rupees </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 209,47,585 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Rupees </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 178,08,100 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> In pounds sterling these imports amount
                            to...L.2,356,603 </cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> In pounds sterling these exports amount
                            to...L.2,003,411 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Bombay is estimated to contain 220,000 inhabitants, of whom nearly three fourths
                    are Hindoos. The other fourth is composed of persons from almost every Asiatic
                    nation. The number of Persees is estimated at 8000; there is nearly the same
                    number of Mahometans, and there are 4000 Jews. The Portuguese are also to be
                    found in considerable numbers. The Persees rank next to the Europeans, and carry
                    on, many of them, extensive commercial transactions. They are the brokers and
                    factors of Europeans, and have a concern in most of the foreign speculations of
                    European mercantile houses. They are a rich, industrious, and active body of
                    men, who contribute greatly to the prosperity of the settlement, and are treated
                    by the government with much favour and ιn-dulgence<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193199260" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9260-0765"/>. For the protection which
                    they enjoy they are exceedingly grateful, and openly express their conviction
                    that they could not obtain the same advantages in any other part of the East.
                    They are the descendants of the ancient Persians who fled from the persecution
                    of Shah Abbas in the sixteenth century, when he expelled the worshippers of fire
                    from his dominions, and compelled them to seek an asylum in other countries. The
                    Persees at Bombay appear to be quite domesticated in their new residence, in
                    which they have purchased valuable properties. Besides the Persees,-many
                    considerable Portuguese, American, and Hindoo merchants reside at Bombay, who
                    have acquired valuable property, and have the reputation of great integrity.
                    There are likewise some Bonah merchants, or Mahommedan Jews, who carry on a
                    great trade with Gujerat, and other places to the northward. All these different
                    classes of inhabitants live happily together, and enjoy great prosperity under
                    the mild and equitable rule of the British government.</p>
                <p>The company’s naval force at Bombay in 1827 consisted of twenty fighting vessels,
                    besides armed boats, adviceboats, and other craft; and to man this navy a
                    regular establishment of officers and seamen is maintained. The western coast of
                    India, from the shores of the Persian Gulf to Goa, is infested by swarms of
                    pirates, who are distinguished, particularly those in the northerly tracts, by
                    courage, address, and habits of extreme ferocity. It is to protect the country
                    trade against the depredations of these banditti, who have haunted those seas
                    since the time of Alexander the Great, that the company finds it necessary to
                    maintain this naval force. Out of 104 marine covenanted servants of the company,
                    Bombay employs ninety-three.</p>
                <p>The annual expense of the Bombay army is, for king’s troops L.161,317; native
                    troops L.1,050,646; local corps, garrisons, &amp;c. L.827,535; total
                    L.2,039,498. In 1827 the civil servants of the company on the Bombay
                    establishment amounted to 128; the judicial, ecclesiastical, &amp;c. to 109; and
                    their pay and allowances to L.376,995, being an increase since 1817 of
                    L.190,796.</p>
                <p>The island of Bombay scarcely produces any articles of food; these have to be
                    imported from various parts of India, and are consequently much dearer here than
                    in the other presidencies. Considerable quantities of rice and other grain are
                    annually imported. The prices are continually fluctuating, from the state of the
                    market, which is under the superintendence of the police. Potatoes, which,
                    though recently introduced, are now produced in the greatest abundance in this
                    quarter of India, are brought to the Bombay market from Gujerat, which also
                    supplies cheese, but of a kind hard and ill flavoured. The only vegetable Bombay
                    is celebrated for is the onion, which is esteemed excellent. All other
                    vegetables are scarce and dear.</p>
                <p>The bazar mutton, when well fed, is thought to be as good as the English. Kid is
                    always good; and there is abundance of poultry, which is not good, however,
                    unless when fed on purpose. The fish are excellent, but those of a large size
                    are not plentiful. The prawns are uncommonly fine; and though the island is too
                    small to furnish great abundance of game, the red-legged partridge is not
                    uncommon, and snipes are sometimes seen. The frogs here are large, and are
                    sometimes eaten by the Chinese and Portuguese.</p>
                <p>On the 1st January 1827 a supreme court of judicature was established in Bombay,
                    by a regulation of the governorin council. It consists of a chief justice, and
                    of three or more puisne judges, appointed by the king; and its jurisdiction
                    extends over all the territories subordinate to the presidency of Bombay. In
                    1828 a collision of jurisdiction took place between this court and the
                    government of the presidency. One of the judges, Mr Justice Grant, having issued
                    a writ of <hi rend="italic">habeas corpus</hi> to produce in court the body of a
                    native of high rank, confined against his will by an uncle, the governor and
                    council interfered, and opposed the execution of the writ, on the ground that
                    the court had no jurisdiction except over British subjects or the servants of
                    the company; and an appeal having been made to the privy council, it was decided
                    that the supreme court had no authority to issue a writ of <hi rend="italic"
                    >habeas corpus,</hi> except in the case of persons either residing within the
                    island of Bombay, in which it has a general jurisdiction, or of those who are
                    personally subject to its civil and criminal jurisdiction.</p>
                <p>The same passion for country-houses prevails at Bombay as at Madras. These houses
                    are generally comfortable and elegant; and if they have not the splendid Grecian
                    porticos of Calcutta and Madras, they seem to be better adapted to the climate,
                    and have the advantage of the most beautiful and picturesque views; the island
                    of Bombay being broken by several beautiful hills, either covered with cocoa-nut
                    tree groves, or villas of the inhabitants. The only English church in Bombay is
                    in the fort. There are numbers of Portuguese and Arminian churches both within
                    and without the walls, and there are also three or four synagogues, with many
                    temples and mosques.</p>
                <p>Bombay, from its situation, might be supposed to be healthy; but this is said not
                    to be the case, the liver complaint being more fatal and frequent here than in
                    any part of India. A land breeze sets in every evening, which is described as
                    being peculiarly noxious, and is frequently followed by fever, and by loss of
                    the use of the limbs. This breeze is stated by Lord Valentia to have been
                    chillingly cold at the time he visited Bombay; but he attributes its deleterious
                    effects not merely to this cause, but to the noxious vapours with which it is
                    tainted in its passage over the rank vegetation that springs up in the marshy
                    parts of the bay immediately after the rains. Moderate living affords the best
                    security for health; the extremes of intemperance and over abstemiousness being
                    equally injurious.</p>
                <p>Bombay was first settled by the Portuguese, to whom it was ceded in 1530; having
                    been before dependent on one of the native chiefs. In 1661 it was ceded by the
                    crown of Portugal in full sovereignty to Charles IL, by the treaty of marriage
                    concluded with that power when he espoused the infanta. In order to take
                    advantage of this acquisition, and to make it a profitable dependence on the
                    crown, a fleet was dispatched under the command of the Earl of Marlborough in
                    1662, to receive formal possession of the island and its dependencies. Some
                    doubts arising, however, as to the construction of the treaty, the viceroy
                    refused to surrender the island, on which the Earl of Marlborough returned to
                    Europe, after having left the troops, amounting to 500 men, in the island, where
                    most of them died. In 1664 a treaty was concluded by this nobleman’s successor
                    with the viceroy of Goa, in which the former renounced all pretensions to the
                    dependencies of Bombay, and accepted of the cession of the island alone, which
                    the English accordingly received in 1665, the troops who had survived the
                    ravages of disease only mustering 119 rank and file.</p>
                <p>It was soon discovered that the revenues of the island were not equal to the
                    expense of retaining it, and that the East India Company were much injured by a
                    contraband trade carried on by persons in the king’s service. In consequence of
                    these and other reasons, the sovereignty of the island was, in 1668, transferred
                    to the East India Company. The company’s servants made every exertion to place
                    this new acquisition in a respectable state <pb break="no" facs="nls:193199273"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-9273-0766"/>of defence, and to encourage settlers; and, in
                    1673, the island of Bombay, from being almost a desert, had become the centre of
                    the company’s trade, protected by fortifications with 100 pieces of cannon
                    mounted, and a suitable garrison. In 1676 letters-patent were obtained from the
                    king to establish a mint at Bombay, at which they were empowered to coin rupees
                    and other smaller pieces. At this period Bombay continued to be of very little
                    importance, which partly proceeded from the vigorous government of Aurengzebe,
                    and the rising power of the Mahrattas. These two powers contended for the
                    possession of the island of Kenery, which was seized on by the troops of both,
                    the Bombay government not daring to oppose either party, but trembling for its
                    own safety amid these formidable contentions. Bombay was soon afterwards, in
                    consequence of the capture of Bantam by the Dutch, constituted an independent
                    English settlement, and the seat of the English power in the East Indies.</p>
                <p>In 1678, the company, finding it necessary to retrench the expenses of the
                    establishment, proceeded to reduce the salaries and to lower the rank of their
                    military officers, which produced general discontent, and finally, a serious
                    revolt, which threatened the most alarming consequences to the company’s
                    affairs. This insurrection was headed by Captain Richard Reigwin, commander of
                    the garrison, who seized the governor, and such members of the council as still
                    adhered to him; and having assembled the troops and militia, annulled the
                    authority of the company by proclamation, requiring the inhabitants to renounce
                    obedience to their authority, and to take the oaths of allegiance to the king.
                    The whole inhabitants and all the troops immediately complied with the terms of
                    this proclamation; and all the exertions of the governor of Surat to persuade
                    the revolters to return to their duty were in vain. The mutiny was at length
                    quelled by the prudence of Sir Thomas Grantham, who arrived from Surat with a
                    commission from the king, and had a conference with Reigwin, in the course of
                    which the latter agreed to deliver up the fort, on condition of receiving a free
                    pardon for himself and his associates.</p>
                <p>Since this period, the settlement of the English East India Company at Bombay has
                    been frequently in a very precarious condition, sometimes from the unhealthiness
                    of the climate, and at other times from the jealousy of the native powers. But,
                    after the power of the company became more firmly rooted in India, it has
                    continued gradually increasing in wealth and consequence, and may now be
                    accounted ’ one of the most important and durable possessions of the British in
                    India.</p>
                <p>The government of Bombay and its dependencies is by law vested in a governor and
                    three counsellors, who are placed under the control of the supreme government of
                    Bengal, and are in all cases to obey such orders as they may receive, provided
                    they have no different instructions in their possession from the court of
                    directors, of which they are bound to send immediate notice to the Bengal
                    government. The court of directors appoint the governor and members of the
                    council, and likewise the commander in chief of the forces, who is not
                    officially a member of the council, but may receive such an appointment from the
                    directors, and in that case he takes precedence of all the other members.</p>
                <p>It is difficult to fix with precision the extent of the territories included
                    within the presidency of Bombay, as some districts belonging to the native
                    powers are intermingled with them. On a general estimate, however, they may be
                    calculated to comprehend 10,000 square miles, and to contain a population
                    exceeding altogether two millions and a half, which maybe supposed to consist of
                    one Mahommedan to fifteen Hindoos. Of the Persees no exact estimate has ever
                    been made. The travelling distance from Bombay to Calcutta is 1300 miles; to
                    Delhi 965; to Hyderabad 480; to Madras 770; to Poonah 98; to Seringapatam 620;
                    and to Surat 177 miles. (See Milburn’s <hi rend="italic">Oriental Commerce;
                    Voyages and Travels of Lord Valentia;</hi> Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">East
                    India Gazetteers</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >BOMB-ketch,</hi> a small vessel built and strengthened with large beams, and
                    mounting mortars only.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
