<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-5438-0471-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BEARD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 471</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vm0g">Beard</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hs7q">Fashion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:829278">Beards</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:921600">Fashion</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1174571">Whiskers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:847566">Caring</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193195438" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BEARD</label>, the hair growing on the chin and adjacent
                    parts of the face, chiefly of adults and males.</p>
                <p>Various have been the ceremonies and customs of nations in regard to the beard.
                    The Tartars, from a religious principle, waged a long and bloody war with the
                    Persians, declaring them infidels, merely because they would not cut their
                    whiskers after the fashion of Tartary; and we find that a considerable branch of
                    the religion of the ancients consisted in the management of their beards. The
                    Greeks wore their beards till the time of Alexander the Great; but that prince
                    ordered the Macedonians to be shaved, lest the beard should afford a handle to
                    their enemies. According to Pliny, the Romans did not begin to shave till the
                    year of Rome 404, when P. Ticinius brought over a colony of barbers from Sicily.
                    Persons of quality <pb break="no" facs="nls:193195451"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-5451-0472"/>had their children shaved for the first time by a
                    person of the same or greater quality, who, by this means, became godfather or
                    adoptive father of the children.</p>
                <p>As to ecclesiastics, the discipline has varied touching the article of beards;
                    sometimes they have been enjoined to wear them, from a notion of there being too
                    much effeminacy in shaving, and that a long beard was more suitable to the
                    ecclesiastical gravity; and sometimes again they have been forbidden to do so,
                    from an idea that pride lurked beneath a venerable beard. The Greek and Roman
                    churches have been long together by the ears about their beards. Since the time
                    of their separation, the Romanists seem to have given more into the practice of
                    shaving, by way of opposition to the Greeks; and have even made some express
                    constitutions <hi rend="italic">de radendis barbis.</hi> The Greeks, on the
                    contrary, espouse very zealously the cause of long beards, and are extremely
                    scandalized at the beardless images of saints in the Roman churches. By the
                    statutes of some monasteries, it appears that the lay-monks were to let their
                    beards grow, and the priests among them to shave; and that the beards of all who
                    were received into the monasteries were blessed with a great deal of ceremony.
                    There are still extant the prayers used in the solemnity of consecrating the
                    beard to God, when an ecclesiastic was shaven.</p>
                <p>Le Comte observes that the Chinese affect long beards extravagantly; but nature
                    has balked them, by only giving them a scanty growth, which, however, they
                    cultivate with infinite care. Chrysostom observes that the kings of Persia had
                    their beards woven or matted together with gold thread; and some of the first
                    kings of France had their beards knotted and buttoned with gold.</p>
                <p>Among the Turks, it is more infamous for any one to have his beard cut off, than
                    among us to be publicly whipt or branded with a hot iron. The Arabs make the
                    preservation of their beards a capital point of religion, because Mahommed never
                    cut his. Hence the razor is never drawn over the grand signior’s face; and the
                    Persians, who clip their beards and shave above the jaw, are reputed downright
                    heretics. The slaves who serve in the seraglio have their beards shaven as a
                    sign of their servitude.</p>
                <p>The most celebrated ancient writers, and several modern ones, have spoken
                    honourably of the fine beards of antiquity. Homer commemorates the white beard
                    of Nestor, and that of old King Priam. Virgil describes that of Mezentius, which
                    was so thick and long as to cover all his breast; and Chrysippus praises the
                    noble beard of Timotheus, a famous player on the flute. Pliny the younger tells
                    us of the white beard of Euphrates, a Syrian philosopher; and he takes pleasure
                    in relating the respect mixed with fear which it inspired the people withal.
                    Plutarch speaks of the long white beard of an old Laconian, who, being asked why
                    he let it grow to such length, replied, “It is that, seeing continually my white
                    beard, I may do nothing unworthy of its whiteness.” Strabo relates that the
                    Indian philosophers called gymnosophists were particularly attentive to have
                    their beards of sufficient length to “captivate” the veneration of the people
                    ;—Diodorus gives a very circumstantial history of the beards of the Indians
                    ;—Juvenal does not forget that of Antilochus the son of Nestor ;— Fenelon, in
                    describing a priest of Apollo in all his magnificence, tells us that he had a
                    white beard down to his girdle -and Persius, convinced that a beard was the
                    symbol of wisdom, thought he could not bestow a greater encomium on Socrates,
                    than by calling him the bearded master, <hi rend="italic">Magistrum
                    barbatum.</hi></p>
                <p>Whilst the Gauls were under the sway of their native sovereigns, none but the
                    nobles and Christian priests were permitted to wear long beards. But the Franks
                    having made themselves masters of Gaul, assumed the same au thority as the
                    Romans; the bond-men were expre <hi rend="subscript"> ss</hi> i <hi
                    rend="subscript"> v</hi> commanded to shave their chins; and this law continued
                    in force until the entire abolishment of servitude in France So, likewise, in
                    the time of the first race of kings, a lon&lt;i∙ beard was the sign of nobility
                    and freedom; and the kings as being the highest nobles in their kingdom,were
                    emulous likewise to have the largest beards. Eginard, secretary to Charlemagne,
                    speaking of the last kings of the first race says they came to the assemblies in
                    the field of Mars in a carriage drawn by oxen, and sat on the throne with their
                    hair dishevelled, and a very long beard, <hi rend="italic">crine profuso, bαrha
                    submissa, solio residerent, et speciem dominantis effingerent.</hi></p>
                <p>To touch any one’s beard, or cut off a bit of it, was among the first French, the
                    most sacred pledgeof protection and confidence. For a long time all letters that
                    came from the sovereign had, for greater sanction, three hairs of his beard in
                    the seal; and there is still in being a charter of 1121, which concludes with
                    the following words: <hi rend="italic">Quod, ut ratum et stabile perseveret in
                    posterum, praesenti scripto sigilli mei robur apposui cum tribus pilis barbae
                    mere.</hi></p>
                <p>Several great men received or adopted the surname of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bearded.</hi> The emperor Constantine is distinguished by the epithet of <hi
                    rend="italic">Pogoniates;—</hi> in the time of the Crusades, we find there was a
                    <hi rend="italic">Geoffrey the Bearded ;—</hi> Baldwin IV. earl of Flanders, was
                    surnamed <hi rend="italic">Handsome Beard;—</hi> and, in the illustrious house
                    of Montmorenci, there was a famous <hi rend="italic">Bouchard,</hi> who took a
                    pride in the surname of <hi rend="italic">Bearded,</hi> and was always the
                    declared enemy of the monks, without doubt because of their being
                    shavelings.</p>
                <p>In the tenth century, we find that King Robert of France, the rival of Charles
                    the Simple, was not more famous for his exploits than for his long white beard,
                    ln order that it might be more conspicuous-to the soldiers when he was in the
                    field, he used to let it hang down outside his cuirass; and this venerable sight
                    encouraged the troops in battle, nay served to rally them when defeated. A
                    celebrated painter in Germany, called John Mayo, had so large a beard that he
                    was nicknamed <hi rend="italic">John the Bearded.</hi> In fact it was so long
                    that he wore it fastened to his girdle; and though he was a very tall man, it
                    hung upon the ground when he stood upright. John took the greatest care of this
                    extraordinary beard, which he would sometimes untie in the presence of the
                    emperor Charles V., who took great pleasure in seeing the'wind make it fly
                    against the faces of the lords of his court. In England, the chancellor Sir
                    Thomas More, one of the greatest men of his time, being on the point of falling
                    a victim to court intrigues, was able, when on the fatal scaffold, to procure
                    respect for his beard, and saved it, by a pleasantry, from the fatal stroke
                    which he could not escape himself. When he had laid his head on the block, he
                    perceived that his beard was likely to be hurt by the axe of the executioner; on
                    which he took it away, observing, “My beard has not been guilty of treason; it
                    would be an injustice to punish it.’</p>
                <p>Every one has admired on medallions and in portraits the beard of the renowned
                    Henry IV. of France, which gave to the countenance of that prince a majestic
                    dignity and openness, and which ought to serve as a model for that of every
                    great king, as the beard of his illustrious minister should for that of every
                    statesman. But~there is little dependence on the stability of the things of this
                    world. By an event equally fatal and unforeseen, the beard, which had arrived at
                    its highest degree of glory, <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> H <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> f <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> sudden lost its
                    favour, and was at length entirely proscribed. The unexpected death of Henry the
                    Great, and the youth of his successor, were the sole causes of this
                    revolution.</p>
                <p>Louis XIII. mounted the throne of his glorious ancestors without a beard. Every
                    one concluded immediately that the courtiers, seeing their young king with a
                    smooth <pb break="no" facs="nls:193195464" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5464-0473"/>chin,
                    would look upon their own as too rough; and the conjecture proved correct. They
                    presently reduced their beards to whiskers, and a small tuft of hair under the
                    nether lip. But the people at first refused to follow this dangerous example.
                    The duke of Sully also persisted in clinging to his beard. This man, great as a
                    general and a minister, was likewise so in his retirement, and had the courage
                    to keep his long beard, nay, to appear with it at the court of Louis XIΠ., when
                    called thither to give his advice in an affair of importance. The young
                    smooth-shaven courtiers laughed outright at the grave look and old-fashioned
                    appearance of the venerable minister; on which the latter, probably jealous of
                    the honour of his beard, observed to the king, “Sir, when your father, of
                    glorious memory, did me the honour to consult me on his great and important
                    affairs, the first thing he did was to send away all the buffoons and
                    stage-dancers of his court.”</p>
                <p>The czar Peter, who had so many claims to the surname of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Great,</hi> seems to have been but little worthy of it in the matter of beards.
                    He had the boldness to impose a tax on the produce of his subjects’ chins. He
                    ordered that the noblemen and gentlemen, tradesmen and artisans, should pay a
                    hundred rubles for the privilege of retaining their beards, and that the lower
                    class of people should pay a copec for the same liberty; and he established
                    clerks at the gates of the different towns to collect these duties. Such a new
                    and singular impost troubled the vast empire of Muscovy. Both religion and
                    manners were thought in imminent danger. Complaints were heard on all sides; and
                    some ill-natured persons even went so far as to write libels against the
                    sovereign. But Peter was inflexible, and shaving began in good earnest; the
                    Russians very generally coming to the conclusion that it was better to cut off
                    their beards than to give serious offence to a man who had the power of cutting
                    off their heads.</p>
                <p>Example, more powerful than authority, produced in Spain what the Czar Peter had
                    not accomplished in Russia without great difficulty. Philip V. ascended the
                    throne with a shaven chin. The courtiers imitated the prince, and the people in
                    turn imitated the courtiers. However, although this revolution was brought about
                    without violence and by degrees, it caused much lamentation and murmuring; the
                    gravity of the Spaniards lost by the change, and they said, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Desde que no hay barba, no hay mas alma;</hi> “since we have lost our beards,
                    we have lost our souls.” In fact, among thoseEuropean nations which have been
                    most curious in beards and whiskers, we must distinguish Spain. This grave
                    romantic people has always regarded the beard as an ornament which ought to be
                    peculiarly prized, and indeed has often made the loss of honour consist in that
                    of their whiskers. Nor have the Portuguese, whose national character is much the
                    same, been behind them in this respect. In the reign of Catherine queen of
                    Portugal, the brave John de Castro had taken the castle of Diu m India.
                    Victorious, but in want of every thing, he found himself obliged to ask the
                    inhabitants of Goa to lend him a thousand pistoles for the maintenance of his
                    fleet; and, as a security for that sum, he sent them one of his whiskers,
                    telling them,—“All the gold in the world cannot equal die value of this natural
                    ornament of my valour; and I deposit it in your hands as a security for the
                    money.” the whole town was penetrated with his heroism, and every one interested
                    himself about this invaluable whisKer: even the women were desirous to give
                    marks of their zeal for so brave a man; several sold their bracelets to increase
                    the sum asked for; and the inhabitants of Goa <hi rend="superscript"> se</hi> nt
                    him immediately both the money and his whisker.</p>
                <p>hi Louis XIII.’ s reign, whiskers attained the highest de-Ş 'β of favour, at the
                    expense of the expiring beards. In</p>
                <p>0∙*e days of gallantry, not yet empoisoned by wit, they became the favourite
                    occupation of lovers. A fine black whisker, elegantly turned up, was a very
                    powerful recommendation to the favour of the fair sex. Whiskers were still in
                    fashion in the beginning of Louis the Fourteenth’s reign; and this king, with
                    all the great men of his time, took a pride in wearing them. They were
                    consequently the ornament of Turenne, Condé, Colbert, Corneille, Molière,
                    &amp;c. It was then no uncommon thing for a favourite lover to have his whiskers
                    turned up, combed, and dressed by his mistress; and hence a man of fashion took
                    care to be always provided with every little necessary article, especially
                    whisker-wax. It was highly flattering to a lady to have it in her power to
                    praise the beauty of her lover’s whiskers, which, far from being disgusting,
                    gave his person an air of vivacity; and several even thought them an incitement
                    to love. But the levity of the French made the whiskers undergo several changes
                    both in form and name; there were <hi rend="italic">Spanish, Turkish,
                    guard-dagger</hi> whiskers, nay even <hi rend="italic">royal</hi> ones, which
                    were the last worn; the smallness of these proclaiming their approaching
                    fall.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Consecration of the</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard</hi>
                    was a ceremony among the Roman youth, who, when they were shaved the first time,
                    kept a day of rejoicing, and were particularly careful to put the hair of their
                    beard into a silver or gold box, and make an offering of it to some god,
                    particularly to Jupiter Capitolinus, as was done by Nero, according to
                    Suetonius.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Kissing the</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard.</hi> The
                    Turkish wives kiss their husbands’ beards, and children their fathers’, as often
                    as they come to salute them. The men kiss one another’s beards reciprocally on
                    both sides, when they salute in the streets or return from a journey.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Fashion of the</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard</hi>
                    has varied in different ages and countries; some cultivating and entertaining
                    one part of it, some another. Thus the Hebrews wear a beard on the chin, but not
                    on the upper lip or cheeks. Moses forbids them to cut off entirely the angle or
                    extremity of their beard; that is, to manage it after the Egyptian fashion,
                    leaving only a little tuft of beard at the extremity of the chin; whereas the
                    Jews to this day suffer a little fillet of hair to grow from the lower end of
                    their ears to their chins, where, as well as on their lower lips, their beards
                    are in a pretty long bunch. The Jews, in time of mourning, neglected to trim
                    their beards or cut off the superfluous growth on the upper lips and cheeks. In
                    time of grief and great affliction they also plucked off the hair of their
                    beards.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Anointing the</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard</hi> with
                    unguents was an ancient practice both among the Jews and Romans, and still, we
                    believe, continues in use among the Turks. One of the principal ceremonies
                    observed among the latter in serious visits, is to throw sweet-scented water on
                    the beard of the visitant, and to perfume it afterwards with aloes-wood.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard</hi><hi rend="italic">of α Comet,</hi> the
                    rays which the comet emits towards that part of the heavens to which its proper
                    motion seems directed; so that the beard of a comet is distinguished from the
                    tail, which is understood of the rays emitted towards that part from which its
                    motion appears to carry it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard</hi><hi rend="italic">of a Horse,</hi> that
                    part underneath the lower mandible on the outside and above the chin, which
                    bears the curb. It is also called the chuck.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Beard</hi><hi rend="italic">of a Muscle,
                    Oyster,</hi> or the like, denotes an assemblage of threads or hairs, by which
                    these animals fasten themselves to stones. The hairs of this beard terminate in
                    a flat spongy substance, which being applied to the surface of a stone, sticks
                    thereto, like the wet leather used by boys.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Beards,</hi> in the history of insects, are two small,
                    oblong, fleshy bodies, placedjust above the trunk, as in gnats, moths, and
                    butterflies.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193195477" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5477-0474"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Bearded</hi><hi rend="italic">Women.</hi> Of these
                    there have been several remarkable instances. In the cabinet of curiosities of
                    Stut-gart in Germany, there is the portrait of a woman called Bartel Graetje,
                    whose chin is covered with a very large beard. Her portrait was painted in 1587,
                    at which time she was only twenty-five years of age. It is said that the duke of
                    Saxony had the portrait taken of a poor Swiss woman, remarkable for her long
                    bushy beard; and those who attended the carnival at Venice in 1726 saw a female
                    dancer astonish the spectators not more by her talents than by her chin covered
                    with a black bushy beard. Charles XII. had in his army a female grenadier, who
                    had both the beard and courage of a man. She was taken prisoner at the battle of
                    Pultowa, and carried to Petersburg, where she was presented to the Czar in 1724;
                    her beard measured a yard and a half. A woman was once seen at Paris, who had
                    not only a bushy beard on her face, but her body likewise covered all over with
                    hair· Amongst a number of examples of this nature, that of Margaret, the
                    governess of the Netherlands, is very remarkable. She had a very long stiff
                    beard, which she prided herself in; and being persuaded that it contributed to
                    give her an air of majesty, she took care not to lose a single hair of it. The
                    Lombard women, it iš said, when they went to war, made themselves beards with
                    the hair of their heads, which they ingeniously arranged on their cheeks, in
                    order that the enemy, deceived by the likeness, might take them for men; and
                    Suidas informs us, that in a similar case the Athenian women did as much.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
