<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-4216-0377-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARCLAY, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 377</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p161">Surgeons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1144248">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878236">Cooperativeness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878116">Cooperation</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193194216" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BARCLAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, M.D. a
                    distinguished anatomist, was born in Perthshire in 1760, and died at Edinburgh
                    in 1826. After the usual routine of parochial education, Dr <hi rend="subscript"
                    > ι</hi> Barclay was entered as a student at the United College of St Andrews,
                    where he distinguished himself as a classical scholar. He subsequently studied
                    divinity in the same university, and was licensed as a preacher by the
                    presbytery of Dunkeld. Having repaired to Edinburgh in 1789, as tutor to the
                    family of Sir James Campbell of Aberuchill, Dr Barclay began to give his
                    attention to the study of medicine, and particularly to anatomy, both human and
                    comparative. He became assistant to the late Mr John Bell, and took the degree
                    of doctor of physic in the university of Edinburgh in 1796, after having
                    defended an inaugural dissertation, <hi rend="italic">De Anima, seu Principio
                    Vitali.</hi> This subject seems very early to have engaged his attention; and
                    his last work, on <hi rend="italic">Life and Organization,</hi> in which his
                    views are more fully developed, affords a proof of the continued <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193194229" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4229-0378"/>assiduity with which Dr
                    Barclay prosecuted his inquiries in this interesting field of research.</p>
                <p>Immediately after his graduation, having determined, it is believed somewhat
                    suddenly, to come forward as a teacher of anatomy, he repaired to London, and
                    studied for some time under the late Dr Marshall of Thavies Inn, at that time a
                    very distinguished teacher of anatomy in the metropolis.</p>
                <p>Soon after his return from London, Dr Barclay commenced his lectures on anatomy
                    in Edinburgh in November 1797; and by his punctual attention to his engagements,
                    and assiduous devotion to the instruction of his pupils, he speedily attracted a
                    respectable audience, which continued gradually to increase in numbers until the
                    period of his retirement, a short time before his death.</p>
                <p>Of Dr Barclay’s professional writings, the earliest, we believe, was the article
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi> which he furnished for the third edition
                    of this work.</p>
                <p>In 1803, six years after he commenced his career as a teacher, Dr Barclay
                    attempted a reform in the language of anatomy, with a view to render it more
                    accurate and precise; a task for which his acquirements as a classical scholar
                    rendered him peculiarly fit. Although the <hi rend="italic">Nomenclature</hi>
                    which he published upon that occasion has not yet been generally adopted, we
                    believe that the profession, with one voice, acknowledges the importance of the
                    object which he had in view, and the talent and learning with which it was
                    executed. Some of his illustrations of the defects in the existing language of
                    anatomy, particularly in the terms expressive of position and aspect, were
                    peculiarly striking, and highly characteristic of his overflowing humour. “The
                    terms <hi rend="italic">above, below, behind,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >before”</hi> he used to observe, “would be sufficiently definite if the body
                    were uniformly to preserve the same position; and so,” said he, “would be the
                    expression in Hudibras, where the author makes Crowdero apply a squeaking-engine
                    to the <hi rend="italic">north-east</hi> side of his neck; this would be
                    sufficiently definite if one could ascertain, by compass, in what particular
                    position the fiddler stood.”</p>
                <p>His next work, published in 1808, was a <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the
                    Muscular Motions of the Human Body,</hi> calculated to encourage a more
                    attentive study of the simple and combined actions of the muscles, with a view
                    to a more scientific and successful treatment of fractures and luxations; a
                    department of surgery which, even now, although illustrated by his distinguished
                    friend Sir Astlcy Cooper, can scarcely be said to be rescued from those popular
                    prejudices under which it has so long laboured.</p>
                <p>In 1812 Dr Barclay published the first edition of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Description of the Arteries of the Human Body;</hi> a work displaying much
                    acute observation and laborious research, and which may perhaps be considered
                    the most practically useful of all his writings. The labour which this work must
                    have cost him may be judged of by the fact, that he wrote no description of any
                    artery until he had studied its delineation, as given by Haller, and every other
                    standard authority, and until he had actually examined its course and
                    distribution in every preparation to which he had access; in some instances
                    repairing to Glasgow to examine the excellent collection of vascular
                    preparations then in the possession of his friend Mr Allan Burns.</p>
                <p>His last publication, completed only a few years before his death, was <hi
                    rend="italic">An Inquiry into the Opinions, Ancient and Modern, concerning Life
                    and Organization;</hi> a work replete with learning and original criticism, and
                    well calculated to check the progress of those idle and dangerous speculations
                    by which some of our modern philosophers have been distinguished. This, like all
                    his former publications, is dedicated to Dr Ihomas Thomson, professor of
                    chemistry in the university of Glasgow, one of the earliest and most
                    distinguished of his numerous friends.</p>
                <p>These several works, which afford such remarkable proofs of the inexhaustible
                    energies of Dr Barclay’s mind were undertaken and completed amidst the incessant
                    and laborious toils which his courses of anatomical lectures necessarily imposed
                    upon him. Of these he gave two very full ones every winter, commencing each of
                    them early in November, and terminating at the end of April. For several years
                    previous to his death he had also given a course of comparative anatomy during
                    the summer months. To this branch of study Dr Barclay had always shown a marked
                    partiality, not only as an object of scientific research, but of great practical
                    utility. He pressed upon the Highland Society of Scotland, of which he was a
                    distinguished member, the propriety of giving encouragement to the study of
                    veterinary medicine; and to him, in conjunction with his friend Mr Robert
                    Johnston, the public is chiefly indebted for the establishment of the-veterinary
                    school, so successfully conducted by his pupil Mr Dick, under the auspices of
                    the liberal and patriotic body above mentioned.</p>
                <p>At the period of his death Dr Barclay was engaged in revising and preparing for
                    the press his introductory lectures, which have since been published, and
                    contain a valuable abridgement of the history of anatomy.</p>
                <p>His successful progress as a teacher of anatomy Dr Barclay always gratefully
                    attributed, in a great measure, to the patronage which, at an early period, he
                    received from the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh; and to that learned
                    and public-spirited body he bequeathed his anatomical collection, now known as
                    the Barclayan Museum, which contains many valuable specimens in comparative
                    anatomy, and some of the finest vascular preparations which are anywhere to be
                    found. <hi rend="smallcaps">(q. q.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
