<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-5373-0466-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAYLE, Peter</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 466</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1201065">Publications</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1083449">Publicity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193195373" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAYLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter</hi></label>, author of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Historical and Critical Dictionary,</hi> was born on the 18th
                    of November 1647, at Carla, a village in the county of Foix, in France, where
                    his father, John Bayle, was a Protestant minister. In 1666 he went to the
                    Protestant university at Puylaurens, where he studied with the greatest
                    application; and in 1669 he removed to the university of Toulouse, whither the
                    Protestants at that time frequently sent their children to study under the
                    Jesuits; but here, to the inexpressible grief of his father, he embraced the
                    Romish religion. However, being soon sensible of his error, he left that
                    university and went to study at Geneva, after which he was chosen professor of
                    philosophy at Sedan; but this Protestant university having been suppressed by
                    Louis XIV. in 1681, he was obliged to leave the city, and was soon after chosen
                    professor of philosophy and history at Rotterdam. The year following he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Letter concerning Comets.</hi> And Father
                    Maimbourg having about this time published his <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Calvinism,</hi> in which he endeavoured to draw upon the Protestants the
                    contempt and resentment of the Catholics, Mr Bayle wrote a piece to confute it.
                    The reputation which he had now acquired induced the states of Friesland, in
                    1684, to offer him a professorship in their university; but he wrote them a
                    letter of thanks, and declined the offer. The same year he began to publish his
                    <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles de la République des Lettres.</hi></p>
                <p>In 1686 he was drawn into a dispute in relation to the celebrated Christina,
                    queen of Sweden. In his Journal for April he took notice of a printed letter
                    supposed to have been written by her Swedish majesty to the chevalier de Terlon,
                    in which she condemns the persecution of the Protestants in France. He inserted
                    the letter itself in his Journal for May; and in that of June following he says,
                    “What we hinted at last month is confirmed to us from day to day, that Christina
                    is the real author of the letter concerning the persecutions in France, which is
                    ascribed to her: it is a remainder of Protestantism.” Mr Bayle received an
                    anonymous letter, complaining that, in speaking of her majesty, he had called
                    her simply <hi rend="italic">Christina,</hi> without any title; finding great
                    fault with his describing the letter as “a remainder of Protestantism ;” and
                    blaming him likewise for inserting the words “I am,” in the conclusion. “These
                    words,” says this anonymous writer, “are not her majesty’s; a queen, as she is,
                    cannot employ these words but with regard to a very few persons, and Μ. de
                    Terlon is not of that number.” The author of this letter stated that he wrote of
                    his own accord, being in duty bound to do so, “as a servant of the queen.” Mr
                    Bayle wrote a vindication of himself as to these particulars with which the
                    author of the anonymous letter declared himself satisfied, excepting what
                    related to “the remainder of Protestantism.” He would not admit the validity of
                    the defence in regard to that expression, and in another letter advised Mr Bayle
                    to retract it. He adds in a postscript, “You mention, in your Journal of August,
                    a second letter of the queen, which you scruple to publish. Her majesty would be
                    glad to see that letter; and you will do a thing agreeable to her if you would
                    send it to her. You might take this opportunity of writing to her majesty. This
                    counsel may be of some use to you; do not neglect it.” Mr Bayle took the hint,
                    and wrote a letter to her majesty, dated the 14th of November 1686, to which the
                    queen, on the 14th of December, returned the following answer :—</p>
                <p>“Mr Bayle, I have received your excuses, and am willing you should know by this
                    letter that I am satisfied with them. I am obliged to the zeal of the person who
                    gave you occasion of writing to me, for I am very glad to know you. You express
                    so much respect and affection for me, that I pardon you sincerely; and I would
                    have you know, that nothing gave me offence but that <hi rend="italic">remainder
                    of Protestantism,</hi> of which you accused me. 1 am very delicate on that head,
                    because nobody can suspect me of it without lessening my glory, and injuring me
                    in the most sensible manner. You would do well if you should even acquaint the
                    public with the mistake you have made, and with your regret for it. This is all
                    that remains to be done by you, in order to deserve my being entirely satisfied
                    with you. As to the letter which you have sent me, it is mine without doubt; and
                    since you tell me that it is printed, you will do me a pleasure if you send me
                    some copies of it. As I fear nothing in France, so neither do I fear anything at
                    Rome. My fortune, my blood, and even my life, are entirely devoted to the
                    service of the church; but I flatter nobody, and will never speak anything but
                    the truth. I am obliged to those who have been pleased to publish my letter, for
                    I do not at all disguise my sentiments. I thank God, they are too noble and too
                    honourable to be disowned. However, it is not true that this letter was written
                    to one of my ministers. As I have everywhere enemies and persons who envy me, so
                    in all places I have friends and servants; and I have possibly as many in
                    France, notwithstanding the court, as anywhere in the world. This is purely the
                    truth, and you may regulate yourself accordingly. But you shall not get off so
                    cheaply as you imagine. I will enjoin you a penance; which is, that you will
                    henceforth take the trouble <hi rend="italic">οf</hi> sending me all curious
                    books that shall be published in Latin, French, Spanish, or Italian, on whatever
                    subject or science, provided they are worthy of being looked into; I do not even
                    except romances or satires; and above all, if there are any books of chemistry,
                    I desire you may send them to me as soon as possible. Do not forget likewise
                    tosend me your Journal. I shall order that you be paid for whatever you lay out;
                    do but send me an account of it. This will be the most agreeable and most
                    important service that can be done me. May God prosper you.”</p>
                <p>On receiving this letter, which was signed “Christina Alexandra,” it now only
                    remained that Mr Bayle should acquaint the public with the mistake he had made,
                    in order to merit that princess’s entire approbation; and this he did in the
                    beginning of his Journal for January 1687.</p>
                <p>The persecution which the Protestants at this time suffered in France affected Mr
                    Bayle extremely. He made occasionally some reflections on their sufferings in
                    his Journal; and he wrote a pamphlet also on the subiect. <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193195386" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5386-0467"/>Some time afterwards he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Commentaire Philosophique</hi> upon these words,
                    “Compel them to come in.” The great application he bestowed on this and other
                    works threw him into a fit of sickness, which obliged him to discontinue his
                    Literary Journal. Being advised to try a change of air, he left Rotterdam on the
                    8th of August, and went to Cleves; whence, after a time, he removed to
                    Aix-la-Chapelle, and thereafter returned to Rotterdam on the 18th of October. In
                    the year 1690, the famous book entitled <hi rend="italic">Avis aux
                    Réfugiez,</hi> &amp;c. made its appearance. Mr Jurieu, who took Mr Bayle for the
                    author of it, wrote a piece against it; and he prefixed an advice to the public,
                    in which he calls Mr Bayle a profane person, and a traitor engaged in a
                    conspiracy against the state. As soon as Mr Bayle had read this libel against
                    him, he went to Rotterdam, and offered to go to prison, provided his accuser
                    would accompany him, and undergo the punishment he deserved if the accusation
                    were found unjust. He published also an answer to Mr Jurieu’s charge; and as his
                    reputation, nay his very life, was at stake in case the accusation of treason
                    were proved, he therefore thought himself not obliged to keep any terms with his
                    accuser, and attacked him with the utmost severity. Mr Jurieu lost all patience,
                    and applied to the magistrates of Amsterdam, who advised him to a reconciliation
                    with Mr Bayle, enjoining them not to publish any thing against each other till
                    it was examined by Mr Boyer, the pensioner of Rotterdam. But notwithstanding
                    this prohibition, Mr Jurieu again attacked Mr Bayle with so much passion, that
                    he forced the latter to write a new vindication of himself.</p>
                <p>In November 1690 Μ. de Beauval advertised in his Journal <hi rend="italic">A
                    Scheme for a Critical Dictionary.</hi> This was the <hi rend="italic">magnum
                    opus</hi> of Bayle. The articles of the first three letters of the alphabet were
                    already prepared; but a dispute which happened between him and Μ. de Beauval
                    obliged him for some time to lay aside the work. Nor did he resume it till the
                    month of May 1692, when he published his scheme; but the public not approving of
                    his plan, he threw it into a different form, and the first volume was published
                    in August 1695, and the second in October following. The work in its new shape
                    was extremely well received by the public; but it engaged him in fresh disputes,
                    particularly with Mr Jurieu and the abbé Renaudot. Mr Jurieu published a piece,
                    in which he endeavoured to engage the ecclesiastical assemblies to condemn the
                    Dictionary, and presented it for that purpose to the synod sitting at Delft; but
                    they took no notice of the affair. The consistory of Rotterdam granted Mr Bayle
                    a hearing; and after having considered his answers to their remarks on his
                    Dictionary, they declared themselves satisfied, and advised him to communicate
                    this to the public. Mr Jurieu made another attempt with the consistory in 1698,
                    and so far prevailed with them, that they exhorted Mr Bayle to be more cautious
                    with regard to his principles in the second edition of his Dictionary, which was
                    published in 1702, with many additions and improvements.</p>
                <p>Bayle was a most laborious and indefatigable writer. In one of his letters to
                    Maizeaux, he says that since his twentieth year he hardly remembers to have had
                    any leisure. His intense application contributed perhaps to impair his
                    constitution, for it soon began to decline. He suffered from an affection of the
                    lungs, which weakened him considerably; and as this was a distemper which had
                    cut off several of his family, he judged it mortal, and would take no remedies.
                    He died on the 28th of December 1706, after he had been writing the greater part
                    of the day. He was the author of several pieces besides those we have mentioned,
                    many of which were written in his own defence against attacks made upon him by
                    the abbé enaudot, Clarke, Jaquelot, and others. Among the productions which do
                    honour to the age of Louis XIV. Μ. Voltaire has not omitted the Critical
                    Dictionary of our author. “It is the first work of the kind,” he says, “in which
                    a man may learn to think.”...“In placing him,” continues the same author,
                    “amongst the writers who do honour to the age of Louis XIV., notwithstanding his
                    being a refugee in Holland, I only conform to the decree of the parliament of
                    Toulouse, which, when it declared his will valid in France, notwithstanding the
                    rigour of the laws, expressly said, <hi rend="italic">that such a man could not
                    he considered a foreigner”</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
