<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4606-0407-05" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BARRINGTON, John Shute</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 407</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:794775">Abstracts</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:794769">Abstraction</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:794752">Abstracting</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:832970">Birds</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z749">Abstraction</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193194606" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BARRINGTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Shute</hi></label>,
                    Lord Viscount Bar- ∏∏gton, a nobleman distinguished for theological learn- <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ∏g, was the youngest son of Benjamin Shute, merchant,
                    and was born in 1678. He received part of his education at the university of
                    Utrecht; and, after returning to Eng-and, studied law in the Inner Temple. In
                    1701 he commenced author by writing in favour of the civil rights of rotestant
                    dissenters, to which body he belonged. On o recommendation of Lord Somers, he
                    was employed to engage the Presbyterians in Scotland to favour the union of the
                    two kingdoms; and, in 1708, he was rewarded for this service, by being appointed
                    to the office of commissioner of the customs. From this, however, he was removed
                    by the Tory ministry of Queen Anne; but his fortune had, in the meantime, been
                    improved by the bequest of two considerable estates, one of them left him by
                    Francis Barrington of Tofts, Esq. whose name he assumed by act of parliament. Mr
                    Barrington now stood at the head of the dissenters. On the accession of George
                    I. he was returned member of parliament for Berwick-upon-Tweed; and in 1720 the
                    king raised him to the Irish peerage, by the style and title of Viscount
                    Barrington of Ardglass. But having unfortunately engaged in one of the bubbles
                    of the time, the Harburg lottery, he incurred the disgrace of expulsion from the
                    House of Commons in 1723; a punishment which was thought greatly too severe,
                    indeed altogether unmerited on his part. In 1725 he published his principal
                    work, entitled <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea Sacra, or α New Method of
                    considering so much of the History of the Apostles as is contained in Scripture,
                    in an Abstract of their History, an Abstract of that Abstract, and four Critical
                    Essays,</hi> 2 vols. 8vo. This work, which traces the methods employed by the
                    first preachers of the gospel in propagating Christianity, and explains the
                    several gifts of the Spirit by which they were enabled to discharge their
                    office, has always been reckoned a valuable and judicious defence of the
                    Christian cause; and it was reprinted with additions and corrections, in 3 vols.
                    8vo, 1770, by his son, afterwards bishop of Durham. In the same year (1725) he
                    published <hi rend="italic">An Essay on the several Dispensations of God to
                    Manhind,</hi> in the order in which these are unfolded in the Scriptures; and he
                    was the author of various other tracts, chiefly on subjects relating to
                    toleration in matters of religion. He died in 1734, in the 56th year of his age,
                    leaving a number of children, of whom five sons had the singular good fortune to
                    rise to high stations in the church, the law, the army, and the navy. Lord
                    Barrington was a friend and disciple of Locke, whose sentiments he adopted as to
                    the right and advantage of free inquiry, and the value of civil and religious
                    liberty; and he contributed greatly to the rising spirit of liberal scriptural
                    criticism amongst those who wished to render religion a subject of rational
                    belief. He was a man of great moderation, and, though chiefly connected with the
                    dissenters, he occasionally frequented and communicated with the established
                    church.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Barrington,</hi><hi rend="italic">Daines,</hi> fourth son
                    of Lord Viscount Barrington, distinguished as an antiquary and naturalist, was
                    educated for the profession of the law, and, after filling various posts, was
                    appointed a Welsh judge in 1757, and afterwards second justice of Chester. He
                    never rose to much eminence at the bar, but he showed his knowledge of the law
                    as a subject of liberal study, by a valuable publication entitled <hi rend="italic">Observations on the Statutes, chiefiy the more ancient, from Magna
                    Charta</hi> to 21 <hi rend="italic">James I. c.</hi> 27, <hi rend="italic">with
                    an Appendix, being a proposal for new-modelling the Statutes,</hi> 1766, 4to; a
                    work which has been quoted with merited commendation by many of our historians
                    and constitutional antiquaries. In 1773 he published an edition of Orosius, with
                    Alfred’s Saxon version, and an English translation with notes of his own, which
                    was severely animadverted on by the critics. His <hi rend="italic">Tracts on the
                    Probability of reaching the North Pole,</hi> 1775, 4to, were written in
                    consequence of the northern voyage of discovery undertaken by Captain Phipps,
                    afterwards Lord Mulgrave. In these he has accumulated a variety of evidence
                    favourable to his own opinion of the practicability of attaining the object in
                    which that voyage had failed; and it is not improbable that his views and
                    arguments had some effect in <pb break="no" facs="nls:193194619" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4619-0408"/>determining the government of our time to renew
                    the attempt, though with no better success. Mr Barrington’s other writings are
                    chiefly to be found in the publications of the Royal and Antiquarian Societies,
                    of both of which he was long an assiduous member, and of the latter
                    vicepresident. These relate to a variety of topics in natural history and
                    antiquities, and show great industry and research, though with an occasional
                    leaning to singularity ‘and paradox. Many of his tracts were collected by him in
                    a quarto volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Miscellanies on various
                    Subjects,</hi> 1781. His <hi rend="italic">Experiments and Observations on the
                    Singing of Birds,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Language of
                    Birds,</hi> are among the most curious and ingenious of his papers, and, with
                    other productions of his pen, prove that he was not only deeply conversant with
                    books, but an attentive and sagacious observer of nature. In private life he was
                    a man of worth and integrity, unambitious, and devoted to study and literary
                    conversation. He resigned his office of justice of Chester in 1785, and
                    afterwards lived in retirement in his chambers in King’s-Bench Walks, Inner
                    Temple; associating chiefly with his brother benchers, and amusing himself with
                    superintending the improvements of the gardens. He died on the 14th March 1800,
                    and was buried in the Temple church.</p></div></body></text></TEI>