<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4580-0405-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BARRACKS</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 405</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="13" ref="fasttopic:827721">Barracks</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:864129">Clerks</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1076230">Pricing</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16q19">Barracks</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193194580" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BARRACKS</label>, called by the French <hi rend="italic">Casernes,</hi> places for soldiers to lodge in, especially in garrisons. Till
                    the middle of the year 1792, when there was a prospect of war with revolutionary
                    France, and the British ministry became apprehensive of disturbances in this
                    country, barracks were not numerous, nor were they under the control and
                    management of a separate and peculiar board. Previous to this they were built
                    under the authority and directions of the Board of Ordnance, which also supplied
                    them with bedding and the necessary utensils; and any extra articles that were
                    requisite were furnished by the secretary at war. In 1792 orders were issued by
                    the ministry for building cavalry barracks with the utmost dispatch, and the
                    deputy-adjutant-general was directed to superintend the building and fitting
                    them up. In January 1793 the same officer was appointed superintendent-general
                    of barracks; and on the first of May the king’s warrant was issued for their
                    regulation. Greater powers were given to the superintendentgeneral in the year
                    1794; but as these seemed to interfere with the duties and powers of the Board
                    of Ordnance, a new warrant was issued in the year 1795, defining and limiting
                    the respective duties and powers of the Board of Ordnance, and the
                    superintendent-general, or barrackmaster-general, as he was now called. In the
                    year 1796 the barrack-office establishment consisted of a barrackmaster-general,
                    with two clerks; a deputy-barrack-mastergeneral; an
                    assistant-barrack-master-general, with three clerks; an accountant, with five
                    clerks; an assistant-barrack-master-general for the general inspection of
                    barracks, and six other assistant-barrack-masters-general for the particular
                    inspection of barracks in different districts; five clerks for general business;
                    one assistant-barrackmaster-general for the building branch; one checking clerk,
                    and seven other clerks; two architects and surveyors; one
                    assistant-barrack-master-general in North Britain, with two assistants and
                    clerks; one treasurer; and three other assistant-barrack-masters-general for
                    general duties, and visiting barracks. The salaries and extra pay of these
                    officers amounted in 1796 to L.9524. 17s. 2d. The establishment was afterwards
                    considerably increased, in proportion as the number of barracks throughout the
                    kingdom increased, and by the creation of some new officers, among whom was a
                    law clerk.</p><p>During the year 1800 the Commis.sioners of Military Inquiry began their duties;
                    and their first reports were on the subject of the barrack establishment. In the
                    arrange^ ment of this establishment, and the mode in which its duties were
                    performed, the commissioners pointed out many things that were highly
                    objectionable; and concluded their reports by recommending that the offices of
                    barrack-master-general and deputy-barrack-master-general should be totally
                    abolished, and that the superintendence of the barrack establishment should be
                    vested in commissioners. This suggestion, and some others relative to the mode
                    of transacting the business of the department, and preventing useless and
                    extravagant expenditure, were followed, and the barrack establishment was placed
                    under the direction of four commissioners, one of whom was generally a military
                    man..</p><p>But as it frequently happened that barracks required to be built on an emergency,
                    when there was no time to summon a jury to value the land before the
                    commencement θt the building, and as most persons were averse to have barracks
                    near their dwelling-houses, or even on their property, government was
                    consequently obliged, in all such cases, to pay an extravagant price for the
                    land which Was needed for their erection. In order to remedy this therefore, it
                    was provided by the act usually called <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> defence
                    act, 43 Geo. III. cap. 55, that justices of the peace might <hi rend="italic">de
                    plano</hi> put any general officer into the possession of such ground as he
                    might deem fit for the erection of barracks, provided the immediate necessity
                    for such ground was certified by the lord lieutenant or two deputylieutenants of
                    the county; the value of the ground so appropriated to be afterwards fixed by a
                    jury in the ordinary way.</p><p>Barracks throughout the country are more immediately under the management and
                    care of the resident barrackmasters, especially since the reduction of the
                    barrackoffice establishment, and the further reduction of the
                    assistant-barrack-masters-general attached to districts.</p><p>The barrack districts in Great Britain are as follow :— 1. the northern,
                    containing Northumberland, Cumberland, Westmoreland, and Durham; 2. York,
                    containing Yorkshire; 3. the eastern, containing Norfolk, Suffolk, Cambridge,
                    Huntingdonshire, and all Essex, except Tilburyfort; 4. the southern, containing
                    Kent, Tilbury-fort, and Sussex; 5. the south-western, containing Hampshire and
                    Dorsetshire; 6. Isle of Wight; 7. the western, containing Devonshire, Cornŵall,
                    and Somerset; 8. Severn, containing Gloucestershire, Herefordshire,
                    Monmouthshire, and South Wales; 9. the north-western, containing Cheshire,
                    Shropshire, Lancashire, North Wales, and the Isle of Man; 10. London; 11. the
                    home, containing Middlesex, Surrey, Hertfordshire, and part of Kent; 12. the
                    north-inland, containing Derbyshire, Nottinghamshire, Staffordshire,
                    Warwickshire, Leicestershire, and Rutlandshire; 13. the southinland, containing
                    Bedfordshire, Northamptonshire, Oxfordshire, and Buckinghamshire; 14. Jersey,
                    Guernsey, and Alderney.</p><p>The Scottish districts are, 1. the northern, containing Caithness, Sutherland,
                    Ross-shire, Inverness-shire, Nairnshire, Morayshire, and Banffshire; 2. the
                    western, containing Aberdeenshire, Argyleshire, Ayrshire, Bute, Kincardineshire,
                    Lanarkshire, Renfrewshire, and Wigtonshire; 3. the central, containing
                    Angusshire, Clackmannanshire, Dumbartonshire, Fifeshire, Kinross-shire,
                    Perthshire, and Stirlingshire; and 4. the southern, containing the Lothians,
                    Berwickshire, Peeblesshire, Selkirkshire, Roxburghshire; and Dumfriesshire.</p><p>On the 14th of July 1805 there were in Great Britain, the Island of Jersey,
                    &amp;c. 84 established barracks of brick and stone, 12 of wood, 75 temporary
                    barracks, and 41 rented; in all 212. But the number was afterwards considerably
                    increased. The annual rents at this time amounted to L.40,231. The whole of
                    these barracks were calculated to accommodate nearly 100,000 infantry and 15,000
                    cavalry. In the cavalry barracks, field-officers have two rooms each; captains
                    one; subalterns, staff, and quarter-masters, one; serjeants of each troop of
                    dragoons, and corporals of each troop of horse, one; eight rank and file one
                    among them; and two rooms are allowed for the officers’ mess. In infantry
                    barracks, fieldofficers are allowed two each; captains one; one is allotted to
                    two subalterns; the staff has one; twelve noncommissioned officers and private
                    men one among them; the serjeant-major and quarter-master-serjeant one; and two
                    are allotted for the officers’ mess. The barracks are supplied by the
                    barrack-office with beds, bedding, sheets, blankets, towels, house and stable
                    utensils, coals, and candles; beer was formerly supplied, but now an allowance
                    is made instead of it. Forage is supplied by the commissariat.</p><p>The expense of erecting barracks must of course greatly depend on the price of
                    materials at the time, and, in some measure, on the part of the kingdom where
                    they are erected. In the year 1805 permanent barracks for a battalion of 800
                    men, in the south of England, cost L.37,000; and barracks for 1200 infantry and
                    400 cavalry L.60,000. The following statement exhibits the several particulars </p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193194593" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4593-0406"/><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"> of the total expense incurred by the nation for barracks,
                            and the barrack-office, in Great Britain, between the 25th of December
                            1792, and the 10th of November 1804:— </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Buildings and purchases of land </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>L.3,930,223</p><p>846,246</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 5 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 8 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Forage </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 7 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 10 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bppγ</hi></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 643,030 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 9 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 6 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Coals, candles, furniture, rents, repairs, supplied by
                            barrack-masters, and salaries </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 1,685,487 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 8 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 0 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Office-establishment </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 256,129 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 10 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 4 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Fees at war-office </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 80,346 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 3 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 6 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Insurance </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 1,519 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 2 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 2 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Additional rents </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>36,860</p><p>139,582</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 13 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 5 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Lodging-money to officers </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 16 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 0 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 11,866 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 0 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 5 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Bedding, furniture, &amp;c. issued by the barrack-office, and in
                            store </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 1,357,215 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 7 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 3 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> Miscellaneous </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 35,498 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 4 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 8 </cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> L.9,024,005 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 8 </cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 9 </cell></row></table><p>During the last war the annual expense of the barrack establishment in Great
                    Britain varied from L.350,000 to L.500,000. But in Ireland, where barracks are
                    more numerous, the expense generally equalled, and often exceeded, that of Great
                    Britain in this particular. Thus, in 1814, the sum required for Great Britain
                    was L.309,826, whilst that necessary for Ireland was L.360,515; and a similar
                    excess appears in the peace estimate for 1816, which was for Great Britain
                    L.173,500, and for Ireland L.213,000. Since this period the annual expense has
                    of course varied, though within limits so narrow that it seems unnecessary to
                    particularize the sums voted for the service of each year. The barrack estimate
                    of 1828 was, for Great Britain and the colonies L. 105,963, and for Ireland
                    L.81,705; that of 1829 amounted, for Great Britain and the colonies, to L.l
                    17,636, and for Ireland, to L.102,721. The estimate for 1830 embraces the
                    different heads of repairs; barrack-masters’ expenditure; allowances to
                    barrack-masters, serjeants, and miscellaneous charges for barrack service; and
                    colonial expenditure: under the first of which the sums voted were, for Great
                    Britain L.67,746, for Ireland L.60,000; under the second, L.54,827; under the
                    third L.l 1,762; and under the fourth L.56,539: total, L.250,874.</p><p>See first, second, third, and fourth <hi rend="italic">Reports of the
                    Commissioners of Military Inquiry,</hi> 1806; the <hi rend="italic">Finance
                    Reports</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Estimates</hi> laid before parliament for the
                    years 1814 and 1816; and the <hi rend="italic">Army Estimates</hi> for 1828,
                    1829, and 1830.</p></div></body></text></TEI>