<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-8935-0740-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOLINGBROKE, Henry St John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 740</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1006755">Mallets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110280">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:875336">Connectionism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nj3s">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193198935" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOLINGBROKE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry St John</hi></label>,
                    lord viscount, a great statesman, an indifferent philosopher, and an admirable
                    writer, was descended from an ancient and noble family, and born about the year
                    1672. He had a regular and liberal education, and, by the time he left the
                    university, was considered as a person of uncommon qualifications; but with
                    great parts, he had,'as usually happens, strong passions, and these hurried him
                    into many indiscretions and follies. Contrary to the inclinations of his family,
                    he cultivated tory connections, and gained such an influence in the house of
                    commons, that, in 1704, he was appointed secretary of war and of the marines. He
                    was so closely united in all political measures with Mr Harley, that when the
                    latter was removed from the seals in 1707, Mr St John resigned his employment;
                    and in 1710, when Mr Harley was made chancellor of the exchequer, the post of
                    secretary of state was given to Mr St John. In 1712 he was created Baron St John
                    of Lediard-Tregoze in Wiltshire, and Viscount Bolingbroke. But being overlooked
                    in the bestowal of vacant ribbons of the order of the garter, he resented the
                    affront, renounced the friendship of Harley then earl of Oxford, and made his
                    court to the whigs. Nevertheless on the accession of George I. the seals were
                    taken from him; and being informed that a resolution was taken to pursue him to
                    the scaffold, for his conduct regarding the treaty of Utrecht, he withdrew into
                    France. Here he accepted an invitation to enter into the Pretender’s service,
                    and received the seals as bis secretary; but he was as unfortunate in his new
                    connections as in those which he had renounced; for the year 1715 had scarcely
                    expired, when, at the same time that he was attainted of high treason at home,
                    the seals and papers of his foreign secretary’s office were taken from him; and
                    this was followed by an accusation from the Pretender and his party, of neglect,
                    incapacity, and treachery. Such a complication of distressful events threw him
                    into a state of reflection that produced a <hi rend="italic">consolatio
                    philosophica,</hi> in the manner of Seneca and of Boethius, which he wrote the
                    same year under the title of <hi rend="italic">Heflections upon Exile;</hi> and
                    the following year he drew up a vindication of his conduct with respect to the
                    tories, in the form of <hi rend="italic">A Letter to Sir William Wyndham.</hi>
                    About this time he espoused as his second wife a niece of the famous Madame
                    Maintenon, and widow of the Marquis de Villette, with whom he received a very
                    large fortune. In 1723, the king was prevailed on to grant him a free pardon,
                    and he returned in consequence to England; but he was by no means satisfied with
                    being a mere titular lord, and remaining excluded from the house of peers. This
                    stigma operated to fix his hatred of Sir Robert Walpole, to whose secret enmity
                    he attributed his not receiving the full extent of the kings clemency. Hence he
                    distinguished himself by a multitude of political writings, chiefly directed
                    against that minister, till the year 1735; when, being thoroughly convinced that
                    the door was finally shut against him, he returned once more to France. In this
                    foreign retreat he began his <hi rend="italic">Letters on the Study and Use of
                    History,</hi> for the use of the grandson of the celebrated Lord Clarendon, to
                    whom they are addressed. Upon the death of his father, who lived to be extremely
                    old, he settled at Battersea, the ancient seat of his family, where he passed
                    the remainder of his life in philosophical retirement, uniting, as we are told
                    by his admirers, the wit of Horace with the dignity of Pliny and the wisdom of
                    Socrates. Pope and Swift, the one the greatest poet, the other the greatest wit
                    of the time, were completely devoted to him; and it is well known that the
                    former received from him the materials <pb break="no" facs="nls:193198948"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-8948-0741"/>for his <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man.</hi> He
                    died in 1751, and left the care and benefit of his MSS. to Mr Mallet, who
                    published them, together with his formerly printed works, in 5 vols. 4to∙ They
                    are also printed in 9 vols. 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
