<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5204-0453-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BATTLE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 453</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:824464">Axes</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010167">Marketing</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010316">Markets</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:939002">Gauls</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193195204" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BATTLE</label>, a market-town in the rape of Hastings and
                    county of Sussex, 56 miles from London. It was the scene of the conflict in 1066
                    which insured to William the Norman the crown of England. The abbey founded by
                    him forms a most magnificent pile of ruins, and the ancient gatehouse is still
                    in good preservation. The place is now celebrated for its manufactories of the
                    best gunpowder. There is a weekly market on Thursday, and a monthly market on
                    the first Tuesday of each month. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 2040, in
                    1811 to 2531, and in 1821 to 2852.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Battle,</hi> an action or engagement between the forces of
                    two armies. A battle is either general or partial; general, where the whole, or
                    at least the greater part, of each army is brought into action; and partial,
                    where only brigades, divisions, or corps d’armée are engaged. But, however the
                    numbers may vary, the great principles to be applied in délivering battle are in
                    almost every case the same.</p><p>It has indeed been said, by a high military authority, that there is nothing
                    invariable in the art of combats; and, looking to the endless diversity of
                    circumstances under which battles have been fought, as well as to the apparent
                    results, which are often at variance with the profoundest calculations of
                    science, the observation would seem to have some foundation in truth. But a
                    closer examination will be sufficient to convince us that this is not the case,
                    and that the maxim in question, like many others which pass <pb break="no" facs="nls:193195217" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5217-0454"/>current in the
                    world, involves a fallacy equally glaring and dangerous. It is no doubt true
                    that, in the circumstances under which battles are fought, there is nothing
                    invariable; on the contrary, it is scarcely possible to suppose two cases, we do
                    not say alike in every particular, but resembling each other even in their great
                    or leading features. From the very nature of things, the data of the problem are
                    variable; but the grand principles by which the solution is to be evolved
                    continue immutably the same. The elements which enter into the calculations of a
                    general are constantly changing; and it is this circumstance which affords scope
                    for the exercise of his genius, his sagacity, and his military science. But it
                    would be manifestly absurd to maintain, that because the conditions are
                    incessantly diversified, the principles of the art experience equal mutations.
                    The issue of battle is always uncertain; because the calculations of the general
                    may be defective, his combinations unscientific, his foresight limited, or his
                    temperament rash and impetuous; and because, even where none of these causes of
                    failure exist, events which no human sagacity could have divined may occur to
                    defeat the wisest plans and the ablest dispositions. But all this implies, that
                    if every thing could have been foreseen and provided for, the result would not
                    have been doubtful; and that the “grand chances” are always on the side of him
                    who forms his plan with the greatest sagacity, and executes it with
                    corresponding vigour and ability. For, variable as the results of battles
                    appear, the most decisive success has generally crowned the exertions of the
                    greatest commanders; and victory in the long-run has seldom failed to pay homage
                    to science. There is nothing, therefore, invariable in the art of combats,
                    except those principles which science has established as, <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis,</hi> universally applicable.</p><p>A battle is not only the most imposing, but also the most important event in war.
                    It is the consummation to which all the previous combinations of commanders
                    necessarily tend; it is that grand act of war which may decide the fate of
                    kingdoms and empires, as well as that of armies and campaigns. The highest and
                    dearest interests of nations, nay even of humanity itself, may be involved in
                    its issue; and the mighty cause of civilization may be accelerated or retarded
                    according as the scales of the battle turn. It cannot, therefore, we should
                    think, be uninteresting or uninstructive, if we endeavour, by recurring to the
                    works of the great masters, to exhibit a condensed digest of those general
                    principles, by the skilful application of which the fate of battles, in all
                    ages, has more or less been determined.</p><p>All the combinations of a battle may be reduced to three systems. The first,
                    which is purely defensive, consists in waiting for the enemy in a strong
                    position, without any other object than that of maintaining it against him. Such
                    were the dispositions of Marshal Daun at Torgau, and of the Comte de Marsin in
                    the lines at Turin; dispositions, we may add, which proved wholly unavailing
                    against Frederick and Eugene, and forcibly exemplify the danger of receiving an
                    attack even in the strongest position. The second system, on the other hand, is
                    entirely offensive. It consists in attacking the enemy wherever he can be found,
                    as Frederick did at Leuthen and at Torgau, Buonaparte at Jena and at Ratisbon,
                    and the allied armies at Leipsic. The third system is in some sort a mean term
                    between the first and second. It consists in choosing a field of battle
                    possessing certain advantages both in a strategical and tactical point of view,
                    in order to wait there for the enemy, and, even in the day of battle, to watch
                    the favourable moment for assuming the initiative, and falling upon the
                    adversary with every chance of success. The combinations of Buonaparte at Rivoli
                    and at Austerlitz, and those of Wellington at Waterloo, as well as in the
                    greater part of his defensive battles during the peninsular war, are examples of
                    the mixed system, and must therefore be classed under this head.</p><p>It would be difficult, not to say impossible, to lay down any fixed rules for
                    determining when either of these two last systems, which are the only suitable
                    ones, ought to be employed. Regard must be had to the moral condition of the
                    troops of each party; to the national character, considered as more or less
                    solid or impetuous; and, lastly, to the obstacles presented by the ground. These
                    are circumstances which must always influence the decision of a general; but
                    allowing sufficient latitude for such considerations, the following principles
                    will nevertheless be found generally applicable: lóŕ, That with veteran troops,
                    and in an open country, the absolute offensive or initiative of attack is always
                    most advantageous; 2&lt;∕∕y, That in ground which, by reason of its physical
                    conformation or other causes, is of difficult access, the better course is to
                    allow the enemy to arrive in a position which has been previously reconnoitred,
                    and to assume the initiative as soon as his troops shall have been exhausted by
                    their first efforts; 3&lt;7Zy∕, That the strategical situation of the two
                    parties may nevertheless sometimes require that the positions of an adversary be
                    attacked by main force, without regard to any local consideration whatever; as,
                    for example, when it is necessary to prevent the junction of two hostile armies,
                    or to fall upon a portion of an army detached, or upon a corps isolated beyond a
                    river. In these and in all similar cases a skilful general will direct an
                    immediate and combined attack, without concerning himself about any
                    consideration extrinsic to the main object of overwhelming the body opposed to
                    him before it can be reinforced.</p><p>Orders of battle, or the dispositions best suited for conducting troops to the
                    combat, ought to have for their object to insure at once mobility and solidity;
                    and hence they ought neither to be too extended nor too profound. An-attenuated
                    order is weak: and troops crowded together in too dense an order are paralyzed;
                    for as the head of the mass only is engaged, disorder is easily introduced, and
                    the enemy’s artillery causes frightful ravages. To avoid this double evil, and
                    to fulfil both the conditions of a good order of battle, troops which remain
                    upon the defensive should be partly deployed and partly in columns of
                    battalions, like the Russian army under Beningsen at the battle of Eylau. But
                    troops disposed for the attack of a decisive point ought to be drawn up in two
                    lines of battalions, each of which, instead of being deployed, should be formed
                    in columns by divisions. This order presents infinitely more solidity than a
                    deployed line, the fluctuations of which deprive it of the impulsion necessary
                    for such an attack, and render it impossible for the officers to exercise the
                    necessary control over the troops. Nevertheless, in order to facilitate the
                    march, to avoid too great depth in the mass, and to extend the front without
                    materially lessening the consistence of an army, it may be advantageous to draw
                    up the infantry in two ranks. The battalions will thus possess greater mobility;
                    and, besides, they will have all the force desirable, since the three divisions
                    deployed will possess six ranks in depth, which is more than sufficient; while
                    the extended front will increase in a corresponding ratio the effect of the
                    musketry. In grounds of difficult access, as vineyards, inclosures, gardens, and
                    wooded heights, the defensive order of battle should be composed of battalions
                    deployed, covered by numerous platoons of sharpshooters. But the troops destined
                    tor the attack, as well as the reserve, maybe advantageous y disposed in columns
                    of attack by the centre. The reserve, however, may be kept in part deployed
                    until the mome∏∙</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193195230" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5230-0455"/><p>of advance, in order, by its apparent extent, to impose on the enemy. In a
                    defensive battle upon open ground, squares of battalions may be substituted for
                    columns, by doubling the lines of two ranks so as to form four deep; and each
                    battalion will thus present a sufficient mass, with a front varying from forty
                    to fifty files. This order, which was that employed by the duke of Wellington at
                    Waterloo, appears advantageous when there is reason to apprehend attacks of
                    cavalry; for it affords at once safety to the infantry, and protection to the
                    cannoneers and train of artillery. But as it has both less mobility and less
                    impulsion than that in columns of attack, the latter has been judged preferable;
                    because, with well-disciplined troops, squares may be easily formed in each
                    battalion by a simple conversion to the right and left of the division of the
                    centre. The duke of Wellington, it is true, commonly fought deployed; but, to
                    say nothing of the incomparable military qualities of his troops, his lines were
                    generally formed four deep; so that, after all, the exception is more apparent
                    than real.</p><p>See Jomini, <hi rend="italic">Traité des Grandes Operations Militaires;</hi>
                    Archduke Charles, <hi rend="italic">Der Strategie;</hi> Rogniat, <hi rend="italic">Considérations sur l’Art de la Guerre;</hi> Guibert, <hi rend="italic">Essai Général de Tactique;</hi> Bulow’s <hi rend="italic">Principles of</hi> ∏+r. translated by Ma-lortie. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi rend="italic">BAΤΤLΕ-Axe,</hi> an ancient military weapon. Axes formed a
                    principal part of the offensive arms of the Celtae. At the siege of the Capitol
                    by the Gauls under Brennus, one of the most distinguished of their warriors was
                    armed with a battle-axe; and Ammianus Marcellinus, many centuries afterwards,
                    describing a body of Gauls, states that all of them were armed with battle-axes
                    and swords. Some of these weapons have been found in the sepulchres of the
                    ancient Britons on the downs of Wiltshire and in the north of Scotland. Four or
                    five centuries ago the Irish went constantly armed with axes. At the battle of
                    Bannockburn, King Robert Bruce cleft an English champion to the chine with one
                    blow of his battle-axe. The Lochaber axe also remained long a formidable weapon
                    in the hands of the Scottish Highlanders; and it constituted the principal arm
                    of the city guard of Edinburgh till the year 1817, when that body of military
                    conservators of the peace was abolished.</p></div></body></text></TEI>