<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9364-0773-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BOOK</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 773</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:794221">Abbots</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:877187">Convents</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z981">Abbots</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193199364" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BOOK</label>, the general name of almost every literary
                    composition, but, in a more limited sense, applied only to such compositions as
                    are large enough to make a volume.</p><p>Several sorts of materials were formerly used in making books. Plates of lead and
                    copper, the bark of trees, bricks, stone, and wood, were the substances
                    anciently employed to engrave such things upon as men were willing to have
                    transmitted to posterity. Josephus speaks of two columns, the one of stone and
                    the other of brick, on which the children of Seth wrote their inventions and
                    astronomical discoveries; and Porphyry mentions some pillars preserved in Crete,
                    on which the ceremonies observed by the Corybantes in their sacrifices were
                    recorded. Hesiod’s works were originally written upon tablets of lead, and
                    deposited in the temple of the Muses, in Boeotia; the ten commandments delivered
                    to Moses were written upon stone; and the laws of Solon were inscribed upon
                    wooden planks. Tables of wood, box, and ivory, were common among the ancients;
                    but when of wood, they were latterly covered with wax, and the letters traced in
                    the soft matter of the coating by means of a pointed style, so that writing in
                    this fashion might be exactly executed, and as easily obliterated. The leaves of
                    the palm-tree were afterwards used instead of wooden planks; and also the finest
                    and thinnest part of the bark of such trees as the lime, the ash, the maple, and
                    the elm; whence comes the word <hi rend="italic">liber</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> i</hi> which literally signifies the inner bark of a tree. And as
                    these barks were rolled up, in order to be removed with greater ease, the rolls
                    were called <hi rend="italic">volumxn,</hi> a volume; a name afterwards given to
                    the like rolls of paper or parchment.</p><p>Thus we find books were first written on stones, as the decalogue of Moses; then
                    on the parts of plants, as leaves, chiefly of the palm-tree, the rind and barks,
                    especially of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193199377" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9377-0774"/>the tilia, or phillyrea, and the Egyptian papyrus.
                    By degrees wax came to be used; then leather, especially the skins of goats and
                    sheep, of which at length parchment was prepared; then lead was employed; then
                    linen, silk, and horn; and lastly paper itself.</p><p>The first books were in the form of blocks and tablets; but when flexible matter
                    came into use it was found more convenient to make books in the form of rolls,
                    which were composed of several sheets fastened to each other, and rolled upon a
                    stick, or <hi rend="italic">umbilicus;</hi> the whole forming a kind of column
                    or cylinder, which was managed by the umbilicus as a handle. The outside of the
                    volume was called <hi rend="italic">frons,</hi> and the ends of the umbilicus
                    <hi rend="italic">cornua;</hi> which were usually carved, and adorned with
                    silver, ivory, or even gold and precious stones. The title, c <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> υλλα⅛os, was struck on the outside; and the whole
                    volume, when extended, might be about a yard or more in width, and fifty in
                    length. The form which obtains among us is the square, composed of separate
                    leaves; and it was also known, though little used, by the ancients.</p><p>To the form of books belongs also the internal economy, embracing the order and
                    arrangement of points and letters into lines and pages, with margins and other
                    accessories. This has undergone many varieties. At first the letters were
                    divided only into lines; then into separate words; and these, by degrees, were
                    noted with accents, and distributed, by points and stops, into periods,
                    paragraphs, chapters, and other divisions. In some countries, as among the
                    orientals, the direction of the lines was from right to left; in others, as
                    among the northern and western nations, from left to right; while the early
                    Greeks followed both directions, writing alternately from right to left and from
                    left to right, which was called <hi rend="italic">boustrophedon,</hi> from its
                    analogy to the path of oxen in ploughing. In most countries the lines run from
                    one side to the other; in some, particularly among the Chinese, their direction
                    is from top to bottom. The Egyptian monumental writing, or hieroglyphics, is
                    arranged in all these directions, and in several peculiar to itself. Sometimes
                    we find it proceeding from right to left; sometimes from left to right; very
                    frequently from top to bottom, in regular parallel columns; in a few instances,
                    and but a few, <hi rend="italic">boustrophedon;</hi> occasionally arranged in
                    groups or clusters, as in anaglyphs; and, where the space was irregular, as on
                    the sides of obelisks, disposed in an arbitrary manner, varying according to the
                    circumstances. But this total Avant of system, or rather this mode of arranging
                    the characters upon all systems and in all ways, can never be productive of any
                    difficulty or ambiguity, as the disposition and true sequence of the writing is
                    in every case clearly and almost intuitively indicated by the direction given to
                    the principal figures, more especially to those which represent animals, or the
                    human form. With regard to the other modes of writing practised by the ancient
                    Egyptians, that called the hieratic follows to a certain extent the varieties of
                    the hieroglyphic; but the demotic, enchorial, or civil form, is generally
                    disposed from right to left, in the ordinary manner of oriental writing.</p><p>Of the scarcity and value of books during the seventh and subsequent centuries,
                    the following curious account is given by Mr Warton :—</p><p>“1owards the close of the seventh century,” says this writer, “even in the papal
                    library at Rome, the number of books was so inconsiderable, that Pope Saint
                    Martin requested Sanctamund, bishop of Maestricht, if possible, to supply this
                    defect from the remotest parts of Germany. In the year 855 Lupus, abbot of
                    Ferrières, in France, sent two of his monks to Pope Benedict III. to beg a copy
                    of <hi rend="italic">Cicero de Oratore,</hi> and Quintilian’s Institutes, and
                    some other books: <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> for, says the abbot, <hi rend="superscript"> ζ</hi> although we have part of these books, yet there is no
                    whole or complete copy of them in all France.’ Albert, abbot of Gemblours,' who
                    with incredible labour and immense expense had collected a hundred volumes on
                    theological, and fifty on profane subjects, imagined he had formed a splendid
                    library. About the year 790 Charlemagne granted an unlimited right of hunting to
                    the abbot and monks of Sithin, for making their gloves and girdles of the skins
                    of the deer they killed, and covers for their books. We may imagine that these
                    religious were more fond of hunting than reading. It is certain that they were
                    obliged to hunt before they could read; and at least it is probable that, under
                    these circumstances, and of such materials, they did not manufacture many
                    volumes. At the beginning of the tenth century books were so scarce in Spain,
                    that one and the same copy of the bible, Saint Jerome’s Epistles, and some
                    volumes of ecclesiastical offices and martyrologies, often served several
                    different monasteries. Among the constitutions given to the monks of England by
                    Archbishop Lanfranc, in the year 1072, the following injunction occurs. At the
                    beginning of Lent the librarian is ordered to deliver a book to each of the
                    religious: a whole year was allowed for the perusal of this book, and at the
                    returning Lent those monks who had neglected to read the books they had
                    respectively received are commanded to prostrate themselves before the abbot,
                    and to supplicate his indulgence. This regulation was partly occasioned by the
                    low state of literature which Lantranc found in the English monasteries. But at
                    the same time it was a matter of necessity, and is in a great measure to be
                    referred to the scarcity of copies of useful and suitable authors. In an
                    inventory of the goods of John de Pontissara, bishop of Winchester, contained in
                    his capital palace of Wulvesey, all the books which appear are nothing more than
                    <hi rend="italic">Septendecim sp&gt;ecies librorum de diversis scientiis.</hi>
                    This Avas in the year 1294. The same prelate, in the year 1299, borrows of his
                    cathedral convent of St SAvithin at Winchester, <hi rend="italic">Bibliam bene
                    glossatam;</hi> that is, the bible Avith marginal annotations, in two large
                    folio volumes; but gives a bond for due return of the loan, drawn up with great
                    solemnity. This bible had been bequeathed to the convent the same year by
                    Pontissara’s predecessor, Bishop Nicholas de Ely; and in consideration of so
                    important a bequest, that is, <hi rend="italic">pro bona Biblia dicti episcopi
                    bene glossata,</hi> and one hundred merks in money, the monks founded a daily
                    mass for the soul of the donor. When a single book Avas bequeathed to a friend
                    or relation, it was seldom Avithout many restrictions and stipulations. If any
                    person gave a book to a religious house, he believed that so valuable a donation
                    merited eternal salvation; and he offered it on the altar Avith great ceremony.
                    The most formidable anathemas Avere peremptorily denounced against those <hi rend="smallcaps">av1io</hi> should dare to alienate a book presented to the
                    cloister or library of a religious house. The prior and convent of Rochester
                    declare that they will every year pronounce the irrevocable sentence of
                    damnation on him who shall purloin or conceal a Latin translation of Aristotle’s
                    Physics, or even obliterate the title. Sometimes a book Avas given to a
                    monastery on condition that the donor should have the use of it during his life;
                    and sometimes to a private person, with the reservation that he who receives it
                    should pray for the soul of his benefactor. The gift of a book to Lincoln
                    Cathedral by Bishop Repingdon, in the year 1422, occurs in this form, and under
                    these curious circumstances. The memorial is written in Latin with the bishop’s
                    own hand, which I Avill give in English, at the beginning of Peter’s Breviary of
                    the Bible. ‘ I Philip of Repyndon, late bishop of Lincoln, give this book,
                    called <hi rend="italic">Peter de Areolis,</hi> to the new library to be built
                    within the church of Lincoln; reserving<pb break="no" facs="nls:193199390" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9390-0775"/> the use and
                    possession of it to Richard Trysely, clerk, canon, and prebendary, of Miltoun,
                    in fee, and to the term of his life; and afterwards to be given up and restored
                    to the said library, or the keepers of the same, for the time being, faithfully,
                    and without delay. Written with my own hand, <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi>
                    1422.’ When a book was bought, the affair was of so much importance, that it was
                    customary to assemble persons of consequence and character, and to make a formal
                    record that they were present on this occasion. Among the royal manuscripts in
                    the book of the Sentences of Peter Lombard, an archdeacon of Lincoln has left
                    this entry: ‘ This book of the Sentences belongs to master Robert archdeacon of
                    Lincoln, which he bought of Geoffrey the chaplain, brother of Henry vicar of
                    Northelkington, in the presence of master Robert de Lee, master John of Lirling,
                    Richard of Luda clerk, Richard the almoner, the said Henry the vicar, and his
                    clerk, and others; and the said archdeacon gave the said book to God and St
                    Oswald, and to Peter abbot of Barton, and the convent of Barden.’ The disputed
                    property of a book often occasioned the most violent altercations. Many claims
                    appear to have been made to a manuscript of Matthew Paris, belonging to the
                    last-mentioned library; in which John Russel, bishop of Lincoln, thus
                    conditionally defends or explains his right of possession. ‘ If this book can be
                    proved to be or to have been the property of the exempt monastery of St Alban,
                    in the diocese of Lincoln, I declare this to be my mind, that in that case I use
                    it at present as a loan under favour of those monks who belong to the said
                    monastery. Otherwise, according to the condition under which this book came into
                    my possession, 1 will that it shall belong to the college of the blessed
                    Winchester Mary at Oxford, of the foundation of William Wykham. Written with my
                    own hand at Buck-dane, 1st Jan. <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 1488. Jo.
                    Lincoln. Whoever shall obliterate or destroy this writing, let him be anathema.’
                    About the year 1225, Roger de Insula, dean of York, gave several Latin bibles to
                    the university of Oxford, with a condition that the students who perused them
                    should deposit a cautionary pledge. The library of that university, before the
                    year 1300, consisted only of a few tracts, chained or kept in chests in the
                    choir of St Mary’s church. In the year 1327 the scholars and citizens of Oxford
                    assaulted and entirely pillaged the opulent Benedictine abbey of the
                    neighbouring town of Abingdon. Among the books they found there were one hundred
                    psalters, as many grayles, and forty missals, which undoubtedly belonged to the
                    choir of the church; but besides these there were only twenty-two <hi rend="italic">codices,</hi> which 1 interpret books on common subjects. And
                    although the invention of paper at the close of the eleventh century contributed
                    to multiply manuscripts, and consequently to facilitate knowledge, yet, even so
                    late as the reign of our Henry VI. I have discovered the following remarkable
                    instance of the inconveniences and impediments to study, which must have been
                    produced by a scarcity of books. It is in the statutes of St Mary’s College at
                    Oxford, founded as a seminary to Oseney Abbey in the year 1446: <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Let no scholar occupy a book in the library above one
                    hour, or two hours at most, so that others be hindered from the use of the
                    same.’ The famous library established in the university of Oxford by that
                    munificent patron of literature Humphrey duke of Gloucester, contained only 600
                    volumes. About the commencement of the fourteenth century there were only four
                    classics in the royal library of Paris. These were one copy of Cicero, Ovid,
                    Lucan, and Boethius. The rest were chiefly books of devotion, which included but
                    few of the fathers; many treatises of astrology, geomancy, chiromancy, and
                    medicine, originally written in Arabic, and translated into Latin or French;
                    pandects, chronicles, and romances. This collection was principally made by
                    Charles V., who began his reign in 1365. This monarch was passionately fond of
                    reading; and it was the fashion to send him presents of books from every part of
                    the kingdom of France. These he ordered to be elegantly transcribed and richly
                    illuminated; and he placed them in a tower of the Louvre, from thence called <hi rend="italic">La Tour de la Libraire.</hi> The whole consisted of 900 volumes.
                    They were deposited in three chambers, which on this occasion were wainscotted
                    with Irish oak, and ceiled with cypress curiously carved. The windows were of
                    painted glass, fenced with iron bars and copper wire. The English became masters
                    of Paris in the year 1425, on which event the duke of Bedford, regent of France,
                    sent the whole library, then consisting of only 853 volumes, and valued at 2223
                    livres, into England, where perhaps they became the ground-work of Duke
                    Humphrey’s library just mentioned. Even so late as the year 1471, when Louis XI.
                    of France borrowed the works of the Arabian physician Rhasis from the faculty of
                    medicine at Paris, he not only deposited, by way of pledge, a quantity of
                    valuable plate, but was obliged to procure a nobleman to join with him as surety
                    in a deed, by which he bound himself to return it under a considerable
                    forfeiture. Of the excessive prices of books in the middle ages there are
                    numerous and curious proofs. I will mention a few only. In the year 1174 Walter,
                    prior of St Swithin’s at Winchester, afterwards elected abbot of Westminster, a
                    writer in Latin of the lives of the bishops who were his patrons, purchased of
                    the monks of Dorchester in Oxfordshire, Bede’s Homilies and St Austin’s Psalter,
                    for twelve measures of barley, and a pall, on which was embroidered in silver
                    the history of St Birinus converting a Saxon king. Among the royal manuscripts
                    in the British Museum there is Comestor’s Scholastic History in French, which,
                    as it is recorded in a blank page at the beginning, was taken from the king of
                    France at the battle of Poictiers; and being purchased by William Montague, earl
                    of Salisbury, for 100 marcs, was ordered to be sold by the last will of his
                    Countess Elizabeth for forty livres. About the year 1400 a copy of John of
                    Meun’s <hi rend="italic">Roman de la Roze,</hi> was sold at Paris for forty
                    crowns, or L.33. 6s. 6d.” (Warton’s <hi rend="italic">History of English
                    Poetry,</hi> vol. i. For further information regarding books, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Book-binding,</hi> the
                    art of gathering together and sewing the sheets of a book, and covering it.</p></div></body></text></TEI>