<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-5139-0448-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BATHURST, Ralph</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 448</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193195139" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BATHURST, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ralph</hi></label>, M. D. an
                    eminent physician, poet, and divine, was born in the year 1620. He studied
                    divinity in Trinity College, Oxford; but the civil commotions ensuing, he
                    changed the course of his studies, and applying himself to physic, took a
                    doctor’s degree in that faculty. By dint of assiduous application, he soon rose
                    to eminence in his profession, and in the time of the commonwealth was appointed
                    physician to the state. At the restoration, however, he quitted the practice of
                    physic; was elected a fellow of the Royal Society, and president of his college;
                    and, having entered into holy orders, was made chaplain to the king, and
                    afterwards dean of Wells. Soon after, he filled the office of vice-chancellor of
                    Oxford, and was nominated by King William and Queen Mary to the see of Bristol;
                    but this honour he declined. His learning and talents were various. To the
                    accomplishments of an orator, philosopher, and poet, he added an inexhaustible
                    fund of wit, and was a facetious companion at eighty years of age. Ridicule was
                    the weapon with which he used to correct the delinquents of his college; and he
                    was so absolute a master of it, that he had it always at command. His poetical
                    pieces in the <hi rend="italic">Musae Anglicanes</hi> are excellent in their
                    kind. He wrote several poems, both in English and Latin, and died on the 14th
                    June 1704, in the eighty-fourth year of his age.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bathurst,</hi><hi rend="italic">Allen,</hi> earl of
                    Bathurst, one of the last luminaries of Queen Anne’s reign, was born in the year
                    1684. His studies and education were equally conducive to the brilliant figure
                    he was destined to make in social life and in the senate, as a polite scholar,
                    patriot, and statesman. These talents he had an opportunity of displaying as
                    early as the year 1705, when, at the request of his father Sir Benjamin
                    Bathurst, and the solicitation of the constituency of Cirencester, he served in
                    parliament for that borough, his native place, with reputation and integrity. He
                    distinguished himself particularly in the struggles and debates relative to the
                    union between the two kingdoms; firmly supporting a measure which he thought
                    calculated to strengthen the government and add to the prosperity of the
                    country. Though he was contented to act a subordinate part in the opposition
                    plannedbyMr Harley and Mr St John, ħis intimate friends, in order to sap the
                    credit of the duke of Marlborough and his adherents, nevertheless he did good
                    service to his party by arraigning, with more eloquence than truth, the conduct
                    of the general and of the earl of Godolphin, whom he accused of lavishing the
                    treasures of the nation on conquests more splendid than serviceable. The loss of
                    the battle of Almanza, which happened about this time, seconded his efforts and
                    those of his associates in dispelling what they called the intoxication of
                    former successes, and disparaging achievements which reflect immortal honour on
                    the British name. But his personal regard for Lord Somers, president of the
                    council, suffered no abatement, although they were of different opinions in
                    polities; and when that great man was deprived of office Mr Bathurst acted with
                    such tenderness and delicacy as to preserve his esteem in a private station. In
                    consideration of his zeal and services, the queen, in 1711, advanced him to the
                    peerage by the title of Baron Bathurst, of Bat-tlesden, in Bedfordshire.</p>
                <p>His lordship continued to speak his sentiments with undaunted freedom in the
                    upper house, and became a vigorous opponent of the court measures in the reign
                    of George I. and during Sir Robert Walpole’s administration. The acrimony of the
                    prosecutions carried on against the earl of Oxford, Lord Bolingbroke, and the
                    duke of Ormond, stimulated his indignation against such vindictive proceedings;
                    and he observed, “that the king of a faction was but the sovereign of half his
                    subjects.”</p>
                <p>The South Sea Scheme having infected all classes with a spirit of wild
                    speculation, when the people awoke from their delirium a vast number of families
                    were involved in ruin. Lord Bathurst publicly impeached the directors, whose
                    arts had enabled them to amass enormous fortunes during the prevalence of the
                    mania; he represented that the national honour was concerned in stripping them
                    of their ill-gotten wealth; and he moved for having all the directors of the
                    South Sea Company punished for their sordid knavery, by the forfeiture of their
                    estates.</p>
                <p>When the bill was brought into the house of lords against Dr Atterbury, bishop of
                    Rochester, that learned prelate, who to the graces of dictioń and style united
                    the accomplishment of a just delivery, made a conquest of Lord Bathurst, who was
                    one of the many friends whom the bishop’s eloquence, politeness, and ingenuity
                    had procured him. His lordship spoke against the bill with great vehemence and
                    propriety, observing, “that if such extraordinary proceedings were countenanced,
                    he saw nothing remaining for him and others to do, but to retire to their
                    countryhouses, and there, if possible, quietly to enjoy their estates within
                    their own families, since the least correspondence or intercepted letter might
                    be made criminal.” Then turning to the bishops, he said, he “could hardly
                    account for the inveterate hatred and malice some persons bore the ingenious
                    bishop of Rochester, unless it was that they were infatuated like the wild
                    Americans, who fondly believe they inherit not only the spoils, but even the
                    abilities, of the man they destroy.” He was one of the lords who entered his
                    protest against the bill.</p>
                <p>Lord Bathurst concurred with all his might in the opposition to Sir Robert
                    Walpole, who now tottered on the brink of ruin. And when, after an obstinate
                    struggle, this minister was forced to resign all his employments, Lord Bathurst
                    was sworn of the privy council, and made captain of the gentlemen pensioners, a
                    post which he resigned in 1744. In 1757 he was appointed treasurer to George
                    III. then prince of Wales, and continued in the list of privy counsellors at
                    that monarch’s accession to the throne; but, on account of his advanced age, he
                    preferred enjoying his <hi rend="italic">otium cum dignitate,</hi> to embarking
                    again in political contentions.</p>
                <p>Lord Bathurst’s integrity gained him the esteem even of his opponents, while his
                    humanity and benevolence procured him the affection of all who knew him more
                    intimately; and he added to his public virtues all the good breeding,
                    politeness, and elegance, of social intercourse. Congreve, Vanbrugh, Swift,
                    Prior, Rowe, Addison, Pope, Arbuthnot, Gay, and most of the men of genius of his
                    own time, cultivated his friendship, and were proud of his correspondence.
                    Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Epistle on the Use of Piches</hi> is addressed to Lord
                    Bathurst, whom the bard of Twickenham compliments in some highly characteristic
                    lines. Sterne, too, in his letters to Eliza, speaks of him in terms of
                    affectionate<pb break="no" facs="nls:193195152" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5152-0449"/>
                    admiration. “This nobleman,” says he, “is an old friend of mine: he was always
                    the protector of men of wit and genius, and has had those of the last century
                    always at his table. The manner in which his notice began of me was as singular
                    as it was polite. He came up to me one day as I was at the princess of Wales’
                    court. &lt; I want to know you, Mr Sterne; but it is fit you should know also
                    who it is that wishes this pleasure: you have heard,’ continued he, ‘ of an old
                    Lord Bathurst, of whom your Popes and Swifts have sung and spoken so much: I
                    have lived my life with geniuses of that cast, but have survived them; and
                    despairing ever to find their equals, it is some years since I closed my
                    accounts, and shut up my books, with thoughts of never opening them again: but
                    you have kindled a desire in me of opening them once more before I die, which I
                    now do; so go home and dine with me.’ This nobleman, I say, is a prodigy: for at
                    eighty-five he has all the wit and promptness of a man of thirty; a disposition
                    to be pleased, and a power to please others, beyond what I ever knew; added to
                    which, a man of learning, courtesy, and feeling.”</p>
                <p>His lordship, in the latter part of his life, preserved his natural cheerfulness
                    and vivacity, remaining always accessible, hospitable, and beneficent. Latterly
                    he delighted in rural amusements, and enjoyed, with philosophical satisfaction,
                    the shade of the lofty trees he had planted himself. Till within a month of his
                    death he regularly rode out on horseback two hours before dinner, and drank his
                    bottle of claret or Madeira after it. He used to observe jocularly that he could
                    never think of adopting Dr Cadogan’s method, although Dr Cheyne had assured him
                    fifty years before, that he would not live seven years longer unless he abridged
                    himself of his wine. This was not doctrine at all suited to his lordship’s
                    taste, or at least to his lordship’s practice. For, shortly before his death,
                    having invited some friends to spend a few cheerful days with him at his seat at
                    Cirencester, and being one evening very loth to part with them, his son, the
                    late chancellor, who was present, objected to their sitting up any longer,
                    adding that health and long life were best secured by regularity. The father
                    thought and acted otherwise. He suffered the learned lord to retire, after
                    delivering himself of the above admonition; but,as soon as he was
                    gone,exclaimed,“Come, my good friends, since the old gentleman is gone to bed, I
                    think we may venture to crack another bottle.”</p>
                <p>Lord Bathurst was advanced to the dignity of earl in 1772, and lived to see his
                    eldest son promoted to the peerage by the title of Baron Apsley, and several
                    years lord high chancellor of Great Britain. His lordship married Catharine,
                    daughter of Sir Peter Apsley, by whom he had two other sons, and five daughters.
                    His death happened, after a few days illness, at his scat near Cirencester, in
                    the ninty-first year of his age, and on the 16th of September 1775.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
