<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-2853-0753-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUTLER, Charles (7th edition, volume 5, page
                    753)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:843075">Butlers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193742853?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUTLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi></label>, a native
                    of Wycomb, in the county of Bucks, and a master of arts in Magdalen College,
                    Oxford, who published a book entitled “The Principles of Music in singing and
                    setting; with the twofold use thereof, ecclesiastical and civil.” 4to, London,
                    1636. The author of this book was a person of singular learning and ingenuity,
                    which he manifested in sundry other works enumerated by Wood in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Aihenae Oxonienses.</hi> Among these is an English Grammar,
                    published in 1633, in which he proposes a scheme of regular orthography, and
                    makes use of characters, some borrowed from the Saxon, and others of his own
                    invention, which it is impossible to represent by means of ordinary types; and
                    of this imagined improvement he appears to have been so fond, that all his
                    tracts are printed in the same manner as his grammar; the consequence of which
                    has been an almost general disgust at every thing he has written. His treatise
                    on the Principles of Music is, however, a very learned, curious, and
                    entertaining book; and, by the help of the advertisement from the printer to the
                    reader, prefixed to it, explaining the powers of the several characters made use
                    of by him, may be read to great advantage, and may also be considered as a
                    judicious supplement to Morley’s introduction.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Butler,</hi><hi rend="italic">Samuel,</hi> a celebrated
                    poet, was the son of a respectable Worcestershire farmer, and was born in 1612.
                    He passed some time at Cambridge, but was never matriculated in that university.
                    Returning to his native country, he lived some years as clerk to a justice of
                    peace, and found sufficient time to apply himself to history., poetry, and
                    painting. Being recommended to Elizabeth, countess of Kent, he enjoyed in her
                    house not only the use of all kinds of books, but the conversation of the
                    illustrious Selden, who often employed Butler to write letters, and translate
                    for him. He lived also some time with Sir Samuel Luke, a gentleman of an ancient
                    family in Bedfordshire, and a famous commander under Oliver Cromwell; and he is
                    supposed at this time to have written, or at least to have planned, his
                    celebrated <hi rend="italic">Hudibras,</hi> and under that character to have
                    ridiculed the knight. The poem itself furnishes this key in the first canto,
                    where Hudibras says</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> 'Tis sung, there is a valiant Mameluke </l>
                    <l part="N"> In foreign land yclep’d — — </l>
                    <l part="N"> To whom we oft have been compar’d </l>
                    <l part="N"> For person, parts, address, and beard. </l>
                </lg>
                <p>After the Restoration, Mr Butler was appointed secretary to the Earl of Carbury,
                    lord president of Wales, who appointed him steward of Ludlow Castle when the
                    court was revived there. No one proved a more generous friend to him than the
                    Earl of Dorset and Middlesex, to whom it was owing that the court relished his
                    <hi rend="italic">Hudibras,</hi> He had promises of a good place from the Earl
                    of Clarendon, but they were never accomplished; though the king was so much
                    pleased with the poem as often to quote it pleasantly in conversation. It is
                    indeed said that Charles ordered him the sum of L.3000; but the sum being
                    expressed in figures, somebody through whose hands the order passed reduced it,
                    by cutting off a cypher, to L.300, and though it passed the offices without
                    fees, it proved not sufficient to pay what he then owed; so that Butler was not
                    a shilling the better for the king’s bounty. He died in 1680; and, though he met
                    with many disappointments, he was never reduced to any thing like want, nor did
                    he die in debt. Mr Granger observes, that Butler “stands without a rival in
                    burlesque poetry. His <hi rend="italic">Hudibras”</hi> he adds, “is in its kind
                    almost as great an effort of genius as the <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>
                    itself. It abounds with uncommon learning, new rhymes, and original thoughts.
                    Its images are truly and naturally ridiculous. There are many strokes of
                    temporary satire, and some characters and allusions which cannot be discovered
                    at this distance of time.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Butler,</hi><hi rend="italic">Joseph,</hi> Bishop of Durham,
                    a prelate distinguished by his piety and learning, as well as by the depth and
                    originality of his metaphysical and ethical views, was the youngest son of Mr
                    Thomas Butler, a respectable shopkeeper at Wantage, in Berkshire, where he was
                    born in the year 1692. His father, who was a Presbyterian, observing that he had
                    a strong inclination to learning, sent him from a grammar-school where he had
                    been placed, to an academy in Gloucestershire, in order to qualify him for a
                    dissenting minister; and while there he wrote some remarks on Dr Clarke’s first
                    sermon at Boyle’s lecture. Afterwards, resolving to conform to the established
                    church, he studied at Oriel College, where he contracted an intimate friendship
                    with Mr Edward Talbot, son of the Bishop of Durham, and brother to the lord
                    chancellor, who laid the foundation of his subsequent advancement. Soon after
                    his admission into the university he took orders, and in 1718 he was appointed
                    preacher at the Rolls Chapel. He held this situation for about eight years, when
                    he published a volume of sermons delivered in that chapel, which elevated him to
                    great reputation as a profound and original thinker. The Bishop of Durham
                    bestowed upon him the rectory of Haughton, and afterwards that of Stanhope,
                    where he resided a considerable time, entirely devoted to the duties of his
                    pastoral functions. Through the recommendation of his friend and fellow-student
                    Seeker, afterwards Archbishop of Canterbury, he was in 1733 nominated chaplain
                    to the Lord Chancellor Talbot; and a prebend in the church of Rochester followed
                    this appointment. He now took the degree of LL.D., and in 1736 was appointed
                    clerk of the closet to the queen, whom he attended every day by her majesty’s
                    special command, from seven till nine in the evening. In the same year he
                    published his celebrated work <hi rend="italic">The Analogy of Religion, Natural
                    arid Revealed, to the Constitution and Course of Nature,</hi> which is allowed
                    to be the most original and profound work in any language on the philosophy of
                    religion, and has accordingly placed the author in the first rank of deep and
                    comprehensive thinkers. In 1738 Dr Butler was promoted to the bishopric of
                    Bristol, on the recommendation of Queen Caroline, who had a philosophical taste,
                    and highly esteemed this distinguished philosopher. Two years afterwards he was
                    made Dean of St Paul’s, when he resigned the living of Stanhope. In the year
                    1746 he was appointed clerk of the closet to the king, and in 1750 he obtained
                    his highest preferment, the bishopric of Durham. This rich benefice he, however,
                    enjoyed but a short time; for he died at Bath on the 16th of June 1752. His
                    corpse was interred in the cathedral at Bristol, where there is a monument, with
                    an inscription, erected to his memory. Dr Butler died a bachelor. His profound
                    and comprehensive mind appears sufficiently in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sermons</hi> at the Rolls Chapel, and in his celebrated work on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Analogy of Religion.</hi> An account of his character as a
                    philosopher has been drawn with great ability and discrimination by Sir James
                    Mackintosh, in his Dissertation on the Progress of Ethical Philosophy, prefixed
                    to this work. See vol. i. p. 343.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Butler,</hi> the name anciently given to an officer in the
                    court of France, being the same as the grand echanson or great cupbearer of
                    later times.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Butler,</hi> in the common acceptation of the word, is an
                    officer in the houses of princes and great men, whose principal business is to
                    look after the wine, plate, and other similar articles.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
