<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-2203-0703-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUNDELCUND, or Bandelkhand</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 703</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8br9k">Hens</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:955173">Hens</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1095872">Rest</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:938081">Garrisons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193742203" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUNDELCUND, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Bandelkhand</hi></label>,
                    an extensive district of the province of Allahabad, in Hindustan, between <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193742216" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2216-0704"/> the rivers Cane
                    and Betwah, occupying a superficies of about 11,000 square miles. The south-west
                    frontier lies in about 24° north latitude, and 80° 45' east longitude, and the
                    territory extends about two degrees farther north. In general the face of this
                    country is mountainous, high, and rocky; its vegetation is scanty, and the
                    inhabitants do not bestow much care on the cultivation of it. The summits of
                    many of the hills,, however, are covered with low copses, amidst which there is
                    but little grass interspersed. Other parts of the district exhibit a close
                    jungle; and there are portions, consisting of fertile soil, which are brought
                    under suitable culture. ,</p>
                <p>The most valuable of all fossils, diamonds, have been long found here,
                    particularly near the town of Purna or Pannah. The mines producing them are
                    situated in a range of hills called by the natives Bund-Ahill, extending above
                    twenty miles in length by between two and three in breadth, and are said to be
                    partitioned into twenty-one divisions; but we do not know that the whole belong
                    to Bundelcund. Of these, the mines of Maharajepoor, Raje-poor, Kimmerah, and
                    Guddaseah, contain the finest diamonds; and one dug from the last has been
                    reputed the largest in the world. It was kept in the fort of Callinger, among
                    other treasures of Rajah Himmut Bahadur. Several different rajahs are
                    proprietors of the mines, each having the charge of his own, without any
                    interest in the produce of the rest. A superintendent is appointed to inspect
                    the produce; and every diamond, when found, is registered, valued, and, if the
                    rajah does not choose to keep it, is offered for sale. When sold, he receives
                    two thirds of the value. In the reign of the emperor Acbar, the mines of Pannah
                    produced to the amount of L. 100,000 annually, and were then a considerable
                    source of revenue; but for many years they have not been nearly so profitable,
                    and it appears that about the year 1750 the government did not derive more from
                    them than about L.50,000 per annum. Their present value is not exactly known.
                    According to tradition, the mines were discovered by a fakir or religious
                    mendicant.</p>
                <p>The country at a distance from the mountains is agreeably diversified with
                    clusters of eminences or small hills, separate from each other, exhibiting a
                    picturesque appearance; and the inhabitants invariably build their villages at
                    the bottom of a hill. They are seldom seen in any situation, and it is chiefly
                    around the villages that the small quantity of grain raised in the district is
                    cultivated. But Bundelcund not being a fertile country in itself, grain is
                    brought from the banks of the Jumna and the Ganges. Many other commodities are
                    supplied from the Deccan, or middle region of the peninsula; and large herds of
                    bullocks are seen continually passing to the hilly part of the territory. The
                    forests abound with tigers, and the nhil-gau or white-footed antelope, as also
                    the wild boar, which are all hunted by the chief men of the country.</p>
                <p>he inhabitants, who are called Bondelas, are a brave and warlike people,
                    entertaining high notions of independence, and impatient of constraint or
                    indignity. They act under the full impulse of those violent passions which sway
                    the inhabitants of the East, and lead to catastrophes of a nature unknown to
                    Europeans. An instance of this once occurred, when the fortress of Adjyghur,
                    besieged by the British troops, was evacuated by the garrison. The removal of
                    the family of the refractory zemindar who had occasioned hostilities having been
                    directed, his father-in-law was desired to prepare the females of the family for
                    it. Instead of doing so, however, he murdered the whole with their children,
                    eight in number, and then put an end to his own existence. But what was still
                    more extraordinary, the perpetration of this horrible deed was apparently with
                    the consent of the sufferers,, and without any complaint from them. The Bondelas
                    are either Brahmins or Rajpoots. About Ditteah and Jhansi they are a stout and
                    handsome race of men, exhibiting an appearance of opulence and contentment. They
                    commonly go armed with a bow and spear, both of which are of excellent quality;
                    and they know very well how to use them. They testify no apprehension in
                    engaging veteran troops. Owing to the intestine commotions which long pervaded
                    this district, every man carried arms; and many, availing themselves of superior
                    force, attacked and plundered travellers, or levied contributions from them on
                    pretence of guarding the passes which they had necessarily to traverse among the
                    hills. Very little of their manners and customs is known. Women occasionally
                    burn themselves along with the bodies of their deceased husbands, according to a
                    remarkable religious principle diffused in the East, which now seems universally
                    on the decline. The inhabitants dwell in towns and villages, of which the latter
                    are much better than most others in India; and they have numerous strong forts,
                    which they are accustomed to take and defend with determined vigour.</p>
                <p>There are several considerable towns in the district, ∣ such as Pannah, Pirna, or
                    Purna, where the rajah resides, on account of its proximity to the diamond
                    mines; Chatterpoor, Ditteah, Callinger, Jyghtpoor, and Jhansi. Chatterpoor,
                    thirty miles distant from Pannah, and six hundred and ninety-eight from
                    Calcutta, is extensive and well built, the houses consisting chiefly of stone.
                    Formerly it was ih a flourishing condition, a place of great and active
                    commercial transactions, and a kind of depot for goods carried between the
                    Deccan and Mirzapour, which is also in the province of Allahabad, and one of the
                    principal trading towns of Hindustan. The goods were afterwards transported by
                    numerous bullocks and camels to the places of their destination; and so much
                    commerce was conducted here, that when Chatterpoor preserved its greatest
                    importance, the duties levied amounted to L.50,000 yearly. It was founded by one
                    of the rajahs of Bundelcund, and was occasionally his residence. Ditteah or
                    Dutteah is a large town, surrounded with a stone wall, and provided with gates.
                    It extends a mile and a half in length by nearly as much in breadth, and is
                    populous and well built, the houses being of stone, and covered with tiles. A
                    spacious edifice, with seven cupolas, stands at the north-west extremity, and
                    was the former residence of the rajahs; but a palace has recently been built for
                    them on an eminence without the town, close to which is a considerable lake. The
                    district of Ditteah was tributary to the Mahrattas, and the rajah could raise
                    two thousand horse and as many infantry, esteemed excellent troops. Some years
                    ago they testified how much they were to be dreaded, in an engagement with the
                    veteran forces under Μ. de Boyne, a famous French general in the Mahratta
                    service, where all the skill and ability <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> of the
                    commander could scarcely preserve the latter from destruction. But among the
                    most important places of Bundelcund is Callinger, the chief town of a
                    subdivision of this district, which seems to have once been an independent
                    government, and now includes ten pergunnahs or circles of villages. It has a
                    fortification built on a lofty rock, of great extent, and is deemed impregnable
                    by the natives. The walls are said to be six or seven miles in circuit; a
                    hundred and seventy pieces of cannon are mounted on them, and a garrison of five
                    thousand men is necessary for their defence. Nevertheless, its natural strength
                    has enabled a smaller number to sustain long sieges; and the earlier invaders of
                    Bundelcun have been compelled to retire, after unsuccessful blocka es protracted
                    during several years. So lately as the year 1810, the British army having
                    attempted to take it J storm, was repulsed with great slaughter. However, t <hi
                    rend="superscript"> e</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193742229"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0705-2229-0705"/>garrison of this fortress, probably dreading a
                    repetition of the assault, evacuated the place during the night. No fortress can
                    be more secure against the irregular approaches of an Indian army. Here the
                    rajah kept his military stores and treasure, and it was also the residence of
                    the Europeans in his service. It is twenty or thirty miles from Pannah, and lies
                    in 24° 58' north latitude. Jhansi is a considerable town, but smaller than
                    Ditteah, commanded by a stone fort on a high hill in 25° 31' north latitude, and
                    thirty-two miles distant from Chatterpoor. There is a district dependent on the
                    town, which, from having been seventy or eighty years in the uninterrupted
                    possession of the peshwa or chief of the Mahrattas, is in a more tranquil state,
                    and better cultivated, than most of the neighbouring territories, which have
                    undergone frequent changes. Hence it is frequented by caravans from various
                    commercial towns of India; and its wealth is augmented by a trade in cloths, and
                    the manufacture of carpets, bows, arrows, and spears, the principal arms of the
                    Bondela tribes. In the year 1790 it afforded a revenue of about L.50,000
                    annually. There is an ancient city called Ouncha, but now in decay, whose rajah
                    was formerly the head of all the tribes of Bundelcund, and from whom their
                    chiefs received tokens of their investiture. A castle which stands here, or in
                    the neighbourhood, resembles a Gothic building, and is said to have been erected
                    by a rajah of old, who in one day gave orders for building fifty-two forts. This
                    may account for the places of strength seen in Bundelcund, for which the
                    particular character of its surface is extremely favourable.</p>
                <p>Besides these, there are several towns, villages, and fortifications of
                    consequence in this district; but recent events have rendered the preservation
                    of the latter of less importance to their owners.</p>
                <p>From ancient times Bundelcund has been divided into many petty territories, whose
                    chiefs have incessantly disturbed the peace of their subjects by predatory
                    incursions on each other. The successful capture of strongholds in the mountains
                    was an encouragement to the subsistence of warfare; and in addition to the
                    numerous ordinary sources of dispute, it is not unlikely that their joint
                    interests in the diamond mines contributed to excite dissension. Though the
                    predominance of power induced some one of the contending parties to claim the
                    superiority, it was reluctantly acknowledged by the rest; and hence, instead of
                    a common bond of union to defend the country, it was weakened by the
                    distractions of the whole. The rajahs of Callinger are mentioned by Mahommedan
                    writers as early as the year 1008; but it does not appear to have been
                    incorporated with Bundelcund for several centuries afterwards. Some time in the
                    sixteenth century, it is said that a Bondela, living in Benares, removed to a
                    fort in the district of Ouncha, then governed by a rajah, whose confidence he
                    speedily obtained. This Bondela had a daughter of exquisite beauty, of whom the
                    rajah became enamoured, and demanded her in marriage. But her father,
                    considering the proposal as a grievous insult from one whom certain
                    circumstances now unknown prompted him to regard as his inferior in rank, he, in
                    concert with his daughter, plotted a diabolical revenge. Acquiescence was given
                    on the part of both; and the rajah was invited by his bride to the house of the
                    Bondela, where the ceremony was to be performed. Here a magnificent
                    entertainment was prepared, of which he partook plentifully along with his
                    attendants; but it was soon succeeded by excruciating tortures: poison had been
                    treacherously administered; and when the victims became incapable of lefence,
                    they were barbarously massacred. The Bondela -hen placed himself on the musnud
                    of the rajah, which <hi rend="superscript"> le</hi> enjoyed peaceably until his
                    death. He was succeeded by his son Ber Sing Deo, whose descendant is the rajah
                    of Ouncha; and he gained an accession of power by his services to the Soubahdar
                    of Allahabad. But he is accused of being a great plunderer; and his history is
                    stained by the assassination of the celebrated Abul Fazel, prime minister of
                    Acbar, which is said to have been committed by a banditti under his command.
                    Nay, it is affirmed that he acted in compliance with the wishes of Jehangeer,
                    the emperor’s son, who was jealous of Abul Fazel’s influence over his father,
                    and who, on his accession to the throne of Delhi, intrusted Ber Sing Deo with
                    the government of all Bundelcund, then called Dungush. On descending to a later
                    period, we find that this territory was invaded during the government of the
                    rajah Chattersaul, about the middle of last century, by the chief of
                    Furruckabad; and the rajah, to aid him in repelling the enemy, applied for
                    support to the peshwa, Sewai Bajerow. Success having attended them, he adopted
                    Sewai Bajerow as his son, and partitioned Bundelcund between him and his own
                    sons, allotting him a third of his dominions, the land revenue of which was
                    estimated at about L.1,300,000 sterling, but under an express stipulation that
                    his posterity should be protected by the peshwa in independent possession of the
                    remainder. The rest of his male issue, said to exceed fifty, were in a state of
                    dependence on their two brothers. In time this division opened the way to
                    dissensions, a civil war ensued, and the consequent weakness of the chiefs
                    afforded an opportunity for other invasions. Ali Bahauder, an illegitimate
                    grandson of Bajerow, held a command in the army of Scindia, the noted Mahratta
                    chief; and in the same army was the rajah Himmut Bahauder, who not only
                    commanded a great body of cavalry, but was the spiritual head and military
                    leader of a numerous sect of devotees called Gosseins. Both seem to have fallen
                    under the displeasure of the peshwa; and the latter, after retiring to his
                    estate in 1786, soon united with the other in attempting the conquest of
                    Bundelcund. The rajah Himmut seems to have had it in contemplation to establish
                    a sovereignty elsewhere; and about the year 1787 he was actively engaged in
                    assisting the prince Mirza Jurvaim Buklit in raising an army; but the death of
                    the latter, which happened suddenly in 1788, probably allowed him more leisure
                    to attend to the other object in view. He and his associates agreed that a large
                    portion of the territory to be conquered should be assigned to himself, and its
                    revenue applied to the support of certain troops which he engaged to maintain in
                    the service of Ali Bahauder. The projected invasion took place in 1789, when Ali
                    Bahauder conquered much of the district in the name of the peshwa, of whom he
                    rendered himself nearly independent; and in a short time the whole was subdued
                    except some fortresses, which the Mahrattas have never been able to reduce.</p>
                <p>Some years elapsed before the complete establishment of their authority; but an
                    arrangement was made with the peshwa, whereby he was acknowledged lord paramount
                    of all the conquests effected in Bundelcund by Ali Bahauder, who engaged to obey
                    him as his sovereign, and to pay him tribute. But the latter contrived to evade
                    both conditions; and, after being occupied fourteen years in endeavouring to
                    subjugate the country, died in 1802, during the blockade of Callinger, which,
                    during ten years, he had fruitlessly endeavoured to capture. All was succeeded
                    by his eldest son, Shumshere Bahauder, then absent at Poonah; and Himmut
                    Bahauder, who, to retain his own influence, had for years been exciting
                    disaffection among the different chiefs, now appointed a relation of Shumshere,
                    the young rajah, regent of Bundelcund until his return.</p>
                <p>A war next broke out between the British and the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193742242" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2242-0706"/>Mahrattas. Himmut Bahauder
                    endeavoured to accomplish the transference of this district to the former, while
                    Shumshere was determined to oppose them vigorously. In September 1803 Colonel
                    Powell crossed the river Jumna for the purpose of entering Bundelcund, and was
                    joined by Himmut, with a body of thirteen or fourteen thousand men. The united
                    forces, arriving on the banks of the river Cane, which passes the fort of
                    Callinger, and falls into the Jumna near the town of Oorah, found the army of
                    Shumshere on the opposite side. It was numerous, occupied a great extent, and
                    was strongly posted; but, after a short cannonade on both sides, it
                    precipitately retreated.</p>
                <p>At this time a proposal was made by the Mahrattas, and acceded to by the British,
                    for the cession of a portion of the territory of Bundelcund in lieu of certain
                    districts in the Deccan, which had been ceded to them by a former treaty. Forces
                    were then stationed in Bundelcund for the protection of other parts; and
                    successive engagements of a conciliatory nature were formed with Shumshere and
                    all the rest of the chiefs, whereby the British authority was rendered
                    paramount. Himmut Bahauder had previously secured an advantageous arrangement
                    for himself; and his death ensuing in the year 1804, government provided for his
                    family, and assumed possession of his territory. The troops who had been
                    retained in his service, a kind of irregular force, now dispersed. Still,
                    however, the tranquillity of the country was liable to be disturbed; and indeed
                    the cession of some parts of it by the Mahrattas was only nominal, as they had
                    never been able to occupy the strongholds themselves. Thus it was judged
                    expedient by the British to bestow a considerable tract in 1807 on a descendant
                    of the rajah Chattersaul, who had been long dispossessed amidst contending
                    factions, on condition of guarding the passes, and preserving his territory in
                    peace. Other arrangements were made, conceding to the chief of Calpee, on the
                    confines of Bundelcund, a portion of the interior, in lieu of the city and
                    district of Calpee, and several villages on the Jumna. Meantime it became
                    necessary to besiege the fortress of Callinger; but notwithstanding the British
                    forces had captured many strongholds of the Indians, previously deemed
                    impregnable, they were unsuccessful in attempting to take it by assault, and, as
                    already observed, gained possession by the garrison retiring in the night. Its
                    reduction proved a great accession of power, and tended materially to
                    tranquillize the district, which had previously been incorporated with the
                    British empire in the East, and a civil establishment constituted for the
                    regular management of its affairs.</p>
                <p>The possession of a country such as Bundelcund, occuPy <hi rend="superscript">
                    in</hi> g 11,θθ0 square miles, is of considerable consequence in several
                    respects; and it has been suggested that the revenue derived from it might be
                    materially augmented, by assuming the direction of the diamond mines of Pannah.
                    Nevertheless the occupation of the whole does not seem to have been judged an
                    important object, more especially as, by the arrangement above alluded to with
                    the chief of Calpee, he was left in the enjoyment of a third part of them, to
                    which he was originally entitled.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
