<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0718-2541-0782-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">QUEBEC</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1201065">Publications</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1083449">Publicity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240888">Australasia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193542541?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">QUEBEC</label>, the capital of Lower Canada, is
                    situated upon the north-eastern extremity of a promontory called Cape Diamond,
                    three hundred and fifty feet above the water level, on the left bank of the
                    river St Lawrence. The rocky ridge upon which the city stands is formed by the
                    St Lawrence and the St Charles, the former river flowing to the southward of
                    Quebec, and the latter to the northward, and the junction taking place in front
                    of the town, where they expand into a considerable basin forming the harbour of
                    Quebec. The distance from the one river to the other, across the ridge, is
                    rather more than a mile. It is divided into two parts, Upper and Lower Quebec.
                    The latter is built at the base of the promontory, nearly on a level with
                    high-water mark. The communication from this to the upper town is by a long,
                    narrow, winding, and extremely steep street, which terminates close to the city
                    walls, at an elevation of two hundred feet above the river. Here Upper Quebec
                    commences, extending its limits considerably to the westward along the slope of
                    the ridge, and up the promontory towards the cape, within fifty or sixty yards
                    of its summit, which is crowned by the citadel. This part of the town contains
                    the government buildings, the residence of the governor, the military, and the
                    most opulent of the inhabitants, with the best and handsomest streets, and the
                    most agreeable mansions. The lower town is much more crowded and mean in
                    appearance, and is very filthy and inconvenient. The streets are narrow, the
                    foot-pavement being barely sufficient for a single passenger; the houses have a
                    gloomy and monotonous aspect, and many of them are said to be built of wood,
                    although there exists a statute forbidding the use of this material in the
                    construction of the main part of buildings, as a security against the dreadful
                    conflagrations which have so often desolated the cities of the west. The
                    warehouses are built of stone; and this ill-favoured portion of Quebec is the
                    chief seat of the commerce and traffic by which the city is enriched. Amongst
                    the public buildings may be mentioned the castle of St Louis, a huge vice-regal
                    chateau, supported by piers, and overhanging the precipice; the Hotel Dieu, the
                    Protestant and Catholic cathedrals, and a numbçr of other religious edifices;
                    the exchange, bank, court-house, hospitals,barracks, gaol, and others. There is
                    a French seminary or college, containing usually about two hundred pupils, and
                    other establishments connected with education. In the district of Quebec there
                    are five public or free schools, in the district of Montreal twenty-four, and in
                    the district of Three Rivers six public schools, under the superintendence of
                    the Board of Royal Institution for the Advancement of Learning, incorporated by
                    the provincial act 41st Geo. III. cap. 17. To this board the legislature makes
                    an annual grant. Each teacher is bound to instruct one third of the number of
                    pupils gratuitously, and in no case to charge more than three shillings and
                    fourpence per month. The visitors may vary the rate according to the number of
                    children in each family who attend school, and the circumstances of the parents.
                    There are also two grammar-schools, one at Quebec and another at Montreal,
                    supported by an annual grant of L.200 each from the Jesuit Estates Fund, with
                    L.90 and L.50 respectively for house-rent. These are also under the
                    superintendence of the Royal Institution. The system of instruction is that of
                    the public grammar schools of England. Twenty-six free scholars are admitted
                    into each of them. The rate of tuition for others is L.12 per annum. There are
                    also upwards of a thousand schools established under the provincial act 9 Geo.
                    IV. cap. 46, attended by about 45,600 scholars of both sexes. L.20 are allowed
                    to each teacher having at least twenty children under his care. These schools
                    are under the direction of trustees annually elected by the inhabitants. No
                    particular system of tuition is followed, but the Lancasterian is pursued in a
                    few of them. There are also several Roman Catholic colleges in the province, aud
                    a number of private seminaries for the higher branches of education. Besides
                    these, there were in Lower Canada, in 1835, 1170 elementary schools, attended by
                    21,014 boys and 16,654 girls, of whom 12,495 were taught gratis, and 25,173 were
                    paid for. The houses were mostly roofed with shingles, but many of those of a
                    better sort, and the public buildings and great warehouses, are covered with tin
                    or iron plates. There are several distilleries, breweries, tobacco, soap,
                    candle, and other manufactories. Excellent ships are built here, and every
                    variety of tradesmen may be found in the upper or lower town. Many of the shops,
                    or stores as they are called in America, are elegantly fitted up, and well
                    supplied with every commodity in demand. There are suburbs attached to each
                    town.</p>
                <p part="N">One of the leading features of Quebec is its fortifications, it being
                    the strongest place in America. “As a fortress,” says Mr Montgomery Martin,
                    “Quebec may now be ranked in the first class, the citadel, on the highest point
                    of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193542554?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0718-2554-0783"/> Cape Diamond, together with a formidable
                    combination of strongly constructed works, extending over an area of forty
                    acres. Small batteries, connected by ramparts, are continued from the edge of
                    the precipice to the gateway leading to the lower town, which is defended by
                    cannon of a large calibre, and the approach to it up Mountain Street (which
                    connects the upper and lower town) enfiladed and flanked by many large guns. A
                    line of defence connects with the grand battery a redoubt of great strength,
                    armed with twenty-four pounders, entirely commanding the basin and passage of
                    the river. Other lines add to the impregnability of Quebec if properly defended,
                    the possession of which may be said to give the mastery of Upper as well as of
                    Lower Canada.” To the west, and in front of the citadel, are the celebrated
                    plains of Abraham, where was achieved the victory which wrested Canada from
                    France, and annexed it to the British empire. An obelisk marks the field where
                    Wolf and Montcalm fought and perished. The basin or harbour of Quebec is very
                    beautiful, safe, and spacious, being sufficient to contain a hundred sail of the
                    line. The river St Lawrence is twelve miles broad above the city, but is here
                    contracted to one mile in breadth. The commerce of Quebec is considerable,
                    indeed nine tenths of the trade of Canada is carried on from this city. The
                    imports consist of British manufactures, wine, rum, and other spirits, sugar,
                    coffee, tea, salt, and tobacco. The exports, the produce of the Canadas, arc
                    ships’ masts, spars, timber, various kinds of prepared wood, pot and pearl ash,
                    fish, oil, seal-skins, pork, beef, butter, lard, live-stock, hides, castoreum,
                    capillaire, natural curiosities, wheat, Indian corn, and the like, as also furs;
                    and there is likewise a re-exportation of British fabrics, West India produce,
                    and teas. The imports into Lower Canada, during the year 1835, amounted to
                    L.l,496,376, and the exports to L.896,847, of which L.7750 was for fish,
                    L.30,590 for corn, and L.620,182 for wood. The amount of the paper currency in
                    1835 was L.268,88l, of which L.52,535 was in notes of the Quebec bank, and
                    L.216,346 in notes of the Montreal bank. The following table shows the amount of
                    shipping in 1835.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >countries.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="6" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Inwards.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Ç</p><p part="N"
                            >Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">&gt;uebec.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Montreal.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">St John’s.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Tons.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Tons.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Tons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Great Britain</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">869</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">277,125</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">78</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">19,984</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">British
                            colonies...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">21,158</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">27</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2,524</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">340</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">United States</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">24</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6,507</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">155</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1324;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">69,086</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Foreign
                            states....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">26</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6,700</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">210</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1105∣ail.4Ω0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">108</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">22,873</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1328</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">‘ 69,426</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Γ ’</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Men employed...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">13,425</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1134</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3422</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="6" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >Outwards.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Great Britain</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">946</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">300,097</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">69</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">17,893</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"/></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">British
                            colonies...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">14,003</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">28</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2,767</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">320</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">United States</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">397</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,678</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">820</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">68,607</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Foreign
                            states....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,477</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N"><hi rend="superscript">
                                    1</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">263</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1144</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">315,974 1 106</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">22,601</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">824</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">68,927</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Men employed...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">13,614</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1 1103</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2909</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">Emigration to Quebec was for many years carried on to a great extent;
                    the number of arrivals in the year 1832 being 51,746. The recent disturbances in
                    Canada, and the opening up of a new field for emigration in Australasia, have
                    combined to check the influx of Europeans, so that in the year 1836 they had
                    diminished to 27,728, in 1837 to 22,500, and in 1838 to only 4992. The seasons
                    of Quebec may be briefly noticed. Winter sets in towards the close of November,
                    and for several weeks heavy falls of snow, hail, and sleet, follow each other in
                    rapid succession. The snow falls very deep, and it is often a difficult matter
                    to keep even a narrow pathway open. Towards the end of December the weather
                    clears, and the solid sheet of snow which covers the surrounding country becomes
                    enlivened by multitudes of citizens, who now sally forth with horse, sledge, and
                    carriole, and drive along the smooth, and shining plain. In March the weather
                    gets mild, and even hot, and in April the ice of the St Lawrence breaks with a
                    mighty crash. May and June are generally wet; but July and August arc marked by
                    intense heat and the plague of insects. September is the most agreeable month;
                    but, in October, winter returns “to rule the inverted year.” Quebec was settled
                    by the French in the year 1608; taken by the English, first in 1629, and
                    afterwards in 1759; and finally ceded to us by the treaty of Paris in 1766. In
                    1776 an unsuccessful attack was made upon it by the Americans under General
                    Montgomery, who fell, together with about 7000 men. The population ' of Quebec
                    in 1825 amounted to 20,396, and in 1831 to 25,916. Long. 70. 72. W. from
                    Greenwich, Lat. 46. 48. N.</p>
                <p part="N">Since the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Canada</hi> in this work made its
                    appearance, a revolution has broken out in that part of the British empire, and
                    proved of so serious a nature as to cause a considerable loss of life both in
                    the field and upon the scaffold. It is not our purpose to enter into minute
                    details regarding either the origin of the revolt or the course of events. A
                    brief statement of the leading facts is all that can be given here. Since this
                    colony was annexed to the British crown, two parties have existed in it, the
                    French, the original settlers, or their descendants; and the British, or their
                    descendants, who were the subjugators of the province. The two races have never
                    amalgamated, but, on the contrary, their animosity to each other has been
                    aggravated by recent circumstances to such a degree, that it is constantly in
                    danger of breaking out in acts of open hostility. Although the British race are
                    possessed of the greatest wealth, intelligence, and enterprise, the French
                    Canadians have always been by far the most numerous class, and, on the ground of
                    their numerical superiority, they aspire to have the leading sway in the affairs
                    of the province. But, as the government of Canada is constituted, this has been
                    found impossible; for although they may preponderate in the lower house or house
                    of assembly, they are checked by the legislative council, the members of which
                    are not popularly elected, but chosen by the governor in the name of the
                    sovereign of Great Bri tain. It] is alleged by the house of assembly that abuse
                    of power has resulted from this mode of election; that extreme partiality to the
                    British, and neglect of the French, has been shown, not only in the formation of
                    the legislative council itself, but in the distribution of government]
                    appointments. Amongst the grievances of which they complained were, the tenures
                    act, the want of control over the public revenue of the province, and others,
                    which were embodied in a document transmitted to the imperial government in
                    1832-33. This memorial consisted of ninety-two resolutions, and was drawn up by
                    the leading men of the house of assembly. The substance of them was as follows:
                    Is/, That the legislative council should be elective; <hi rend="italic"
                        >2dly</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> that the executive council
                    should be converted into a ministry, responsible to the assembly; 3√∕y, that the
                    tenures act and land company’s act should be repealed; 4M⅞∕, that the crown
                    revenues should be surrendered unconditionally; <hi rend="italic">bthly,</hi>
                    that the management of the waste lands should be given up to them. And they
                    further declared, that they would pay no arrears, nor vote any civil list, until
                    these demands should be complied with. The arrears spoken of were the salaries
                    of public functionaries, which for several years had remained unpaid, being
                    stopped by the members of assembly. The delegates from Canada met with a patient
                    hearing from the committee appointed <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193542567?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0718-2567-0784"/>to
                    investigate the subject; but the British government refused to accede to the
                    propositions, and a scries of resolutions were carried in parliament, the
                    substance of which is as follows: 1s&lt;, That whilst no change could be made in
                    the mode of electing the legislative council, it was expedient to adopt measures
                    for securing to it a higher degree of public confidence; 2&lt;7Z <hi
                        rend="subscript"> j</hi> y, that whilst it was expedient to improve the
                    composition of the executive council, it was unadvisable to render it
                    responsible to the assembly; <hi rend="italic">3dly,</hi> that the title of the
                    land company was to remain inviolate; <hi rend="italic">⅛thly,</hi> “that as
                    soon as the legislative shall make provisions by law for discharging lands from
                    feudal dues and services, and for removing any doubts as to the incidents of the
                    tenure of land, in free and common soccage, it is expedient to repeal the Canada
                    tenures act, and the Canada trade act, so far as the latter relates to the
                    tenures of land in this province, saving, nevertheless, to all persons the
                    rights vested in them under or in virtue of those acts ;”· <hi rend="italic"
                        >r&gt;tMy,</hi> that provision should be made for paying arrears due; and,
                    lastly, “that it is expedient that the legislatures of Lower and Upper Canada
                    respectively be authorized to make provision for the joint regulation and
                    adjustment of questions respecting their trade and commerce, and of other
                    questions wherein they have a common interest.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Nothing has given rise to
                            greater discontent and heart-burnings than the provision made for the
                            support of the church by means of portions of land set apart for this
                            purpose. The grants of land, as a reward for public services, have
                            likewise been considered as very injurious. This cannot be better
                            explained than in the words of Lord Durham, in his Report on the affairs
                            of British North America.</p><p part="N">“The system of clergy reserves
                            was established by the act of 1791, commonly called the Constitutional
                            Act, which directed that, in respect of all grants made by the crown, a
                            quantity equal to one seventh of the land so granted should be reserved
                            for the clergy. A quantity equal to one seventh of all grants would be
                            one eighth of each township, or of all the public land. Instead of this
                            proportion, the practice has been, ever since the act passed, and in the
                            clearest violation of its provisions, to εet apart for the clergy in
                            Upper Canada a seventh of all the land, which is a quantity equal to a
                            sixth of the land granted. There have been appropriated for this purpose
                            300,000 acres, which, legally, it is manifest, belong to the public. And
                            of the amount for which clergy reserves have been sold in that province,
                            namely, L.317,000 (of which about L.100,000 have been already received
                            and invested in the English funds), the sum of about L.45,000 should
                            belong to the public.</p><p part="N">“In Lower Canada the same violation
                            of the law has taken place, with this difference, that upon every sale
                            of crown and clergy reserves, a fresh reserve for the clergy has been
                            made, equal to a fifth of such reserves. The result has been the
                            appropriation for the clergy of 673,567 acres, instead of 446,000, being
                            an excess of 227,559 acres, or half as much again as they ought to have
                            received. The Lower Canada fund already produced by sales amounts to
                            L.50,000, of which, therefore, a third, or about L.16,000, belong to the
                            public. If, without any reform of this abuse, the whole of the unsold
                            clergy reserves in both provinces should fetch the average price at
                            which such lands have hitherto sold, the public would be wronged to the
                            amount of about L.280,000; and the reform of this abuse will produce a
                            certain and almost immediate gain to the public of L.60,000. In
                            referring, for further explanation of this subject, to a paper in the
                            appendix, which has been drawn up by Mr Hanson, a member of the
                            commission of inquiry which I appointed for all the colonies, I am
                            desirous of stating my own conviction that the clergy have had no part
                            in this great misappropriation of the public property, but that it has
                            arisen entirely from heedless misconception, or some other error, of the
                            civil government of both provinces.</p><p part="N">“The great objection
                            to reserves for the clergy is, that those for whom the land is set apart
                            never have attempted, and never could successfully attempt, to cultivate
                            or settle the property, and that, by that special appropriation, so much
                            land is withheld from set- .tiers, and kept in a state of waste, to the
                            serious injury of all settlers in its neighbourhood. But it would be a
                            great mistake to suppose that this is the only practice by which such
                            injury has been, and still is, inflicted on actual settlers. In the two
                            Canadas especially, the practice of rewarding, or attempting to reward,
                            public services by grants of public land, has produced, and is still
                            producing, a degree, of injury to actual settlers which it is difficult
                            to conceive without having witnessed it. The very principle of such
                            grants is bad, inasmuch as, under any circumstances, they must lead to
                            an amount of appropriation beyond the wants of the community, and
                            greatly beyond the proprietor’s means of cultivation and settlement. .
                            In both the Canadas, not only has this principle been pursued with
                            reckless profusion, but the local executive governments have managed, by
                            violating or evading the instructions which they received from the
                            secretary of state, to add incalculably to the mischiefs that would have
                            arisen at all events.</p><p part="N">“In Upper Canada, 3,200,000 acres
                            have been granted to ‘ U. E. Loyalists,’ being refugees from the United
                            States, who settled in the province before 1767, and their children;
                            730,000 acres to militiamen, 450,000 acres to discharged soldiers and
                            sailors, 255,000 acres to magistrates and barristers, 136,000 acres to
                            executive councillors and their families, 50,000 acres to five
                            legislative councillors and their families, 36,900 acres to clergymen as
                            private property, 264,000 acres to persons contracting to make surveys,
                            92,526 acres to officers of the army and navy, 500,000 acres for the
                            endowment of schools, 48,520 acres to Colonel Talbot, 12,000 acres to
                            the heirs of General Brock, and 12,000 acres to Doctor Mountain, a
                            former bishop of Quebec; making altogether, with the clergy reserves,
                            nearly half of all the surveyed land in the province. In Lower Canada,
                            exclusively of grants to refugee loyalists, as to the amount of which
                            the crown lands’ department could furnish me with no information,
                            450,000 acres have been granted to militiamen, to executive councillors
                            72,000 acres, to Governor Milne about 48,000 acres, to Mr Cushing and
                            another upwards of 100,000 acres (as a reward for giving information in
                            a case of high treason), to officers and soldiers 200,000 acres, and to
                            ‘ leaders of townships’ 1,457,209 acres; making altogether, with the
                            clergy reserves, rather more than half of the surveyed lands originally
                            at the disposal of the crown.” ∙ '</p></note></p>
                <p part="N">On the 18th of August 1837, an extraordinary session of the parliament
                    of Lower Canada was called together by Lord Gosford, the governor-in-chief; but
                    the assembly again refused all supplies, and continued to decline exercising any
                    legislative functions. Confusion and disorganization now began to spread
                    throughout the whole social as well as political system of Canada. On the 23d of
                    October, a meeting of delegates, named by the different parishes in five
                    counties, was held at St Charles, in Lower Canada. The persons assembled were
                    addressed by Papineau, speaker of the house of assembly, and other individuals,
                    and a series of resolutions were passed expressing dissatisfaction with the
                    manner in which Canada was governed. That same day a meeting of the friends of
                    the constitution was held at Montreal, and resolutions were passed in favour of
                    supporting the government, and condemnatory of the revolutionary movements.
                    Disaffection now assumed the shape of insurrection, and anarchy was immediately
                    followed by bloodshed. The insurrection was suppressed without much difficulty
                    ∙, but the country still remains in a very unsettled condition. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(r. r.</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> r</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
