<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0326-0307-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARAMAIC LANGUAGES (9th edition, volume 2, page
                    307)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:892462">Dialectic</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="fast:992973">Lates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25g11">Dialects</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w849">Dialectics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n326/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARAMAIC LANGUAGES</label> are so called from <hi
                        rend="italic">Aram,</hi> a geographical term, which in old Semitic usage
                    designates nearly the same districts as the Greek word Syria. Aram, however,
                    does not include Palestine, while it comprehends Mesopotamia <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Heb.</hi> Aram of two rivers), a region which the Greeks frequently
                    distinguish from Syria proper. Thus the Aramaic languages may be geographically
                    defined as the Semitic dialects originally current in Mesopotamia and the
                    regions extending S. W. from the Euphrates to Palestine. Philologically these
                    dialects form a distinct group of Semitic languages (North Semitic), separated
                    by grammatical and lexical peculiarities alike from the Middle Semitic (Hebrew,
                    Phoenician) and from the South Semitic (Arabic, Ethiopie). Babylonia is not part
                    of Aram, and the Semitic language of the Assyrian and Babylonian-arrowhead
                    inscriptions is not Aramaic.</p>
                <p>All Aramaic dialects are characterised by poverty of vowels, by the disappearance
                    of many of the forms of internal declension so characteristic of the original
                    genius of Semitic speech, and by a tendency to analytical construction by the
                    aid of relative particles in place of the earlier usage of the construct state.
                    Along with these marks of degradation they retain some antique features lost in
                    Hebrew and Arabic, and in particular, generally present the oldest consonantal
                    forms, having mutes instead of sibilants and aspirates, in a way quite analogous
                    to the relation of Low to High Dutch. A special Aramaic peculiarity is the
                    enclitic use of the article as in modern Danish.</p>
                <p>The tribes of ancient Aram never possessed political unity, their settlements
                    being intersected by strips of desert with Arabian population. Thus, there must
                    have been from an early time considerable diversity of dialect within the group,
                    and apart from differences due to the very various ages of the extant
                    literature, we are able to divide Aramaic into two main branches, commonly known
                    as Chaldee and Syriac respectively, and distinguished partly by differences of
                    pronunciation and vocabulary, but more conclusively by differences of
                    grammatical flexion, especially in the verb. In comparison with the great age of
                    this branch of Semitic, the whole Aramaic literature is of comparatively late
                    date, and presents the languages in an advanced and in some sense exhausted
                    stage of development.</p>
                <p>The historical and geographical relations of Syriac and Chaldee respectively are
                    involved in some obscurity. As the entire Chaldee literature is of Jewish
                    origin, Hupfeld and others have attempted to refer the whole difference of this
                    language from Syriac to an infusion of Hebrew elements. This view, however, is
                    now generally given up, and it is agreed that Chaldee is no corrupt dialect, but
                    a genuine Aramaic development. But where and when did the Jews give up their old
                    language and adopt a foreign tongue <hi rend="italic">1</hi> The explanation
                    formerly adopted and embodied in the name Chaldee, which from the days of Jerome
                    has been commonly used to designate the Jewish Aramaic, is that the change took
                    place in Babylon. That the so-called Biblical Chaldee, in which considerable
                    portions of the books of Ezra and Daniel .are written, was really the language
                    of Babylon, was supposed to be clear from Dan. ii. 3, where the Chaldeans are
                    said to have spoken to the king in Aramaic, and accordingly the writer in the
                    following verse passes from Hebrew to that language. But the cuneiform
                    inscriptions show that the proper language of the Chaldeans was not Aramaic; and
                    an examination of the very large part of the Hebrew Old Testament written later
                    than the exile seems conclusively to prove that the substitution of Aramaic for
                    Hebrew as the vernacular of Palestine took place very gradually. Under the
                    Persian empire Aramaic was a sort of official language for the western
                    provinces, and the Hebrews were in constant contact with Aramaic populations, so
                    that the language of the many could not fail ultimately to supersede the
                    language of the few. Hence most scholars are now agreed in holding that the term
                    Chaldee is a misnomer, and that the dialect so called is really the language of
                    the South-Western Arameans, who were the immediate neighbours of the Jews.
                    Probably this doctrine would be no longer disputed but for the connection
                    between the question before us and that of the date and authorship of Daniel. In
                    any case, the substitution of Aramaic for Hebrew as the vernacular of Palestine
                    was completed before the time of Christ, and it is this dialect (not the
                    language of the Old Testament Scriptures) which is designated in the New
                    Testament as “Hebrew.” The old Hebrew Scriptures were understood only by the aid
                    of interpretations, which, at first oral, were set down in writing in the early
                    centuries of our era, and form after the Biblical Chaldee the second main
                    element of Chaldee literature, the so-called Targums. These versions or
                    paraphrases arose partly in the Palestinian, partly in the Babylonian schools,
                    and accordingly display considerable variety of dialect—the Palestinian Targums
                    approaching most nearly to the Aramaic of Daniel and Ezra. But the Aramaic of
                    the Targums is again very different from the language of every day life, as
                    presented in the Talmuds of Babylon and Jerusalem. The Talmudic dialects show
                    extreme phonetic and grammatical decay, but have hitherto been very inadequately
                    investigated. The Aramaic of the Babylonian Talmud is more nearly allied to the
                    Aramaic of the East than to the language of Palestine.</p>
                <p>Of much greater historical importance than these Jewish dialects is the Aramaic
                    of the north and east, which rose to a literary language under the name of
                    Syriac, in the Chrstian schools of North Mesopotamia. Like so many other
                    languages, the Syriac first received stable literary form by the translation of
                    the Bible, the so-called Peshito. On this basis the language was assiduously
                    cultivated for many centuries, especially in the renowned schools of Edessa and
                    Nisibis, and possesses a very large literature, in which theology has a leading
                    place, but which is also strong in other forms of composition, as history and
                    poetry, and even extends into the domain of Occidental philosophy and science.
                    The treatment of the latter subjects in a Semitic speech was rendered possible
                    by the very great infusion of Greek elements (not merely technical terms, but
                    even particles and the like) brought into the language by long centuries of
                    Greek domination and culture. The period during which Syriac literature was most
                    flourishing extends from the 4th to the 10th Christian century. From the later
                    date onward, the language began to give way to Arabic, though some very
                    distinguished authors, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> Barhebraeus, wrote as late
                    as the 13th century. Even now the Syriac is used to some extent as the
                    ecclesiastical <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n327/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0327-0308"/> language of various bodies of Christians,
                    Jacobites, Nes-torians, and Maronites. The systematic study of Syriac by
                    grammars and lexicons was commenced pretty early. Of native grammarians, may be
                    mentioned Jacob of Edessa (7th century) and Barhebraeus; of lexicographers,
                    Bar-Ali and Bar-Bahlul (9th and 10th centuries respectively). By the Maronites
                    the study of Syriac was transplanted to Europe in the 16th century. A corrupt
                    dialect (NeoSyriac) is still spoken in some districts near Mosul, in
                    Antilibanus, &lt;fcc., and has been grammatically handled by Stoddart, Noldeke,
                    and others. Besides the two main branches of Aramaic already discussed, several
                    minor Aramaic dialects claim to be noticed. The Samaritan dialect, spoken by the
                    mixed population introduced into Northern Palestine after the deportation of the
                    Ephraim-ites, has long been superseded as a living tongue by Arabic, but is
                    still the sacred language of the Samaritan communities. The most important
                    literary monument of this dialect is the Samaritan translation of the
                    Pentateuch; but we possess also Samaritan liturgies and other remains. Another
                    written dialect is the Mandean, the language of a mystical sect on the Euphrates
                    and Tigris, whose <hi rend="italic">Book of Adam</hi> has been edited by
                    Norberg. Other dialects are known only from inscriptions, as the dialect of the
                    Hauran, and that of certain Egyptian monuments.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Helps to the Study of the Aramaic Dialects.—</hi> There is as
                    yet no good Grammar of the Chaldee dialects. That most commonly used is Winer’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Grammatik des biblischen und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >targumischen ChdUdaismus,</hi>-which has passed through several editions,
                    and of which there is an .American translation by Riggs. Luzzato’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Elementi grammaticali</hi><hi rend="italic">del Caldeo Biblico
                        e del dialetto Talmudico Babilonese</hi> (Padua, 1865) is in some respects
                    preferable to Winer. The <hi rend="italic">Chaldäische Grammatik</hi> of Fuerst
                    (Leipsic, 1835) is unfinished. The best Chaldee Lexicon is still the old <hi
                        rend="italic">Lexicon</hi><hi rend="italic">Chaldaicum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Talmudixum</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Rabbinicum</hi>
                    of Buxtorf (Basil, 1640). The worthless modern reprint by Fischer is to be
                    avoided, but the <hi rend="italic">Chaldäisches</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Wδrterbuch</hi> of J. Levy, 2 vols. Leipsic, 1867-68, may be used with
                    caution. On the controversy as to the real character of the Chaldee dialects,
                    the student may be referred to the books of introduction to the Old Testament,
                    especially to Schrader’s edition of De Wette, which gives full references to
                    relevant literature. Of recent Syriac Grammars may be mentioned those of
                    Hoffmann <hi rend="italic">(Grammatical</hi><hi rend="italic">Syriacae</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">III.,</hi> Halae, 1827) and
                    Uhlemann <hi rend="italic">(Grammatik der Syrischen Sprache,</hi> 2 Aufl.,
                    Berlin, 1857) in Germany, and of Cowper (London, 1858) in English. An elaborate
                    and pretentious reconstruction of Hoffmann’s Grammar by Professor Merx of
                    Tübingen, treats all the Aramaic dialects, but is not yet finished (part i.
                    1867, part ii. 1870). The Grammar of Amira (Rome, 1596) is still referred to.
                    There is no complete Syriac Lexicon adequate to modern requirements. Michaelis’s
                    edition of Castellus (Gottingen, 1788), and Schaafs <hi rend="italic">Lexicon
                        Concordantiale</hi> to the New Testament (Leyden, 1708), are valuable; and a
                    great Thesaurus, compiled from numerous sources, and from the collections of
                    several scholars, is now being published by the Clarendon Press under the
                    editorship of Dr Payne Smith. On the Samaritan literature see the introduction
                    to Nutt’s <hi rend="italic">Fragments of a Samaritan Tar gum,</hi> London, 1874.
                    There is a Samaritan Grammar by Uhlemann (Leipsic, 1837), and an Essay on the
                    Mandean dialect by Noldeke (Göttingen, 1862). The Aramaic inscriptions have been
                    investigated by Gesenius, De Vogué, Noldeke, and others. (W. R. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
