<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0561-0502-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARIOSTO, Lodovico</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 502</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hs61">Moslems</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n561/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARIOSTO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lodovico</hi></label>, one of
                    the greatest poets of Italy, was born at Reggio, in Lombardy, on the 8th Sept.
                    1474. His father was Niccolo Ariosto, commander of the citadel of Reggio. He
                    showed a strong inclination to poetry from his earliest years, but was obliged
                    by his father to study the law—a pursuit in which he lost five of the best years
                    of his life. Allowed at last to follow his inclination, he applied himself to
                    the study of the classics under Gregorio da Spoleti. But after a short time,
                    during which he read the best Latin authors, he was deprived of his teacher by
                    Gregorio’s removal to France as tutor of Prince Sforza. Ariosto thus lost the
                    opportunity of learning Greek, as he intended. His father dying soon after, he
                    was compelled to forego his literary occupations to undertake the management of
                    the family, whose affairs were embarrassed, and to provide for his nine brothers
                    and sisters, one of whom was a cripple. He wrote, however, about this time some
                    comedies in prose and a few lyrical pieces. Some of these attracted the notice
                    of the cardinal Ippolito of Este, who took the young poet under his patronage,
                    and appointed him one of the gentlemen of his household. This prince usurped the
                    character of a patron of literature, whilst the only reward which the poet
                    received for having dedicated to him the <hi rend="italic">Orlando Furiosο,</hi>
                    was the question, “Where did you find so many stories, Master Ludovic <hi
                    rend="italic">V</hi> ’ The poet himself tells us that the cardinal was
                    ungrateful; deplores the time which he spent under his yoke; and adds, that if
                    he received some niggardly pension, it was not to reward him for his poetry,
                    which the prelate despised, but to make some just compensation for the poet’s
                    running like a messenger, with risk of his life, at his eminence’s pleasure. Nor
                    was even this miserable pittance regularly paid during the period that the poet
                    enjoyed it. The cardinal went to Hungary in 1518, and wished Ariosto to
                    accompany him. The poet excused himself, pleading ill health, his <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n562/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0562-0503"/> love of study, the care of his private affairs,
                    and the age of his mother, whom it would have been disgraceful to leave. His
                    excuses were not received, and even an interview was denied him. Ariosto then
                    boldly said, that if his eminence thought to have bought a slave by assigning
                    him the scanty pension of 75 crowns a year, he was mistaken and might withdraw
                    his boon—which it seems the cardinal did.</p>
                <p>The cardinal’s brother, Alphonso, duke of Ferrara, now took the poet under his
                    patronage. This was but an act of simple justice, Ariosto having already
                    distinguished himself as a diplomatist, chiefly on the occasion of two visits to
                    Rome as ambassador to Pope Julius IL The fatigue of one of these hurried
                    journeys brought on a complaint from which he never recovered; and on his second
                    mission he was nearly killed by order of the violent Pope, who happened at the
                    time to be much incensed against the duke of Ferrara. On account of the war, his
                    salary of only 84 crowns a year was suspended, and it was withdrawn altogether
                    after the peace; in consequence of which Ariosto asked the duke either to
                    provide for him, or to allow him to seek employment elsewhere. A province,
                    situated on the wildest heights of the Apennines, being then without a governor,
                    Ariosto received the appointment, which he held for three years. The office was
                    no sinecure. The province was distracted by factions and banditti, the governor
                    had not the requisite means to enforce his authority, and the duke did little to
                    support his minister. Yet it is said that Ariosto’s government satisfied both
                    the sovereign and the people confided to his care; and a story is added of his
                    having, when walking out alone, fallen in with a party of banditti, whose chief
                    on discovering that his captive was the author of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Orlando</hi><hi rend="italic">Furioso,</hi> humbly apologised for not having
                    immediately shown him the respect which was due to his rank. Although he had
                    little reason to be satisfied with his office, he refused an embassy to Pope
                    Clement VII. offered to him by the secretary of the duke, and spent the
                    remainder of his life at Ferrara, writing comedies, superintending their
                    performance, as well as the construction of a theatre, and correcting his <hi
                    rend="italic">Orlando</hi><hi rend="italic">Furioso,</hi> of which the complete
                    edition was published only a year before his death. He died of consumption on
                    the 6th of June 1533.</p>
                <p>That Ariosto was honoured and respected by the first men of his age is a fact;
                    that most of the princes of Italy showed him great partiality is equally true;
                    but it is not less so that their patronage was limited to kind words. It is not
                    known that he ever received any substantial mark of their love for literature:
                    he lived and died poor. He proudly wrote on the entrance of a house built by
                    himself,</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “Parva, sed apta mihi, sed nulli obnoxia, sed non </l>
                    <l part="N"> Sordida, parta meo sed tamen sere domus;” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>which serves to show the incorrectness of the assertion of flatterers, followed
                    by Tiraboschi, that the duke of Ferrara built that house for him. The only one
                    who seems to have given anything to Ariosto as a reward for his poetical talent
                    was the Marquess del Vasto, who assigned him an annuity of 100 crowns on the
                    revenues of Casteleone, in Lombardy; but it was only paid, if ever, from the end
                    of 1531. That he was crowned as poet by Charles V. seems untrue, although a
                    diploma may have been issued to that effect by the emperor.</p>
                <p>The character of Ariosto seems to have been fully and justly delineated by
                    Gabrielle, his brother :—</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “Ornabat pietas et grata modestia Vatem, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Sancta fides, dictique memor, munitaque recto </l>
                    <l part="N"> Justitia, et nullo patientia victa labore, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Et constans virtus animi, et clementia mitis, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Ambitione procul puisa, fastûsque tumore.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>His satires, in which we see him before us such as he was, show that there was no
                    flattery in this portrait. In these compositions we are struck with the noble
                    independence of the poet. He loved liberty with a most jealous fondness. His
                    disposition was changeable withal, as he himself very frankly confesses in his
                    Latin verses, as well as in the satires.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “Hoc olirn ingenio vitales hausimus auras, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Multa cito ut placeant, displicitura brevi. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Non in amore modo mens haec, sed in omnibus impar </l>
                    <l part="N"> Ipsa sibi longa non retinenda mora.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Hence he never would bind himself, either by going into orders, or by marrying,
                    till towards the end of his life, when he espoused Alessandra, widow of Tito
                    Strozzi. He had no issue by his wife, but he left two natural sons by different
                    mothers.</p>
                <p>His Latin poems do not perhaps deserve to be noticed: in the age of Flaminio,
                    Vida, Fracastoro, and Sannazzaro, better things were due from a poet like
                    Ariosto. His lyrical compositions show the poet, although they do not seem
                    worthy of his powers. His comedies, of which he wrote four, besides one which he
                    left unfinished, are avowedly imitated from Plautus and Terence; and although
                    native critics may admire in them the elegance of the diction, the liveliness of
                    the dialogue, and the novelty of some scenes, few will feel interest either in
                    the subject or in the characters, and none would now approve the immoral
                    passages by which they are disfigured, however grateful these might be to the
                    audiences and patrons of theatrical representations in Ariosto’s own day.</p>
                <p>Of all the works of Ariosto, the most solid monument of his fame is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Orlando</hi><hi rend="italic">Fumoso,</hi> the extraordinary
                    merits of which have cast into oblivion the numberless romance poems which
                    inundated Italy during the 15th, 16th, and 17th centuries.</p>
                <p>The popularity which an earlier poem on the same theme, <hi rend="italic">Orlando
                    Innamorato,</hi> by Boiardo, enjoyed in Ariosto’s time, cannot be well
                    conceived, now that the enthusiasm of the Crusades, and the interest which was
                    attached to a war against the Moslems, have passed away. Boiardo wrote and read
                    his poem at the court of Ferrara, but died before he was able to finish it. Many
                    poets undertook the difficult task of its completion; but it was reserved for
                    Ariosto both to finish and to surpass his original. Boiardo did not, perhaps,
                    yield to Ariosto either in vigour or in richness of imagination, but he lived in
                    a less refined age, and died before he was able to recast or even finish the
                    poetical romance which he had written under the impulse of his exuberant fancy.
                    Ariosto, on the other hand, united to a powerful imagination an elegant and
                    cultivated taste. He began to write his great poem about 1503, and after having
                    consulted the first men of the age of Leo. X., he published it in 1516, in only
                    40 cantos (extended afterwards to 46); and up to the moment of his death never
                    ceased to correct and improve both the subject and the style. It is in this
                    latter quality that he excels, and for which he had assigned him the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Diυiηo Lodovico.</hi> Even when he jests, he never compromises his
                    dignity; and in pathetic description or narrative, he excites the reader’s
                    deepest feelings. In his machinery he displays a vivacity of fancy with which no
                    other poet can vie; but he never lets his fancy carry him so far as to omit to
                    employ, with an art peculiar to himself, those simple and natural pencil-strokes
                    which, by imparting to the most extraordinary feats a colour of reality, satisfy
                    the reason without disenchanting the imagination. The death of Zerbino, the
                    complaints of Isabella, the effects of discord among the Saracens, the flight of
                    Astolfo to the moon, the passion which causes Orlando’s madness, teem with
                    beauties of every variety. The supposition that the poem is not connected
                    throughout is wholly unfounded; there is a connection which, with a little
                    attention, will become evident. The love of Ruggero <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n563/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0563-0504"/> and Bradamante forms the main subject of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Fumoso</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> every part of it, except some
                    episodes, depends upon this subject; and the poem ends with their marriage.</p>
                <p>The first complete edition of the <hi rend="italic">Orlando</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Furioso</hi> was published at Ferrara in 1532, as noted above. The edition of
                    Morali (Milan, 1818) follows the text of the 1532 edition with great
                    correctness. Of editions published in England, those of Baskerville (Birmingham,
                    1773), and Panizzi (London, 1834), are the most important. The indifferent
                    translations into English of Harrington and Hoole have been superseded by the
                    spirited rendering of Bose.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
