<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0184-0171-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">APHASIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 171</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57h86">Aphasia</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cb2k">Brain</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bc9t">Expression</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:811278">Aphasia</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1055033">Patients</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:837570">Brain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:918881">Expression</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:936106">Functions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n184/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">APHASIA</label> (from <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and φάσις;
                    synonyms, <hi rend="italic">Aphemia, Alalia, Aphrasia, Aphthongia,
                    Aphthenxia),</hi> a term apphed to indicate a condition in which the function of
                    expressing ideas by articulate sounds is arrested, perverted, or destroyed, in
                    consequence of lesion of the brain. Loss or perversion of the power of
                    expressing ideas by written signs is often associated with this condition. The
                    term Aphasia is generally held to comprise two great varieties: (1), Amnesic
                    Aphasia, in which the memory of words is lost or perverted; and (2), Ataxic
                    Aphasia, in which the function of articulation is lost or perverted. Although
                    this broad distinction is very properly made, it very rarely lιappens that a
                    case occurs in which the two conditions are not to a greater or less extent
                    coexistent.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Amnesic (a, pvησιs)</hi> aphasia is symptomatised very
                    variously. The earliest and most common indication consists in—(a.) The loss of
                    the memory of substantives and names, other parts of speech being properly
                    applied; in such cases a periphrasis is employed to express the term. <hi
                    rend="italic">(β.)</hi> The memory of a language with which the patient had been
                    thoroughly conversant may become lost, (γ.) Terms are persistently misapplied;
                    for instance, in recorded cases “pamphlet" has been used for “camphor,"
                    “hogshead” for “sugar," “horse” for “man,” Ac., &amp;c. This symptom has been
                    named Heterophasia (ercpoç, <hi rend="italic">φacrL&lt;s).</hi> In <hi
                    rend="italic">ataxic</hi> (a, τ&lt;⅛ς) aphasia—(a.) the function of articulation
                    is. completely lost, the patient being only able to indicate by signs that he is
                    conscious of the idea conveyable by the term; thus an ataxic aphasic, who had
                    been an engine-driver, when asked what had been his trade, could only express
                    himself by imitating the sound made by an engine when starting, “Hish, hish,
                    hish.” In many instances even this power of imitation is in complete
                    abeyance—assent to the fitness of a spoken word to indicate the object exhibited
                    being given by a nod or other gesture, <hi rend="italic">(β.)</hi> The function
                    of articulation is modified; thus a word may be only half articulated; for
                    instance “watch" can only be pronounced as “wa," no prompting, or effort on his
                    own part, enabling the patient to complete the word, (γ.) Only automatic phrases
                    can be articulated, oaths, “yes,” “no,” “aye,” Ac. (δ.) The patient makes use of
                    a set phrase, which may consist of actual words, but more frequently of confused
                    sounds, such as “tan tan,” “ta ta," “didoes doe the doe,” Ac.; but such phrases
                    do not appear to satisfy him as expressive of ideae, although only one is
                    persistently employed. In almost all cases of ataxic aphasia there is a
                    well-marked desire and effort to enunciate words, the muscles of articulation
                    often working strongly but convulsively. The great diagnostic point between
                    amnesic and ataxic aphasia is, that in the former the patient can always
                    articulate the forgotten word when it is suggested to him; in the latter, no
                    prompting or assistance can enable him to enunciate the proper sound. Closely
                    associated with both forms of aphasia is the loss of the power of expressing
                    ideas by written signs. To this condition the term agraphia (a, <hi
                    rend="italic">γράφειν)</hi> has been applied. Most frequently this power is
                    completely lost, the effort of putting pen to paper being only followed by a
                    confused scribbling; occasionally a strong effort is made to write; for
                    instance, the patient makes a feeble endeavour to make his signature, which
                    results in the production of a badly-formed initial letter, the subsequent ones
                    being either quite unformed, or represented by a confusion of wrong signs. In
                    the most slightly-marked cases of agraphia, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> those
                    in which the patient is able to produce actual graphic signs, the general
                    character of the handwriting is completely changed from that which had existed
                    during health.</p>
                <p>Aphasia, whether amnesic or ataxic, may, but seldom does exist disassociated from
                    absolute insanity.</p>
                <p>Great interest has centred around the question of the pathology of aphasia, as
                    many observations have been adduced which appear to connect with this condition
                    lesion of a specific portion of the brain, and from this it has been sought to
                    deduce the absolute localisation of the function of speech in the hemispherical
                    ganglia. The large proportion of cases of ataxic aphasia occur in association
                    with right-sided hemiplegia, although others are on record in which it has
                    appeared in connection with leftsided hemiplegia in left handed persons.
                    Bouillard, Andral, and Dax placed on record a series of cases which bore upon
                    the association of disease of the frontal lobes of the brain, with loss of the
                    faculty of articulate speech. In 1861 Broca of Paris enunciated the theory,
                    founded on the clinical and pathological observation of two carefully reported
                    cases, that the portion of the cerebrum which is necessarily diseased in aphasia
                    is the <hi rend="italic">posterior third of the third or inferior left frontal
                    convolution.</hi> A large number of cases have since been published which appear
                    to support this theory; but an almost equally large number have been recorded in
                    which disease of this portion of the above-named convolution has been found
                    without material impairment of speech, in which it has been found intact in
                    cases of aphasia, or in which disease of other convolutions has been accompanied
                    by similar symptoms. Broca’s positive localisation of the function of speech has
                    been disproved by several well-authenticated cases; it is, nevertheless, held by
                    many prominent pathologists, that, although his deduction is not absolutely
                    correct, it is in the main true, as lesion of the portion of the brain indicated
                    by Broca may affect neighbouring convolutions of the frontal lobes, in which
                    their observations lead them to believe the function of speech is localised,
                    although its seat cannot be exactly indicated. Another, section of pathologists
                    hold that the nutrition of the whole encephalon is effected by lesion of this
                    particular convolution, the locality of which, by its anatomical relations to
                    the middle cerebral artery, is peculiarly liable to embolus and apoplexy, and
                    that as a consequence, the faculty of speech is affected in common with other
                    cerebral functions; and they further argue, that, as destruction of other
                    portions of the cerebrum has been known to be accompanied by similar symptoms
                    affecting speech (the left inferior frontal convolution being intact), it is in
                    no wise proved that localisation of function can be fairly deduced from the
                    occasional association of lesion of this convolution with aphasia.</p>
                <p>(See Dr Bateman, <hi rend="italic">On Aphasia;</hi> papers by Drs Tuke and J.
                    Fraser in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of</hi><hi rend="italic">ALentai</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Science,</hi> 1870; Dr Ferrier “On the Localisation of Brain
                    Function,” <hi rend="italic">West Riding Reports;</hi> and for bibliography, <hi
                    rend="italic">Dictionnaire Encyclopédique</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Sciences</hi><hi rend="italic">Médicales.)</hi> (j. B. τ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
