<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0401-0380-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARCHIMEDES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 380</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rn3093k">Parabola</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk4n">Screws</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1052775">Parabola</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1109382">Screws</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARCHIMEDES</label>, the greatest mathematician and the most
                    inventive genius of antiquity, was born at Syracuse, in Sicily, about 287 B.c.
                    In his youth he went to Alexandria, and completed his education there under
                    Conon, at the royal school of the Ptolemies, of which Euclid had been the
                    ornament some half a century before. On his return to his native city he devoted
                    himself to geometrical investigations, and by his great energy and inventiveness
                    carried the science far beyond the limits it had then attained. Combined with
                    his remarkable faculty of analysis was a power of practical application which
                    enabled him to establish the science of engineering upon a solid mathematical
                    basis. Of the facts of his private life we have but a few disconnected notices.
                    He was the devoted friend, and, according to some accounts, the relative of
                    Hiero, king of Syracuse; and he was ever ready to exercise his ingenuity in the
                    service of his admirer and patron. Popularly, Archimedes is best known as the
                    inventor of ingenious contrivances, though many of the ßtories handed down about
                    these are probably fabulous. He devised for Hiero engines of war, which almost
                    terrified the Romans, and which protracted the siege of Syracuse for three
                    years. There is a story that he constructed a burning mirror which set the Roman
                    ships on fire when they were within a bow-shot of the wall. This has been
                    discredited because neither Polybius, Livy, nor Plutarch mention it; mirrors
                    may, however, as Buffon showed, be so arranged as to burn at a considerable
                    distance, and it is probable that Archimedes had constructed some such burning
                    instrument, though the connection of it with the destruction of the Roman fleet
                    is more than doubtful. Among the most celebrated of his contributions to
                    practical science are his discoveries in hydrostatics and hydraulics. The
                    account usually given of one of these is remarkable. Hiero, it is said, had set
                    him to discover whether or not the gold which he had given to an artist to work
                    into a crown for him had been mixed with baser metal. Archimedes was puzzled
                    till one day, as he was stepping into a bath and observed the water running
                    over, it occurred to him that the excess of bulk occasioned by the introduction
                    of alloy could be measured by putting the crown and an equal weight of gold
                    separately into a vessel filled with water, and observing the difference of
                    overflow. He was so overjoyed when this happy thought struck him that he ran
                    home without his clothes, shouting, “<hi rend="italic">eυpηκa, ζvρηκa,"—</hi> I
                    have found it, I have found it. It may have been this that led to his
                    establishing the fundamental principle still known by his name, that a body
                    immersed in a liquid sustains an upward pressure equal to the weight of the
                    liquid displaced. Among a number of other mechanical inventions ascribed to him,
                    the water-screw may be mentioned, which still bears his name. His estimate of
                    the capabilities of the lever is expressed in the saying attr.buted to him, ∆os
                    7roi) ∏τω, και <hi rend="italic">την γην κινήσω,</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    ti</hi> Give me a fulcrum on which to rest, and I will move the earth.”</p>
                <p>The life of this philosopher ends with the capture of Syracuse by Marcellus, 212
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> In the general massacre which followed the fall
                    of the city, Archimedes, while engaged in drawing a mathematical figure on the
                    sand, was run through the body by a Roman soldier. No blame attaches to the
                    Roman general, Marcellus, since he had given orders to his men to spare the
                    house and person of the sage; and in the midst of his triumph he lamented the
                    death of so illustrious a person, directed an honourable burial to be given him,
                    and befriended his surviving relatives. In accordance with the expressed desire
                    of the philosopher, his tomb w as marked by the figure of a sphere inscribed in
                    a cylinder—the discovery of the relation between the volumes of a sphere and its
                    circumscribing cylinder being regarded by him as his most valuable achievement.
                    When Cicero was quaestor in Sicily (75 B.C.), he found the tomb of Archimedes,
                    near the Agrigentine gate, overgrown with thorns and briers. “Thus,” says Cicero
                    <hi rend="italic">(Tusc. Disp.</hi> v. 23), “would this most famous and once
                    most learned city of Greece have remained a stranger to the tomb of one of its
                    most ingenious citizens, had it not been discovered by a man of Arpinum.” The
                    range and importance of the scientific labours of Archimedes will be best
                    understood from a brief account of those wτitings which have come down to us;
                    and it may be remarked that though some useful and important works may have
                    perished, it is probable that these are chiefly details of his mechanical
                    inventions, and that all his most valuable mathematical discoveries have been
                    preserved. The following treatises have escaped the ravages of time :—</p>
                <p>(1.) <hi rend="italic">On the Sphere and Cylinder (τrep</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >∖</hi><hi rend="italic">της σφαίρας και του κυλίνδρου).</hi> This treatise
                    consists of two books, dedicated to Dositheus, and containing a number of
                    propositions relative to the dimensions of spheres, cones, and cylinders, all
                    demonstrated in a strictly geometrical method. The first book contains fifty
                    propositions, the most important of which are :—Prop. XIV. on the measure of the
                    curve surface of a cylinder; Props. XV. and XVI. on the surface of a cone; Prop
                    XVII. of a frustrum of a cone; Prop. XXII. of a circle; Prop. XXXV. of the
                    surface of a sphere; and Prop. XXXVII. of the relation between a sphere and its
                    circumscribing cylinder. The second book contains ten propositions, which
                    chiefly relate to plane spherical sections.</p>
                <p>(2.) <hi rend="italic">The Measure of the Circle (κυκλoυ μiτρησις)</hi> is a
                    short book of three propositions. Prop. I. proves that the area of a circle is
                    that of a triangle whose base is equal to its circumference, and height equal
                    toits radius; Prop. II. shows that the circumference of a circle exceeds three
                    times its diameter by a small fraction, which is less than and greater than ∣⅜;
                    and Prop. III. that a circle is to its circumscribing square nearly as 11 to 14.
                    He arrived at these wonderfully accurate results by inscribing in and
                    circumscribing about a circle two polygons, each of 96 sides; and, assuming that
                    the perimeter of the circle lay between these of the polygons, he obtained by
                    actual measurement the limits he has assigned.</p>
                <p>(3.) <hi rend="italic">Conoids and Spheroids (πepι κωvoeι8eωv κaι σφaιρotι-</hi>
                    δεωv) is a treatise in forty propositions, on the superficial and solid
                    dimensions of the solids generated by the revolutions of the conic sections
                    about their axes.</p>
                <p>(4.) <hi rend="italic">On Spirals (πepi tλiκωv),</hi> is a book, in twenty-eight
                    propositions, upon the properties of the curve now known as the spiral of
                    Archimedes, which is traced out by a radius vector, whose length is proportional
                    to the angle through which it has turned from the initial position.</p>
                <p>(5.) <hi rend="italic">Equiponderants and Centres of Gravity (πtpι lπιτrl8ωv
                    lσoppoπικωv</hi><hi rend="italic">η</hi><hi rend="italic">κlvτρa βaρωv</hi>
                    tτrt7reδωv). This COΠ-si<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n402/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0402-0381"/> st s of two books, and may be called the
                    foundation of theoretical mechanics, for the previous contributions of Aristotle
                    were comparatively vague and unscientific. In the first book there are fifteen
                    propositions, with eight postulates; and demonstrations are given, much the same
                    as those still employed, of the centres of gravity—(1) of any two weights, (2)
                    of any parallelogram, (3) of any triangle, (4) of any trapezoid. The second book
                    is devoted to the finding the centres of gravity of parabolic segments.</p>
                <p>(6.) <hi rend="italic">The Quadrature of the Parabola</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(Τετραγωνισμός παραβολής)</hi> is a book in twenty-four propositions,
                    demonstrating that the area of a parabola is ⅜ of the triangle having its double
                    ordinate for base and abscissa for height His method of arriving at this result
                    is most interesting, as being a sort of rude approximation to the modem process
                    of area summation by integration. The expedients to which he resorted to avoid
                    the idea of infinity are no less curious than they are admirable.</p>
                <p>(7.) <hi rend="italic">On Bodies floating in Liquids</hi> (∏∈pι <hi rend="italic"
                    >τωv v8aτι εφιστaμεvωv),</hi> is a treatise in two books, on the principles of
                    floating, and the positions of equilibrium of floating parabolic conoids.</p>
                <p>(8.) <hi rend="italic">The Psammites</hi> (ύ <hi rend="italic">ψαμμίτης,</hi>
                    Lat. <hi rend="italic">Arenarius,</hi> or sand counter), a small treatise,
                    dedicated to Gelo, the eldest son of Hiero, on arithmetical numeration, applied
                    to reckoning grains of sand <hi rend="subscript"> x</hi> is curious as
                    containing the germ of the modem system of logarithms.</p>
                <p>(9.) <hi rend="italic">A collection of Lemmas,</hi> consisting of fifteen
                    propositions in plane geometry. This has come down to us through a Latin version
                    of an Arabic manuscript, and its authenticity has been questioned.</p>
                <p>In the edition of Archimedes, published by Revault at Paris in 1G15, the
                    following works are said to be lost :— On the <hi rend="italic">Crown of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Hiero</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cochleon, or Water-Screw;</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Helicon, or Endless
                    Screw;</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Trispaston, or Combination of Wheels and
                    Axles;</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Machines employed at the Siege of
                    Syracuse;</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Burning Mirror;</hi> on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Machines moved by Air and Water;</hi> and on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Material Sphere.</hi> We do not know, however, that he ever committed accounts
                    of his mechanical inventions to writing.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Edito princeps</hi> of the works of Archimedes, with the
                    commen-tιry of Eutocius, is that printed at Basil, in 1544, in Greek and Latin,
                    by Hervagius. A Latin translation of them was published by Isaac Barrow in 1675
                    (London, 4to). Nicholas Tartalea (a celebrated algebraist), published in Greek
                    and Latin the treatises on the <hi rend="italic">Centre of Gravity,</hi> on the
                    <hi rend="italic">Quadrature of the Parabola,</hi> and on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Floating Bodies</hi> (Venice, 1543). Frederic Commandine edited the beautiful
                    Aldine edition of 1558, 4to, which contains <hi rend="italic">Circuli
                    Dimensio,</hi><hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Lineis Spiralibus,
                    Quadratura Paraboles,</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;L∙c.,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Conoidibus et Spheroidibus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De numero</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Arcnoe</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and in 1565 the same
                    mathematician published the two books <hi rend="italic">De iis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">quoe</hi><hi rend="italic">vehuntur</hi><hi rend="italic">in
                    Aqud.</hi> The most complete and magnificent edition of the works is that edited
                    by Torelli, and published with the commentaries of Eutocius at Oxford, in 1792,
                    folio. The most valuable edition of the <hi rend="italic">Arenarius,</hi> which
                    is also the first modem translation of any part of Archimedes, is that published
                    in English by Anderson (London, 1784), with useful notes and illustrations. The
                    first modem translation of the works is the French edition published by F.
                    Peyrard (Paris, 1808, 2 vols. 8vo). A German translation, by Nizze, was
                    published at Stralsund in 1824, and another by Gutenacker, at Wurzburg, 1828,
                    8vo. See <hi rend="italic">Quart. Rev.,</hi> vol. iii. p. 89; Plutarch’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Marcellus;</hi> Pope Blount’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Censura</hi><hi rend="italic">Celebrium</hi><hi rend="italic">Authorum</hi>
                    (London, 1690); the <hi rend="italic">Arenarius</hi><hi rend="italic">of
                    Archimedes,</hi> Oxford, 1837; <hi rend="italic">Ed. Rev.,</hi> vol. xi. p. 185;
                    <hi rend="italic">Powell’3 History of Natural Philosophy</hi> (Lardner’s Cycl.),
                    p. 40.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
