<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0801-0736-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ASTHMA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 736</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:819313">Asthma</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:853874">Chests</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:853827">Chest</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1037627">Night</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x50f">Asthma</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s26r">Chest</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42f7jr95">Breathing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n801/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ASTHMA</label><hi rend="italic">(aσθμa,</hi> a gasping, <hi
                    rend="italic">ασθμαίνω,</hi> to gasp for breath), a disorder of respiration
                    characterised by severe paroxysms of difficult breathing, usually followed by a
                    period of complete relief, with recurrence of the attacks at more or less
                    frequent intervals. The term is often incorrectly employed in reference to
                    states of embarrassed respiration, which are plainly due to permanent organic
                    disease within the chest, and which have none of the distinctive characters of
                    true asthma. The onset of an attack of asthma is usually sudden, although there
                    may exist certain premonitory symptoms which warn the sufferer of its approach,
                    such as a feeling of discomfort, drowsiness, irritability, and depression of
                    spirits. The period when the asthmatic paroxysm comes on is generally during the
                    night, or rather in the early hours of morning. The patient then awakes in a
                    state of great anxiety and alarm, with a sense of weight and tightness across
                    the chest, which he feels himself unable to expand with freedom. Respiration is
                    performed with great difficulty, and is accompanied with wheezing noises. His
                    distress rapidly increases, and he can no longer retain the recumbent position,
                    but gets up, and sits or stands with his shoulders raised, his head thrown back,
                    and his whole body heaving with his desperate efforts to breathe. His
                    countenance is pale or livid, and wet with perspiration, while his extremities
                    are cold; his pulse is rapid and weak, and frequently irregular or intermitting.
                    All his clothing must be loose about him; he cannot bear to be touched, and the
                    very presence of others around him seems to aggravate his distress. His one
                    desire is to breathe fresh air; and he will place himself by an open window and
                    sit for hours in the middle of the night, unmindful of the exposure. His
                    appearance is alarming in the extreme, and it often seems as if each breath
                    would be his last. The paroxysm, after continuing for a variable length of time,
                    often extending over many hours, begins to abate, the breathing becomes easier,
                    and the subsidence of the attack is frequently marked by the occurrence of
                    coughing with expectoration. When the expectoration is abundant the asthma is
                    called <hi rend="italic">humid,</hi> but where there is a little or none it is
                    termed <hi rend="italic">dry.</hi> After the cessation of the attack the patient
                    appears to be and feels comparatively well. In cases, however, of long standing
                    the subject of asthma comes to bear permanent evidence of its effects. He is
                    easily put out of breath on exertion and he requires to lie with his head
                    elevated, circumstances to be ascribed to organic changes in the chest, which
                    oft-recurring attacks of asthma are liable to induce. The asthmatic paroxysms,
                    although occasionally periodic, do not generally observe any regularity in their
                    return. They may recur each successive night for several days, or there may be
                    no return for many weeks or months, this being to a large extent dependent on a
                    renewal of the exciting cause. Asthma is much more common in men than in women.
                    In may be developed at any age, but is most frequently observed in early and
                    middle life. A large number of cases take their origin in diseases affecting the
                    respiratory system during infancy, such as hooping-cough, measles, and
                    bronchitis. Asthma is often hereditary, and in all cases one attack appears to
                    predispose to others.</p>
                <p>With respect to the pathology of asthma, it is now generally held that the
                    essential nature of the disease consists in a spasmodic contraction of the
                    bronchial tubes. This is due to some deranged condition of the nervous system,
                    affecting, either directly or by reflex action, the nerves supplying the
                    contractile fibres lining the bronchi and regulating their calibre. The
                    bronchial tubes being thus spasmodically narrowed, and losing for the time their
                    expansile power, air can only, with the utmost difficulty, be got into or out of
                    the chest. In these circumstances the muscles of the trunk concerned in
                    respiration are called on to act with great violence to expand the chest, but
                    with little avail, and hence the distress and threatened suffocation. But while
                    asthma is thus to be regarded as essentially a nervous ailment, its occurrence,
                    apart from some organic disease in the chest or elsewhere, is admitted to be
                    comparatively rare. Some cases, however, appear to be of purely nervous origin.
                    To these the term <hi rend="italic">Nervous</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Spasmodic
                    Asthma</hi> is applied, and it is more particularly to this form that the
                    symptoms above narrated refer. In such cases no actual disease can be discovered
                    with which the asthma could be directly connected. Attacks of this nature appear
                    capable of being excited in those subject to them in very various ways. Thus
                    violent emotions are not unfrequently the cause of asthmatic paroxysms. The
                    effect of the inhalation of certain effluvia in exciting attacks of asthma is
                    undoubted, as in the familiar instances of the odour of hay and of ipecacuan. In
                    no particular is the eccentric character of this disease more remarkable than in
                    that of locality. Changes of air, otherwise inappreciable, may give occasion to
                    the most severe attacks of asthma, as, on the other hand, they maybe the means
                    of accomplishing a cure of the disease where it exists. Circumstances,
                    apparently the most trifling, have been known to give rise to severe paroxysms
                    of asthma, as the extinguishing of a light in a sleeping apartment or the
                    shutting of a door. But asthma is very frequently associated with some form <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n802/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0802-0737"/> of chest complaint, more particularly bronchitis,
                    and hence the term <hi rend="italic">Bronchitic Asthma.</hi> The relation
                    between the two ailments in such cases is rendered sufficiently obvious by the
                    fact that the one does not occur without the other; ami it is evident that the
                    irritation of the bronchial mucous memorane gives rise by reflex nervous action
                    to narrowing of the tubes. When the bronchitis is cured the asthma disappears.
                    Asthmatic-like paroxysms are also of occasional occurrence in some forms of
                    heart disease, and the term <hi rend="italic">Cardiac Asthma</hi> is used to
                    describe such cases. They can, however, scarcely be regarded as cases of asthma,
                    but rather as attacks of difficult breathing referable to some impediment to the
                    pulmonary circulation, the result of the heart disease.</p>
                <p>The treatment of asthma consists in the employment of remedies to allay the
                    paroxysms, and in the adoption of measures likely to prevent their recurrence.
                    During the attack the patient should be placed in as favourable circumstances
                    for breathing as practicable. He usually selects the position easiest for
                    himself. Abundance of air should be admitted to the apartment, and he should be
                    interfered with as little as possible. The remedial agents employed with the
                    view of relieving the paroxysms are very numerous, and only a few of the more
                    important of them can be alluded to. Opiates administered internally or
                    hypodermically are of known efficacy, as is also the inhalation of anaesthetic
                    vapours. Much value is attached by many to the smoking of stramonium, and even
                    tobacco smoking appears in some instances to give relief. The fumes of
                    nitre-paper (blotting-paper prepared by being dipped in a saturated solution of
                    nitre and dried) burnt in the apartment often succeed in mitigating the
                    paroxysm. The use of the tincture of <hi rend="italic">Lobelia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">inflata</hi> is recommended by many high authorities, as are also
                    the employment of emetics, the latter moro especially where the attack can be
                    traced to errors in diet. None of these remedies, however, ought to be tried
                    without medical advice. Coffee is a popular and useful remedy, but to do good
                    the infusion must be very strong, and taken upon an empty stomach. To prevent
                    the recurrence of the paroxysms special care must be taken by the sufferer to
                    avoid those influences, whether connected with locality or mode of life, which
                    his experience may have proved to have been the occasion of former attacks.
                    Where the paroxysms are of periodic occurrence the use of quinine or arsenic has
                    been tried with good results. (j. o. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
