<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0200-0187-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">APOLLONIUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 187</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rn3093k">Parabola</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7751w">Press</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1765196">Space</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1052775">Parabola</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1075837">Press</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:885683">Cutting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n200/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">APOLLONIUS</label> of <hi rend="smallcaps">Perga</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(Pergaeus),</hi> next to Archimedes the most illustrious of the
                    ancient Greek geometricians, was born probably about 250 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> and died during the reign of Ptolemy Philopator (222-205 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>), flourishing thus about forty years later than
                    Archimedes. He studied at Alexandria under the successors of Euclid, and is one
                    of the brightest ornaments of that famous mathematical school.</p>
                <p>But few of the mathematical works of Apollonius have escaped the ravages of time.
                    Of the greater part we have merely the names and general description given by
                    Pappus in his preface to book vii. of the <hi rend="italic">Mathematical
                    Collections.</hi> His treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Conic Sections</hi>
                    gained him the title of The Great Geometer, and is that by which his fame has
                    been transmitted to modem times. It is not, indeed, to be for a moment supposed
                    that Apollonius discovered all, or even the greater part, of the demonstrations
                    which he gives, any more than that Euclid devised the propositions that go by
                    his name. Pappus mentions several treatises on conics known to have existed
                    previously—in particular the five books of Aristaeus “The Ancient” (350 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> on Solid Loci; and there can be little doubt that
                    Apollonius availed himself of these, as well as of the discoveries of Conon,
                    Euclid, Eudoxus, Menechmus, Nicoteles, Thrasidaeus, and others, who had explored
                    the way before him. At this distance of time we cannot distinguish the original
                    from the borrowed propositions; but, though it is certain that he both added to
                    and improved upon the existing theory of conics, the mere embodying in a
                    complete and logical treatise of a number of miscellaneous theorems was in
                    itself a work of great mathematical genius. Eutocius informs us that Apollonius
                    was the first to show that all the three sections may be cut from the same cone,
                    by varying the position of the intersecting plane; for previous authors had
                    supposed the plane of section always perpendicular to the slant side of the
                    cone,—an hypothesis which requires that the three sections be cut from cones of
                    different species, namely, the parabola from a right-angled cone, the ellipse
                    from one with an obtuse, and the hyperbola from one with an acute vertical
                    angle. But Archimedes, as Ubaldus shows in his commentary on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Aequipon-</hi><hi rend="italic">derantes,</hi> had been acquainted
                    with this fact. Pappus ascribes to Apollonius the names by which the three
                    sections are now distinguished; the term <hi rend="italic">Parabola,</hi>
                    however, occurs in the writings of Archimedes. Of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Conicorum Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">Octo</hi> of Apollonius, unfortunately
                    only four have reached us directly through the original Greek. Three more have
                    been preserved in an Arabic version, but the eighth has never been found. Though
                    many attempts had been made to discover the last four books, they continued to
                    be regarded as lost till 1658, when Borelli, the celebrated author of the
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">motu Animalium,</hi>
                    discovered in the Medici library at Florence an Arabic manuscript, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergcei</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Conicorum Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">Octo.</hi> With the assistance of Abraham
                    Ecchellensis he translated and published in 1661 the fifth, sixth, and seventh
                    books; but the eighth, notwithstanding the title, was wanting. Some years
                    previously Golius, Oriental professor at Leyden, had returned from the East with
                    an Arabic version of the whole seven books, and had projected the publication of
                    a translation; but it never appeared. A note appended to the MS. of Golius
                    stated that the eighth book had never been translated into Arabic. It was long a
                    favourite problem with geometers to attempt to restore the lost books of
                    Apollonius, that is, to infer from the general nature of their contents, as
                    described by Pappus, the propositions they had contained. Maurolycus, a Sicilian
                    geometer of the 16th century, Viviani, the last favourite pupil of Galileo,
                    Fermat, Halley, Simson, and a number of others, all attempted this with more or
                    less success. Halley, guided by the descriptions of Pappus, and the assertion
                    that his preliminary lemmas to the seventh book really belonged tc the eighth,
                    as well as by the statement of Apollonius himself that the eighth was a
                    continuation of the seventh book, restored this book for the edition issued by
                    the Oxford Press in 1710, the only edition of the Greek text that has as yet
                    appeared. The last four books of the conics of Apollonius formed the chief part
                    of the higher geometry of the ancients; and they present some elegant
                    geometrical solutions of problems, which offer considerable difficulty even to
                    the modern analytical method. For example, the fifth book treats of the greatest
                    and least lines that can be <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n201/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0201-0188"/> drawn from given points to the peripheries of
                    conics, and contains the chief properties of normals and radii of curvature.</p>
                <p>The other treatises of Apollonius mentioned by Pappus are—lsi, The Section of
                    Ratio, or Proportional Sections; 2&lt;∕, the Section of Space; 3&lt;7, the
                    Determinate Section · <hi rend="italic">4dh,</hi> the Tangencies; <hi
                    rend="italic">5th,</hi> the Inclinations <hi rend="italic">; 6th,</hi> the Plane
                    Loci. Each of these was divided into two books, and, with the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Data</hi> of Euclid and the <hi rend="italic">Porisms,</hi> they formed the
                    eight treatises which, according to Pappus, constituted the body of the ancient
                    analysis.</p>
                <p>Isi, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Dationis Sectione</hi> had for
                    its subject the resolution of the following problem: Given two straight lines
                    and a point in each to draw through a third given point a straight line cutting
                    the two fixed lines, so that the parts intercepted between the given points in
                    them and the points of intersection of this third line, may have a given
                    ratio.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2d, De</hi><hi rend="italic">Spatii Sectione</hi> discussed the
                    similar problem, which requires that the space contained by the three lines
                    shall be equal to a given rectangle.</p>
                <p>Dr Halley published in 1706 a restoration of these two treatises, founded on the
                    indications of their contents given by Pappus. An Arabic version of the first
                    had previously been found in the Bodleian library at Oxford by Dr Edward
                    Bernard, who began a translation of it, but broke off on account of the extreme
                    inaccuracy of the MS.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">3d, De</hi><hi rend="italic">Sectione Determinata</hi> resolved
                    the problem: In a given straight line to find a point, the rectangles or squares
                    of whose distances from given points in the given straight line shall have a
                    given ratio. Several restorations of the solution have been attempted, one by
                    Snellius, another by Alex. Anderson of Aberdeen, in the supplement to his <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonius</hi><hi rend="italic">Redivivus</hi> (Paris, 1612), but
                    by far the most complete and elegant by Dr Simson of Glasgow.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ath, De</hi><hi rend="italic">Tactionibus</hi> embraced the
                    following general problem: Given three things (points, straight lines, or
                    circles) in position, to describe a circle passing through the given points, and
                    touching the given straight lines or circles. The most difficult case, and the
                    most interesting from its historical associations, is when the three given
                    things are circles. This problem, though now regarded as elementary, was
                    proposed by Vieta in the 16th century to Adrianus Romanus, who gave a very
                    clumsy solution. Vieta thereupon proposed a simpler construction, and restored
                    the whole treatise of Apollonius in a small work, which he entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonius Gallus</hi> (Paris, 1660.) Both Descartes and Newton
                    have discussed this problem, though they failed to give it that simplicity of
                    character which it has since been shown to possess. A very full and interesting
                    historical account of the problem is given in the preface to a small work of
                    Camerer, entitled <hi rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergoei
                    que</hi><hi rend="italic">supersunt, ac maxime Lemmata Pappi in hos Libros, cum
                    Observationibus,</hi> &amp;c. (Gothae, 1795, 8vo).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">5 th,</hi><hi rend="italic">De Inclinationibus</hi> had for its
                    object to insert a given straight line, tending towards a given point, between
                    two given (straight or circular) lines. Restorations have been given by Marinus
                    Ghetaldus, by Hugo de Omerique <hi rend="italic">(Geometrical Analysis,</hi>
                    Cadiz, 1698), and elegantly by Dr Horsley (1770).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">3th, De</hi><hi rend="italic">Locis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Plants</hi> is merely a collection of properties of the straight line and
                    circle, and corresponds to the construction of equations of the first and second
                    degrees. It has been successfully restored by Dr Simson.</p>
                <p>The great estimation in which Apollonius was held by the ancients, and the great
                    value attached to his productions, are manifest from the number and celebrity of
                    the commentators who undertook to explain them. Among these we find the names of
                    Pappus, the learned and unfortunate Hypatia, Serenus, Eutocius, Borelli, Halley,
                    Barrow, and others. Various discoveries in other departments of mathematical
                    science were also ascribed to him by the ancients. Pappus says that he made
                    improvements on the modes of representing and multiplying large arithmetical
                    numbers. The invention of the method of projections has been attributed to him;
                    and he has the honour of being the first to found astronomical observations on
                    the principles of geometry.</p>
                <p>The best editions of the works of Apollonius are the following :— 1. <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergoei</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Conicorum libri</hi><hi rend="italic">quatuor, ex versione Frederici</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Commanding</hi> Bononiae, 1566, fol. 2. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergoei</hi><hi rend="italic">Conicorum
                    libri</hi> V. vi. vii. <hi rend="italic">Paraphraste Abalphato Asphanensi nunc
                    primum editi: Additus in calce Archimedis Assumtorum Liber, ex Codicibus
                    Arabicis Manuscr.: Abrahamus Ecchellensis Latinos reddidit: J. Alfonsus Borellus
                    curam in Geometricis Versioni contulit, et Notas uberiores in universum opus
                    adjecit.</hi> Florentiae, 1661, fol. 3. <hi rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pergoei</hi><hi rend="italic">Conicorum libri octo, et Sereni
                    Antissensis de Sectione Cylindri et Coni libri</hi><hi rend="italic">duo.</hi>
                    Oxoniae, 1710, fol. (This is the splendid edition of Dr Halley.) 4. The edition
                    of the first four books of the Conics given in 1675 by Barrow. 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergoei</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >de</hi><hi rend="italic">Sectione Rationis libri duo: Accedunt ejusdem de
                    Sectione Spatii libri duo Restituti:</hi><hi rend="italic">Proemittitur,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">kc. Opera et Studio</hi><hi rend="italic">Edmundi Halley.</hi>
                    Oxoniae, 1706, 4to.</p>
                <p>See Bayle’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary;</hi> Bossut, <hi rend="italic">Essai
                    sur</hi><hi rend="italic">THist.</hi><hi rend="italic">Gén. des</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Math.,</hi> tome i.; Montucla, <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Math.,</hi> tome i.; Vossius, <hi rend="italic">De Scient.
                    Math.;</hi> Simson’s <hi rend="italic">Sectiones</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Conicoe,</hi> preface; and Hutton’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical
                    Dictionary.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
