<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0704-0643-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARTEMIS [Diana] (9th edition, volume 2, page
                    643)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c55w">Amazons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f25">Hellenism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806706">Amazons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954758">Hellenism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944180">Goddesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119758">Sisters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847566">Caring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n704/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARTEMIS <hi rend="smallcaps">[Diana]</hi></label>, in <hi
                        rend="italic">Greek Mythology,</hi> twin sister of Apollo, but born a day
                    before him, as it was said at Athens for the sake of explaining the fact of the
                    6th of each month being sacred to her, while the 7th was his day. It might seem,
                    too, that their mother, Leto, had borne them in two different places, since the
                    birth-place of Apollo was Delos, while that of his sister is called Ortygia. But
                    the word Ortygia, meaning strictly, a “haunt of swallows,” applies still to
                    Delos, and may well have been a synonym for that island. In this, its original
                    sense, it does not apply either to the island of Ortygia at Syracuse, or to the
                    spot so named near Ephesus, which were the two principal competitors for the
                    honour of having been the birth-place of the goddess. Besides, she slew Orion in
                    Ortygia, and that incident is connected with the mythology of Delos.
                    Consistently with her relation to Apollo, she was conceived as sharing his
                    aspect and attributes, her occupations and even her beauty tending rather to
                    what would be appropriate for males. Both were endowed with perpetual youth, and
                    this, if it did not originally help to suggest the idea of their being twins, is
                    consistent with a universal feeling as regards that relationship. Like him she
                    is armed with bow and arrows, which, jointly with him, she used against
                    offending mortals as in the case of the Niobides, or of Laodamia, and the wife
                    of Eëtion <hi rend="italic">{Iliad,</hi> vi. 205, 428), she slaying women—he,
                    men. At other timee, with no sign of anger, her arrows brought soft death, such
                    as Penelope desired <hi rend="italic">{Odyssey,</hi> xviii. 201, xx. 62, 80).
                    But, unlike Apollo’s, the bow in her hands was chiefly employed, as a borrowed
                    weapon might be, for the amusement of the chase. And here a broad line must be
                    drawn between two sides of her character. On the one hand she is a sister of
                    Apollo, and shares several of his functions, even taking part on occasion in his
                    favourite music and dance. But in this respect her actions seem sometimes
                    forced, as if grafted upon her in comparatively later times, as indeed seems
                    also her name = <hi rend="italic">apτep,ης,</hi> “spotless,” as applied to a
                    virgin. On the other hand she had what appears to be a more primitive name,
                    Oupis or Opis, and a wide variety of functions, which are not only obviously
                    suggested by the real and supposed influence of the moon on nature, but~also
                    approximate often closely enough to the functions of Apollo to have led to the
                    identification of the two deities as brother and sister. The name Opis is taken
                    to refer to the light of the moon. With that luminary she was distinctly
                    associated, but not as guiding its movement,—a task which devolved on Selene
                    (Luna), just as the course of the sun was directed by Helios, not by Apollo. To
                    regard the goddess of the moon as sister of the god of the sun was natural, but
                    it was an observation of a secondary kind, and founded only on the appearance
                    and movement of those orbs. Primitive observations would refer to the sensations
                    immediately awakened by the moonlight In general terms Artemis, the moon
                    goddess, was styled <hi rend="italic">φώσφορος</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >σeλaσφopoς,</hi> and carried, besides bow and arrows, a torch, here only
                    with the idea of spreading light, and not as when, under the name of <hi
                        rend="italic">hegemone,</hi> she carried a torch to light the way for
                    travellers, as in the typical instance of Demeter searching for Persephone. At
                    Athens she had an annual festival, <hi rend="italic">Munychia,</hi> on the 16th
                    of April, for which cakes were made in the form of a full moon stuck over with
                    lights. But, in particular, the spread of vegetation from the dew under a
                    peaceful moonlight was ascribed to her influence. Her presence was felt near
                    springs, streams, bays, on the sea, and in marshy places, whence she bore the
                    titles of πoτα∕√α, λιuvaia, λι∕zvSτιs. In lifting the veil of night she revealed
                    to the imagination the world of wild animals, among which she was an intrepid
                    and unwearied huntress, and over which she exercised the care of a godde≡3. Her
                    favourite animal was the deer, whence she obtained in Olympia and Elis the title
                    of <hi rend="italic">lλaφia</hi> or cλαψιαια, Because Agamemnon had killed a
                    deer sacred to her she detained the Greek fleet in Aulis, and required the
                    sacrifice of his daughter Iphigenia. But while deer, goats, rams, and wild
                    animals were generally regarded as dependent on her control, certain animals
                    were specially associated with her in particular districts of Greece, as was the
                    wild boar in Aetolia and elsewhere, and the bear in Arcadia, and in her worship
                    as Artemis Brauronia, and Munychia at Athens. When a wild boar appeared ravaging
                    a district, as did the Caly-donian boar, it was sent by Artemis in anger. The
                    boar, however, was not an instrument of her moods, but rather, it would seem, a
                    symbol of the awakening every spring of the hunting season after the sleep of
                    winter. “Bears” (άρκτοι) was the name sometimes applied at Athens to young girls
                    who there, as throughout the rest of Greece, were under her special protection,
                    in token of which it was usual for them to dedicate to her a lock of hair, a
                    trinket, or some plaything. Boys also were under her care. With the symbol of a
                    bear she was worshipped among the Arcadians, or “bear people,” who claimed her
                    as the primeval mother of their race, till, through the increasing prominence of
                    her virginal character, that honour devolved upon Callisto, whose name is an
                    obvious variation of <hi rend="italic">κaλλiστη,</hi> the title of Artemis, and
                    her transformation into a bear an invention for the purpose. Arcadia was her
                    chief huntingground, and more numerous were her sanctuaries there than elsewhere
                    in Greece. As <hi rend="italic">Artemis agrotera,</hi> a title under which she
                    was worshipped in Attica, she was conceived not only as goddess of the chase,
                    but also as in some way providing the wild impetus with which men rush into
                    battle. Hence the 500 goats annually sacrificed at Athens, to commemorate the
                    battle of Marathon, were sacrificed to her. It was customary with the Spartans
                    to sacrifice a goat before closing with an enemy (Xenophon, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hellen.,</hi> iv. 2, 20). Possibly, also, the curious dance with which the
                    maidens of Caryae (Caryatides), in the valley of the Eurotas, celebrated her
                    festival had reference to her part iu war. Her care over children was recognised
                    in Laconia and Messenia under the name of κopυ0αλiα,to w hose temple, by the
                    stream Tiasa, nurses brought their charges at the festival of the Tithenidia,
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> festival of nurses. As λoχια or λoχ&lt;√a she
                    divided the w orship of Ilithyia by her helping presence at childbirth. With
                    marriage her care almost ceased, and hence it has been supposed that the dresses
                    which women dedicated to her were such as they had worn as virgins, and were
                    intended to express piety for her past protection. In reference to this,
                    apparently, she was styled <hi rend="italic">∙χyrωvy</hi> or χιτώνια. Youth,
                    innocence, modesty, and a good name were thought to find high favour with her,
                    and as an illustration of this was often told, in works of art andin the
                    tragedies of Sophocles andEuripides. the story of Hippolytus. Her own purity was
                    unsullied <hi rend="italic">(αγνή,</hi> Aeschylus, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Agamem.,</hi> 135 <hi rend="italic">; alεv</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >άδρήτα,</hi> Sophocles, <hi rend="italic">Electr.,</hi> 1239). Actaeon, the
                    huntsman, she caused to be devoured by his own hounds, because he had seen her
                    bathing. She slew Orion because of his pressing advances to Aurora. She
                    transformed Daphne into a laurel to preserve her from pursuit. Meadows in their
                    spring verdure and flowers, fields with the seeds springing, and the gay seasons
                    of rural life, gave occasion for thoughts of her overseeing care. She was hailed
                    by rustic choruses, all manner of rejoicings, and, in particular, on a hill at
                    the back of Mount Taygetus with songs known as καλαβοιδια. In Arcadia she was
                    called <hi rend="italic">hymnia.</hi> At the mouth of the Alpheus she was
                    worshipped as ’ Aλ≠cιωι iα or ’ <hi rend="italic">Aλφeiovσa,</hi> the common<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n705/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0705-0644"/> belief being enlivened with the story of how
                    she defeated the god of that river in his passion for her nymph Arethusa, by
                    leading the spring Arethusa underground away to the island of Ortygia at
                    Syracuse.</p>
                <p>So far the various phases of her character are such as were more or less
                    generally accepted in the times of literature and art. But there had also
                    survived certain peculiarities in her worship from apparently very early times,
                    though the fact of their being found only in certain localities renders it
                    impossible to know whether they had been originally only local peculiarities or
                    universally admitted. Of this kind was the Tauric Artemis, peculiar at first to
                    the Crimea and the shores of the Black Sea. From the Crimea, Orestes, it was
                    said, brought the ancient image of the goddess to Sparta, and with it her
                    worship, the chief characteristic of which was the sacrifice of human beings
                    which it required. At Sparta these sacrifices were afterwards commuted by
                    Lycurgus for the ceremony of flogging youths at her altar, but not till this
                    barbarous phase of her worship had spread to several places in Greece, Asia
                    Minor, and Italy. Her title at Sparta was <hi rend="italic">Orthia,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">Orthosia.</hi> Again, originally peculiar to Crete was <hi
                        rend="italic">Artemis</hi><hi rend="italic">Britomartis,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">Dictynna,</hi> the latter name being interpreted by the legend
                    that Minos had loved and pursued her till she leapt into the sea, and was saved
                    by being caught in a fisherman’s net. In this character she was chiefly the
                    goddess of seafarers, and as such was widely worshipped on the islands and
                    coasts of the Mediterranean. But nowhere w¾s the worship of Artemis so
                    non-Hellenic in character as among the Greeks at Ephesus. It would seem as if
                    the Greek colonists there had found among the native Carians and Leleges a form
                    of the moon goddess, which, though widely different from their own, had the
                    advantage of an image that had fallen from heaven <hi rend="italic"
                        >(diopetes),</hi> and an established hold on the people with whom the
                    colonists had to deal. Like theirs she was a goddess with power over wild
                    animals, and identified with their productivity, as appears from her being
                    represented with many breasts,—a characteristic of animals, and not necessarily
                    to be understood as expressing her interest in matérnity in the usual sense,
                    which would have been strongly opposed to the Greek feeling towards their virgin
                    goddess. Her worship was surrounded by hierodulae and eunuchs. She was the
                    goddess of the warlike Amazons, whose fondness of the chase presented another
                    point of contact between the Asiatic and thé Greek goddess. But however much of
                    the Greek element may in time have become grafted upon her, Diana of Ephesus was
                    only in rare instances accepted by the Greeks outside of Asia Minor. The wealth
                    and splendour of the temple made Ephesus a powerful attraction for devotees in
                    the neighbourhood. A figure of her similar to that at Ephesus existed near
                    Magnesia on the Meander, where from the name of the Spot she was called <hi
                        rend="italic">Λ-evκoφpvηvη. </hi></p>
                <p>The usual figure of the Ephesian Artemis, as preserved in works of art, is in the
                    form of a female with many breasts, from the waist to the feet resembling a
                    pillar, narrowing downwards, and sculptured all round with rows of animals. In
                    archaic works, as on the chest of Cypselus of Corinth, she appeared winged, and
                    holding a lion with each hand. As to the original image, believed to have fallen
                    from heaven, it is not impossible that it had been made tc take the place of a
                    meteorite. But the Greek Artemis was usually represented as a huntress with bow
                    and quiver, in face very like Apollo, her drapery flowing to her feet, or, more
                    frequently, girt high for speed. She is accompanied often by a deer or a dog.
                    Perhaps the finest existing statue of her is the Diana of Versailles On the
                    coins of Arcadia, Aetolia, Crete, and Sicily, are to be seen varied and
                    beautiful representations of her head as conceived by the Greek artists in the
                    best times. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. s. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
