<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0555-0496-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARGONAUTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 496</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:965403">Hyla</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:995592">Legends</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:955558">Heroes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w07f">Argonauts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j62t">Legends</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205534">Libya</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1245970">Sun</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n555/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARGONAUTS</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Greek Legend,</hi> a
                    band of heroes who sailed in the ship “Argo” from Iolcus, in Thessaly, to Aea,
                    in Colchis, on the further shore of the Black Sea, to fetch the golden fleece,
                    which was there guarded by a dragon in a grove sacred to Mars. This task had
                    been imposed on Jason that he might prove himself by a perilous adventure worthy
                    of the throne of Iolcus, which he claimed from the usurper Pelias, at whose
                    hands he and his father Aeson had suffered persecution. To accompany him, Jason,
                    when the “Argo” was ready, called upon the principal heroes of his own race, the
                    Minyae, whose distant voyages and colonisation in very early times seem to have
                    suggested the legend of this expedition. Of these Acastus the son of Pelias,
                    Admetus of Pherae, Euphemus (represented as connected with the colonisation of
                    Thera and Cyrene), Periclymenus, Erginus, and Tiphys the steersman, joined him.
                    So far the crew appears well fitted to conduct the “Argo” to Colchis, leaving
                    Jason to reserve his strength for the culminating act, in which also they had
                    mostly, apart from their friendship for Jason, a special interest, because of
                    previous events connected with the golden fleece, the story of which was as
                    follows. Jason’s uncle Athamas had by his wife Nephele two children, Phrixus and
                    Helle. The mother died, and her place was taken by Ino, a daughter of Cadmus,
                    who from hatred of her step-children persuaded Athamas, by means of a false
                    oracle, to offer his son Phrixus as a sacrifice, in consequence of a famine
                    which she had caused by having the grain secretly roasted before it was sown.
                    But before the sacrifice the shade of Nephele appeared to Phrixus, bringing a
                    ram with a golden fleece, on which he and his sister Helle were to escape over
                    the sea. Helle fell off and was drowned in the strait, which thence took the
                    name of Hellespont. Phrixus reached the other side, and proceeding on land to
                    Colchis, sacrificed the ram, and hung up its fleece in the grove of Mars. With
                    the family of Athamas the original crew of the “Argo” were more or less
                    connected. But in the later versions of the story it is clear that such a voyage
                    could not in after times be conceived without a variety of adventures, for which
                    other and better known heroes had to be added. Of these the chief were Hercules,
                    Castor and Pollux, Orpheus, Mopsus, and the sons of Boreas, Calais and Zetes.
                    The outward course of the “Argo” was the same as that of the Greek traders,
                    whose settlements as early as the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    dotted the southern shore of the Black Sea. The first landing-place was Lemnus,
                    which the Argonauts found occupied only by women who, at the instigation of
                    Aphrodite, had slain their husbands, fathers, &amp;c. Here some stay was made,
                    and Hypsipyle bore Jason a son, Euneos, who afterwards traded with the Greeks
                    before Troy and with the Phoenicians. That the Minyae had at a very early period
                    formed settlements in Lemnus is known from Herodotus (iv. 145). They landed at
                    Cyzicus next, and here occurred the incident of Hercules and Hylas. The former
                    having broken an oar after they started, went into a wood to cut a new one,
                    Hylas accompanying him to fetch water. Some nymphs admiring the beauty of the
                    youth carried him off. Hercules followed his cries, but could not find him. Nor
                    was he ever found, though the hero exacted hostages till this should be done. On
                    reaching the modern Scutari, they again landed to get water, and were challenged
                    by the king, Amycus, to match him with a boxer. Pollux came forward, and in the
                    end overpowered his adversary, and bound him to a tree. At the entrance to the
                    Black Sea they met Phineus, the blind and aged king whose food was being
                    constantly polluted by the Harpies. He knew the course to Colchis, and offered
                    to tell it, if the Argonauts would free him from the Harpies. This was done by
                    the winged sons of Boreas, and Phineus now told them their course, and that the
                    way to pass through the Symplegades —two cliffs which moved on their bases and
                    crushed whatever sought to pass—was first to fly a pigeon through, and when the
                    cliffs, having closed on the pigeon, began to retire to each side, to row the
                    “Argo” swiftly through. His advice was successfully followed. The next place
                    they landed at, and the last before reaching Colchis, was Heraclea, where the
                    steersman Tiphys died. To the early Greeks Colchis was the eastern extremity of
                    the earth, as the Pillars of Hercules were the western. Behind both was the
                    Oceanus, into which the river Phasis flowed at Colchis. At Colchis was the
                    rising of the sun, and Aeetes the king was a sen <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n556/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0556-0497"/> of Helios; while his daughter Medea was, by her
                    knowledge of witchcraft, connected with the worship of the moon. Aeetes required
                    of Jason that he should first yoke to a plough his bulls which snorted fire and
                    had hoofs of brass, and with them plough the field of Mars. That done, the field
                    was to be sown with dragons’ teeth, from which armed men were to spring.
                    Successful so far by means of the mixture which Medea had given him as proof
                    against fire and sword, Jason was next allowed to approach the dragon which
                    watched the fleece; Medea soothed the dragon with another mixture, and Jason
                    became master of the fleece. Then the voyage homeward began, Medea accompanying
                    Jason, and Aeetes pursuing them. To delay him and obtain escape, Medea
                    dismembered her young brother Absyrtus, whom she had taken with her, and cast
                    the limbs about in the sea for his father to pick up. In another report Absyrtus
                    had grown to manhood then, and met his death in an encounter with Jason, in
                    pursuit of whom he had been sent. Of the homeward course various accounts are
                    given. In the oldest existing account, the “Argo” sailed along the river Phasis
                    into the Oceanus, thence to the mythical lake Tritonis, after being carried
                    twelve days over land through Libya, and thence again to Iolcus. Hecataeus of
                    Miletus suggested that from the Oceanus it may have sailed into the Nile, and so
                    to the Mediterranean. Others, like Sophocles, described the return voyage as
                    differing from the outward course only in taking the northern instead of the
                    southern shore of the Black Sea. Some supposed that the Argonauts had sailed up
                    the river Tanais, passed into another river, and by it reached the North Sea,
                    returning to the Mediterranean by the Straits of Gibraltar. And again, others
                    laid down the course as up the Danube (Istros), from it into the Adriatic by a
                    supposed mouth of that river, and on to Corcyra, where a storm overtook them.
                    Next they sailed up the Eridanus into the Rhodanus, passing through the country
                    of the Celts and Ligurians, and reaching the Tyrrhenian Sea and the island of
                    Circe, who absolved them from the murder of Absyrtus. Then they passed safely
                    through Scylla and Charybdis, past the Sirens, through the Planctae, over the
                    island of the Sun, Trinacria, and on to Corcyra again, the land of the
                    Phaeacians, where Jason and Medea held their nuptials. They had sighted the
                    coast of the Peloponnesus when a storm overtook them and drove them to the coast
                    of Libya, where they were saved from a quicksand by the local nymphs. The “Argo”
                    was now carried twelve days and twelve nights to the Hesperides, and thence to
                    lake Tritonis, whence Triton conducted them to the Mediterranean. At Crete the
                    brazen Talos, who would not permit them to land, was killed by the Dioscuri. At
                    Anaphe they were saved from a storm by Apollo. Finally they reached Iolcus, and
                    the “Argo” was placed in a grove sacred to Neptune on the isthmus of Corinth.
                    Jason’s death, it is said, was afterwards caused by part of the stern giving way
                    and falling upon him. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. s. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
