<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0389-0368-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARCHANGEL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 368</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:813025">Archangels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1143526">Tatars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:927119">Flax</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:866956">Cold</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1012484">Matting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:918764">Exports</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fc9v">Cola</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gw7g">Flax</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41834445">Cold</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4cv97">Matting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h03c">Exports</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205503">Finland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n389/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARCHANGEL</label>, a government of European Russia, lying
                    between lat. 61° and 71° N., and long. 29° and 68° E. It is bounded on the N. by
                    the White Sea and Arctic Ocean, on the W. by Finland and Olonetz, on the S. by
                    Vologda, and on the E. by the Ural Mountains. It comprehends the islands of
                    Nova-Zembla, Waigatz, and some others. Its area is estimated at 286,739 square
                    miles, and its population in 1867 was 275,779. The climate is for the greater
                    part of the year intensely cold. That part of Archangel which lies within the
                    arctic circle has a very desolate and sterile aspect, presenting little to the
                    eye but extensive plains of sand and moss. The winter is long and severe, and
                    even in summer the soil is frozen at a little depth below the surface. The
                    rivers are closed in September, and scarcely thawed before July. South of the
                    arctic circle the greater part of the country is covered with immense forests,
                    with extensive lakes and morasses, while other parts afford excellent pasturage.
                    The spring is moist, with cold, frosty nights; the summer, a succession of long
                    foggy days; the autumn moist; and the rivers are closed from October to April.
                    The northern districts are incapable of being cultivated, and the inhabitants
                    support themselves by fishing and the chase. In the southern districts
                    considerable quantities of hemp and flax are raised, but grain crops are little
                    attended to, and the bark of trees is ground with com to eke out the scanty
                    products of the harvest.· Potatoes are grown as far north as 65°. The principal
                    wealth of the government consists in its immense forests, furnishing materials
                    for shipbuilding, which is carried on to a considerable extent. The horses and
                    cattle are diminutive, except in the district of Kholmogory, where excellent
                    cattle are reared. The calves are sent to the St Petersburg market, where the
                    veal is especially prized. Gold is found in the circle of Cola, naphtha and salt
                    in those of Kem and Pinega, and coal, or rather lignite, in several places in
                    Mezen. The preparation of pitch and tar is an active branch of industry; and in
                    the districts around Archangel coarse linens are manufactured to a considerable
                    extent, as well as cordage, mats, leather, tallow, turpentine, and potash. This
                    government is divided into eight circles, viz.—Archangel, Shenkursk, Mezen,
                    Cola, Onega, Pinega, Kholmogory, and Kem. Its chief rivers are the Onega,
                    Pinega, Dwina, Mezen, Petshora, and Ousa. Sulphurous springs are found in the
                    circles of Kholmogory and Shenkursk. The population was originally Finnish, but
                    it is now chiefly Russian, with some Samoides and Laplanders.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Archangel,</hi> the chief town of the Russian government of
                    the same name, is situated at the head of the delta of the Dwina, on the right
                    bank of the river, in lat. 64 <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> 32' 8" N., and
                    long. 40° 33' E. As early as the 10th century the Norsemen had commercial
                    settlements in the district; but the modern town may be said to date from the
                    visit paid by the English voyager, Chancelor, to the monastery of St Nicholas,
                    whither he was driven by stress of weather in 1553. An English factory was soon
                    after erected there by consent of Ivan II., and in 1584 a fort was built, and a
                    town gradually gathered round it, which received the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Arlehangelsleoi^Gorod,</hi> from a monastery dedicated to the archangel
                    Michael. The town long remained the only seaport of Russia, and enjoyed
                    remarkable prosperity. Czar Boris Godunoff (1598-1605) made the trade through
                    Archangel to Moscow open to all nations, and Holland and Germany took advantage
                    of the permission. In 1655 the exports amounted to 600,000 roubles. In 1668 the
                    great bazaar, or <hi rend="italic">“Gostinnoi-Gorod,'</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi> â strong building of stone, was commenced at the command of
                    Alexei Michaelovich, and employed the labour of thousands of Tatar prisoners for
                    16 years. In 1693-94 Peter the Great visited the town, which was then at the
                    height of its prosperity; the average annual value of the exports from 1691-1700
                    to England alone amounting to £112,210. When, in the beginning of the 18th
                    century the czar was establishing St Petersburg, he did all he could to divert
                    the population and prosperity of Archangel to the new metropolis, causing many
                    of the wealthier inhabitants to remove, and imposing heavy taxes on the
                    commerce. As a natural consequence, the northern city declined. In 1762 it
                    received the same immunities as St Petersburg, and since that time has gradually
                    recovered its former prosperity. It is the seat of an archbishop and of a civil
                    and a military governor, and has one Protestant and ten Greek churches, an
                    ecclesiastical seminary, a gymnasium, academies for navigation and engineering,
                    a naval hospital, and a Government bank. The manufactures are linen, leather,
                    canvas, cordage, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n390/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0390-0369"/> mats, sugar, and beer. The exports are flax,
                    flax-tow and codilia, oats, linseed, wheat, deals, tar, pitch, rosin, mats, beef
                    and pork, calf and seal skins, train-oil, cordage, feathers, and linseed cakes.
                    Flax, in large quantity, is used in the spinning factories in the interior. The
                    imports are coal, oil, wine, coffee, sugar, tea, logwood, furs, lead, salt, and
                    fish. The total value of the exports in 1874 amounted to £1,234,390 in 472
                    ships, of which 62 were steamers and 220 coasting vessels, a large proportion
                    being carried to Great Britain. The coasting trade between Archangel and
                    Norwegian Finmark is extensive. The domestic trade consists chiefly in meat,
                    fish, train-oil, game, and furs. By river and canal Archangel is in connection
                    with a large part of European Russia, and a telegraph line unites it with St
                    Petersburg. The harbour is at the island of Solombaly, about a mile below the
                    town, and is open only from June to October. A bar at the month of the Dwina,
                    with only 13 or 14 feet of water, obliges vessels of greater draught to load and
                    unload outside by means of lighters. About 12 miles below the town there is a
                    Government dockyard, with slips for building vessels, and also some warehouses
                    belonging to merchants in the city. The best season of the year in Archangel is
                    from the middle of June to the middle of August. After that period the nights
                    become cold; and in September it is often stormy. The shortest day has only 3
                    hours 12 minutes, the longest 21 hours 48 minutes. Population in 1867,
                    19,936.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
