<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0697-0636-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ART</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 636</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:861276">Ciceronianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="42" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="42" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c0c">Logic</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n697/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ART</label>, in the most extended and most popular sense of
                    the word, means everything which we distinguish from Nature. Art and Nature are
                    the two most comprehensive genera of which the human mind has formed the
                    conception. Under the genus Nature, or the genus Art, we include all the
                    phenomena of the universe. But as our conception of Nature is indeterminate and
                    variable, so in some degree is our conception of Art. Nor does such ambiguity
                    arise only because some modes of thought refer a greater number of the phenomena
                    of the universe to the genus Nature, and others a greater number to the genus
                    Art. It arises also because we do not strictly limit the one genus by the other.
                    The range of the phenomena to which we point when we say Art, is never very
                    exactly determined by the range of the other phenomena which at the same time we
                    tacitly refer to the order of Nature. Everybody understands the general meaning
                    of a phrase like Pope’s “Blest with each grace of nature and of art.” In such
                    phrases we intend to designate familiarly as Nature all which exists
                    independently of our study, forethought, and exertion—in other words, those
                    phenomena in ourselves or the world which we do not originate but find; and we
                    intend to designate familiarly as Art, all which we do not find but originate—or
                    in other words, the phenomena which we do add by study, forethought, and
                    exertion to those existing independently of us. But we do not use these
                    designations consistently. Sometimes we draw an arbitrary line in the action of
                    individuals and societies, and say, Here Nature ends and Art begins—such a law,
                    such a practice, such an industry even, is natural, and such another is
                    artificial; calling those natural which happen spontaneously and without much
                    reflection, and the others artificial. But this line different observers draw at
                    different places. Sometimes we adopt views which waive the distinction
                    altogether. One such view is that wherein all phenomena are regarded as equally
                    natural, and the idea of Nature is extended so as to include “all the powers
                    existing in either the outer or the inner world, and everything which exists by
                    means of those powers.” In this view Art becomes a part of Nature. It is
                    illustrated in the familiar passage of Shakspeare, where Polixenes reminds
                    Perdita that—</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “Nature is made better by no mean, </l>
                    <l part="N"> But nature makes that mean: so, over that art </l>
                    <l part="N"> Which, you say, adds to nature, is an art </l>
                    <l part="N"> That nature makes.” … </l>
                    <l part="I"> “there is an art </l>
                    <l part="F"> Which doth mend nature,—change it, rather, but </l>
                    <l part="N"> The art itself is nature.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>A posthumous essay of Mr John Stuart Mill contains a full philosophical
                    exposition and defence of this mode of regarding the relations of Nature and
                    Art. Defining Nature as above, and again as a “collective name for all facts,
                    actual and possible,” that writer proceeds to say that such a definition—·</p>
                <quote> "Is evidently inapplicable to some of the modes in which the word is
                    familiarly employed. For example, it entirely conflicts with the common form of
                    speech by which Nature is opposed to Art, and natural to artificial. For in the
                    sense of the word Nature which has thus been defined, and which is the true
                    scientific sense, Art is as much Nature as anything else; and everything which
                    is artificial is natural—Art has no independent powers of its own: Art is but
                    the employment of the powers of Nature for an end. Phenomena produced by human
                    agency, no less than those which, as far as we are concerned, are spontaneous,
                    depend on the properties of the elementary forces, or of the elementary
                    substances and their compounds. The united powers of the whole human race could
                    not create a new property of matter in general, or of any one of its species. We
                    can only take advantage for our purposes of the properties we find. A ship
                    floats by the same laws of specific gravity and equilibrium as a tree uprooted
                    by the wind and blown into the water. The corn which men raise for food, grows
                    and produces its grain by the same laws of vegetation by which the wild rosé and
                    the mountain strawberry bring forth their flowers and fruit. A house stands and
                    holds together by the natural properties, the weight and cohesion of the
                    materials which compose it. A steam engine works by the natural expansive force
                    of steam, exerting a pressure upon one part of a system of arrangements, which
                    pressure, by the mechanical properties of the lever, is transferred from that to
                    another part, where it raises the weight or removes the obstacle brought into
                    connection with it. In these and all other artificial operations the office of
                    man is, as has often been remarked, a very limited one; it consists of moving
                    things into certain places. W e move objects, and by doing this, bring some
                    things into contact which were separate, or separate others which were in
                    contact; and by this simple change of place, natural forces previously dormant
                    are called into action, and produce the desired effect. Even the volition which
                    designs, the intelligence which contrives, and the muscular force which executes
                    these movements, are themselves powers of Nature.” </quote>
                <p>Another mode of thought, in some sort complementary to the last, is based on the
                    analogy which the operations of forces external to a man bear to the operations
                    of man himself. Study, forethought, and exertion are assigned to Nature, and her
                    operations are called operations of Art. This view was familiar to ancient
                    systems of philosophy, and especially to that of the Stoics. According to the
                    report of Cicero, Nature as conceived by Zeno was a fire, and at the same time a
                    voluntary agent having the power or art of creating things with regularity and
                    design (naturam esse ignem artificiosum ad gignendum progredientem via). To this
                    fire not merely creative force and systematic action were ascribed, but actual
                    personality. Nature was “non artificiosa solum, sed plane artifex.” “That which
                    in the works of human art is done by hands, is done with much greater art by
                    Nature, that is, by a fire which exercises an art and is the teacher of other
                    arts.” This conception of Nature as an all-generating fire, and at the same time
                    as a personal artist both teaching and including in her own activity all the
                    human arts, on the one hand may be said, with Polixenes and Mr Mill, to merge
                    Art in Nature; but on the other hand it finds the essence of Nature in the
                    resemblance of her operations to those of Art. “It is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >proprium</hi> of art,” according to the same system, “to create and beget,” and
                    the reasoning proceeds—Nature creates and begets, therefore Nature is an artist
                    or Demiurgus.</p>
                <p>But these modes of thought by which Art is included under Nature, or Nature
                    identified with Art, or both at once, are exceptional. In ordinary use the two
                    conceptions, each of them somewhat vague and inexact, are antithetical. Their
                    antithesis was what Dr Johnson had chiefly in his mind when he defined Art as
                    “the power of doing something which is not taught by Nature or by instinct.” But
                    this definition is insufficient, because the abstract word Art, whether used of
                    all arts at once or of one at a time, is a name not only for the power of doing
                    something, but for the exercise of the power; and not only for the exercise of
                    the power, but for the rules according to which it is exercised; and not only
                    for the rules, but for the result. Painting, for instance, is an art, and the
                    idea includes not only the power, to paint, but the act of painting; and not
                    only the act, but the laws for performing the act rightly; and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n698/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0698-0637"/> not only all these, but the material consequences
                    of the act or the thing painted. So of agriculture, navigation, and the rest.
                    Exception might also be taken to Dr Johnson’s definition on the ground that it
                    excludes all actions of instinct from the genus Art, whereas usage has in more
                    languages than one given the name of Art to several of those ingenuities in the
                    lower animals which popular theory at the same time declares to be instinctive.
                    Dante, for instance, speaks of boughs shaken by the wind, but not so violently
                    as to make the birds forego their Art,—</p>
                <p>“Non perδ dal lor esser dritto sparto Tanto, ehe gl’augelletti per lor cime
                    Lasciasser &lt;Γoperar ogni lor <hi rend="italic">arte.”</hi></p>
                <p>And Fontenelle, speaking the language not of poetry but of science :—“Most
                    animals—as, for instance, bees, spiders, and beavers—have a kind of art peculiar
                    to themselves; but each race of animals has no more than one art, and this one
                    has had no first inventor among the race. Man, on the other hand, has an
                    infinity of different arts which were not born with his race, and of which the
                    glory is his own.” Dr John-son might reply that those properties of variety and
                    of originality or individual invention, which Fontenelle himself alleges in the
                    ingenuities of man but not in those of the lower animals, are sufficient to make
                    a generic difference, and to establish the impropriety of calling a honeycomb or
                    a spider’s web a work of Art. It is not our purpose to trespass on ground so
                    debateable as that of the nature of consciousness in the lower animals. Enough
                    that when we use the term Art of any action, it is because we are thinking of
                    properties in the action from which we infer, whether justly or not, that the
                    agent voluntarily and designedly puts forth skill for known ends and by regular
                    and uniform methods. If, then, we were called upon to frame a general definition
                    of Art, leaving room for every accepted usage of the word, it would run thus :—
                    <hi rend="italic">Every regulated operation or dexterity by which organised
                    beings pursue ends which they know beforehand, together with the rules and the
                    result of every such operation or dexterity.</hi></p>
                <p>Here it will be well to consider very briefly the natural history of the name
                    which has been given to this very comprehensive conception by the principal
                    branches of civilised mankind. Our own word Art the English language has taken,
                    as all the Romance languages of modern Europe have taken theirs, directly from
                    the Latin. The Latin <hi rend="italic">ars</hi> proceeds from a root the
                    primitive force of which is open to question. One distinguished philologist
                    thinks that this syllable AR, in that root from which <hi rend="italic">ars</hi>
                    is descended, means to plough, and is the same as appears in the Greek <hi
                    rend="italic">àp-ovv,</hi><hi rend="italic">ap-oτpov,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >âp-ovpa,</hi> and Latin <hi rend="italic">ar-are, ar-atrum,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">arvum,.</hi> “As agriculture was the principal labour in that
                    early state of society when we must have supposed most of our Aryan words to
                    have been formed and applied to their definite meanings, we may well understand
                    how a word which originally meant this special kind of labour was afterwards
                    used to signify labour in general And as ploughing was not only one of the
                    earliest kinds of labour, but also one of the most primitive arts, I have no
                    doubt that the Latin <hi rend="italic">ars,</hi><hi rend="italic">artis,</hi>
                    and our own word <hi rend="italic">art,</hi> meant originally the art of all
                    arts, first taught by the goddess of all wisdom, the art of cultivating the
                    land.”— (Max Miiller, <hi rend="italic">Leet, on Science of Language,</hi> i.
                    294.) The more common supposition refers the word to a root AR, of which the
                    primitive signification will have been to put or fit two tilings together, and
                    which is to be found in a large family of Greek words, such as <hi rend="italic"
                    >άράρ-ι,σκε,</hi><hi rend="italic">aρ-μεvoς, ap-θpov, aρ-t,θμoς,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">àp</hi><hi rend="italic">-τνω,</hi><hi rend="italic">κ.τ.λ.</hi>
                    As a question of historical probability, the latter account seems the likelier,
                    inasmuch as predatory and nomadic man was certainly in possession of many
                    dexterities, as that of fitting a stone arrow-head to its shaft,—or say, that of
                    putting two and two together,— from which, rather than from the later invention
                    of agriculture, the group of human dexterities in general is likely to have
                    received its name.</p>
                <p>The Greek <hi rend="italic">τεχyη,</hi> the name both for arts in the particular
                    and art in the abstract, is by its root related both to τcκ-τωv and <hi
                    rend="italic">τεκ-vov,</hi> and thus contains the allied ideas of making and
                    begetting. The <hi rend="italic">proprium,</hi> of art in the logic of the
                    Stoics “to create and beget” (see above) was strictly in accordance with this
                    etymology.</p>
                <p>The Teutonic <hi rend="italic">Kunst</hi> is formed from <hi rend="italic"
                    >können,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">können</hi> is developed from a primitive
                    <hi rend="italic">Ich kann.</hi> In <hi rend="italic">kann</hi> philology
                    recognises a preterite form of a lost verb, of which we find the traces in <hi
                    rend="italic">Kin-d,</hi> a child; and the form <hi rend="italic">Ich kann,</hi>
                    thus meaning originally “I begot,” contains the germ of the two several
                    developments,— <hi rend="italic">können,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> to be
                    master,” “to be able,” and <hi rend="italic">kennen,</hi> “to know.”</p>
                <p>Putting by, then, as too doubtful the etymology of <hi rend="italic">ars</hi>
                    from ploughing, we see that the chief Aryan languages have with one consent
                    extended a name for the most elementary exercise of a constructive or productive
                    power, till that name has covered the whole province of the skilled and
                    deliberate operations of sentient beings.</p>
                <p>In proportion as men left out of sight the idea of creation, of constructing or
                    producing, “artificiosum esse ad gignendum,” which is the primitive half of this
                    extended notion, and attended only to the idea of skill, of proceeding by
                    regular and disciplined methods, “progredi via,” which is the superadded half,
                    the whole notion Art, and the name for it, might become subject to a process of
                    thought which, if analysed, would be like this :—What is done by regular and
                    disciplined methods is Art; facts are observed and classified, and a systematic
                    view of the order of the universe obtained, by regular and disciplined methods;
                    the observing and classifying of facts, and obtaining a systematic view of the
                    order of the universe, is therefore Art. To a partial extent this did
                    unconsciously take place. Science, of which the essence is only in knowledge and
                    contemplation, came to be spoken of as Art, of which the essence is all in
                    practice and production. Cicero, notwithstanding his citation of the Stoical
                    dictum that practice and production were of the essence of Art, elsewhere
                    divides Art into two kinds—one by which things are only contemplated in the
                    mind, another by which something is produced and done. (“Quumque artium aliud
                    eiusmodi sit, ut tantummodo rem cernat; aliud, ut moliatur aliquid et faciat.”—
                    <hi rend="italic">Λcad.</hi> ii. 7.) Of the former kind his instance is
                    geometry; of the latter the art of the violin player. Now geometry,
                    understanding by geometry an acquisition of the mind, that is, a collected body
                    of observations and deductions concerning the properties of space and magnitude,
                    is a science and not an art; although there is an art of the geometer, which is
                    the skill by which he solves any given problem in his science, and the rules of
                    that skill, and his exertion in putting it forth. And so every science has its
                    instrumental art or practical discipline; and in as far as the word Art is used
                    only of the practical discipline or dexterity of the geometer, the astronomer,
                    the logician, the grammarian, or other person whose business it is to collect
                    and classify facts for contemplation, in so far the usage is just. The same
                    justification may be extended to another usage, whereby in Latin, and some of
                    its derivative languages, the name Art came to be transferred in a concrete
                    sense to the body of rules, the written code or manual, which lays down the
                    discipline and regulates the dexterity; as <hi rend="italic">ars</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">grammatica,</hi><hi rend="italic">ars</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >rhetorica,</hi> and the rest. But when the word is stretched so as to mean the
                    sciences themselves as acquisitions of the mind, that meaning is illegitimate.
                    Whether or not Cicero, in the passage above quoted, had in his mind the science
                    of geometry as a collected body of observations and deductions<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0699-0638"/>, it is certain that the Ciceronian phrase of the
                    <hi rend="italic">liberal arts,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">ingenuozιs arts,</hi>
                    both in Latin and its derivatives or translations in modern speech, has been
                    used currently to denote the sciences themselves, and not merely the disciplines
                    instrumental to them. The <hi rend="italic">trivium</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">quadrivium</hi> (grammar, logic, and rhetoric—geometry, astronomy,
                    music, and arithmetic) have been habitually called arts, when some of them have
                    been named in that sense in which they mean not arts but sciences, “only
                    contemplating things in the mind?’ In the German language particularly the words
                    Art and Science have in general been loosely interchanged. The etymology of the
                    word for Art secured a long continuance for this ambiguity. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kunst</hi> was employed indiscriminately in both the senses of the primitive
                    <hi rend="italic">Ich kann,</hi> to signify what I know, or Science, and what I
                    can do, or Art. It was not till the end of the 17th century that a separate word
                    for Science, the modern <hi rend="italic">Wissenschaft,</hi> came into use. On
                    the other hand, the Greek word <hi rend="italic">τeχyη,</hi> with its distinct
                    suggestion of the root signification to make or get, acted probably as a
                    safeguard against this tendency. The distinction between <hi rend="italic"
                    >τcχyη,</hi> Art or practice, and <hi rend="italic">eπurrημη,</hi> knowledge or
                    Science, is observed, though not systematically, in Greek philosophy. But for
                    our present purpose, that of making clear the true relation between the one
                    conception and the other, further quotation is rendered superfluous by the
                    discussion the subject has received at the hands of the modern writer already
                    quoted. Between Art, of which we. practise the rules, and Science, of which we
                    entertain the doctrines, Mr Mill establishes the difference in the simplest
                    shape, by pointing out that one grammatical mood is proper for the conclusions
                    of Science, and another for those of Art. Science enunciates her conclusions in
                    the indicative mood, whereas “the imperative is the characteristic of Art, as
                    distinguished from Science.” And as Art utters her conclusions in her own form,
                    so she supplies the substance of her own major premise.</p>
                <p>“Every art has one first principle, or general major premise, not borrowed from
                    science, that which enunciates the object aimed at, and affirms it to be a
                    desirable object. The builder’s art assumes that it is desirable to have
                    buildings; architecture (as one of the fine aids) that it is desirable to have
                    them beautiful and imposing. The hygienic and medical arts assume, the one that
                    the preservation of health, the other that the cure of disease, are fitting and
                    desirable ends. These are not propositions of science. Propositions of science
                    assert a matter of fact—an existence, a co-existence, a succession, or a
                    resemblance. The propositions now spoken of do not assert that anything is, but
                    enjoin or recommend that something should be. They are a class by themselves. A
                    proposition of which the predicate is expressed by the words <hi rend="italic"
                    >ought</hi> or <hi rend="italic">should be</hi> is generically different from
                    one which is expressed by <hi rend="italic">is</hi> or <hi rend="italic">will
                    be."</hi></p>
                <p>And the logical relation of Art and Science, in other words, the manner of
                    framing the intermediate member between the general major premise of Art and its
                    imperative conclusion, is thus defined :—</p>
                <p>“The Art [in any given case] proposes to itself an end to be attained, defines
                    the end, and hands it over to the Science. The Science receives it, considers it
                    as a phenomenon or effect to be studied, and having investigated its causes and
                    conditions, sends it back to Art with a theorem of the causes and combinations
                    by which it could be produced. Art then examines these combinations of
                    circumstances, and according as any of them are or are not in human power,
                    pronounces the end attainable or not. The only one of the premises, therefore,
                    which Art supplies, is the original major premise, which asserts that the
                    attainment of the given end is desirable. Science, then, lends to Art the
                    proposition (obtained by a series of inductions or deductions) that the
                    performance of certain actions will attain the end. From these premises Art
                    concludes that the performance of these actions is desirable, and finding it
                    also practicable, converts the theorem into a rule or precept The grounds, then,
                    of every rule of</p>
                <p>Art are to be found in the theorems of Science. An Art, or a body of Art,
                    consists of the rules, together with as much of the speculative propositions as
                    comprises the justification of these rules. The complete Art of any matter
                    includes a selection of such a portion from the Science as is necessary to show
                    on what conditions the effects, which the Art aims at producing, depend. And Art
                    in general consists of the truths of Science arranged in the most convenient
                    order for practice, instead of the order which is most convenient for thought.
                    Science groups and arranges its truths so as to enable us to take in at one view
                    as much as possible of the general order of the universe. Art, though it must
                    assume tho same general laws, follows them only into such of their detailed
                    consequences as have led to the formation of rules of conduct, and brings
                    together from parts of the field of Science most remote from one another, the
                    truths relating to the production of the different and heterogeneous causes
                    necessary to each effect which the exigencies of practical life require to be
                    produced.”—(Mill’s <hi rend="italic">Logic,</hi> vol. ii. pp. 542-549.)</p>
                <p>The whole discussion may be summed up thus. Science consists in knowing, Art
                    consists in doing. What I must do in order to know, is Art subordinate to or
                    concerned in Science. What I must know in order to do, is Science subordinate to
                    or concerned in Art.</p>
                <p>Art, then, is defined by two broad distinctions: first, its popular distinction
                    from Nature; and next, its practical and scientific distinction from Science.
                    Both of these distinctions are observed in the terms of our definition given
                    above. Within the proper limits of this definition, the conception of Art, and
                    the use of the word for it, have undergone sundry variations. These variations
                    correspond to certain vicissitudes or developments in the order of historical
                    facts and in society. It remains very briefly to consider the chief of these.
                    The requirements of society, stimulating the ingenuity of its individual
                    members, have led to the invention of arts and groups of arts, constantly
                    progressing, with the progress of civilisation, in number, in complexity, and in
                    resource. The religious imagination of early societies, who find themselves in
                    possession of such an art or group of arts, forgets the history of the
                    invention, and assigns it to the inspiration or special grace of some god or
                    hero. So the Greeks assigned the arts of agriculture to Triptolemus, those of
                    spinning and navigation to Athene, and of music to Apollo. At one stage of
                    civilisation one art or group of arts is held in higher esteem, another at
                    another. In societies, like most of those of the ancient world, where slaves
                    were employed in domestic service, and upon the handicrafts supplying the
                    immediate utilities of life—food, shelter, and clothing—these constituted a
                    group of servile arts. The arts of husbandry or agriculture, on the other hand,
                    have alternately been regarded as servile and as honourable according as their
                    exercise has been in the hands of a subject class, as under feudal institutions,
                    or, as under the Roman republic, of free cultivators. Under feudal institutions,
                    or in a society in a state of permanent war, the allied arts of war and of
                    government have been held the only honourable class. In commercial states, like
                    the republics of Italy, the arts of gain, or of production (other than
                    agricultural) and distribution, have made good their title to equal estimation
                    and greater power beside the art of captains. But among peaceful arts,
                    industries, or trades, some have always been held to be of higher and others of
                    lower rank; the higher rank being assigned to those that required larger
                    operations, higher training, or more thoughtful conduct, and yielded ampler
                    returns—the lower rank to those which called for simple manual exercise,
                    especially if such exercise was of a disagreeable or degrading kind. In the
                    cities of Italy, where both commerce and manufactures were for the first time
                    organised on a considerable scale, the name <hi rend="italic">arte,</hi> Art,
                    was retained to designate the guilds or corporations by which the several
                    industries were exercised; and, according to the nature of the industry, the art
                    was classed as higher or lower <hi rend="italic">(maggiore</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">minore).</hi></p>
                <p>The arts of which we have hitherto spoken have arisen from positive requirements,
                    and supply what are strictly utilities, in societies, not excluding the art of
                    war, at least <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n700/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0700-0639"/> so far as concerns one-half of war, the defensive
                    half. But war continued to be an honourable pursuit, because it λvas a pursuit
                    associated with birth, power, and wealth, as well as with the virtue of courage,
                    in cases where it had no longer the plea of utility, but was purely aggressive
                    or predatory; and the arte of the chase have stood in this respect in an
                    analogous position to those of war.</p>
                <p>There are other arts which have not had their origin in positive practical needs,
                    but have been practised from the first for pleasure or amusement. The most
                    primitive human beings of whom we have any knowledge, the cave-dwellers of the
                    palaeolithic period, had not only the useful art of chipping stones into
                    spear-heads, knife-heads, and arrow-heads, and making shafts or handles of these
                    implements out of bone; they had also the ornamental art of scratching upon the
                    bone handle the outlines of the animals they saw—mammoth, rhinoceros, or
                    reindeer—or of carving such a handle into a rude resemblance of one of these
                    animals. Here we have a skill exercised, in the first case, for pure fancy or
                    pleasure, and in the second, for adding an element of fancy or pleasure to an
                    element of utility. Here, therefore, is the germ of all those arts which produce
                    imitations of natural objects for purposes of entertainment or delight, as
                    painting, sculpture, and their subordinates; and of all those which fashion
                    useful objects in one way rather than another because the one way gives pleasure
                    and the other does not, as architecture and the subordinate decorative arts of
                    furniture, pottery, and the rest. Arts that work in a kindred way with different
                    materials are those of dancing and music. Dancing works with the physical
                    movements of human beings. Music works with sound. Between that imitative and
                    plastic subdivision, and the subdivision of these which only produce motion or
                    sound and pass away, there is the intermediate subdivision of eloquence and the
                    drama, which deal with the expression of human feeling in spoken words and acted
                    gestures. There is also the comprehensive art of poetry, which works with the
                    material of written words, and can ideally represent the effects proper to any
                    or all of the other arts. All of these arts have, as a matter of history, been
                    at one time or another intimately associated with religion. Painting, sculpture,
                    architecture, drawing, music, poetry, have all been at one time or another
                    principally devoted to the honour of supernatural beings imagined to have power
                    over mankind for good and evil. But this use, though a part of their history, is
                    not inseparable from their nature. What is inseparable from them, and essential
                    to the nature of this group of arts, is twofold. First, of their effect upon
                    those to whom they are addressed: there are certain highly complex properties
                    and relations of rhythm, proportion, and harmony, .upon which the
                    pleasur-ableness of these arts depends, and which each of them, if its appeal to
                    the perceptions and the imagination is to be successful, is bound to observe.
                    Secondly, of the mode in which they are practised: these complex effects can
                    only be produced by the exercise of an equally complex set of faculties in the
                    artist; it is therefore of the essence of this group of arts, that they cannot
                    be practised by habit, rote, or calculation; habit, rote, and calculation may
                    help the artist a certain way, but in the essential parts of his art he passes
                    beyond the reach of rules, and acts by what is called inspiration, that is, by
                    the spontaneous and unreasoned working together of infinitely complex and highly
                    developed sensibilities and dexterities in his constitution.</p>
                <p>We shaU not concern ourselves with the many definitions that have been framed by
                    thinkers seeking to classify these arts either according to simple observation
                    and comparison, or according to the principles each of his chosen metaphysical
                    system. (For an account of these matters, see articles <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >^Esthetics</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Fine Arts.)</hi> Enough that to-</p>
                <p>gether with the useful arts, there exists this great group of arts of which the
                    end is not use, but pleasure, or pleasure before use, or at least pleasure and
                    use conjointly. In modern language, there has grown up a usage which has not
                    only put these and their congeners into a class by themselves, but sometimes
                    appropriates to them alone the use of the generic word Art, as if they and they
                    only were the arts, κατ’ <hi rend="italic">⅛oχηv.</hi> First as the liberal or
                    polite arts, and then as the fine arts, the languages of modern Europe have
                    separated from the class of arts which exist only for use the class which exist
                    only or chiefly for pleasure. They have gone further, and have reduced the
                    number which the class-word is meant to include. When Art is now currently
                    spoken of in this sense, not even music or poetry is frequently denoted, but
                    only architecture, sculpture, and painting by themselves, or with their
                    subordinate, and decorative branches. And in correspondence with this usage,
                    another usage has removed from the class of <hi rend="italic">arts,</hi> and put
                    into a contrasted class of <hi rend="italic">manufactures,</hi> a large number
                    of industries and their products, to which the generic term Art, according to
                    our definition, properly applies. That definition covers the mechanical arts,
                    which can be efficiently exercised by mere habit, rote, or calculation, just as
                    well as the fine arts, which have to be exercised by a higher order of powers.
                    But the word Art, becoming appropriated to the fine arts, has been treated as if
                    it necessarily carried along with it, and as if works to be called works of art
                    must necessarily possess, the attributes of individual skill and invention
                    expressing themselves <hi rend="smallcaps">id</hi> ever new combinations of
                    pleasurable contrivance. The progress of what an older nomenclature called the
                    mechanical arts—the consequence of inventions for making production easier and
                    more rapid by the application of physical agencies and the economising of human
                    labour—has led to the multiplication of products all alike, all equally bearing
                    the stamp of habit, rote, and calculation, and all equally destitute of those
                    properties of individual contrivance and pleasureableness. And so works of
                    Manufacture, or the products of machinery, which bear only very dully and
                    remotely the mark of their original source in the hand and brain of man, have
                    come to be contrasted with works of Art which bear such marks vividly and
                    directly. For a century the mechanical kingdom, or reign of pure Manufacture,
                    had spread apace in Europe, engrossing an ever larger field of human production.
                    Of late years there is a sign of a reaction in favour of an extension of the
                    kingdom of Art, or at least of endeavours to bring reconciliation and alliance
                    between the two. (s. c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
