<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0198-0185-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">APOLLO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 185</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:965486">Hymns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:896967">Dorians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1747846">Hyacinthia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m29x">Dorians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6g77p">Colophons</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n198/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">APOLLO</label>. The influence of the sun on nature in a
                    country like Greece, either brightening the fields and cheering mankind, or
                    scorching and destroying with a pestilence, or again dispelling the miasma
                    collected from marshes by night, was taken by the Greeks to be under the control
                    of a divine being, to whom they ascribed, on human analogy, a form and character
                    in which were reflected then-own ensations. That divine being they called
                    Apollo, a name which applied to him in two ways, either as αττoλλυωv, from
                    aπoλλυ∕Λt, “the destroyer,” or as ατreλλωv, from ατr∈λλω = α7rapγω, the
                    “repeller of ills.” Apellon is both the Doric and the old Roman form of his
                    name. Under the frequent title of Phoebus, he was hailed as god of the streaming
                    ligh of the sun. Next to its daily course, which, however, was under the
                    guidance of a special subordinate deity, Helios, the most obvious and invariable
                    phenomenon of the sun was its withdrawal in winter and return in summer, and
                    accordingly on this was based one of the principal features in the character of
                    the god, which was also recognised in annual festivals in his honour, and made
                    more explicit by the myth, in which after his birth, amid the splendid summer
                    light of Delos, he is carried off in a car drawn by swans to the fabulous region
                    of the Hyperboreans, where the sun was believed to tarry during the winter. The
                    other class of solar phenomena, being variable in their occurrence, appeared to
                    be directed by a precarious will, and from this was evolved for Apollo the
                    double character of a god possessed of power over the sun, and a the same time
                    guided in the exercise of it by the conduct of mankind. Hence the prominence of
                    expiatory offerings in the worship of a god whom no act of wrong escaped. By his
                    knowledge of what transpired on earth and in the councils of Olympus, he was
                    prepared to be the god of oracles, which threw light on the future and banished
                    the monsters begotten of terror at its obscurity. From observing the jubilant
                    voice of nature greeting the sunshine, it was an easy step to regard Apollo as
                    the god of music; while again the function of a god of medicine was peculiarly
                    appropriate to a deity who, if he destroyed life, also saved it. In many ways
                    the sun gladdened the herdsman and favoured his flock. Hence both Apollo and
                    Helios (Sol) had sacred herds of cattle of their own, while the former when in
                    exile on earth himself acted as a herdsman.</p>
                <p>The honour of having been the birth-place of Apollo was claimed by many
                    districts, but chiefly by Xanthus in Lycia, and the island of Delos, the latter
                    being at last generally agreed upon. In Lycia his worship was of high antiquity,
                    and its extent is vouched for by the identity of the name of that country with
                    one of the favourite epithets of the god, Aυκ∈7oς, from root <hi rend="italic"
                    >λυκ,</hi> as in λυκόφως, Lat. <hi rend="italic">luc-s = lux.</hi> There also
                    his mother Leto (Latona) appears to have been widely worshipped, and thither the
                    solar hero Bellerophon goes to accomplish his labours, showing a community of
                    religious belief between Lycia and Argolis, the home of Bellerophon, for which
                    there is also other evidence. But when the myths concerning Apollo came to be
                    shaped by the poets, his worship had acquired an independent standing in Delos,
                    and had established for that island a claim to the honour of being his
                    birth-place. The belief was that Leto, pursued by the j ealoue Hera (Juno),
                    after long wandering, found shelter in Delos, and there bore to Zeus (Jupiter) a
                    son, Apollo. To this it was added, after the time of Pindar, that Delos had
                    before been a barren rock floating about in the sea, but had been for this
                    purpose and for ever after fastened down by pillars, as also happened to the
                    island of Rhodes, the centre of the worship of Helios. The labour of Latona
                    lasted nine days and nine nights. Then she seized hold of a palm tree, and when
                    the boy was born all the island was dazzled with a flood of golden light. Sacred
                    swans flew in a circle round the island seven times. The day was the 7th of the
                    month Thargelion (May). The 7th of every month was sacred to him. He was styled
                    <hi rend="italic">Εβδoμaγcvη&lt;s,</hi> and otherwise the number seven played a
                    part in his worship. His first step was to seize a bow and to announce his will
                    to found an oracle. To this end his father Jupiter gave him, besides a lyre, and
                    a mitra to bind his hair, a car drawn by swans, with which to proceed to Delphi.
                    But the swans carried him off to their home among the Hyperboreans. Returning
                    with the summer to Delphi, he slew with an arrow the Python, a monster dragon,
                    which was then laying waste the district, established his oracle, and took the
                    title of Pythios. Gaea (Terra) first, and next Themis had previously given
                    oracles there. But this, though the current belief, is at variance with the
                    Homeric Hymn to Apollo, which describes him as selecting Delphi for its site
                    alone, and then relating how, after a temple was built, the difficulty of
                    finding priests was overcome. Seeing a trading ship from Cnossus in Crete, under
                    way for Pylus, the god threw himself on board in the form of a dolphin and
                    guided it to Crissa, the harbour of Delphi, where, like the flash of a star, he
                    resumed his divine form, appointed the traders his priesthood, and with his lyre
                    led the first paean there. Hence his title of Delphinios. But here a confusion
                    has been effected; for, while in one sense Apollo Delphinios was god of the
                    sunny voyages, in another sense he may have derived that epithet from having
                    slain the dragon, the proper name of which was Delphine. Except on the latter
                    theory, there seems to be no explanation of this, among other facts, that his
                    sanctuary at Athens, the Delphinion, was a court for the trial of bloodshed. It
                    may then be supposed that the Dorians from Crete, who had in early times
                    established themselves on the coasts of the Peloponnesus and at Crissa, having
                    an Apollo whose symbol was a dolphin, and finding at Delphi an Apollo styled
                    Delphinios for another reason, combined the two in the new myth which is found
                    in the Homeric Hymn. Besides at Delphi, which however retained the first place,
                    Apollo gave oracles also at Colophon, and at Didymi near Miletus; in the latter
                    place through the priestly family of the Branchidae. To certain mortals he
                    communicated the prophetic gift, as to Cassandra, the Cumaean sibyl, and the
                    seer Epimenides. With his oracular power was associated his function as god of
                    music (Citharoedus), and leader of the Muses (Musagetes), in which capacity he
                    caused Marsyas to be flayed alive because ho had boasted superior skill in
                    playing the flute, or again, caused the ears of Midas to grow long because he
                    had decided in favour of Pan, who contended that the flute was a better
                    instrument than the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n199/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0199-0186"/> lyre. But that which brought Apollo most closely
                    home to the hearts of the people was his character of a destroying but yet an
                    appeasable god. Pestilence and death by an unseen cause, or in the beauty of
                    youth, were traced to him, and to prevent doubt as to his having a good reason
                    in each case, there were the myths which told how, for example, he sent a
                    pestilence on the Greeks before Troy, because Chryseis, the daughter of his
                    priest, was retained in captivity by Agamemnon; or again, how with the aid of
                    his sister Artemis (Diana) he slew the children of Niobe, because she had
                    boasted of their beauty. A typical instance of his causing death undesignedly is
                    that of his favourite, the beautiful young Hyacinthus, who was killed by the
                    disc (a symbol of the sun) which Apollo had thrown in play. Besides accepting
                    atonement in such cases, he was the god of the penitent generally, but
                    especially of those, like Orestes, guilty of a crime which required years of
                    expiation. For such he was himself the prototype, having been twice banished
                    from Olympus, and compelled first to act for a period as herdsman to Admetus,
                    the king of Pherae, and next to assist Poseidon (Neptune) in building the walls
                    of Troy for Laomedon. While thus the power of the sun god was recognised with
                    varying feelings according to occasion, it was, on the other hand, always kept
                    in view as an active principle in nature by the regular system of festivals. Of
                    these the most remarkable was that called Carneia, which was annually held at
                    Sparta in August, the whole population withdrawing from the town for several
                    days, and living in tents to avoid the effect of intense heat. In July, also,
                    the Spartans held a festival of nine days in his honour, called Hyacinthia, the
                    burden of the ceremony being the transitoriness of life mingled with trust in
                    its return. In Athens the festival of Thargelia was held in his honour in May,
                    to celebrate the ripening of the fruits of the field; while in the Metageitnia,
                    in August, he was regarded as the god of plenty, and as the source of
                    neighbourly feeling. At Delphi, among a constant round of ceremonies, two
                    festivals weιe conspicuous: at the beginning of winter, when the god was
                    supposed to go away to the Hyperborean region, and at the beginning of summer,
                    when he was believed to return; the latter event being hailed with every
                    expression of delight in music and song. At Thebes was held every eighth year a
                    peculiar ceremony, Daphnephoria, in honour of Apollo Ismenios, consisting of a
                    procession in which was carried a branch of olive, hung with wreaths and
                    representations of the sun, moon, planets, and stars, the number of wreaths
                    being 365. This object was called the Kopo. In May the ancient national festival
                    at Delos was celebrated. It remains to notice the very prevalent association of
                    Apollo as sun-god with Artemis (Diana) as moon-goddess, the aspect of these two
                    luminaries having readily suggested that their presiding deities were twins. But
                    Apollo and Diana resembled each other also in many attributes of their character
                    as well as in appearance. Just as he was god of the influence of the sun on
                    nature, with a subordinate deity Helios (Sol) to guide the orb, so she
                    personified the power of the moon, delegating its course to the goddess Selene
                    (Luna). In Rome the worship of Apollo was not introduced until 320 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> in which year the city had been visited with a
                    pestilence. The most frequent symbols of Apollo are the bow and the lyre; the
                    tripod, suggesting his oracular power; the laurel, which was carried by
                    penitents as well as worn by victors, and into which Daphne was changed for not
                    yielding to his love; the palm, the wolf, the deer, and the raven. In the ripe
                    period of art Apollo appears in a form which seeks to combine manhood and
                    eternal youth. His long hair is usually tied, like that of his sister Diana, in
                    a large knot above his forehead. As leader of the Muses, he wears long ample
                    drapery girt at the waist, his tresses falling on his shoulders. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a. s. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
