<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0787-0722-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ASSASSINS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 722</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211569">Montserrat</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:979776">Islam</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:818974">Assassins</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:818962">Assassination</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:967643">Imamate</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4086353j">Ansarii</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40000538">Islam</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b40v89h53">Assassination</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mv15">Sects</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n787/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ASSASSINS</label>, a secret military and religious sect
                    formed in Persia and Syria during the 11th century <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.
                    To</hi> understand clearly its nature and tenets, it is necessary to refer to
                    the doctrines of the Ismaélites, of whom it was a branch, and who were
                    themselves an offshoot from the great body of the Shiites. The Shiites, one of
                    the two sects into which the Mahometans had separated, held in opposition to the
                    Sunnites, or orthodox, that the true and only legitimate successor of the
                    Prophet was his son-in-law, Ali. They did not succeed in establishing by force
                    the claims of this family; and, under the dynasties of the 0mmiade and Abbaside
                    caliphs, they were compelled to keep their opinions secret. The large body of
                    Shiites was further divided into several distinct parties, differing principally
                    with regard to the recognised line of -succession from Ali; of these the most
                    powerful was that of the Ismaélites, so called because they held that the Imamat
                    descended in an unbroken line from Ali to Ismael, his seventh successor. The
                    adherents of this sect were most widely spread in Persia, and naturally the
                    special object of their opposition was the Abbaside caliphate of Baghdad, but no
                    active steps were taken by them, until under one of the Persian magi,
                    Abdallah-ibn-Maimun Kadah, they had been organised into a secret society, with
                    definite political objects and peculiar religious or philosophical views.
                    Abdallah, like many of his countrymen, was a free-thinker, and he succeeded in
                    establishing among the Ismaélites a faith, or rather a philosophy, wholly
                    opposed to the doctrines of Islam. The fundamental principles of his creed
                    appear to have been—(1.) The rejection of all fixed rules either of religion or
                    morality; all actions were therefore indifferent, only the internal disposition
                    was of any value; (2.) The belief that the Imams of the line of Ismael were at
                    present invisible, and that, consequently, it was the duty of true believers to
                    yield implicit obedience to the vicegerents on earth of these secret rulers;
                    (3.) The allegorical interpretation of the Koran, whereby any doctrine might be
                    either defended or rejected. He also established a regular system of grades or a
                    hierarchy of ranks among the members of the society; only a few members were
                    fully initiated into the philosophy of indifference, the others were kept in a
                    state of profound ignorance, for the rulers knew how necessary this was in order
                    to secure their obedience.</p>
                <p>The first open attempt to put their principles into practice was made by one
                    Ahmed, surnamed Karmath, whence his followers were called Karmathites. After a
                    sanguinary struggle with the caliphs, lasting during many years, this revolt was
                    quelled. But about the same time an adherent of the sect, named Abdallah, a
                    lineal descendant of Ismael, escaped from prison, into which he had been thrown,
                    and, making his way to Egypt, succeeded in placing himself upon the throne of
                    that country. Under the name of Obeid-Allah-Mahdi, he founded the dynasty of the
                    Fatimites, who took their title from their ancestress, the daughter of Mahomet.
                    Ismaelism thus secured a firm footing in the west, and its doctrines were
                    propagated there with great success. At Cairo a grand lodge was formed in which
                    their philosophical principles were perfected, and the process of initiation
                    carried on in its several grades. While this lodge was at the height of its
                    prosperity there arrived in Egypt a learned <hi rend="italic">dai</hi> or
                    missionary of the Eastern <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n788/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0788-0723"/> Ismaélites, called Hassan Ben Sabbah. The father
                    of this man, a native of Khorassan, and an adherent of the Shiites, had been
                    frequently compelled to profess Sunnite orthodoxy, and from prudential motives
                    had sent his son to study under an orthodox doctor at Nishapur. Here Hassan made
                    the acquaintance of Nizam-el-Mulk, afterwards vizier of the Sultan Malik-Shah.
                    During the reign of Alp-Arslan he remained in obscurity, and then appeared at
                    the court of Malik-Shah, where he was at first kindly received by his old friend
                    the vizier. Hassan, who was a man of great ability, tried to supplant him in the
                    favour of the sultan, but was outwitted and compelled to take his departure from
                    ^ Persia. He went to Egypt, and, on account of his high reputation, was received
                    with great honour by the lodge at Cairo. He soon stood so high in the Caliph
                    Mostansar’s favour as to excite against him the jealousy of the chief general,
                    and a cause of open enmity soon arose. The caliph had nominated first one and
                    then another of his sons as his successor, and in consequence a party division
                    took place among the leading men. Hassan, who adopted the cause of Nezar, the
                    eldest son, found his enemies too strong for him, and was forced to leave Egypt.
                    After many adventures he reached Aleppo and Damascus, and after a sojourn there,
                    settled near Kuhistan. He gradually spread his peculiar modification of
                    Ismaélite doctrine, and having collected a considerable number of followers,
                    formed them into a secret society. In 1090 he obtained, it is said by stratagem,
                    the strong mountain fortress of Alamut in Persia, and removing there with his
                    followers, settled as chief of the famous society afterwards called the
                    Assassins.</p>
                <p>The speculative principles of this body were identical with those of the
                    Ismaelites, but their external policy w as marked by one peculiar and
                    distinctive feature—the employment of secret assassination against all enemies.
                    This practice was introduced by Hassan, and formed the essential characteristic
                    of the sect. In organisation they cl03ely resembled the western lodge at Cairo.
                    At the head was the supreme ruler, the <hi rend="italic">Sheikh-al-Jebal,
                    i.e.,</hi> Chief, or, as it is commonly translated, Old Man of the Mountains.
                    Under him were three <hi rend="italic">Dai-al-Kirbal,</hi> or, as they may be
                    called, grand priors, who ruled the three provinces over which the sheikh’s
                    power extended. Next came the body of <hi rend="italic">Dais,</hi> or priors,
                    who were fully initiated into all the secret doctrines, and were the emissaries
                    of the faith. Fourth were the <hi rend="italic">Refiks,</hi> associates or
                    fellows, who were in process of initiation, and who ultimately advanced to the
                    dignity of <hi rend="italic">dais.</hi> Fifth came the most distinctive class,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Fedavies,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Fedais (i.e.,</hi> the
                    devoted ones), who were the guards or assassins proper. These were all young
                    men, and from their ranks were selected the agents for any deed of blood. They
                    were kept uninitiated, and the blindest obedience was exacted from and yielded
                    by them. When the sheikh required the services of any of them, the selected <hi
                    rend="italic">fedais</hi> were intoxicated with the <hi rend="italic"
                    >hashish,</hi> an opiate made from the juice of hemp leaves, and from which the
                    name Assassin is derived. When in this state they were introduced into the
                    splendid gardens of the sheikh, and surrounded with every sensual pleasure. Such
                    a foretaste of Paradise, only to be granted by their supreme ruler, made them
                    eager to obey his slightest command; their lives they counted as nothing, and
                    would resign them at a word from him. Finally, the sixth and seventh orders were
                    the <hi rend="italic">Lasiks,</hi> or novices, and the common people. Hassan
                    well knew the efficacy of established law and custom in securing the obedience
                    of a mass of people; accordingly, upon all but the initiated, the observances of
                    Islamism were rigidly enforced. As for the initiated, they knew the
                    worthlessness of positive religion and morality; they believed in nothing, and
                    scoffed at the practices of the faithful. The Assassins soon began to make their
                    power felt. One of their first victims was Hassan’s former friend,
                    Nizam-el-Mulk, whose son also died under the dagger of a secret murderer. The
                    death by poison of the Sultan Malik-Shah was likewise ascribed to this dreaded
                    society, and contributed to increase their evil fame. Sultan Sanjar, his
                    successor, made war upon them, but he was soon glad to come to terms with
                    enemies whose operations were invisible, and against whom no precaution seemed
                    available. After a long and prosperous rule Hassan died at an advanced age in
                    1124. He had previously slain both his sons, one on suspicion of having been
                    concerned in the murder of a <hi rend="italic">dai</hi> at Kuhistan, the other
                    for drinking wine, and he was therefore compelled to name as his successor his
                    chief <hi rend="italic">dai,</hi> Kia-Busurg-Omid.</p>
                <p>During the fourteen years’ reign of this second leader, the Assassins were
                    frequently unfortunate in the open field, and their castles were taken and
                    plundered; but they acquired a stronghold in Syria, while their numerous murders
                    made them an object of dread to the neighbouring princes, and spread abroad
                    their evil renown. A long series of distinguished men perished under the daggers
                    of the <hi rend="italic">fedais;</hi> even the most sacred dignity -was not
                    spared. The Caliph Mostarschen-ali-Mansur was assassinated in his tent, and not
                    long after, the Caliph Rashid suffered a similar fate. Busurg-Omid was succeeded
                    by his son Mahomet I., who, during the long period of 25 years, ruthlessly
                    carried out his predecessor’s principles. In his time Massiat became the chief
                    seat of the Syrian branch of the society. Mahomet’s abilities were not great,
                    and tho affections of the people were drawn towards his son Hassan, a youth of
                    great learning, skilled in all the wisdom of the initiated, and popularly
                    believed to be the promised Imam become visible on earth. The old sheikh
                    prevented any attempt at insurrection by slaying 250 of Hassan’s adherents, and
                    the son was glad to make submission. When, however, he attained the throne, he
                    began to put his views into effect. On the 17th of tho month Ramadan, he
                    assembled the people and disclosed to them the secret doctrines of the
                    initiated; he announced that the doctrines of Islam were now abolished, that the
                    people might give themselves up to feasting and joy, for he was the promised
                    Imam, the Caliph of God upon earth. To substantiate these claims he gave out
                    that he was not the son of Mahomet, but was descended from Nezar, son of the
                    Egyptian Caliph Mostansar, and a lineal descendant of Ismael. After a short
                    reign of four years Hassan was assassinated by his brother-in-law, and his son
                    Mahomet II. succeeded. One of his first acts was to slay his father’s murderer,
                    with all his family and relatives; and his long rule, extending over a period of
                    46 years, was marked by many similar deeds of cruelty. He had to contend with
                    many powerful enemies, especially with the great Atabeg Sultan Noureddin, and
                    his more celebrated successor, Jusuf Salaheddin, or Saladin, who had gained
                    possession of Egypt after the death of the last Fatimite caliph, and against
                    whom even secret assassination seemed powerless. During his reign, also, the
                    Syrian branch of the society, under their <hi rend="italic">dai,</hi> Sinan,
                    made themselves independent, and remained so ever afterwards. It was with this
                    Syrian branch that the Crusaders made acquaintance; and it appears to have been
                    their emissaries who slew Count Raymond of Tripoli and Conrad of Montserrat.</p>
                <p>Mahomet III. died from the effects of poison, administered, it is believed, by
                    his son, Jelaleddin Hassan III., who succeeded. He restored the old form of
                    doctrine,— secret principles for the initiated, and Islamism for the people,—and
                    his general piety and orthodoxy procured for him the name of the new Mussulman.
                    During his reign of 12 years no assassinations occurred, and he obtained <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0789-0724"/> a high reputation among the neighbouring princes.
                    Like his father, he was removed by poison, and his son, Ala-eddin Mahomet III.,
                    a child of nine years of age, weak in mind and body, was placed on the throne.
                    Under his rule the mild principles of his father were deserted, and a fresh
                    course of assassination entered on. In 1255, after a reign of 30 years, Alaeddin
                    was slain, with the connivance of his son, Rokneddin, the last ruler of the
                    Assassins. In the following year Hulaku, brother of the Tatar, Mangu Khan,
                    invaded the hill country of Persia, took Alamut and many other castles, and
                    captured Rokneddin. He treated him kindly, and, at his own request, sent him
                    under escort to Mangu. On the way, Rokneddin treacherously incited the
                    inhabitants of Kirdkuh to resist the Tartars. This breach of good faith was
                    severely punished by the khan, who ordered Rokneddin to be put to death, and
                    sent a messenger to Hulaku commanding him to slay all his captives. About 12,000
                    of the Assassins were massacred, and their power in Persia was completely
                    broken. The Syrian branch flourished for some years longer, till Bibars, the
                    Mameluke sultan of Egypt, ravaged their country and nearly extirpated them.
                    Small bodies of them lingered about the mountains of Syria, and are believed
                    still to exist there. Doctrines somewhat similar to theirs are to be met with
                    among the Druses, and particularly among the Ansarii or Nosarii, a small Syrian
                    people, dwelling not far from Latakia. Some writers have thought that these
                    Ansarii are the remnants of the Assassins, but this does not seem possible, for
                    the two sects are at enmity, and in 1809 the stronghold of Massiat, then in
                    possession of some Ismaélites, was attacked and pillaged by the Ansarii.</p>
                <p>See Von Hammer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Assassinen,</hi> 1818; De Sacy, <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">Institut,</hi> iv., 1818, who discusses
                    the etymology fully; <hi rend="italic">Calcutta Review,</hi> vols. lv. lvi.; A.
                    Jourdain in Michaud’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >des</hi><hi rend="italic">Croisades,</hi> ii. pp. 465-484, and translation of
                    the Persian historian Mirkhond in <hi rend="italic">Notices</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et Extraits des Manuscrits,</hi> xiii. p. 143, <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi> On the Ansarii, see Michaud et Poujoulat, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Correspondance d’Orient,</hi> vi. p. 458, <hi rend="italic">sq.;</hi> and F.
                    Walpole, <hi rend="italic">The Ansayrii, or Assassins,</hi> 3 vols., 1851.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
