<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0064-0055-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANIMISM (9th edition, volume 2, page 55)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tb93">Heaven</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n64/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANIMISM</label>, a term formerly employed in Biology to
                    denote the theory of which Stahl is the chief expositor; the theory of the soul
                        <hi rend="italic">(anima)</hi> as the vital principle, cause of the normal
                    phenomena of life, or of the abnormal phenomena of disease. It is now current in
                    the wider anthropological sense given to it by Dr E. B. Tylor <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Primitive Culture,</hi> chapters xi.-xvii.), as including the <hi
                        rend="italic">general doctrine of souls and other spiritual beings.</hi>
                    This application is not only appropriate, but is even rendered indispensable by
                    the absence of any other suitable word; for <hi rend="italic">spiritualism,</hi>
                    though occasionally used in a general sense, has become associated with a
                    particular modern development of animistic doctrine; <hi rend="italic"
                        >anthropomorphism,</hi> if less objectionable, is also to some degree
                    inadequate; while the term <hi rend="italic">theology</hi> cannot be extended to
                    include the lower forms of the doctrine of spiritual beings, and indeed many of
                    its higher developments, except by an ill-considered departure from ordinary
                    usage, which raises in many minds a prejudice against the most reliable results
                    of anthropological inquiry.</p>
                <p>An animistic philosophy, explaining the more strange or striking phenomena of
                    nature by the hypothesis of spiritual agency, is universally prevalent among
                    savage races; and unless the wide-spread animistic beliefs of savages are to be
                    regarded as but degenerate or corrupted relics of those possessed by more
                    cultured peoples,—a theory which can scarcely be held to account for the
                    essential and native appropriateness of animism as it flourishes among races of
                    low culture, and its less appropriate and apparently derivative character as it
                    survives in higher civilisations,—there seems tenable ground for the inference,
                    that an animistic philosophy must have been that which was earliest developed
                    among the prehistoric societies of mankind. Ih accordance with this view,
                    animism may be described as the distinctive philosophy of primitive culture. It
                    is manifestly the outcome and development of that earliest analogical reasoning,
                    which concludes external objects to be animated with a life essentially similar
                    to our own; it is the expression and application of our first general theory of
                    natural causes,—a theory rude and inadequate, yet marvellously self-consistent
                    and serviceable: and its history appears primarily to be that of a dominant and
                    pervading philosophy, applied to explain all the phenomena of nature and life,
                    save only those ordinary sequences which the uncivilised man regards as needing
                    no explanation; afterwards, in the progress of culture, that of a system of
                    thought always more or less modified and restricted by the increase of positive
                    knowledge, and surviving only in greatly refined or greatly enfeebled forms, or
                    only reviving at intervals of time.</p>
                <p>Of the origin of animism perhaps no perfect account has yet been given. It can
                    hardly be said to be obvious why, in uncultured races or individuals, there
                    should arise that invariable tendency to represent natural forces as conscious
                    and anthropomorphic. There is reason to believe, however, that the type of all
                    the forms in which the tendency manifests itself, is to be discovered in the
                    conception of the human soul. Evidently the notion of an animating, separable,
                    and surviving soul commends itself as the ready explanation of many familiar
                    phenomena, and the appropriate instrument of a philosophy which ascribes
                    animation to nature at large; so that thus, according to the account given by Dr
                    Tylor, primitive animism may be considered to have arisen simply from the
                    evidence of men’s senses, interpreted by the crude and childlike science of the
                    prehistoric world. From the sight of life and death it was, he conceives,
                    naturally inferred that every man has a life, or vital principle, the departure
                    of which from his body causes death,—this idea being confirmed by apparent
                    temporary departures, such as swoons and sleep. From the appearance of men seen
                    in dreams and visions, it was not less cogently argued that every man has also a
                    phantom likeness of his body, separable from it so as to appear to others at any
                    distance, and continuing to exist and appear after the bodily death of its
                    proper owner. Accordingly, the definition of the soul in primitive religion
                    would, as in the lower existing religions it actually does, combine these
                    leading qualities in the conception of an “apparitional soul,” which is a thin,
                    unsubstantial human image, the cause of life and thought in the individual it
                    animates, capable of quitting his body for a time or altogether, and so leaving
                    him insensible or dead, and when thus absent from the body appearing to other
                    persons asleep or awake. From this conception, then, animism may reasonably be
                    supposed to have had its origin, especially as other animistic doctrines exhibit
                    such a distinct affinity and relationship to this of the apparitional soul, as
                    almost amounts to a proof of direct derivation from it. The hypothesis being
                    correct, it would, for instance, follow that the lower animals ought to be
                    considered as having souls similar to human souls, inasmuch as they have life,
                    and their phantoms are likewise seen. Moreover, though inert objects, such as
                    clothes or weapons, have not life, yet their phantoms appear to men in dreams,
                    and thus they must be considered as having something of the nature of souls,
                    separable from their grosser part, and surviving its destruction. Now, in fact,
                    both these ideas are recognised in the religions of the lower races. They come
                    into special prominence in the savage and barbaric rite of sacrifice for the
                    dead, where not only are wives and slaves slain to do service to their master’s
                    soul in the world of spirits, but horses and cattle are slaughtered to be
                    spiritually transmitted thither, and clothes, ornaments, and other articles are
                    destroyed, that he may wear and use the “object-souls” thus sent to him. The
                    savage doctrine of a future state, presently to be referred to, also strikingly
                    corroborates the theory of the phantom soul as the origin and centre of
                    animistic thought.</p>
                <p>There remains, however, the difficulty of understanding by what process this
                    rudimentary doctrine of the soul has grown into the great system of developed
                    animism: a system of thought so comprehensive as to hold all nature in a web of
                    vital action and spontaneity; so multiform as to invent some new spirit-race for
                    almost every fresh order of phenomena; so coherent as to create a perfect <hi
                        rend="italic">plexus</hi> of ideas that mutually support and interpret one
                    another; finally, so persistent, that even its more extravagant developments can
                    survive for ages in defiance of accurate knowledge. It is difficult to realise
                    how exceedingly slow and gradual must have been that growth of positive science
                    and its methods of verification, which has allowed a fanciful and little
                    regulated philosophy to take root so firmly and cast its branches so far. Yet
                    only by a great and connected development does it seem possible that animism
                    could be so matured and extended. Regarding many, at least, of the varied forms
                    of animistic belief, there is already sufficient evidence to make it probable
                    that they have arisen by one continuous process of evolution, extending through
                    the lower to the higher civilisation.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n65/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0065-0056"/>
                <p>Thisevidence of continuity of development Dr Tylor represents as partly
                    historical, and partly turning upon the principle of survival in culture. Thus,
                    as among savage tribes, the soul is actually identified with the shadow or the
                    breath, the use of such words as σκιά, <hi rend="italic">πνεύμα,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">umbra, anima, shade,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">spirit,</hi>
                    may be held to show the derivation of the civilised conception of the soul from
                    the same primitive and savage idea. The primitive conception of the soul as
                    consisting of a thin, vaporous, material substance, held its place in ancient
                    philosophy and theology, being supported by such writers as Epicurus and Origen,
                    and was only gradually superseded by the more modern belief of the soul’s
                    immateriality. The elves, fairies, goblins, &amp;c., so well known in modern
                    folk-lore, correspond to the nature-spirits and demons of the savage religions.
                    In these cases there has been survival with considerable change; on the other
                    hand, the continuity of animistic thought is likewise indicated by many
                    instances in which an idea survives with little or no modification. Such
                    instances are to be found in many old customs, and especially among peasants,
                    whose notions of the spiritual world are often almost savage. Thus the ancient
                    funeral sacrifice of the warrior’s horse for him to ride into the other world,
                    which was for the last time in Europe actually and officially done at Treves in
                    1781, is still kept up in form by leading the dead soldier’s horse to his grave.
                    The piece of money is still put in the hand of the corpsé at an Irish wake; and
                    in most countries of Europe may still be seen the pathetic custom of setting out
                    offerings of food for the spirits of the departed. Sacrifices to the deities of
                    wells and rivers, trees and rocks, have continued almost unchanged in the rudest
                    districts of such countries as Russia. As a historical example, the primitive
                    theory of convulsions, delirium, madness, &lt;fcc., being caused by demoniacal
                    possession lasted on among educated people through the Middle Ages, and has only
                    been fairly suppressed by the modern medical schools.</p>
                <p>Proceeding on the inference of continuous development, the same writer has
                    attempted a classification of animistic doctrines as they appear in the
                    religious philosophy of the lower and higher culture. The doctrine of souls, as
                    distinguished from that of other spiritual beings, is first considered. It is
                    found possible to trace the conception of the human apparitional soul in various
                    beliefs concerning ghosts, wraiths, doubles, &lt;tc., which survive among
                    civilised societies long after the soul has ceased to be conceived as material
                    or ethereal. The notion of animal-souls, largely prevalent among savage tribes,
                    still faintly survives in our own country. The doctrine of plant-souls seems
                    long to have formed an important element in the religious philosophies of India;
                    and even the doctrine of object-souls, which exercises unlimited dominion in
                    savage religions, can still be traced as influencing some of the actions, though
                    not, perhaps, the explicit opinions, of civilised men. Closely allied, like
                    these doctrines, to the primitive notion of the apparitional soul, is the belief
                    in the 30uΓs existence after death, which appears either as a doctrine of
                    transmigration, describing the re-birth of souls in successive bodies, or in its
                    more general and more important form as the doctrine of a future life. The
                    latter, as commonly held by savage races, supposes the phantom souls of the
                    departed either to remain here as hovering ghosts, or to be transported to some
                    distant region, there to continue a life more or less similar to the present,
                    but with little or no trace of moral retribution: in more advanced
                    civilisations, however, this doctrine exercises the most powerful moral
                    influence, by distinguishing the heaven of the good from the hell of the wicked.
                    The primary doctrine of souls is next described as leading to the development of
                    the doctrine of other spiritual beings, from the lowest ranks of demons and
                    elves, up to the highest deities of the Pantheon. The life and action of the
                    body being ascribed to a soul, all other phenomena of the universe were in like
                    manner ascribed to soul-like beings or spirits, which are thus, in fact,
                    personified causes. So disease among the lower races is accounted for by
                    possession by demons, who are often themselves human souls, and who enter the
                    bodies of their victims, causing all kinds of illness, and especially those
                    phenomena of convulsion and delirium in which the patient seems actually
                    animated by a spirit not his own. Other events and accidents of life are in the
                    same way accounted for among savages as the acts of the demons, good or evil,
                    whom they believe to pervade the universe; and as these beings are, more often
                    than not, conceived to be souls of deceased men, the consequent worship of
                    divine Manes is the principal religion of the lower state of civilisation. The
                    doctrine of object-souls, expanding into the general doctrine of spirits
                    conveying influence through material objects, becomes the origin of Fetichism
                    and idolatry. Spiritual beings, under a thousand names, are multiplied upon the
                    earth; not only th ose guardian spirits and hurtful demons directly influencing
                    the lives of men, but others, far more numerous, with varied functions to
                    discharge in the economy of the external world. To the lower races all nature
                    being animated nature, every brook and well, every rock and glade, is peopled by
                    nature-spirits; while Heaven and Earth, Sun and Moon, Rain and Wind and Thunder,
                    are either themselves adored, or personified in the character of mighty
                    nature-gods, such as Zeus, Apollo, or Poseidon,— spiritual beings who are, as it
                    were, the great animating souls of their special phenomena. Among the lower
                    races, also, there appears in a rudimentary form that antagonism between a good
                    and evil deity, which forms the fundamental idea of Zoroastrism and Manichaeism.
                    Lastly, the conception of a Supreme Deity appears at a very early stage of
                    civilisation, whether one of the great nature-deities, such as Heaven or Sun, is
                    raised to this royal pre-eminence, or whether a being of the nature of a soul of
                    the world, like the Great Spirit of the North American Indians, is venerated as
                    Creator and Lord of the universe. Then, by a natural evolution, Monotheism is
                    established.</p>
                <p>Such, briefly sketched, is Dr Tylor’s account of the development of animism,
                    considered as the main principle of the philosophy of religion, throughout the
                    various grades of civilisation. Whether, having shown many popular superstitions
                    to be undoubted survivals from an ancient state of belief, he has been equally
                    successful in proving a like derivation for doctrines recognised by modern
                    religion, will be questioned by many who perceive the bearing of his conclusions
                    upon the actual validity of theological tenets. It is proper to point out that
                    he has noted one great distinction between the lower and higher animism, which
                    consists in the absence of any distinctly ethical element in the spiritual
                    philosophy of the less cultured races. Only at a comparatively late stage of
                    their development do the moral feelings become associated with animistic
                    beliefs.</p>
                <p>The final decay of many forms of animistic belief, much more readily than the
                    process of their development, admits of being traced with the aid of historical
                    evidence. Indeed, the history of each of the sciences is a record of the
                    progressive substitution of matter for spirit and law for spontaneity; and we
                    can still witness the process of decay in various stages; for while certain
                    sciences—like astronomy, since the time when Kepler imagined minds in the
                    planets—have wholly exterminated the animism within their borders, there are
                    others that have scarcely yet advanced so far—biology, for example, which is
                    still familiar with “vital force” and final causes. Nor is the process commonly
                    a rapid one: in many cases, as a world of illustration has been adduced to
                    prove, a declining <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0066-0057"/> spiritual conception may persist for a length
                    of time, refined and modified into a “principle” or “essence,” whose action,
                    though still automatic like a spirit’s, is also regular like that of a natural
                    law. Among all civilised races, however, animism has long ceased to be known as
                    the universal philosophy or explanation of nature, and its ^remaining
                    manifestations are in great measure reduced to a secondary or rudimentary form.
                    Thus animism survives in the imperfect theories of childhood; it survives also,
                    as we have seen, in the superstitions of the uneducated; and as, in primitive
                    societies, language and imagination fostered the development of spiritual myth,
                    so animism, embodied in metaphor, remains in later civilisations as an important
                    element, if not in truth the very substance of imaginative literature.</p>
                <p>The process by which animism comes to be superseded by positive science is
                    therefore familiar, both in its history and resuite. Regarding its real nature,
                    however, the greatest difference of opinion exists, and there is raised one of
                    the most interesting questions connected with animism—the question of its
                    relation to metaphysics. According to the well-known doctrine of Comte, which,
                    having since his time been expounded and illustrated by several of his
                    followers, would now appear to be accepted by many even of those who do not
                    profess themselves Positivists, animism passes into positive science <hi
                        rend="italic">through</hi> metaphysics. In support of this view there is
                    pointed out, what has just been explained, that as knowledge progresses,
                    anthropomorphic and animistic conceptions rarefy and sublimate into so-called
                    essences or principles, with which conceptions metaphysical discussions are
                    shown to be largely conversant. Systems of ontology betray their history by a
                    hundred clinging vestiges of animism; and all the favourite ideas of the
                    dialectician are to be traced in the symbolism of savage religions. The Platonic
                        <hi rend="italic">ideas,</hi> to take but a single instance, are closely
                    represented by the <hi rend="italic">species-deities</hi> of the North American
                    Indians; while, even in the writings of the master himself, how animistic and
                    mythical is the character they maintain. It is, therefore, concluded that
                    metaphysics is little more than decaying animism, and that a large proportion of
                    animistic theory, before being superseded by positive science, passes through
                    the “metaphysical” stage. From this view of the nature of his science, and its
                    relation to animism, the metaphysician, however, dissents. While admitting that
                    degenerate “metaphysical” conceptions do exist, and that psychology and
                    ontology, more perhaps than other sciences, are confused and retarded by their
                    influence, he refuses to recognise these conceptions as metaphysical in any
                    special or indeed admissible sense. The facts by which the Positivist seeks to
                    prove that animism, as one inadequate explanation of nature, grows into
                    metaphysics, another system of explanation almost equally unsatisfactory, the
                    metaphysician rather regards as proving that metaphysics, a legitimate science,
                    grows out of primitive animism by precisely the same process as other sciences.
                    The discovery in savage or other religions, of dialectical ideas mythically
                    expressed and explained, only confirms him in the belief that there does exist a
                    class of phenomena which it is the business of the science of metaphysics to
                    investigate, since even mythical explanations are seldom formed, unless in the
                    presence of some real problem calling for solution; and he contends that in this
                    way the subject matter of metaphysical science, though long overgrown and
                    encrusted with animistic conceptions, does gradually shine through and assert
                    itself in the light of positive knowledge. If these arguments then be allowed,
                    metaphysics is no decaying animism, but rather a science in the act of
                    struggling free from animism; and animism itself, though often passing in its
                    decay through a phase misnamed metaphysical, is quite improperly represented as
                    undergoing any transformation into metaphysics.</p>
                <p>Reviewing the conclusions countenanced by what evidence we possess touching the
                    nature and history of the doctrine of spiritual beings, we find that while it is
                    possible, and even necessary, to regard animism as a system of primitive
                    philosophy extending through various forms into the higher civilisations, yet
                    this view being for the most part unsupported by direct historical evidence, and
                    depending largely on the inference of a close analogy between primitive and
                    savage thought, is in great measure confessedly theoretical, leaving much room
                    for dispute, both as to the extent to which animistic beliefs have been
                    transmitted and modified by a regular, continuous, and uninterrupted process,
                    and as to the conditions which, in special instances, have led to their
                    formation and development, or disappearance and decay. A theory that represents,
                    not only the extravagances of mythology and superstition, but indeed all that we
                    call spiritual, nay, all that we name divine, as but the fruit of a natural
                    anthropomorphic tendency, much more appropriate to savage than to civilised
                    life, is, it is manifest, in thorough inconsistency with many widely accepted
                    doctrines of philosophy and theology. Regarding the importance of the inquiry
                    there is, however, no dispute. Spiritual philosophy has influenced every
                    province of human thought; and the history of animism, once clearly traced,
                    would record the development, not of religion only, but of philosophy, science,
                    and literature. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. o. l.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
