<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0541-0484-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARES [Mars] (9th edition, volume 2, page 484)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150279">Thracians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914754">Erosion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109953">Scythians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z984">Thracians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w53k">Erosion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n541/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARES <hi rend="smallcaps">[Mars]</hi></label>, in <hi
                        rend="italic">Greek Mythology,</hi> the god of war, not, however, of war in
                    its wide sense, including campaigns, the disposition and command of forces, but
                    in its more primitive meaning of a fierce encounter between bodies of men.
                    Neither the causes nor the ultimate effects of war were ascribed to him. He was
                    simply a personification of the wild impetuous spirit with which battles were
                    fought, and as such he was conceived as the model of a hero, splendidly armed
                    with cuirass, helmet, shield, and spear, swift, of great size (π∈λωpιoς), raging
                        <hi rend="italic">(μαχνόρενος),</hi> murderous <hi rend="italic"
                        >(βροτολοίγός),</hi> unsatiable of war (droς 7roλepoιo). Enyo, the furious
                    war goddess, Eris (Strife), Deimos and Phobos (Dread and Alarm), were usually by
                    his side. Even his mother Hera denounces him <hi rend="italic">(Iliad,</hi> v.
                    761) as senseless, and knowing no bounds. It was doubtless only as an
                    illustration of the habitual strife between Hera and Zeus that Ares was
                    accounted their son. When wounded by Diomedes assisted by Athena <hi
                        rend="italic">(Iliad,</hi> v. 853, <hi rend="italic">ffj),</hi> he fell with
                    a noise like that of nine or ten thousand men in battle; and again <hi
                        rend="italic">(Iliad,</hi> xxi. 400, <hi rend="italic">ffj),</hi> when
                    Athena wounded him with a stone, he fell, and covered with his fall seven acres
                    of ground. On this latter expression it is to be observed, that, while it
                    conveys a picture of broad-strewn carnage consistent with the usual character of
                    Ares, it suggests also, from the measurement given, thoughts of the destruction
                    of cultivated land in war, the more so when taken in connection with the story
                    of Otus and Ephialtes, which reads in the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> (v. 385)
                    like a reminiscence from an earlier time, when war was the dread of the
                    husbandman. These two giants, sons of Aloeus, the planter, born very small, but
                    grown by being fed on grain to immense size, and occupied, as their names imply,
                    with husbandry (Otus = <hi rend="italic">ωθεω,</hi> and Ephialtes =
                    ∈7τι0λλop,αι), had seized Ares and confined him in a large brazen jar for
                    thirteen months, so that for one year there was entire peace over the fields.
                    If, as is not improbable, the first conception of a war god originated in
                    connection with invasion from non-Hellenic tribes, it would be natural to regard
                    him perhaps more as a ruthless destroyer of fields than of human life, and
                    equally natural that this view of his character should die out when war became,
                    so to speak, a trade, as it had become by the time of the Iliad. Even then he
                    was still recognised as a god whose home was among the warlike Thracians <hi
                        rend="italic">(Iliad,</hi> xiii. 298; <hi rend="italic">Odyssey,</hi> viii.
                    361). This, it is true, may have been nothing more than another instance of the
                    Greek tendency to assign a northern or Hyperborean home to deities in whose
                    character something analogous to the stormy elements of nature was found. On the
                    other hand, it appears that the Thracians and Scythians in historical times
                    (Herodotus, i. 59) worshipped chiefly a war god, and that certain Thracian
                    settlements, formed in Greece in prehistoric times, left behind them traces of
                    the worship of a god whom the Greeks called Ares. At Thebes, for instance, had
                    been such a settlement, and there, above all the rest of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n542/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0542-0485"/> Greece, were afterwards found the oldest
                    traditions of the worship of Ares, and that not altogether in the character of a
                    war god. The fountain of Ares guarded by a dragon, and the legend of the
                    Spartae, who sprang from a field sown with dragon’s teeth, seem rather to
                    symbolise some destructive influence in nature, such as that of the sun in
                    summer scorching the fields. That influence of this kind was ascribed to the
                    Thracian god follows from the identification of him with the Sabine and Roman
                    Mars, to the latter of whom the Arvai brethren in Rome made annual sacrifice of
                    a red dog to avert the calamity of the ripe grain taking fire. Apollo is the god
                    who in Greek mythology, as we know it, discharged such functions. But it is
                    argued that in this matter he may have superseded Ares, who on assuming the
                    Thracian character of war god may have gradually resigned his original office.
                    In one of the Homeric hymns Ares is described as a sun god who makes courage and
                    valour stream into the hearts of men, and again, Aeetes, king of Colchis, though
                    a son of Helios, was yet the guardian of the grove of Ares, where was the golden
                    fleece. Meleager, whose valour was displayed against the Calydonian boar, a pest
                    to the fields of Aetolia, was a son of Ares and the fostering nymph Althaea.
                    Oenomaus was a son of Ares and a daughter of the river god Asopus. The dog,
                    which had originally referred to the dog star, remained his symbol, but could
                    only be accounted for by the constant presence of that animal on battle-fields.
                    From the destruction of crops by summer heat to similar destruction by war-like
                    invasion seems a natural step. The next step was to take the point of view of
                    the invader, and to magnify the exploits of war. By the time of Homer this had
                    been done effectually, though traces of an older form of belief remain both in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Odyssey.</hi> Besides
                    those already mentioned, there is the remarkable incident in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> (viii. 266, ff.} where Hephaestos, informed by
                    Helios of the infidelity of his wife Aphrodite with Ares, captures them together
                    in a net, and there holds them for the ridicule of the gods. In what appears to
                    be a very early development of her character, Aphrodite was a war goddess, and
                    was styled Areia. But it is scarcely possible that a phase of character shared
                    also, for example, by Athena, could have suggested such a relation between Ares
                    and Aphrodite, though Hesiod’s statement <hi rend="italic">(fΓheogony,</hi> 934)
                    that Deimos and Phobos were their offspring points in that direction. Again,
                    though Ares and Aphrodite were worshipped together at Thebes, it is not known
                    that they were worshipped there as deities of war. Harmonia, the wife of Cadmus,
                    the founder of that town, was regarded as their daughter. Possibly the
                    connection originated in some other approximation between Ares and Aphrodite in
                    an earlier form of their worship. Women were excluded from the festivals of Ares
                    except at Tegea, in Arcadia, where he was called ywatKoôoAaç. But that exception
                    appears to have been based only on an instance in which that town was
                    successfully defended by its women. While honoured here and there with festivals
                    and sacrifice, as at Sparta, where young dogs, and apparently once men, were
                    offered to him under his title of Enyalios and Theritas, there were yet wanting
                    in his case those local beliefs and traditions which gave vitality to the
                    worship of a god. Next to Thebes, already mentioned, it was at Athens that this
                    vitality obtained most, through the legend attaching to the Areopagus (*Apeιoς
                    7rαγos). The nymph Agraulos had born him a daughter Alcippe, whom Halirrhotius,
                    a son of Neptune, had seized with violence, and for this was slain by Ares, who
                    was tried by a council of the gods sitting on the Areopagus and acquitted. At
                    the foot of the Areopagus was a temple of Arcs, with a statue of the god from
                    the hands of Alcamenes. To judge now of the fluctuation in the conception of
                    Ares from works of art, it is found that previous to the 5th century B.c., he
                    was figured bearded, grim, and heavily armed. From that time, apparently under
                    the influence of Athenian sculptors, who had to render his form in some harmony
                    with their local war goddess Athena, he was conceived as the ideal of a youthful
                    warrior, and for a time associated with Aphrodite and Eros, as in the group of
                    the villa Borghese at Rome, where Eros plays with his weapons, and in many other
                    groups of Ares and Aphrodite in marble and on engraved gems of Roman times. But
                    before this grouping had recommended itself to the Romans, with their legend of
                    Mars and Rhea Silvia, the Greek Ares had again become under Macedonian influence
                    a bearded, armed, and powerful god. The Romans, however, though they readily
                    adopted the Greek Mars and Venus, yet retained the former deity in his native
                    character as a god representing the influence of the sun on cultivated fields,
                    resembling the Mamers of the Mamertines in Sicily, with a wolf as his symbol
                    (Conze, <hi rend="italic">Heroen und</hi><hi rend="italic">Gotter</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Gestalten,</hi> p. 22, Vienna, 1874; Preller, <hi
                        rend="italic">Griechische Mythologie,</hi> i. pp. 251-259; Weicker, <hi
                        rend="italic">Griechische</hi><hi rend="italic">Gotteτlehre,</hi> ί pp.
                    413-424).</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a. s.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">μ.)</hi></p>
                <p>A RESON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jon</hi> (or <hi rend="smallcaps">Hans),</hi> a
                    poet, and the last Roman Catholic bishop in Iceland, was born in 1484. He
                    endured many privations in his youth, and at the age of twenty took holy orders,
                    and was attached as priest to the parish of Helgastad. Here he was taken under
                    the protection of Gottskalk, bishop of Holum, who twice sent him on missions to
                    Norway. He acquitted himself so well that in 1522 he was appointed successor to
                    Gottskalk. To many his election was displeasing, chiefly on account of his
                    ignorance of Latin; and Ogmund, bishop of Skalholt, the other diocese, drove
                    Areson with violence from his bishopric. He was reinstated in 1524, and spent
                    some rather stormy years till 1540, when Frederic III., king of Denmark, wrote
                    to the bishops of Iceland desiring them to take measures for the introduction of
                    Lutheranism. This Areson declined to do, and he even denied the king’s power as
                    head of the church. The greater part of the island, however, became Protestant.
                    In 1548 the Lutheran bishop of Skalholt died, and Areson made an armed excursion
                    into his successor’s territory. For this he was in 1549 declared an outlaw. He
                    again sent an expedition against Skalholt, and captured the bishop, whom he
                    treated with indignity. In 1550 his forces were defeated; he was taken, and
                    executed along with two of his sons. Areson is celebrated as a poet, and as
                    having been the first to introduce printing into Iceland. Several of his poems
                    are collected by Harboe in his <hi rend="italic">History of the Reformation in
                        Iceland.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
