<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0566-0507-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARISTOPHANES (9th edition, volume 2, page 507)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jq0st8x">Wasps</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864856">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170952">Wasps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n566/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARISTOPHANES</label>. The birth-year of Aristophanes is
                    uncertain. He is known to have been about the same age as Eupolis, and is said
                    to have been “almost a boy” (σχ∈δ⅛ <hi rend="italic">peipακiσκο&lt;i)</hi> when
                    his first comedy was brought out in 427 B.c. The most probable conjecture places
                    his birth in or about the year 448 B.c. His father Philippus was a landowner in
                    Aegina. Aristophanes was an Athenian citizen of the tribe Pandionis, and the
                    deme Cydathenê. The stories which made him a native of Cameirus in Rhodes, or of
                    the Egyptian Naucratis, had probably no other foundation than an indictment for
                    usurpation of civic rights <hi rend="italic">(fevlας γpaφf)</hi> which appears
                    to have been more than once laid against him by Cleon. His three sons—
                    Philippus, Arârôs, and Nicostratus—were all comic poets. Philippus, the eldest,
                    was a rival of Eubulus, who began to exhibit in 376 B.c. Arârôs brought out two
                    of his father’s latest comedies,—the Côcalus and the Aeolosicôn, and in 375
                    began to exhibit works of his own. Nicostratus, the youngest, is assigned by
                    Athenaeus to the Middle Comedy, but belongs, as is shown by some of the names
                    and characters of his pieces, to the New Comedy also.</p>
                <p>Plato’s <hi rend="italic">Symposium—</hi> in which Aristophanes has a place at
                    the side of Socrates—shows that Plato bore no more ill-will than his master
                    would have borne to the author of the <hi rend="italic">Clouds.</hi> At the end
                    of that banquet, “Aristodêmus said that Eryximachus, Phaedrus, and others went
                    away; he himself fell asleep, and as the nights were long, took a good rest; he
                    was awakened towards daybreak by a crowing of cocks, and when he awoke, the
                    others were either asleep or had gone away; there remained awake only
                    Aristophanes, Socrates, and Agathon, who were drinking out of a large goblet
                    -which they passed round, and Socrates was discoursing to them. Aristodêmus did
                    not hear the beginning of the discourse, and he was only half awake; but the
                    chief thing which he remembered was Socrates insisting to the other two that the
                    genius of comedy was the same as that of tragedy, and that the writer of tragedy
                    ought to be a writer of comedy also. To this they were compelled to assent,
                    being sleepy, and not quite understanding his meaning. And first of all
                    Aristophanes fell asleep; and then, when the day was already dawning,
                    Agathon.”</p>
                <p>Although tragedy and comedy had their common origin in the festivals of Dionysus,
                    the regular establishment of tragedy at Athens preceded by half a century that
                    of comedy. The Old Comedy may be said to have lasted about 80 years (470-390
                    B.C.), and to have flourished about 56 (4G0-404 B.c.) Of the forty poets who are
                    named as having illustrated it the chief were Cratinus, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n567/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0567-0508"/> Eupolis, and Aristophanes. The Middle Comedy
                    covers a period of about 70 years (390-320 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> its
                    chief poets being Antiphanes, Alexis, Plato Comicus, Theopompus, and Strattis.
                    The New Comedy was in vigour for about 70 years (320-250 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.c.),</hi> having for its foremost representatives Menander Philemon, and
                    Diphilus. The Old Comedy was possible only for a thorough democracy. Its essence
                    was a satirical censorship, unsparing in personalities, of public and of private
                    life—of morality, of statesmanship, of education, of literature, of social
                    usage— in a word, of everything which had an interest for the city or which
                    could amuse the citizens. Preserving all the freedom of banter and of riotous
                    fun to which its origin gave it an historical right, it aimed at associating
                    with this a strong practical purpose—the expression of a democratic public
                    opinion in such a form that no misconduct or folly could altogether disregard
                    it. That licentiousness, that grossness of allusion which too often disfigures
                    it, was, it should be remembered, exacted by the sentiment of the Dionysiae
                    festivals, as much as a decorous cheerfulness is expected at the holiday times
                    of other worships. This was the popular element. Without this the entertainment
                    would have been found flat and unseasonable. But for a comic poet of the higher
                    calibre the consciousness of a recognised power which he could exert, and the
                    desire to use this power for the good of the city, must always have been the
                    uppermost feelings. At Athens the poet of the Old Comedy had an influence
                    analogous, perhaps, rather to that of the journalist than to that of the modern
                    dramatist. But the established type of Dionysiae Comedy gave him an instrument
                    such as no public satirist has ever wielded. When Molière wished to brand
                    hypocrisy he could only make his Tartuffe the central figure of a regular drama,
                    developed by a regular process to a just catastrophe. He had no choice between
                    touching too lightly, and using sustained force to make a profound impression.
                    The Athenian dramatist of the Old Comedy worked under no such limitations of
                    form. The wildest flights of extravagance were permitted to him. Nothing bound
                    him to a dangerous emphasis or a wearisome insistence. He could deal the keenest
                    thrust, or make the most earnest appeal, and at the next moment—if his instinct
                    told him that it was time to change the subject— vary the serious strain by
                    burlesque. He had, in short, an incomparable scope for trenchant satire directed
                    by sure tact.</p>
                <p>Aristophanes is for us the representative of the Old Comedy. But it is important
                    to notice that his genius, while it includes, also transcends the genius of the
                    Old Comedy. He can denounce the frauds of a Cleon, he can vindicate the duty of
                    Athens to herself and to her allies, with a stinging scorn and a force of
                    patriotic indignation which make the poet almost forgotten in the citizen. He
                    can banter Euripides with an ingenuity of light mockery which makes it seem for
                    the time as if the leading Aristo-phanic trait was the art of seeing all things
                    from their prosaic side. Yet it is neither in the denunciation nor in the
                    mockery that he is most individual. His truest and highest faculty is revealed
                    by those wonderful bits of lyric writing in which he soars above everything that
                    can move laughter or tears, and makes the clear air thrill with the notes of a
                    song as free, as musical, and as wild as that of the nightingale invoked by his
                    own chorus in the <hi rend="italic">Birds.</hi> The speech of Dikaios Logos in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Clouds,</hi> the praises of country life in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Peace,</hi> the serenade in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eccleziazusοe,</hi> the songs of the Spartan and Athenian maidens in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Lysistrata,</hi> above all, perhaps, the chorus in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Frogs,</hi> the beautiful chant of the Initiated,—these
                    passages, and such as these, are the true glories of Aristophanes. They are the
                    strains, not of an artist, but of one who warbles for pure gladness of heart in
                    some place made bright by the presence of a god. Nothing else in Greek poetry
                    haβ quite this wild sweetness of the woods. Of modern poets Shakespeare alone,
                    perhaps, has it in combination with a like richness and fertility of fancy.</p>
                <p>Fifty-four comedies were ascribed to Aristophanes. Forty-three of these are
                    allowed as genuine by Bergk. Eleven only are extant. These eleven form a running
                    commentary on the outer and the inner life of Athens during 36 years. We will
                    notice them briefly in the order of their dates. They may be ranged under three
                    periods. The first of these periods, extending to 420 B.c., includes those plays
                    in which Aristophanes uses an absolutely unrestrained freedom of political
                    satire. The second period ends with the year 405. Its productions are
                    distinguished from those of the earlier time by a certain degree of reticence
                    and caution. The third period, down to 388 B.c., comprises two plays in which
                    the transition to the character of the Middle Comedy is well marked, not merely
                    by disuse of the parabasis, but by general self-restraint.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="italic">First Period.</hi></p>
                <p>(1.) 425 B.c. <hi rend="italic">TheAcharnians.—</hi> Since the defeat in Boeotia
                    the peace party at Athens had gained ground, and in this play Aristophanes seeks
                    to strengthen their hands. Dicaeo-polis, an honest countryman, is determined to
                    make peace with Sparta on his own account, not deterred by the angry men of
                    Acharnae, who crave vengeance for the devastation of their vineyards. He sends
                    to Sparta for samples of peace; and he is so much pleased with the flavour of
                    the Thirty Years’ sample that he at once concludes a treaty for himself and his
                    family. All the blessings of life descend on him; while Lamachus, the leader of
                    the war party, is smarting from cold, snow, and wounds.</p>
                <p>(2.) 424 B.c. <hi rend="italic">The Knights.—</hi> Three years before, in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Babylonians,</hi> Aristophanes had assailed Cleon as the
                    typical demagogue. In this play he continues the attack. The Demos, or State, is
                    represented by an old man who has put himself and his household into the hands
                    of a rascally Paphlagonian steward. Nicias and Demosthenes, slaves of Demos,
                    contrive that the Paphlagonian shall be supplanted in their master’s favour by a
                    sausage-seller. No sooner has Demos been thus rescued than his youthfulness and
                    his good sense return together.</p>
                <p>(3.) 423 B.c. <hi rend="italic">The Clouds</hi> (the first edition; a second
                    edition was brought out in 422 B.c.)—This play would be correctly described as
                    an attack on the new spirit of intellectual inquiry and culture rather than on a
                    school or class. Two classes of thinkers or teachers are, however, specially
                    satirised under the general name of “Sophist” (v. 331)— 1. The Physical
                    Philosophers—indicated by allusions to the doctrines of Anaxagoras, Hêracleitus,
                    and Diogenes of Apollonia. 2. The professed teachers of rhetoric, belles
                    lettres, &lt;fcc., such as Protagoras and Prodicus. Socrates is taken as the
                    type of the entire tendency. A youth named Pheidippides—obviously meant for
                    Alcibiades—is sent by his father to Socrates to be cured of his dissolute
                    propensities. Under the discipline of Socrates the youth becomes accomplished in
                    dishonesty and impiety. The conclusion of the play shows the indignant father
                    preparing to burn up the philosopher and his hall of contemplation.</p>
                <p>(4.) 422.B.C. <hi rend="italic">The Wasps.—</hi> This comedy, which suggested <hi
                        rend="italic">Les Plaideurs</hi> to Racine, is a satire on the Athenian love
                    of litigation. The strength of demagogy, while it lay chiefly in the ecclêsia,
                    lay partly also in the paid dica-steries. From this point of view the <hi
                        rend="italic">Wasps</hi> may be regarded as supplementing the <hi
                        rend="italic">Knights.</hi> Philocleon (admirer of Cleon), an old man, has a
                    passion for lawsuits, —a passion which his son, Bdelucleon (detester of Cleon)
                    fails to check, until he hits upon the device of turning the house into a
                    law-court, and paying his father for absence <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n568/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0568-0509"/> from the public suits. The house-dog steals a
                    Sicilian cheese; the old man is enabled to gratify his taste by trying the case,
                    and, by an oversight, acquits the defendant. In the second half of the play a
                    change comes over the dream of Philocleon; from litigation he turns to
                    literature and music, and is congratulated by the chorus on his happy
                    conversion.</p>
                <p>(5.) 421 B.c. (Curtius, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of Greece,</hi> vol. iii. p. 275,
                    transL Ward.) <hi rend="italic">The Peace.—</hi> In its advocacy of peace with
                    Sparta, this play, acted at the Great Dionysia shortly before the conclusion of
                    the treaty, continues the purpose of the <hi rend="italic">Acharnions.</hi>
                    Trygaeus, a distressed Athenian, soars to the sky on a beetle’s back. There he
                    finds the gods engaged in pounding the Greek States in a mortar. In order to
                    stop this, he frees the goddess Peace from a well in which she is imprisoned.
                    The pestle and mortar are laid aside by the gods; and Trygaeus marries one of
                    the handmaids of Peace.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Second Period.</hi></p>
                <p>(6.) 414 B.c. <hi rend="italic">The Birds.—</hi> Peisthetaerus, an enterprising
                    Athenian, and his friend Euelpides persuade the birds to build a
                    city—“Cloud-Cuckoo-borough”—in mid air, so as to cut off the gods from men. The
                    plan succeeds; the gods send envoys to treat with the birds; and Peisthetaerus
                    marries Basileia, daughter of Zeus. Some have found in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Birds</hi> a complete historical allegory of the Sicilian expedition;
                    others, a general satire on the prevalence at Athens of headstrong caprice over
                    law and order; others, merely an aspiration towards a new and purified Athens— a
                    dream to which the poet had turned from his hope for a revival of the Athens of
                    the past. In another view, the piece is mainly a protest against the religious
                    fanaticism which the incident of the Hermae had called forth. It can hardly be
                    doubted that both this fanaticism and the part taken by Alcibiades in promoting
                    the Sicilian expedition were present to the mind of Aristophanes; but in what
                    proportions, and tempered with what other elements, the very form of the comedy
                    makes it idle to inquire.</p>
                <p>(7.) 411 B.c. <hi rend="italic">The Lysιstrata.—</hi> This play was brought out
                    during the earlier stages of those intrigues which led to the Revolution of the
                    Four Hundred. It appeared shortly before Peisander had arrived in Athens from
                    the camp at Samos for the purpose of organising the oligarchic policy. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Lysistrata</hi> expresses the popular desire for peace at any
                    cost. As the men can do nothing, the women take the question into their own
                    hands, occupy the citadel, and bring the citizens to surrender.</p>
                <p>(8.) 411 B.σ. <hi rend="italic">The Thesrnophoriazusae.—</hi> This came out three
                    months later than the <hi rend="italic">Lysistrata,</hi> during the reign of
                    terror established by the oligarchic conspirators, but before their blow had
                    been struck. The political meaning of the play lies in the absence of political
                    allusion. Fear silences even comedy. Only women and Euripides are satirised.
                    Euripides is accused and condemned at the female festival of the
                    Thesmophoria.</p>
                <p>(9.) 405 B.c. <hi rend="italic">The Frogs.—</hi> This piece was brought out just
                    when Athens had made her last effort in the Peloponnesian war, eight months
                    before the battle of Aegospotami, and about fifteen months before the taking of
                    Athens by Lysander. It may be considered as an attempt to distract men’s minds
                    from public affairs. It is a literary criticism. Aeschylus and Euripides were
                    both lately dead. Athens is beggared of poets; and Dionysus goes down to Hades
                    to bring back a poet. Aeschylus and Euripides contend in the under-world for the
                    throne of tragedy; and the victory is at last awarded to Aeschylus.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="italic">Third Period.</hi></p>
                <p>(10.) 393 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi><hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Ecclesiazusoe.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The women,
                    disguised a≡ men, steal into the ecclesia, and succeed in decreeing a new
                    constitution. At this time the demagogue Agyrrhius led the assembly; and the
                    play is, in fact, a satire on the general demoralisation of public life.</p>
                <p>(11.) 388 B.c. <hi rend="italic">ThePlutus.—</hi> The first edition of the play
                    had appeared in 408 B.c., being a symbolical representation of the fact that the
                    victories won by Alcibiades in the Hellespont had brought back the god of wealth
                    to the treasure-chamber of the Parthenon. In its extant form the <hi
                        rend="italic">Plutus</hi> is simply a moral allegory. Chremylus, a worthy
                    but poor man, falls in with a blind and aged wanderer, who proves to be the god
                    of wealth. Asclêpius restores eyesight to Plutus; whereupon all the just are
                    made rich, and all the unjust are reduced to poverty.</p>
                <p>Among the lost plays, the following are the chief of which anything is known
                    :—</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Banqueters</hi> (∆αtταλ∈⅛), 427 B.c. — A satire on young
                    Athens. A father haβ two sons; one is brought up in the good old school, another
                    in the tricky subtleties of the new; and the contrast of results is the chief
                    theme.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Babylonians,</hi> 426 B.c.—Under this name the
                    subject-allies of Athens are represented as “Babylonians” —barbarian slaves,
                    employed to grind in the mill. The oppression of the allies by the demagogues—a
                    topic often touched elsewhere—was, then, the main subject of the piece, in which
                    Aristophanes is said to have attacked especially the system of appointing to
                    offices by lot. The comedy is memorable as opening that Aristophanic war upon
                    Cleon which was continued in the <hi rend="italic">Knights</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Wasps.</hi><hi rend="italic">The Merchantmen, The Farmers, The
                        Preliminary Contest</hi><hi rend="italic">(Proagôn),</hi> and possibly the
                        <hi rend="italic">Old Age (Geras),</hi> belonged to the First Period. The
                        <hi rend="italic">Geras</hi> is assigned by Süvern to 422 B.C., and is
                    supposed to have been a picture of dotage similar to that in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Knights.</hi> A comedy called <hi rend="italic">The
                        Islands</hi> is conjectured to have dealt with the sufferings imposed by the
                    war on the insular tributaries. The <hi rend="italic">Triphales</hi> was
                    probably a satire on Alcibiades; the <hi rend="italic">Storks,</hi> on the
                    tragic poet Patrocles.</p>
                <p>In the <hi rend="italic">Aeolosicôn</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> produced by his
                    son Arârôs in 387 B.c.—Aristophanes probably parodied the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aeolus</hi> of Euripides. The <hi rend="italic">Côcalus</hi> is thought to
                    have been a parody of the legend, according to which a Sicilian king of that
                    name slew Minôs.</p>
                <p>A sympathetic reader of Aristophanes can hardly fail to perceive that, while his
                    political and intellectual tendencies are well marked, his opinions, in so far
                    as they colour his comedies, are too indefinite to reward, or indeed to
                    tolerate, analysis. Aristophanes was a natural conservative. His ideal was the
                    Athens of the Persian wars. He disapproved the policy which had made Athenian
                    empire irksome to the allies and formidable to Greece; he detested the vulgarity
                    and the violence of mob-rule; he clave to the old worship of the gods; he
                    regarded the new ideas of education as a tissue of imposture and impiety. How
                    far he was from clearness or precision of view in regard to the intellectual
                    revolution which was going forward, appears from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Clouds,</hi> in which thinkers and literary workers who had absolutely
                    nothing in common are treated with sweeping ridicule as prophets of a common
                    heresy. Aristophanes is one of the men for whom opinion is mainly a matter of
                    feeling, not of reason. His imaginative susceptibility gave him a warm and loyal
                    love for the traditional glories of Athens, however dim the past to which they
                    belonged; a horror of what was ugly or ignoble in the present; a keen perception
                    of what was offensive or absurd in pretension. The broad preferences and
                    dislikes thus generated were enough not only to point the moral of comedy, but
                    to make lιim, in many cases, a really useful censor for the city. The service
                    which he could render in this way was, however, only negative. He could hardly
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n569/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0569-0510"/> be, in any positive sense, a political or a
                    moral teacher for Athens. His rooted antipathy to intellectual progress, while
                    it affords easy and wide scope for his wit, must, after all, lower his
                    intellectual rank. The great minds are not the enemies of ideas. But as a
                    mocker—to use the word which seems most closely to describe him on this side—he
                    is incomparable for the union of subtlety with riot of the comic imagination. As
                    a poet, he is immortal. And, among Athenian poets, he has it for his distinctive
                    characteristic that he is inspired less by that Greek genius which never allows
                    fancy to escape from the control of defining, though spiritualising, reason,
                    than by such ethereal rapture of the unfettered fancy as lifts Shakespeare or
                    Shelley above it,—</p>
                <lg>
                    <l part="F"> “Pouring his full heart </l>
                    <l> In profuse strains of unpremeditated art.” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Best recent editions, &amp;c.—(1.) <hi rend="italic">Text.—</hi> Bergk, 2 vols.,
                    Teubner, 1867; Holden (expurgated edition), Bell, 1868. (2.) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Commentaries.</hi> —Achamenses, Equites, Nubes, Vespae, W. C. Green, in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Catena</hi><hi rend="italic">Classicorum,</hi> Rivingtons,
                    1870; Nubes and Ranae, A. Sidgwick (for beginners),Rivingtons, 1872. (3.) <hi
                        rend="italic">Translations.—</hi> Mitchell(Acharn., Knights, Clouds, Wasps),
                    2 vols., 1822; J. H. Frere (Acharo., Knights, Birds, Frogs, Peace) being 2d vol.
                    of his works, Pickering, 1871; B. H. Kennedy, The Birds (with an excellent
                    introduction), Macmillan, 1874. (R. C. J.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
