<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0100-0091-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANSELM (9th edition, volume 2, page 91)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1162722">Urbanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n100/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANSELM</label>, Archbishop of Canterbury, was born in 1033,
                    at or near Aosta, in Piedmont. His family was accounted noble, and was possessed
                    of considerable property. Gun-dulph, his father, was by birth a Lombard, and
                    seems to have been a man of harsh and violent temper; his mother, Ermenberga,
                    was a prudent and virtuous woman, from whose careful religious training the
                    young Anselm derived much benefit. At the early age of fifteen he desired to
                    devote himself to the service of God by entering a convent, but he could not
                    obtain his father’s consent. Disappointment brought on an illness, on his
                    recovery from which he seems for a time to have given up his studies, and to
                    have plunged into the gay life of the world. During this time his mother died,
                    and his father’s harshness became unbearable. He left home, and with only one
                    attendant crossed the Alps, and wandered through Burgundy and France. Attracted
                    by the fame of his countryman, Lan-franc, then prior of Bee, he entered
                    Normandy, and, after spending some time at Avranches, settled at the monastery
                    of Bee. There, at the age of twenty-seven, he became a monk; three years later,
                    when Lanfranc was promoted to the abbacy of Caen, he was elected prior. , This
                    office he held for fifteen years, and then, in 1078, on the death of Herluin,
                    the warrior-monk who had founded the monastery, he was made abbot. Under his
                    rule Bee became the first seat of learning in Europe, a result due not more to
                    his intellectual powers than to the great moral influence of his noble
                    character, and his loving, kindly discipline. It was during these quiet years at
                    Bee that Anselm wrote his first philosophical and religious works, the dialogues
                    on Truth and Freewill, and the two celebrated treatises, the Jfon- <hi
                        rend="italic">ologion</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Proslogion.</hi> Meanwhile
                    the convent had been growing in wealth, as well as in reputation, and, among
                    other properties, had acquired considerable possessions in England. Anselm paid
                    frequent visits to that country in connection with the convent lands, and by his
                    mildness of temper and unswerving rectitude, so endeared himself to the English
                    that he was looked upon and desired as the natural successor to Lanfranc, then
                    archbishop of Canterbury. But on the death of that great man, the ruling
                    sovereign, William Rufus, seized the possessions and revenues of the see, and
                    made no new appointment. About four years after, in 1092, on the invitation of
                    Hugh, earl of Chester, Anselm, with some reluctance, for he feared to be made
                    archbishop, crossed to England. He was detained by business for nearly four
                    months, and when about to return, was refused permission by the king. In the
                    following year William fell ill, and thought his death was at hand. Eager to
                    make atonement for his sin with regard to the archbishopric, he nominated Anselm
                    to the vacant: see, and, after a great struggle, compelled him to accept the
                    pastoral staff of office. After obtaining dispensation from his duties in
                    Normandy, Anselm was consecrated in 1093. He demanded of the king, as the
                    conditions of his retaining office, that he should give up all the possessions
                    of the see, accept his spiritual counsel, and acknowledge Urban as Pope, in
                    opposition to the anti-pope, Clement. He only obtained a partial consent to the
                    first of these, and the last involved him in a serious difficulty with the king.
                    It was a rule of the church that the consecration of metropolitans could not be
                    completed without their receiving from the hands of the Pope the <hi
                        rend="italic">Pallium,</hi> or robe. Anselm, accordingly, insisted that he
                    must proceed to Rome to receive the pall. But William would not permit this; he
                    had not acknowledged Urban, and he maintained his right to prevent any Pope
                    being acknowledged by an English subject without his permission. A great council
                    of churchmen and nobles, held to settle the matter, advised Anselm to submit to
                    the king, but failed to overcome his mild and patient firmness. The matter was
                    postponed, and William meanwhile privately sent messengers to Rome, who
                    acknowledged Urban, and prevailed on him to send a legate to the king, bearing
                    the archiépiscopal pall. A partial reconciliation was then effected, and the
                    matter of the pall was compromised. It was not given by the king, but was laid
                    on the altar at Canterbury, whence Anselm took it. Little more than a year
                    after, fresh trouble arose with the king, and Anselm resolved to proceed to Rome
                    and seek the counsel of his spiritual father.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n101/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0101-0092"/>
                <p>With great difficulty he obtained a reluctant permission to leave, and in October
                    1097 he set out for Rome. William immediately seized on the revenues of the see,
                    and retained them to his death. Anselm was received with high honour by Urban,
                    and at a great council held at Bari, he was put forward to defend the Latin
                    doctrine of the Holy Ghost against the objections cf the Greek Church But Urban
                    was too politic to embroil himself with the king of England, and Anselm found
                    that he could obtain no substantial result. He withdrew from Rome, and spent
                    some time at the little village of Schlavia. Here he finished his treatise on
                    the atonement, <hi rend="italic">Cur Deus</hi> Aoτno, and then retired to Lyons.
                    In 1100 William was killed, and Henry, his successor, at once recalled Anselm.
                    But Henry demanded that he should again receive from him in person investiture
                    in his office of archbishop, thus making the dignity entirely dependent on the
                    royal authority. Now, the Papal rule in the matter was plain; all homage and lay
                    investiture were strictly prohibited. Anselm represented this to the king; but
                    Henry would not relinquish a privilege possessed by his predecessors, and
                    proposed that the matter should be laid before the Holy See. The answer of the
                    Pope reaffirmed the law as to investiture. A second embassy was sent, with a
                    similar result. Henry, however, remained firm, and at last, in 1103, Anselm and
                    an envoy from the king set out for Rome. The Pope, Paschal, reaffirmed strongly
                    the rule of investiture, and passed sentence of excommunication against all who
                    had infringed the law, except Henry. Practically this left matters as they were,
                    and Anselm, who had received a message forbidding him to return to England,
                    unless on the king’s terms, withdrew to Lyons, where he waited to see if Paschal
                    would not take stronger measures. At last, in 1105, he resolved himself to
                    excommunicate Henry. His intention was made known to the king through his
                    sister, and it seriously alarmed him, for it was a critical period in his
                    affairs. A meeting was arranged, and a reconciliation between them effected. In
                    1106 Anselm crossed to England, with power from the Pope to remove the sentence
                    of excommunication from the illegally invested churchmen. In 1107 the long
                    dispute as to investiture was finally ended by the king resigning his formal
                    rights. The remaining two years of Anselm’s life were spent in the duties of his
                    archbishopric. He died 21st April 1109. His canonization appears to have taken
                    place in 1494.</p>
                <p>Anselm may, with some justice, be considered the first scholastic philosopher and
                    theologian. His only great predecessor, Scotus Erigena, had more of the
                    speculative and mystical element than is consistent with a schoolman; but in
                    Anselm are found that recognition of the relation of reason to revealed truth,
                    and that attempt to elaborate a rational system of faith, which form the special
                    characteristics of scholastic thought. His constant endeavour is to render the
                    contents of the Christian consciousness clear to reason, and to develop the
                    intelligible truths interwoven with the Christian belief. The necessary
                    preliminary for this is the possession of the Christian consciousness. “He who
                    does not believe will not experience; and he who has not experienced will not
                    understand.” That faith must precede knowledge is reiterated by him. “Neque enim
                    quaero intelligere ut credam, sed credo ut intelligam. Nam et hoc credo, quia,
                    nisi credidero, non intelligam.” “Christianus per fidem debet ad intellectum
                    proficere, non per intellectum ad fidem accedere.” “Rectus ordo exigit, ut
                    profunda Christianae fidei credamus, priusquam ea praesum-amus ratione
                    discutere.” But after the faith is held fast, the attempt must be made to
                    demonstrate by reason the truth of what we believe. It is wrong not to do so.
                    “Negligentiae mihi esse videtur, si, postquam confirmati sumus in fide, non
                    studemus quod credimus, intelligere.” To such an extent does he carry this
                    demand for rational explanation that, at times, it seems as if he claimed for
                    unassisted intelligence the power of penetrating even to the mysteries of the
                    Christian faith. On the whole, however, the qualified statement is his real
                    view; merely rational proofs are always, he affirms, to be tested by Scripture.
                        <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">Cur Deus homo,</hi> i. 2 and 38;
                        <hi rend="italic">De Fide Trin.</hi> 2.)</p>
                <p>The groundwork of his theory of knowledge is contained in the tract <hi
                        rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Veritate,</hi> in which, from the
                    consideration of truth as in knowledge, in willing, and in things, he rises to
                    the affirmation of an absolute truth, in which all other truth participates.
                    This absolute truth is God himself, who is therefore the ultimate ground or
                    principle both of things and of thought. The notion of God comes thus into the
                    foreground of the system; before all things it is necessary that it should be
                    made clear to reason, that it should be demonstrated to have real existence.
                    This demonstration is the substance of the <hi rend="italic">Monologion</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Proslogion.</hi> In the first of these the proof rests on
                    the ordinary grounds of realism, and coincides to some extent with the earlier
                    theory of Augustine, though it is carried out with singular boldness and
                    fulness. Things, he says, are called good in a variety of ways and degrees; this
                    would be impossible if there were not some absolute standard, some good in
                    itself, in which all relative goods participate. Similarly with such predicates
                    as great, just; they involve a certain greatness and justice. The very existence
                    of things is impossible without some one Being, by whom they are. This absolute
                    Being, this goodness, justice, greatness, is God. Anselm was not thoroughly
                    satisfied with this reasoning; it started from <hi rend="italic">a
                        posteriori</hi> grounds, and contained several converging lines of proof. He
                    desired to have some one short demonstration. Such a demonstration he presented
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Proslogion;</hi> it is his celebrated ontological
                    proof. God is that being than whom none greater can be conceived. Now, if that
                    than which nothing greater can be conceived existed only in the intellect, it
                    would not be the absolutely greatest, for we could add to it existence in
                    reality. It follows, then, that the being than whom nothing greater can be
                    conceived, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> God, necessarily has real existence.
                    This proof has rarely seemed satisfactory. It was opposed at the time by the
                    monk Gaunilo, in his <hi rend="italic">Liier</hi><hi rend="italic">pro</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Insipiente,</hi> on the ground that we cannot pass from idea
                    to reality. The same criticism is made by several of the later schoolmen, among
                    others by Aquinas, and is in substance what Kant advances against all
                    ontological proof. Anselm replied to the objections of Gaunilo in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Liier</hi><hi rend="italic">Apologeticum.</hi> The existence
                    of God being thus held proved, he proceeds to state the rational grounds of the
                    Christian doctrines of creation and of the Trinity. With reference to this last,
                    he says we cannot know God from himself, but only after the analogy of his
                    creatures; and the special analogy used is the selfconsciousness of man, it≡
                    peculiar double nature, with the necessary elements, memory and intelligence,
                    representing the relation of the Father and the Son. The mutual love of these
                    two, proceeding from the relation they hold to one another, symbolises the Holy
                    Spirit. The further theological doctrines of man, original sin, free will, are
                    developed, partly in the <hi rend="italic">Monologion,</hi> partly in special
                    treatises. Finally, in his greatest work, <hi rend="italic">Cur Deus homo,</hi>
                    he undertakes to make plain, even to infidels, the rational necessity of the
                    Christian mystery of the atonement. The theory rests on three positions: that
                    satisfaction is necessary on account of God’s honour and justice; that such
                    satisfaction can be given only by the peculiar personality of the God-man; that
                    such satisfaction is really given by the voluntary death of this infinitely
                    valuable person. The demonstration is, in brief, this. All the actione of men
                    are due to the furtherance of God’s glory; if, then, there bo <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n102/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0102-0093"/> sin, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> if God’s
                    honour be wounded, man of himself can give no satisfaction. But the justice of
                    God demands satisfaction; and as an insult to infinite honour is in itself
                    infinite, the satisfaction must be infinite, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> it
                    must outweigh all that is not God. Such a penalty can only be paid by God
                    himself, and, as a penalty for man, must be paid under the form of man.
                    Satisfaction is only possible through the God-man. Now this God-man, as sinless,
                    is exempt from the punishment of sin; His passion is therefore voluntary, not
                    given as due. The merit of it is therefore infinite; God’s justice is thus
                    appeased, and His mercy may extend to man. This theory has exercised immense
                    influence on the form of church doctrine. It is certainly an advance on the
                    older patristic theory, in so far as it substitutes for a contest between God
                    and Satan, a contest between the goodness and justice of God; but it puts the
                    whole relation on a merely legal footing, gives it no ethical bearing, and
                    neglects altogether the consciousness of the individual to be redeemed. In this
                    respect it contrasts unfavourably with the later theory of Abelard.</p>
                <p>Anselm’s speculations did not receive, in the Middle Ages, the respect and
                    attention justly their due. This was perhaps owing to their unsystematic
                    character, for they are generally tracts or dialogues on detached questions, not
                    elaborate treatises like the great works of Albert, Aquinas, and Duns Scotus.
                    They have, however, a freshness and philosophical vigour, which more than makes
                    up for their want of system, and which raises them far above the level of most
                    scholastic writings.</p>
                <p>A full account of Anselm’s life is given by Eadmer, <hi rend="italic">Vita
                        Anselmi.</hi> His works have been frequently published; the best editions
                    are by Gerberon (containing the life, by Eadmer), Paris, 1675, 2nd ed. 1721; and
                    in Migne, <hi rend="italic">Patrologioe</hi><hi rend="italic">Cur sics</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Completus,</hi> vol. civ.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Cur Deus homo</hi> has been frequently published in a
                    separate form. The <hi rend="italic">Monologion</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Proslogion</hi> have been translated, with notes, by Bouchitté, <hi
                        rend="italic">Le Rationalisme</hi><hi rend="italic">Chretien,</hi> Paris,
                    1842. In addition to the copious notices in general histories of theology and
                    philosophy, the following works may be referred to :—Möhler, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anselm,</hi> translated into English, 1842; Franck, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anselm von Canterbury,</hi> 1842; Hasse, <hi rend="italic">Anselm von
                        Canterbury,</hi> I. “Leben,” 1843, II. “Philosophie,” 1852; Remusat, <hi
                        rend="italic">Anselm</hi><hi rend="italic">de Cantorbéry,</hi> 1855, 2d ed.
                    1868; R. W. Church, <hi rend="italic">St Anselm,</hi> 1870.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
