<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0683-0622-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARNDT, Ernst Moritz</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 622</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qs0q">Serfdom</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn5q">Patriotism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1132936">Steins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1055200">Patriotism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1113076">Serfdom</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n683/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARNDT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernst Moritz</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished German patriot, poet, and historical and miscellaneous writer, was
                    a native of the island of Rügen in the Baltic, which at the time of his birth
                    belonged to Sweden. He was born at Schoritz on the 26th December 1769. The
                    second of a family of eight, he inherited from his father the sound mind in the
                    sound body, good sense, practical sagacity, warm feeling, and a strong will; and
                    from his mother the earnest, devout, and Christian spirit which animated all his
                    words and deeds. After passing his boyhood in his father’s house, familiar with
                    the solitudes of sea and wood, trained in habits of accurate observation and
                    cheerful activity, and stimulated by books to literary attempts of his own, he
                    was sent, in 1787, to the gymnasium of Stralsund. There he studied for two
                    years, and, after spending the next two years in the old home, he entered, in
                    the spring of 1791, the university of Greifswald, whence he removed to Jena.
                    There he fell under the influence of Fichte, whose teachings he received with
                    eager love, and whose memory remained ever dear to him. Destined for the church,
                    he applied himself at first to the study of theology, but after some years,
                    conscious of no inward call, he renounced that pursuit. In 1796 he became a
                    private tutor at Altenkirchen; visited afterwards Austria, Hungary, Italy, and
                    France, giving to the world the fruits of his observation in a series of
                    remarkable volumes published in the course of the following years; andin 1800
                    settled at Greifswald as “privat-docent” of history and philology. In 1806 he
                    was named professor extraordinary. His special faculty and vocation distinctly
                    revealed themselves in his bold <hi rend="italic">History of Serfdom in
                    Pomerania and</hi><hi rend="italic">Rügen</hi> (1803), for which he was
                    denounced by the nobles to the king of Sweden. So convincing was the book that,
                    in 1806, serfdom was abolished. In his next work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geist</hi><hi rend="italic">der Zeit</hi> (1807), he aimed at a higher mark. He
                    flung down the gauntlet to Napoleon I. who, in the campaigns of Austerlitz and
                    Jena, had laid Germany prostrate before him, and in burning words he called on
                    his countrymen to rise and shake off the hateful yoke. So great was the
                    excitement produced by this appeal that Arndt, to escape the vengeance of
                    Napoleon, took refuge in Sweden. The work passed through fifteen editions, and
                    grew into four volumes, to which a fifth part, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pro</hi><hi rend="italic">Populo</hi><hi rend="italic">Germanico,</hi> was
                    added in 1854. Arndt having thus erected the banner of German freedom and unity,
                    devoted himself thenceforth with unflagging courage to the great cause. In
                    pamphlets, poems, and songs he communicated his own enthusiasm to his
                    countrymen; and he zealously co-operated with Stein in the reorganisation of the
                    army and preparation for the final struggle. The War of Liberation followed, and
                    Germany was free. Long years were, however, to pass before unity was attained.
                    One of the most famous of Arndt’s songs was that commencing, “<hi rend="italic"
                    >Was</hi><hi rend="italic">ist der Deutschen Vaterland.”</hi> After the peace he
                    returned to Germany, edited at Cologne a political journal, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Der Wächter</hi> (1815-16), and in 1818 was appointed to the chair
                    of history at Bonn. But his bold demands for constitutional reform offended the
                    Diet, and being deprived in the following year, he passed twenty years in
                    retirement and literary activity. In 1840 he was reinstated in his
                    professorship, and in 1841 he was chosen rector of the university. The
                    revolutionary outbreak of 1848 rekindled in the venerable patriot his old hopes
                    and energies, and he took his seat as one of the deputies to the National
                    Assembly at Frankfort. Seeing no prospect of a satisfactory issue he retired
                    with the adherents of Von Gagern. With rare freshness and vigour he continued to
                    lecture and to write, and on his 90th birthday received from all parts of
                    Germany good wishes and love-tokens. About a month later, January 29, 1860, he
                    made a peaceful departure out of the world. Arndt was twice married, first in
                    1800, but his wife died in the following year in giving birth to a son; he
                    married a second time in 1817. Among his numerous works, in addition to those
                    already named, are— <hi rend="italic">N</hi><hi rend="italic">ebenstunden, eine
                    Beschreibung und Geschichte der Schottländischen Inseln und der Orkaden</hi>
                    (1820); <hi rend="italic">Die Frage über die Niederlande</hi> (1831); <hi
                    rend="italic">Erinnerungen aus dem äussem Leben</hi> (1843); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Wanderungen und Wandlungen mit dem Reiclisfreiherrn</hi><hi rend="italic">H.
                    K.</hi><hi rend="italic">F. von Stein</hi> (1858); and a complete edition of his
                    <hi rend="italic">Gedichte</hi> (1860). Lives of Arndt have been written by W.
                    Neumann and Wilhelm Baur; and statues have been erected to his memory at
                    Schoritz, his birth-place, and at Bonn, where he lies buried. (w. L. R. c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
