<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0142-0129-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANTIMONY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 129</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tm5k">Valentines</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nk3w">Tin</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7c14w">Tinning</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xr3k">Ores</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44v51">Silver</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1017914">Metallizing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1018047">Metals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151376">Tinning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151272">Tin</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047551">Ores</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1163796">Valentines</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205660">Nevada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n142/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANTIMONY</label>, a metal found native to a small extent in
                    many of the localities from which its ores are derived. It has been obtained at
                    Sahiberg, near Sahl in Sweden, at Andreasberg in the Harz, at Allemont in
                    Dauphiny, Przibram in Bohemia, besides being brought from Borneo, Chili, Mexico,
                    New Brunswick, &amp;c. It also occurs in nature alloyed with other metals;
                    allemontite being arsenical antimony; dyscrasite, antimonial silver; and
                    breithauptite, a native alloy of antimony and nickel. Among the ores of antimony
                    may be enumerated valentinite, or white antimony, and cervantite, or antimony
                    ochre, both oxides of antimony; and kermesite, red antimony, or antimony blende,
                    an oxysulphide of the metal. Various sulph-antimonites of other metals are also
                    met with, but they possess only a mineralogical interest. The antimony of
                    commerce is derived almost entirely from the sulphide, stibnite, or grey
                    antimony ore (Sb <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> S <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>),
                    which is found in great abundance in Borneo, in Nevada, and at Prince William
                    antimony mine, New Brunswick. It is also mined at Schemnitz and Kremnitz in
                    Hungary, at Przibram in Bohemia, at Wolfsberg in the Harz, and at Braunsdorf,
                    near Freiberg, Bavaria. Formerly it was largely produced in Cornwall, but it is
                    no longer worked on a commercial scale in Great Britain. Stibnite, occurs
                    generally in veins, and has a leaden grey colour, with a metallic, sometimes
                    iridescent lustre; it fuses with great facility, and produces a grey streak. It
                    is the στίμμι or stibium of the ancients, who applied to it the epithet <hi
                    rend="italic">τrλa.τv0φθaλμ.ov</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> from its
                    having been used by women in Eastern countries to give increased lustre to their
                    eyes, by darkening the eye-lashes, a practice still pursued in some parts. The
                    <hi rend="italic">paint</hi> said in the Holy Scriptures to have been used by
                    Jezebel, seems to have been this substance; for St Jerome, who knew the manners
                    of Eastern women, has, in the Vulgate, rendered the passage <hi rend="italic"
                    >“</hi><hi rend="italic">oculos ejus posuit stibio.”</hi> Stibnite was the <hi
                    rend="italic">lupus</hi><hi rend="italic">metallorum</hi> of the alchemists, and
                    Basil Valentin was able to show that it contained sulphur. That famous alchemist
                    was acquainted with metallic antimony, and by him and his successors it was
                    known as <hi rend="italic">regulus,</hi> or regulus of antimony, from the
                    readiness with which it acted on the royal metal gold. The tradition that the
                    name antimony was given to the sulphide on account of a preparation of it having
                    proved fatal to the monks (hence <hi rend="italic">anti·monachos)</hi> in a
                    German religious house will hardly bear investigation. Crude antimony of
                    commerce is the ore separated from its associated earthy gangue—an operation
                    effected by simple fusion. The sulphide is then reduced to an oxide by roasting
                    in a reverberatory furnace. From this oxide metallic antimony is obtained by
                    fusion with charcoal, which has been saturated with a solution of carbonate of
                    sodium. The metal may also be prepared direct from the sulphur ore by roasting
                    with a mixture of cream of tartar and nitre, or with iron filings. Antimony is a
                    brilliant silver-grey metal, having a foliated texture and a strong tendency to
                    assume a crystalline structure, which causes the cakes of metal to present a
                    characteristic stellate surface. Its specific gravity is 6*715; it melts at 842°
                    Fahr., and when heated to redness takes fire, burning with a brilliant white
                    flame. It is brittle, and can be easily pulverised. Antimony is chiefly valuable
                    for the alloys it yields with other metals. Britannia metal is an alloy largely
                    used, containing usually about 81 parts of tin, 16 of antimony, 2 of copper, and
                    1 of zinc. Type metal contains varying proportions of lead and antimony, ranging
                    from 17 to 20 per cent, of the latter, or even more, according to the hardness
                    desired; with sometimes small proportions of other metals for stereotype plates,
                    &amp;c. Babbitt’s anti-friction metal for the bearings of machinery is composed
                    of 83 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 3 parts of tin, 8*3 parts of copper, and 8
                    ’ 3 of antimony. Antimony alloys with lead and tin, separately or in
                    combination, are also used in place of gun metal for the bushes of heavy
                    machinery. Antimonial preparations are of great value in pharmacy, and for such
                    purposes it is essential that they should be absolutely free from the arsenical
                    and other impurities which commercial antimony and its ores always contain. The
                    principal preparation used medicinally is tartarated antimony, or tartar emetic,
                    a tartrate of potash and antimony. Taken in small doses, from τ⅛th to ⅜th of a
                    grain, tartar emetic acts as a diaphoretic, renders mucous surfaces moist, and
                    promotes secretion of urine. In larger doses it excites nausea, and, as its name
                    indicates, vomiting. It is also prepared in the form of an ointment for external
                    application as a counter-irritant, producing a painful pustular eruption.
                    Antimonial wine is a preparation of tartar emetic, used as a diaphoretic and
                    expectorant. Butter of antimony, or the liquor of chloride of antimony, is used
                    as a powerful caustic, and antimonial powder, or James’s powder, is employed as
                    a diaphoretic in fevers and rheumatism. Other officinal preparations containing
                    antimony are—oxide of antimony; black antimony, or the native sulphide,
                    prepared; sulphurated antimony; and compound calomel pills. Crude antimony
                    sulphide is used in the manufacture of black lead pencils. For the action of
                    antimony as a poison, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Poisons.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
