<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0208-0195-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">APOSTOLIC FATHERS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 195</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:883769">Critics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v131">Pastors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">APOSTOLIC FATHERS</label>. The apostolic fathers is a name
                    given to certain writers [in the earliest period of Christianity, who were
                    believed to have been the disciples of the apostles, and to have had intercourse
                    with them. Those generally included under the title are Clemens Romanus,
                    Ignatius, Polycarp, Barnabas, and Hermas. Sometimes the name is extended to
                    Papias of Hierapolis and the writer of the Epistle to Diognetus. A critical
                    examination of the writings attributed to these men, and a critical sifting of
                    the traditions which we have in relation to their history, bring out the
                    circumstance that the name is unsuitable. Clemens Romanus, Barnabas, and Hermas
                    were supposed to be persons mentioned in the New Testament; but criticism proves
                    conclusively that this is a mistake in regard to Barnabas and Hermas, and
                    possibly also in regard to Clemens. Polycarp, in all probability, and according
                    to the best testimony, had intercourse with apostles, but it was in his early
                    youth; and his Letter belongs to a period considerably later than that of the
                    apostles. The Epistles of Ignatius, as well as the personal history of that
                    martyr, are involved in great obscurity, and critics differ widely in regard to
                    both. At the same time, the writings assigned by most critics to these men with
                    some degree of certainty belong to a very early age of Christianity. They’ are
                    among the earliest utterances of the Christian faith which have come down to us.
                    All of them are of the nature of occasional productions, with perhaps the
                    exception of the Pastor of Hermas. All of them breathe a spirit of deep piety.
                    There is no attempt to formulate the truths of Christianity. There are very few
                    references to the books of the New Testament, and very few quotations from them.
                    All of them are written in Greek.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Clemens</hi><hi rend="italic">Romanus.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> According to the statement of Irenaeus, Clemens was the third bishop of
                    the Roman Church; this seems to have been the tradition among the Greek writers.
                    Tertullian, on the other hand, seems to have believed that he was the first
                    bishop, and that he had been ordained by St Peter. Origen regarded him as the
                    Clemens mentioned in the Epistle to the Philippians, and Clemens Alexandrinus
                    often calls him an apostle. Nothing is known of his death. Very late fictions
                    represented him as a martyr. Eusebius gives as the date of his episcopate from
                    93 to 101 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> The only writing which can in any <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0209-0196"/> satisfactory manner be ascribed to Clemens
                    Romanus is an epistle from the Roman Church to the Corinthian. Quarrels had
                    arisen in the Corinthian Church, most probably in the reign of Domitian, as to
                    some of the officebearers of the church. And the Roman Church sent a letter to
                    the Corinthian Church urging it to pursue a peaceful course, to shun envy and
                    jealousy, and to do all things in order. The writing ff this letter is ascribed
                    to Clemens by Dionysius, bishop of the Corinthian Church, in a letter to Soter,
                    bishop of the Roman Church (166-174 A.D.), and all subsequent testimony is in
                    favour of this authorship. The letter was found at the end of the Codex
                    Alexandrinus. Its position there is in harmony with the circumstance noted by
                    several of the ancients, that it was read in the churches on the Sunday. Clemens
                    Alexandrinus also frequently quotes it as the work of the “Apostle Clemens,” and
                    the mode of quotation is such as to lead one to believe that he regarded it as
                    Scripture, though some have maintained that he did not regard it as canonical.
                    The genuineness of the epistle has been generally acknowledged. There is strong
                    external testimony for it, and the internal evidence is at least not against it.
                    But as Dionysius of Corinth (166 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> is the first to
                    mention Clemens as the author, there is a considerable interval between the date
                    usually assigned to the epistle and the time of Dionysius, during which no one
                    testifies to the epistle. Accordingly some critics have refused to recognise
                    Clemens as the author, and they put the letter well on into the 2d century. The
                    date usually assigned to the letter is 96 or 97 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>
                    Some critics have assigned it to the year 68 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> but
                    the arguments are not satisfactory. Some writers have taken exception to a few
                    chapters in the letter which they regard as interpolations, but their opinions
                    have not been generally adopted. The letter is defective. A whole leaf of the
                    MS. is supposed to be wanting. The best edition of the epistle is by Professor
                    Lightfoot (London and Cambridge, 1869). A whole literature arose around the name
                    of Clemens in subsequent times. Of this literature the following'portions have
                    come down to us. 1. A second Epistle to the Corinthians, found along with the
                    first in the Codex Alexandrinus. As far as one can judge from the writing
                    itself, this work is rather a homily than a letter. In all probability its
                    author belonged to Egypt. Various suppositions have been made as to its
                    authorship, but none that commands the assent of a considerable number of
                    critics. It seems to have been written towards the middle or end of the 2d
                    century. 2. Two letters on Virginity, found in Syriac. There is no external
                    testimony that Clemens was the author of these letters, and they breathe a
                    spirit of asceticism and dislike of marriage different from that prevalent in
                    the early times of Christianity. They also refer to customs of a later date.
                    Notwithstanding this, some critics, especially some Roman Catholics, have keenly
                    defended their genuineness. 3. The <hi rend="italic">Clementines.</hi> These
                    appear in two forms: the <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> in Latin, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> in Greek. They are a fiction. The writer
                    attempts to represent the state of the church as it was during the period
                    between the ascension of Christ and the entrance of St Paul on his work as an
                    apostle. St Peter is accordingly the hero of the work, and his great enemy is
                    Simon the magician. The doctrines of the book are peculiar, and are most nearly
                    allied to those that are reckoned to be the doctrines of the Ebionites. The
                    question arises, Did the writer wish to represent the doctrines as the merely
                    temporary doctrines of that period of transition! Or did he regard the doctrines
                    which he has put forth in the work as the only true doctrines, and the
                    subsequent doctrines of the Catholic Church perversions of the true and
                    aberrations from them! Baur and the Tübingen school have regarded the book as
                    giving a genuine picture of the state of the early church and of Ebionitic
                    doctrine, and a great part of their theory of the origin and rise of
                    Christianity is based upon it. They suppose that in Simon the magician the
                    writer has attacked the apostle Paul. Many critics suppose that the work was
                    written at a very early period, but that it received numerous additions. As the
                    work now exists, it seems to belong to the end of the 2d or beginning of the 3d
                    century. 4. The <hi rend="italic">Apostolical Constitutions.</hi> This work is a
                    series of regulations in regard to the management of the church, such as the
                    functions and character of bishops, presbyters, and deacons (see last article).
                    In all probability the work was the result of one addition after another made to
                    an originally small nucleus. Some assign portions of it to th® apostolic age.
                    Whiston thought that it was inspired. Most probably the main portion of it
                    belongs to the 3d century. There is no reason for connecting with it the name of
                    Clemens, though this was done by ancient writers. We should add to this list
                    that some ascribed the canonical Epistle of the Hebrews to Clemens Romanus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ignatius.—</hi> The information we get in regard to Ignatiu3 up
                    till the time of Eusebius is exceedingly scanty. He is mentioned in the epistle
                    of Polycarp. Origen speaks of him in two passages, which, however, may possibly
                    be interpolations. Eusebius in his <hi rend="italic">Chronicon,</hi> at the year
                    70 or 71 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> states that he was appointed bishop of
                    Antioch, and at the year 109 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> that he suffered
                    martyrdom. He repeats the same statements in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ecclesiastical History,</hi> introducing his account of the martyrdom with the
                    words, “The story goes.” After the time of Eusebius our information becomes much
                    more precise and minute. The birthday of the martyr <hi rend="italic"
                    >(i.e.,</hi> the day of his martyrdom) was celebrated in the church of Antioch.
                    Speeches were delivered in his praise. Wonderful stories were told of him. He
                    was one of the children whom Christ took up in his arms and blessed. He
                    introduced antiphonal chants into the service of the church, because he had seen
                    a vision of angels praising God in antiphonal hymns. The details of his
                    martyrdom are given in a document devoted to the purpose. Of this document there
                    are eight forms; but one is generally believed to be better than the rest. This
                    one states that Trajan, in the ninth year of his reign, was in Antioch, that
                    Ignatius was brought before him, and that the emperor condemned the bishop to be
                    sent to Rome, and to be exposed to the wild beasts. The writers then describe
                    the journey of Ignatius to Rome, mention various letters which he wrote on the
                    way, and then narrate his exposure to the wild beasts, and how they saw him
                    afterwards in a vision. The letters of Ignatius cause great difficulty to the
                    critic. Eight of the letters ascribed to him are now universally rejected. There
                    remain seven others. These seven appear in two Greek forms, a longer and a
                    shorter. Latin translations of these forms are found, and they differ somewhat
                    from the Greek. And of the seven letters three are found in Syriac, and the
                    Syriac form is much shorter than the shortest of the Greek. Which are the
                    original letters! Or have we the original letters at all? Unfortunately before
                    the time of Eusebius there is no external testimony to these letters that can
                    give us any clue to-the true nature of the text. And the testimony of Eusebius
                    is of little value. He states distinctly that there were seven letters. But the
                    critics who maintain that the seven shorter Greek letters are largely
                    interpolated, have no hesitation in agreeing to the opinion that these
                    interpolations were made before the time of Eusebius. The shorter form
                    unquestionably belongs to the 2d or 3d century, most probably to the 2d. A few
                    critics have maintained that the longer form is the genuine. A very large number
                    of critics regard the shorter Greek form as the original form, though almost all
                    allow that there are some traces of interpolation <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n210/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0210-0197"/> even in the shorter epistles. Other critics
                    maintain that the shorter Syriac forms are alone genuine, that they are not
                    epitomes, but the original letters, and they appeal to the circumstance that all
                    the references to the epistles up io the time of Eusebius belong exclusively to
                    the three Syriac epistles. ∣ The question is embittered by a keen controversy in
                    regard to Episcopacy, the Ignatian letters being supposed to afford strong
                    evidence of the early institution of that form of church government. The longer
                    text was first known to scholars. Usher discovered a Latin version of the
                    shorter form, and Vossius the Greek original of this version. Tattam found the
                    Syriac translation in an Egyptian monastery, and Cureton edited it in 1845.
                    Cureton’s services in connection with Ignatius deserve the highest praise; and
                    his <hi rend="italic">Corpus Ignatianum</hi> contains almost all the evidence
                    that can be brought to bear on the subject. The contest in regard to Ignatius’s
                    writings has been keen in various periods of the church’s history; and since the
                    Syriac version appeared, the subject has been discussed by a host of writers,
                    among whom may be mentioned Bunsen, Baur, Dusterdieck, Denziger, Hilgen-feld,
                    Lipsius, Ritschl, Merx, Nirs chi, Zahn, and Newman.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Polycarp</hi> was bishop of Smyrna. The principal part of the
                    information we have in regard to him is derived from Irenaeus, and may be
                    accepted with confidence. Irenaeus knew Poly carp personally, and remembered how
                    Poly carp “related his intercourse with John and the rest who had seen the
                    Lord.” The apostles appointed Polycarp a bishop of the church in Smyrna, and he
                    remained there a long time teaching the truth. In the time of Anicetus, Poly
                    carp came to Rome, and showed a strong spirit of love and charity, which was
                    fully reciprocated by the Roman bishop. They differed in regard to the
                    celebration of the day of the passover, but their differences did not interfere
                    with their love for each other. A special document describes the martyrdom of
                    Polycarp. There are good reasons for doubting the minute accuracy of this work,
                    but the main circumstances have the appearance of being true. A persecution had
                    arisen in Smyrna against the Christians, and naturally a demand was made for
                    Polycarp, the chief of the Christians. At first he fled, but finding that this
                    was of no use, he allowed himself to be apprehended and brought back. He was led
                    before the proconsul, and urged to swear by Caesar and revile Christ “Eighty and
                    six years,” said Polycarp, “have I served Him, and He has done me no ill, and
                    how can I blaspheme my King who has saved me!” The multitude wished the Asiarch
                    to expose the bishop to the lions, but the Asiarch refused, as the time for
                    lions was over. So the people gathered wood and lighted a fire. And Polycarp was
                    placed in the fire, and ultimately also stabbed. The date of his martyrdom has
                    been matter of keen discussion. Eusebius fixed it at 166 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Martyrium,</hi> mentions that it took place in
                    the proconsulate of Statius Quadratus. Recently Waddington has tried to show
                    that Quadratus was proconsul in 154-5, and Lipsius has based on this result the
                    conclusion that Polycarp suffered martyrdom in 155. This date, however, is open
                    to serious objections; and even Waddington’s reasons for placing the
                    proconsulate of Quadratus in 154-5, are not of a satisfactory nature. The only
                    writing that can be now attributed to Polycarp is a letter to the Philippians.
                    This letter is mentioned by Irenaeus and by subsequent writers. Jerome mentions
                    that it was read in the churches. It is a simple outpouring of ordinary
                    Christian thought and feeling. The Tübingen School deny the genuineness of the
                    epistle on internal evidence. Ritschl has tried to show that it is largely
                    interpolated, and there are strong reasons for believing the thirteenth chapter
                    an interpolation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Barnabas.—</hi> There has come down to us a work called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Epistle of Barnabas.</hi> This work is unanimously ascribed to
                    Barnabas, the companion of St Paul, by early Christian writers. Clemens
                    Alexandrinus quotes the letter seven times, and speaks of it as the work of the
                    apostle Barnabas. Origen, Eusebius, and Jerome mention it. The internal evidence
                    is conclusive against its genuineness. The writer regards the Jews as entirely
                    wrong in having practised the ceremonial law. He thinks that Moses never
                    intended that the precepts of the law should be carried out literally. They were
                    to be understood from the first spiritually. By this literal interpretation the
                    Jews had forfeited all claim to the covenant. The covenant belongs only to
                    Christians who obey the law in spirit. The writer applies this principle to
                    sacrifices, circumcision, and the Sabbath. It is difficult to imagine that
                    Barnabas could have adopted such a mode of viewing the law. In all probability
                    he adhered to some of the Jewish practices to the end of his days. Moreover, the
                    writer commits such mistakes in relation to the Jewish ritual as no Jew would
                    commit who had had practical experience of it. Some of the opinions in the
                    letter, and the whole tone of thought indicate that the writer had strongly felt
                    the influence of Alexandrian Judaistic speculation. Accordingly, some critics
                    have maintained that it was written in Alexandria. There is no clue to a date;
                    but there are various indications which have been differently interpreted by
                    different critics. Some, as Weizsäcker, have assigned it to the reign of
                    Vespasian; others, as Wieseler, to the reign of Domitian; but the great majority
                    of critics assign it to the reign of Hadrian, some time between 119 and 126 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> The letter consists of two parts. The latter part is
                    somewhat different in style and purport from the former, and, accordingly,
                    doubts have been entertained as to its genuineness. But there is no good reason
                    for doubt, and external testimony is in favour of it. The first five chapters
                    were extant only in the Latin translation until Tischendorf discovered the
                    entire Greek of the first part in the <hi rend="italic">Codex Sinaticus.</hi>
                    The letter is interesting, as throwing light upon a peculiar phase of
                    theological speculation in the early church.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hermas.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pastor of</hi><hi rend="italic">Hermas</hi> is one of the most interesting
                    books of Christian antiquity. The name Hermas occurs several times in the work,
                    and it was therefore natural for the ancients to suppose that this was the name
                    of the author. The book at a very early period became widely known in the East,
                    and was regarded as inspired. Irenaeus, Clemens Alexandrinus, and Origen speak
                    of it and quote it as Scripture, and Eusebius uses somewhat similar language in
                    regard to it. Origen asserts his belief that the author was the Hermas mentioned
                    in the Epistle to the Romans. The African Church held a different opinion in
                    regard to it. Tertullian speaks slightingly of it; and the story became current
                    that it was written by a Hermas, who was brother to Γius, bishop of Rome from
                    140 to 155 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> It may be doubted whether the author
                    has really given his name. The work is fictitious in form, and there is no good
                    reason for supposing that he has introduced any real characters into it. There
                    is no clear indication of a date; but various circumstances lead to the
                    inference that it was written towards the end of the reign of Hadrian, or the
                    beginning of the reign of Antoninus Pius. Internal evidence points strongly to
                    Italy as the place in which it was written. The book is divided into three
                    parts: visions, commandments, and similitudes. It was very popular with the
                    ancient church, and deservedly so. It presents Christian truth in an attractive
                    manner. Its tone is high and noble, and it breathes the spirit of the gospel of
                    love. The name of Christ does not occur in it, and as the references to the Son
                    of God are few, some have characterised the book as strongly Judaistic. Indeed,
                    various heresies and heretical tendencies have been discovered<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n211/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0211-0198"/> in it by keen-eyed critics; but as Clemens
                    Alexandrinus and Origen failed to see them, and as the great mass of the early
                    church accepted it as eminently fitted to edify, we cannot but think that the
                    critics are wrong. The <hi rend="italic">Pastor of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Hermas</hi> has come down to us in several Latin translations. Simonides was
                    the first to give us any portion of it in Greek. He brought three leaves of a
                    codex of it from Mount Athos, with a copy of a considerable portion of the rest.
                    The remainder of the Athos MS. has not been discovered. Tischendorf found a
                    large portion of the <hi rend="italic">Pastor of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Hermas</hi> in Greek at the end of the <hi rend="italic">Codex Sinaiticus.</hi>
                    The Greek is very nearly the same as the Greek of Simonides.</p>
                <p>There are numerous editions of the works of the apostolic fathers, but special
                    mention may be made of those of Cotelerius, Hefele, Dressel, Hilgenfeld, and
                    Jacobson. Professor Lightfoot’s <hi rend="italic">Clemens</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Romanus</hi> is the first part of what promises to be the most satisfactory
                    edition of the apostolic fathers. Translations of all the works mentioned in
                    this article, including the writings attributed to Clemens, are given in Clark’s
                    Ante-Nicene Christian Library; and the works are discussed in Hilgen-feld’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Apostolische Väter,</hi> 1853, and Donaldson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apostolical Fathers,</hi> 1874. (j. D∙)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
