<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0902-0899-0826-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ATAXY, LOCOMOTOR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 2, page 826</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v30g">Symptoms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67561">Visions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20q1q">Vision</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1140998">Symptoms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1167852">Vision</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1167909">Visions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:829879">Beginning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n899/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ATAXY, LOCOMOTOR</label> (α priv., rô£iç, order—Synonyms, <hi
                    rend="italic">Progressive locomotor ataxy, Tabes dorsalis, Posterior spinal
                    sclerosis'),</hi> a disease of the nervous system, manifesting itself
                    principally by disordered movements of the limbs in locomotion. This disorder is
                    not, as was once supposed, a form of paralysis (there being no diminution of
                    muscular strength), but is dependent on the loss of the power of coordinating
                    the muscles into harmonious action, which is essential to the proper performance
                    of the voluntary movements of the body, and the maintenance of its equilibrium.
                    Although the disease had been previously noticed both by Professor Romberg and
                    Dr R. B. Todd, it was first fully described and named by Dr Duchenne in 1858.
                    Its pathology has subsequently been investigated by Mr Lockhart Clarke.
                    Locomotor ataxy usually begins insidiously, and advances slowly. Among the
                    earlier symptoms observed are disorders of vision, with occasionally temporary
                    or permanent paralysis of some of the cranial nerves, a feeling of uneasiness in
                    the back, accompanied with violent shooting pains down the limbs, increased or
                    perverted sensibility in various parts of the body, and disturbance of the
                    genitourinary functions. These initial symptoms may continue without much change
                    for a long period, but generally in the course of time others are superadded,
                    which give more definite intimation of the existence of the disease, and render
                    its diagnosis a matter of little difficulty. The sufferer begins to be aware
                    that he cannot walk with the same freedom as before, and he feels as if some
                    soft substance were interposed between his feet and the ground. His gait assumes
                    a peculiar and characteristic appearance. He begins the act of walking with
                    evident difficulty, and his steps are short and hurried. Each leg is lifted well
                    from the ground; but as he moves forward it is thrown out from him, and his heel
                    descends forcibly, and is followed at a longer than the normal interval by the
                    sole. In walking he requires the aid of his vision to preserve his equilibrium,
                    and he therefore looks at his feet, or rather at the ground a little in front of
                    them, as he advances. He cannot turn about suddenly without the risk of falling.
                    If asked to stand erect with his feet approximated, and then directed to close
                    his eyes or to look upwards, he immediately begins to sway and totter, and would
                    fall if not supported. These various phenomena are the result, not of any
                    weakness of motor power, but simply of defective muscular co-ordination. Along
                    with this there usually exists markedly diminished tactile and cutaneous
                    sensibility, particularly in the feet and legs. Sometimes the disorder
                    implicates the upper extremities, and then the hands and fingers cease to
                    perform their functions with precision, so that the patient is unable to pick up
                    any small object from the ground, to button or unbutton his clothing, and even
                    sometimes to feed himself, although at the same time there is no weakness in the
                    muscular power of the hand, which is capable of grasping as firmly as before.
                    With the advance of the disease the disorder of movements increases. The
                    patient’s efforts <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n900/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0902-0900-0827"/> to walk become more and more difficult and
                    distressing, for his limbs are jerked about wildly without restraint, while even
                    the aid of his vision and the support of a stick are insufficient to prevent him
                    from falling. Ultimately, all efforts of this kind have to be abandoned, and he
                    is compelled to lie in bed. In the later stages of the disease all the symptoms
                    become aggravated. The shooting pains and violent jerkings of the limbs
                    increase, motor power becomes impaired, and the patient sinks under the
                    prolonged and exhausting course of suffering, or dies from some intercurrent
                    disease. Although usually progressive to a fatal termination, locomotor ataxy is
                    sometimes arrested, and even appears occasionally to be recovered from,
                    particularly in its earlier stages. In most instances its duration extends over
                    a number of years.</p>
                <p>The pathological condition giving rise to locomotor ataxy is disease of a certain
                    portion of the spinal cord, viz., the posterior columns and the posterior nerve
                    roots. These undergo various transformations, which result in their ultimately
                    becoming atrophied and indurated. When affecting, as this lesion most commonly
                    does, the lower dorsal and lumbar regions of the cord, the ataxic symptoms are
                    chiefly confined to the legs; but when it affects the cervical portion, the arms
                    are involved. Occasionally the whole posterior columns of the cord are found
                    diseased. The exciting causes of this malady are but ill understood. Exposure to
                    cold and privation, intemperance, over exertion, and mental anxiety have been
                    supposed to give rise to it. In some instances the disease appears to be
                    hereditary. Locomotor ataxy is much more common among men than among women. It
                    is a disease of middle life, being most frequently observed to occur between the
                    ages of 30 and 50. From the nature of the structural changes affecting the
                    spinal cord in locomotor ataxy, it is evident that, beyond the employment of
                    means to alleviate the various painful symptoms, little can be done towards its
                    cure. Numerous medicines have from time to time been brought forward as supposed
                    to possess special efficacy in the treatment of this disease, but none of them
                    have proved to be of much value. The employment of electricity in the form of
                    the continuous current has been recommended by many high authorities. Probably
                    most good will be found to result from careful efforts to maintain the general
                    health by a well-appointed diet and regimen. (j. o. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
