<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0689-0628-10" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARRAN (9th edition, volume 2, page 628)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n689/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARRAN</label>, an island on the west coast of Scotland, near
                    the mouth of the river Clyde, which forms part of the county of Bute. It is
                    about 20 miles in length, by from 8 to 11 in breadth, and contains a superficial
                    area of 165 square miles, or 105,814 acres, of which about 14,431 are
                    cultivated. This island is rugged and mountainous, particularly in the northern
                    part, in which the valleys are deep and romantic. The principal mountain is
                    Goatfell (in Gaelic, Goadh-Bhein, or Mountain of the Winds), 2865 feet above the
                    level of the sea; and a few others, as Beinn Tarsuin and Ben Noosh, approach the
                    same elevation. There are five small lakes and several streamlets in the island.
                    There is little cultivation, the farms being principally pastoral. A good many
                    Highland cattle and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n690/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0690-0629"/> sheep are fed on the island. Game is
                    abundant, consisting of blackcock and grouse. A few red deer and a number of
                    wild goats still find shelter among the mountains.</p>
                <p>The geology of the island is an epitome of that of Scotland. The mountains of the
                    north, especially Goatfell, consist of granite, surrounded on the flanks by
                    micaceous and argillaceous slates; lying on the edges of the slate are well seen
                    red sandstone and conglomerate, especially on the eastern shores, but easily
                    traceable across the island. On the eastern side limestone, containing
                    Carboniferous fossils, is found at several points intercalated among the red
                    sandstones chiefly at Corrie, where several strata divided by shale are
                    quarried. In the southern part of the island the stratified formations^are
                    overlain by a great series of trap-rocks. Several beds of coal were formerly
                    worked on the northeast coast. This coal lies low down in the Carboniferous
                    series, at the base of the Carboniferous limestone, or in the “calciferous
                    sandstones.” Numerous veins of most beautiful pitchstone and pitchstone-porphyry
                    traverse the red sandstone, especially at Drimadoon and between Brodick and
                    Lamlash. On the mountains are found jasper, agates, cairngorms, and small clear
                    specimens of rock-crystal, called the Arran diamond.</p>
                <p>A considerable manufacture of sulphate of baryta as a pigment was at one time
                    carried on in Glen Sannox. The herring fishery is prosecuted by the islanders.
                    Arran possesses two reftarkably fine natural harbours,—Lamlash Bay, on the
                    south-east of the island, and Loch Ranza on the north-west side. The latter is
                    an indentation of the sea on the north of the island, about a mile in length,
                    and is a place of great resort for <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> boats engaged in
                    the herring fishing. The ruins of an old castle stand upon a small peninsula
                    near the entrance. Almost the whole island belongs to the duke of Hamilton,
                    whose seat is at Brodick Castle. The landing-pier for steamers and the principal
                    hotel are at Brodick Bay, where there is a village with church and school. Six
                    miles from Brodick lies the village of Lamlash. Its beautiful semicircular bay,
                    sheltered by the Holy Island, forms an excellent harbour for ships of all sizes.
                    The Holy Isle, an irregular cone 1020 feet high, was once the site of a cell
                    inhabited by St Molios, a disciple of St Columba. Off the south-east point of
                    Arran lies the low rocky islet of Pladda, with a lighthouse having two fixed
                    lights 130 and 77 feet above high water, and visible 16 and 13 miles
                    respectively, in clear weather. It has a telegraph station, from which the
                    arrival of vessels in the Clyde is notified to Glasgow and Greenock. Many parts
                    of the island are traditionally connected with Robert Bruce. Thus one of the
                    largest of the water-worn recesses in the high sandstone cliffs of the west
                    coast is called the king’s cave, another is the king’s kitchen, a third his
                    cellar, and a fourth his table, while the hill above is the king’s hill; the
                    southern extremity of Lamlash Bay is the King’s Cross Point; and an ancient fort
                    in Glencloy is said to have sheltered his men.</p>
                <p>The antiquities of the island, besides those already mentioned, are Druidical
                    circles (of which the most complete are at Tormore, near Drimadoon, and are
                    called Suidhe Choior Fhionn, or Fingal’s cauldron seat), Danish forts, and
                    sepulchral cairns, such as the immense mound, 200 feet in circumference, at the
                    head of Glen Meneadmar or Moneymore.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
