<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0902-0031-0022-06" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANDRONICUS I (9th edition, volume 2, page 22)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125233">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n31/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANDRONICUS I</label>. <hi rend="smallcaps">(Comnenus),</hi>
                    Emperor of Constantinople, son of Isaac, and grandson of Alexis I. Comnenus, was
                    born about the beginning of the 12th century. He was endowed by nature with the
                    most remarkable gifts both of mind and body. He was handsome and eloquent, but
                    licentious; and at the same time active, hardy, courageous, and an excellent
                    soldier. His early years were spent in alternate pleasure and military service.
                    In 1141 he was taken captive by the Turks-Seljuks, and remained in their hands
                    for a year. On being ransomed, he went to Constantinople, where was held the
                    court of his cousin, the emperor Manuel, with whom he was a great favourite.
                    Here the charms of his niece, the princess Eudoxia, attracted him. She became
                    his mistress, while her sister Theodora stood in a similar relation to the
                    emperor Manuel. In 1152, accompanied by Eudoxia, he set out for an important
                    command in Cilicia. Failing in his principal enterprise, an attack upon
                    Mopsuestia, he returned, but was again appointed to the command of a province.
                    This second post he seems also to have left after a short interval, for he
                    appeared again in Constantinople, and narrowly escaped death at the hands of the
                    brothers of Eudoxia. About this time (1153) a conspiracy against the emperor, in
                    which Andronicus participated, was discovered, and he was thrown into prison.
                    There he remained for about twelve years, during which time he made repeated but
                    unsuccessful attempts to escape. At last, in 1165, he was successful; and, after
                    passing through many dangers, reached the court of Jaroslav, grand duke of
                    Russia,, at Kiev. While under the protection of the grand duke, Andronicus
                    brought about an alliance between him and the emperor Manuel, and so restored
                    himself to the emperor’s favour. With a Russian army he joined Manuel in the
                    invasion of Hungary, and assisted at the siege of Semlin. After a successful
                    campaign, they returned together to Constantinople; but a year after (1167),
                    Andronicus refused to take the oath of allegiance to the prince of Hungary, whom
                    Manuel desired to become his successor. He was removed from court, but received
                    the province of Cilicia. Being still under the displeasure of the emperor,
                    Andronicus fled to the court of Raymond, prince of Antioch. While residing here
                    he captivated and seduced the beautiful daughter of the prince, Philippa, sister
                    of the empress Maria. The anger of the emperor was again roused by this
                    dishonour, and Andronicus was compelled to fly. He took refuge with Amaury, king
                    of Jerusalem, whose favour he gained, and who invested him with the town of
                    Berytus, now Beirout. In Jerusalem he saw Theodora, the beautiful widow of the
                    late king Baldwin, and niece of the emperor Manuel. Although Andronicus was at
                    that time fifty-six years old, age had not diminished his charms, and Theodora
                    became the next victim of his artful seduction. To avoid the vengeance of the
                    emperor, she fled with him to the court of the su·ltan of Damascus; but not
                    deeming themselves safe there, they continued <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit02newyrich/page/n32/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0902-0032-0023"/> their perilous journey through Persia and
                    Turkestan, round the Caspian Sea and across Mount Caucasus, until at length they
                    settled among the Turks on the borders of Trebizond. Into that province
                    Andronicus, with a body of adventurers, made frequent and successful incursions.
                    While he was absent upon one of them, his castle was surprised by the governor
                    of Trebizond, and Theodora with her two children were captured and sent to
                    Constantinople. To obtain their release’ Andronicus made abject submission to
                    the emperor; and, appearing in chains before him, implored pardon. This he
                    obtained, and was allowed to retire with Theodora into banishment in the little
                    town of Oenoe, on the shores of the Black Sea. In 1180 the emperor Manuel died,
                    and was succeeded by his son Alexis II., a youth of twelve or fourteen years,
                    who was under the guardianship of the empress Maria. Her conduct excited popular
                    indignation; and the consequent disorders, amounting almost to civil war, gave
                    an opportunity to the ambition of Andronicus. He left his retirement, secured
                    the support of the army, and marched upon Constantinople. Alexis was compelled
                    to acknowlege him as colleague in the empire. The empress was put to death, and
                    her son soon shared the same fate. His dead body is said to have been insulted
                    by Andronicus, but the authorities for this and similar stories are in all
                    probability prejudiced. Andronicus, now (1183) sole emperor, married Agnes,
                    widow of Alexis II., a child eleven years of age. His short reign was
                    characterised by strong and wise measures. He resolved to check many abuses,
                    but, above all things, to limit the power of the nobles. The people, who felt
                    the severity of his laws, at the same time acknowledged their justice, and found
                    themselves protected from the rapacity of their superiors. The aristocrats,
                    however, were infuriated against him, and summoned to their aid William of
                    Sicily. This prince landed in Epirus with a strong force, and marched as far as
                    Thessalonica, which he took and destroyed; but he was shortly afterwards
                    defeated, and compelled to return to Sicily. Andronicus seems then to have
                    resolved to exterminate the aristocracy, and his plans were nearly crowned with
                    success. But in 1185, during his absence from the capital, his lieutenant
                    ordered the arrest and execution of Isaac Angelus, a descendant of the first
                    Alexis. Isaac escaped, and took refuge in the church of St Sophia. He appealed
                    to the populace, and a tumult arose which spread rapidly over the whole city.
                    When Andronicus arrived he found that his power was overthrown, and that Isaac
                    had been proclaimed emperor. His offers of a general pardon, and even of
                    abdication in favour of his son, were rejected; and, after an unsuccessful
                    attempt at escape, he was seized and dragged before the new emperor. Isaac
                    delivered him over to his enemies, and for three days he was exposed to their
                    fury and resentment. At last they hung him up by the feet between two pillars.
                    His dying agonies were shortened by an Italian soldier, who mercifully plunged a
                    sword into his body. He died on the 12th September 1185.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
