<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0622-0607-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IBN BATUTA (9th edition, volume 12, page 607)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hs61">Moslems</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4td9ng4n">Polo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212768">Oman</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242088">Sahara</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1213323">Aden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1070244">Polo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IBN BATUTA</label> (1304-78), whose proper name was
                    Abu-Abdullah Mahommed, one of the most remarkable of travellers and
                    autobiographers, was born at Tangier in 1304. He entered on his travels at the
                    age of twenty-one (1325), and closed them in 1355. Their compass was so vast
                    that we can but give the barest outline of them.</p>
                <p>He began by traversing the whole African coast of the Mediterranean from Tangier
                    to Alexandria, finding time to marry two wives on the road. After some stay at
                    Cairo, then probably the greatest city in the world (excluding China), and an
                    unsuccessful attempt to reach Mecca from Aidhâb on the west coast of the Red
                    Sea, he visited Palestine, Aleppo, and Damascus. He then made the pilgrimage to
                    the holy cities of the Hedjaz, and visited the shrine of Ali at Meshed-Ali,
                    travelling thence to Bussorah, and across the mountains of Khuzistan to Ispahan,
                    thence to Shiraz, and back to Kufa and Baghdad. After an excursion to Mosul and
                    Diarbekr, he made the <hi rend="italic">hdj</hi> a second time, staying at Mecca
                    three years. He next sailed down the Red Sea to Aden (then a place of great
                    trade), the singular position of which he describes, noticing its dependence for
                    water-supply upon those great cisterns for preserving the scanty rainfall which
                    have been cleaned out and restored in our own time. He continued his voyage down
                    the African coast, visiting, among other places, Mombas, and Quiloa in 9° S.
                    lat. Returning north he passed by the chief cities of Oman to New Hormuz, as he
                    calls the city which had, not many years before, been transferred to the island
                    where it became so famous. After visiting other parts of the gulf, he crossed
                    the breadth of Arabia to Mecca, making the <hi rend="italic">hdj</hi> for the
                    third time. Crossing the Red Sea he made a journey of great hardship to Syene,
                    and thence along the Nile to Cairo. After this, travelling through Syria, he
                    made an extensive circuit among the petty Turkish sultanates into which Asia
                    Minor was divided after the fall of the kingdom of Rùm (or Iconium). He now
                    crossed the Black Sea to Caffa, then mainly occupied by the Genoese, and
                    apparently the first Christian city the Moor had seen, for he was much perturbed
                    by the bell-ringing. He next travelled into Kipchak, or the country of the
                    Mongol khans on the Volga, and joined the camp of the reigning khan Mahommed
                    Uzbek, from whom the great and heterogeneous body that we know as <hi
                    rend="italic">Uzbeks</hi> is believed to have taken a name. Among other places
                    in this empire he travelled to Bolgar (54° 54' N. lat.) in order to witness the
                    shortness of the summer night, and desired to continue his travels north into
                    the “Land of Darkness,” of which wonderful things were told, but was obliged to
                    forego this. Rejoining the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n623/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0623-0608"/> sultan’s camp, he was allowed to join the cortege
                    of one of the Khâtùns, who was a Greek princess by birth (probably an
                    illegitimate one), and who was about to visit her own people. In her train he
                    travelled to Constantinople, where he had an interview with the emperor
                    Andronicus the Elder, whom he calls <hi rend="italic">Jirjis</hi> (George). He
                    tells us how, as he passed the city gates in the lady’s train, he heard the
                    guards muttering <hi rend="italic">Sarakinu! Sarakiηu!</hi> Returning to the
                    court of Uzbek, at Sarai on the Volga, he took his way across the steppes to
                    Khwarizm and Bokhara, and thence through Khorasan and Cabul. On this journey he
                    crossed the <hi rend="smallcaps">Hindu Kush (&lt;∕.v.),</hi> to which he gives
                    that name, its first occurrence. Travelling on, he reached the Indus,— according
                    to his own statement, in September 1333. This closes the first part of his
                    narrative.</p>
                <p>From'Sind, which he traversed to the sea and back again, he proceeded by Multan,
                    and eventually, on the invitation of Mahommed Tughlak, the reigning sovereign,
                    to Delhi. Mahommed was a singular character, full of pretence at least to many
                    accomplishments and virtues, the founder of public charities, and a profuse
                    patron of scholars, but a parricide, a fratricide, and as madly capricious,
                    bloodthirsty, and unjust as Caligula. As Ibn Batuta pithily sums up the
                    contradictions of his character, “there was no day that the gate of his palace
                    failed to witness alike the elevation of some object to affluence and the
                    torture and murder of some living soul.” He appointed the traveller to be kâzi
                    of Delhi, with a present of 12,000 silver dinârs (rupees) and an annual salary
                    of the same amount, besides an assignment of village lands. In the sultan’s
                    service he remained eight years; but his good fortune only stimulated his
                    natural extravagance, and at an early period his debts amounted to four or five
                    times his salary. At last he fell into disfavour, and retired from the court,
                    only to be summoned again on a congenial duty. The emperor of China, the last of
                    the Mongol dynasty, had sent a mission to Delhi which was to be reciprocated,
                    and the Moor was to go as one of the envoys. The account of the journey through
                    Central India to Cambay is full of interest. Thence the party went by sea to
                    Calicut, which is classed by the traveller with the neighbouring Kaulam
                    (Quilon), Alexandria, Sudâk in the Crimea, and Zayton (or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Chinchew,</hi><hi rend="italic">q.v.)</hi> in China, as one of the greatest
                    trading havens in the world,—an interesting enumeration from one who had seen
                    them all, The mission party was to embark in Chinese junks (the word used) and
                    smaller vessels, but that carrying the other envoys and the presents, which
                    started before he was ready, was wrecked totally; the vessel that he had engaged
                    went off with his property, and he was left on the beach of Calicut. Not daring
                    to return to Delhi with such a tale, he remained about Honore and other cities
                    of the western coast, taking part in various adventures, among others the
                    capture of Sindâbûr (or Goa), till he took it into his head to visit the Maidive
                    Islands. There he was made welcome, was nominated kâzï, married four wives, and
                    remained some months. But before long he was deep in quarrels and intrigues, and
                    in August 1344 he left for Ceylon. In this island he made the pilgrimage to
                    Adam’s Peak (“The Footmark of our Father Adam,” he calls it), of which he gives
                    an interesting account. Thence hebetook himself to Ma’abar (the Coromandel
                    coast), where he joined a Musulman adventurer who had made himself master of
                    much of that region, with his residence nt Madura. After once more visiting
                    Malabar, Canara, and the Maldives, he departed for Bengal, a voyage of
                    forty-three days, landing at Sadkâwàn (Chittagong). The chief circumstance of
                    his sojourn in Bengal was a visit made to a Musulman saint of singular character
                    and pretensions, Shaikh Jalâluddin, who dwelt in a hermitage among the Silhet
                    hills, and where his shrine (at Silhet) is still maintained as a place of
                    sanctity under the name of <hi rend="italic">Shah</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Jaläl.</hi> Returning to the delta, he took ship at Sunârgânw (near Dacca) on a
                    junk bound for Java (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Java Minor</hi> of Marco Polo, or
                    Sumatra). Touching on the coast of Arakan or Burmah, he reached Sumatra in forty
                    days, and was hospitably received at the court of Malik al-Dhâhir, a zealous
                    disciple of Islâm, which had then recently spread among the states on the
                    northern coast of that island. The king provided him with a junk in which to
                    prosecute his voyage to China. Some of the places which he describes on this
                    line are hard to identify, but apparently one of them was the coast of Camboja.
                    The port which received him in China was Zayton, famous in Marco Polo’s book,
                    and identified with the modern Chinchew. He also visited Sin-Kalan (“Great
                    China” or Màchin), a name by which Canton was then known to the Arabs, and
                    professes to have visited also Khansà <hi rend="italic">{Kiηsay</hi> of Marco
                    Polo, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> Hangchau), and Khânbâlik <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Cambaluc</hi> or Peking). The truth of his visit to these two cities, and
                    especially to the last, is very questionable. The traveller’s own history
                    singularly illustrates the power of the freemasonry of Mahometanism in carrying
                    him with a welcome over all the known world, and some anecdotes of his
                    adventures in China illustrate this even more forcibly.</p>
                <p>We cannot follow in detail his voyage back, or tell bow he saw the great bird <hi
                    rend="italic">Rukh</hi> (evidently, from his description, an island lifted by
                    refraction). Revisiting Sumatra, Malabar, Oman, Persia, Baghdad, he crossed the
                    great desert to Tadmor and Damascus, where he got his first news of home, and
                    heard of his father’s death fifteen years before. Diverging to Hamath and
                    Aleppo, on his return to Damascus he found the Black Death raging, so that two
                    thousand four hundred died in one day. Revisiting Jerusalem and Cairo, he made
                    the <hi rend="italic">haj</hi> for a fourth time, and finally turned westward,
                    reaching Fez, the capital of his native country, 8th November 1349, after an
                    absence of twenty-four years. It was, he says, after all, the best of all
                    countries. “The dirhems of the West are but little ones, ’ tis true; but then
                    you get more for them.”</p>
                <p>After going home to Tangier, he crossed into Spain and made the round of
                    Andalusia, including Gibraltar, which had just then stood a siege from Alphonso
                    XI. (whom the traveller calls “the Roman tyrant Adfunus”). In 1352 the restless
                    man started for Central Africa, passing by the oases of the Sahara (where the
                    houses were built of rock-salt, as Herodotus tells, and roofed with camel skins)
                    to Timbuctoo and Gogo on the Niger, a river which he calls the Nile, believing
                    it to flow down into Egypt, an opinion maintained by some up to the date of
                    Landor’s discovery. Being then recalled by his own king, he returned by Takadda,
                    Hogar, and Tawat to Fez, which he reached in the beginning of 1354. This is the
                    end of his recorded wanderings, which extended over a space of twenty-eight
                    years, andin their main lines alone exceeded 75,000 miles.</p>
                <p>By royal order his history was written down from his dictation by Mahommed Ibn
                    Juzai, the king’s secretary, a work concluded on the 13th December 1355. This
                    editor ends the work with this appropriate colophon :—“Here ends what I have put
                    into shape from the memoranda of the Shaikh Abu-Abdallah Mahommed Ibn Batüta,
                    whom may God honour I No person of sense can fail to see that this Shaikh is the
                    Traveller of Our Age; and he who should call him The Traveller of the whole Body
                    of Islâm would not exceed the truth I” The traveller died in 1377-78,.aged
                    seventy-three.</p>
                <p>Ibn Batuta’s travels have only been known in Europe during the present century,
                    and were known then for many years only by Arabic abridgments existing in the
                    Gotha and Cambridge libraries. Notices or extracts had been published by Seetzen
                    (c. 1808), Kozegarten (1818), Apetz (1819), and Burckhαrdt (1819), when, in 1829
                    Dr 9. Lee published for the Oriental Translation Fund a version <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n624/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0624-0609"/> from the abridged MSS. at Cambridge, which
                    attracted much interest. The French capture of Constantina at last afforded MSS.
                    of the complete work, one of them the autograph of lbn Juzai. And from these,
                    after versions of fragments by various French scholars, was derived at last
                    (1858-59) a careful edition and translation of the whole by Μ. Défrémery and Dr
                    Sanguinetti, with a valuable index and other apparatus, in <hi rend="italic"
                    >4</hi> vols. 8vo.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>P.
                    Jose de S. Antonio Moura previously published at Lisbon a Portuguese translation
                    from a MS. obtained by him at Fez many years before.</p></note></p>
                <p>Though there are some singular chronological difficulties in the narrative, and a
                    good many cursory inaccuracies and exaggerations, there is no part of it except
                    the voyage to China in which its substantial veracity is open to doubt. Nor can
                    it be questioned, we think, that he really visited China, though it is probable
                    that his visit was confined to the ports of the south. The whole of the second
                    part of his story especially is full of vivacity and interest. His accounts, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> of the Maidive Islands, and of the Negro countries on
                    the Niger, are replete with interesting particulars, and appear to be accurate
                    and unstrained. The former agrees surprisingly with that given by the only other
                    foreign resident we know of, viz., Pyrard de la Vai, two hundred and fifty years
                    later. His full and curious statements and anecdotes regarding the showy virtues
                    and very solid vices of Sultan Mahommed Tughlak are in entire agreement with
                    Indian historians, and add many fresh details.</p>
                <p>To do justice to the traveller’s own character, as he has unconsciously drawn it,
                    would require the hand of Chaucer and his freedom of speech. Not deficient
                    either in acuteness or in humanity; full of vital energy and enjoyment; infinite
                    in curiosity; daring, restless, impulsive, sensual, inconsiderate,, extravagant;
                    superstitious in his regard for the Moslem saints and quacks, and plying devout
                    observances when in difficulties; an agreeable companion, for he is always
                    welcomed at first, but clinging like a horseleech when he finds a full-blooded
                    subject, and hence apt to disgust his patrons, and then to turn to intrigue
                    against them,—such is the picture we form of this prince of Moslem travellers.
                    (H. Y.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
