<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0872-0847-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INDUS (9th edition, volume 12, page 847)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40g3h15m">Floods</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864963">Clupea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938092">Gars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927573">Floods</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n872/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INDUS</label>, one of the three greatest rivers of northern
                    India, rises in unknown regions on the northern slopes of the sacred Kailas
                    Mountain in the Himâlayas. . On the south of this same hill rises the Sutlej,
                    the great feeder of the Indus, which unites with it after a separate course of
                    about 1000 miles. The Indus rises in 32° N. lat. and 81° E, long., enters the
                    Punjab in 34° 25' N. lat. and 72° 5Γ E. long., leaves the Punjab in 28° 27' N.
                    lat. and 69° 47' E. long., enters Sind in 28° 26' N. lat. and 69° 47' E. long.,
                    and finally falls into the Arabian Sea in 23° 58' N. lat. and 67° 30' E. long.
                    The basin of the Indus is estimated at 372,700 square miles, and its total
                    length at a little over 1800 miles.</p>
                <p>The first third of its course lies outside of British territory. It at first
                    flows north-west for about 160 miles under the name of “Sinh-ka-bab,” until it
                    receives the Gar. Shortly after this junction it enters Kashmir. Near Iskardoh
                    in Little Tibet is the wonderful gorge by which the river bursts through the
                    western ranges of the Himâlayas, said to be 14,000 feet in depth. For about 120
                    miles the river passes south-west through the wilds of Kohistân until it reaches
                    the Punjab frontier near Derbend.' A little way above Attock, in Rawâl Pindi
                    district, it receives the Cabul river, which brings down to it the waters from
                    Afghânistân <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Jalâlâbâd and the Khyber Pass. The two
                    rivers have about the same volume; both are. very swift, and are broken up with
                    rocks. Their junction during floods is a scene of wild confusion of waters. At
                    Attock the river has fallen from its elevation of 16,000 feet at its source in
                    Tibet to under 2000 feet. After leaving Attock, the Indus flows almost due south
                    down the western side of the Punjab, parallel to the Sulâimân hills. Just above
                    Mithankot, in the south of the Derâ Ghâzi Khân district, the Indus receives the
                    accumulated waters of the Punjab. Between the Indus and the Jumna (Jamunâ) flow
                    the five great streams from which the Punjab (Panj-âb, literally “The land of
                    the five rivers ”) takes its name. These are the Jhelum, the Chenâb, the Râvi,
                    the Bids, and the Sutlej. After various junctions these rivers all unite to form
                    the Panjnad, literally “The five rivers.” The Panjnad marks for a short space
                    the boundary between the Punjab and Bahâwalpur, and unites with the Indus near
                    Mithankot, about 490 miles from the sea. The breadth of the Indus above the
                    confluence is about 600 yards, its velocity 5 miles an hour, its depth from 12
                    to 15 feet, and its estimated discharge 91,719 cubic feet per second. The
                    breadth of the Panjnad above the point of junction is 1076 yards, with a depth
                    of 12 to 15 feet, but a velocity of only 2 miles an hour. . Its estimated
                    discharge is 68,955 cubic feet per second.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n873/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0873-0848"/>
                <p>Below the junction the united stream, under the name of the Indus, has a breadth
                    which varies from 2000 yards to several miles, according to the season of the
                    year. The whole course of the river through the Punjab is broken up by islands
                    and sandbanks. The Indus enters Sind in 28° 26' N. lat. and 69° 47' E. long.,
                    and empties itself by many mouths into the Arabian Sea, after a generally
                    south-westerly course in this province of 580 miles. Its average width during
                    the low season is 680 yards; its depth varies from 4 to 24 feet. Its velocity in
                    the freshes averages 7 knots per hour, at ordinary times 3 knots. The discharge
                    per second varies at the two periods from 446,086 cubic feet to 40,857. The
                    average temperature is 10° lower than that of the air.</p>
                <p>The delta of the Indus covers an area of about 3000 square miles, and extends
                    along the coast-line for 125 miles. It is almost a perfect level, and nearly
                    destitute of timber, the tamarisk and mangrove alone supplying fuel. In the
                    marshy portions good pasturage is obtained, and in the drier rice grows
                    luxuriantly. The climate of the delta is cool and bracing in the “winter”
                    months, excessively hot in the “summer,” and most healthy during the floods.</p>
                <p>The Indus begins to rise in March, attains its maximum depth and width in August,
                    and subsides in September. The registered rise at Gidu-Bandar is 15 feet. Fish
                    abound,—at the mouths, the salt-water varieties, notably the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Clupea</hi><hi rend="italic">neowhii,</hi> a species of herring; the chief of
                    the freshwater varieties is the <hi rend="italic">pala.</hi> The local
                    consumption and export of the dried <hi rend="italic">pala</hi> are both very
                    large. The boats of the Indus are the <hi rend="italic">dundhi</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">zaurak</hi> (cargo boats), the <hi rend="italic">kauntäl</hi> or
                    ferry-boats, and the <hi rend="italic">dûndo</hi> or fishing boats. The
                    aggregate burthen of the native craft on the river in 1861-62 was as follows
                    :—up-stream to Sukkur 20,232 tons, and beyond that town 16,317; down-stream to
                    Sukkur 7694 tons, and beyond it 11,456. In 1874 the number of steamers plying
                    was fourteen, and of barges forty-three, with an aggregate burthen of 10,641
                    tons; the receipts amounted to £83,370.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
