<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0839-0814-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INDIANAPOLIS (9th edition, volume 12, page 814)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17t24g">Traffic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996964">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1154345">Trafficability</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204604">Indiana</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n839/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INDIANAPOLIS</label>, the capital of Indiana, is situated at
                    almost the exact geographical centre of the State, in 39° 47' N. lat., 86° 6' W.
                    long., 824 miles W. of New York by rail, and 194 miles S.E. of Chicago. It
                    stands 721 feet above the sea-level, and 148 above Lake Erie.</p>
                <p>On the admission of Indiana as a State into the Federal Union in 1816, Congress
                    presented 4 square miles of public lands for its seat of government, to be
                    selected by the State. The location was made in 1820 at the confluence of Fall
                    Creek and White River. The site chosen was in the midst of the unbroken forest,
                    60 miles distant from the borders of civilization, and only reached by Indian
                    trails. The name Indianapolis was given by an act of the Legislature on January
                    6, 1821; and Alexander Ralston was appointed to lay out the city. Selecting a
                    slight mound near the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n840/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0840-0815"/> middle of the ground as the centre of the
                    proposed capital, Ralston laid out the town after the manner of Washington city,
                    which he had helped to survey.</p>
                <p>Four avenues radiate from the centre to the four corners of the city. The streets
                    and avenues are 90 feet wide, except Washington, the main street, which is 120.
                    The city has now outgrown its original limits, and extends 4 miles in length and
                    3 in width. It is built upon a level plain and surrounded by a fertile country.
                    It was incorporated in 1836, and received a city charter in 1847. Its growth is
                    shown by the following table :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Population.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Assessed Value of Property.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1850</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8,090</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>$2,326,185</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1860</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18,113</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10,700,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48,244</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25,981,267</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1880 .</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>75,074</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50,254,934</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In 1847 the first railway entered the city. Within a few years thereafter other
                    lines were constructed, until now twelve main lines converge in the Union Dépôt.
                    About one hundred passenger trains, connected with every part of the country,
                    enter and depart daily. The numerous tracks being on a level with the surface of
                    the streets, the obstruction and danger at the numerous crossings became very
                    great on account of the increase of railway traffic, so that in 1877 a loop
                    line, called the “Belt,” had to be made passing round the city, to connect the
                    various railroads. By means of it the “through freight cars” are conveyed past
                    the city without blocking the traffic.</p>
                <p>Indianapolis is in the centre of the swine-producing region, and pork packing is
                    one of the chief industries of the city. The number packed in 1877 was 420,000
                    head; in 1878, 766,000; in 1879, 677,809. It is also largely engaged in the
                    grain trade. The railways have been of greatest service to Indianapolis,
                    compensating for its want of water transit. The manufacturing and mercantile
                    interests, which are large and increasing, are the natural result of the city’s
                    extensive railroad connexions.</p>
                <p>A system of graded free schools is maintained all the year. The city school
                    property is valued at $1,041,000.</p>
                <p>In 1871 a public library was established, and is supported by taxation, which now
                    contains 36,461 volumes, and is rapidly increasing. The masonic temple,
                    oddfellows’ hall, post-office, U. S. arsenal, and chamber of commerce are
                    handsome buildings. The Marion county court-house, standing on a public square
                    in the heart of the city, was completed in 1877 at a cost of $1,411,524. The
                    exterior is of Indiana limestone, the interior of iron and marble, with frescoed
                    walls and ceilings. Its dimensions are 150 by 286 feet, and 240 feet to the top
                    of the dome. The principal benevolent institutions of the State, viz., the
                    institution for the education of the blind, that for the deaf and dumb, and the
                    hospital for the insane, are located here; they are handsome and commodious
                    buildings, the last having accommodation for 1313 patients. The State
                    reformatory for women and girls, where all female offenders are imprisoned,
                    adjoins the city. The institution is under the management of a board of control,
                    composed of women chosen by the governor of the State. In 1877 the State began
                    the erection of a new State house, to be completed in 1888, at a cost of
                    $2,000,000. This will be one of the most imposing capital buildings in the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>By law the power to incur permanent debt is limited to a sum not exceeding 2 per
                    cent, upon the assessed value of the property within the city; and the rate of
                    taxation is limited to 90 cents per $100 for municipal purposes, 20 cents for
                    public schools, and 2 cents for free libraries. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. c.
                    h.</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 1</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
