<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0734-0715-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IMMACULATE CONCEPTION (9th edition, volume 12, page
                    715)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119629">Sins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896225">Dogma</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n734/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IMMACULATE CONCEPTION</label>. The dogma of the immaculate
                    conception of the Virgin Mary, as held by the Church of Rome, is to the effect
                    that “the most blessed Virgin was, in view of the merits of Jesus Christ the
                    Saviour of the human race, by the singular grace and favour of Almighty God,
                    from the first moment of her conception in the womb of her mother, preserved
                    free from all taint of original sin.” The “pious opinion” that the mother of
                    Christ had during her life been preserved from sin in a way in which no other
                    human being ever had been may be traced back to a comparatively early period:
                    indeed, without it her cultus (for some account of the growth of which see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mary)</hi> as it hud developed itself long before the 9th
                    century, would have been impossible. The actual history of an explicit doctrine
                    of her immaculate conception, however, so far as has hitherto been discovered,
                    may be said to begin, in the year 1140,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The allegation that it was taught by Anselm of Canterbury ia
                    based partly upon a spurious tract attributed to him and partly on unauthentic
                    legend. His actual opinion is explicitly enough stated in the treatise <hi
                    rend="italic">Cur Deus Homo,</hi> c. 18:—“Virgo tamen ipsa, unde assumptus est,
                    est in iniquitatibus concepta, et in peccatis concepit eam mater
                    ejus.”</p></note> with the letter of remonstrance which Bernard of Clairvaux
                    wrote to the canons of the cathedral at Lyons <hi rend="italic">(Ep.</hi> 174),
                    who, without consulting the Roman see, had recently introduced into their church
                    a festival in celebration of that doctrine. Bernard argued vigorously against
                    this on the ground of its novelty, its unscripturalness (Ps. li. 5), and its
                    absurdity :—“On the same principle,” said he, “you would be obliged to hold that
                    the conception of her ancestors, in an ascending line, was also a holy one,
                    since otherwise she could not have descended from them worthily, and there would
                    then be festivals without number.” How the recipients, who, it is stated,
                    claimed to have learned their peculiar rite from a document communicated by the
                    Virgin herself, were affected by this letter, is not recorded. Among
                    controversial treatises which appeared shortly afterwards are mentioned those of
                    Potho of Prüm and the Abbot de la Celle against the doctrine, and that of the
                    English monk Nicolas in its favour. In the 13th century all the leading
                    theologians, such as Alexander Halensis (p. iii., qu. 10, membr. 2), Albertus
                    Magnus <hi rend="italic">(Ccmm. in Sent.,</hi> iii. 3), Bonaventura <hi
                    rend="italic">(Comm. in Sent.,</hi> iii. 3. 1, 2), and Thomas Aquinas <hi
                    rend="italic">(Summa,</hi> p. iii., qu. 27, art. 1-3), took the view of St
                    Bernard, their contribution to the theology of the subject consisting in an
                    accurate definition of the moment at which the Virgin’s sanctification in the
                    womb must be held to have taken place. During the same century the feast of the
                    Conception became very popular, and in 1263 it was accepted by a general chapter
                    of the Franciscans at Pisa, without reference, however, to the question of
                    immaculacy. Of great importance to the subsequent history of the dogmu was the
                    appearance in the theological world, towards the beginning of the 14th century,
                    of Duns Scotus, the “subtle doctor” of the Franciscans, who, as in so many other
                    points, so also in this, came into conflict with the still more illustrious
                    “Doctor Angelicus,” the Dominican Aquinas. In one part of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentary</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">Sentences</hi> of Peter of Lombardy
                    (lib. iii., dist. 3, qu. 1, sec. 9) he declares for the thinkableness and even
                    probability of Mary’s having been preserved intact from original sin; in a later
                    passage (dist. 18, qu. 1, sec. 13) the doctrine is categorically stated. It was
                    upon this disputed point that the long and bitter controversy between the two
                    great mendicant orders chiefly turned. In 1389, the Spanish Dominican Joannes de
                    Montesono having maintained in a disputation at Paris that the view of the
                    Scotists was unscriptural and heretical, the university, without committing
                    itself on the main point, condemned his violent theses, and this condemnation
                    was concurred in by the Avignon pope, Clement VII. The members of the entire <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n735/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0735-0716"/> Dominican order, for their refusal to acquiesce,
                    were for several years excluded from the privileges of the university. In the
                    beginning of the 15 th century the famous chancellor, John Gerson, accepted the
                    new dogma, and applied in its favour the well-known doctrine of development. At
                    the council of Basel (in the 36th session, held September 17, 1439) it was
                    defined and declared that the doctrine was consistent with faith, reason, and
                    Scripture, and therefore to be approved and embraced; the contrary doctrine was
                    not condemned, but it was forbidden to preach or to teach it. The university of
                    Paris now made subscription to the doctrine of the Immaculate Conception a
                    condition for its degrees, and various other universities entered into a solemn
                    compact to use every exertion for its spread, but the controversy was far from
                    having been brought to a close even by the action of Pope Sixtus IV., who in
                    1483 published a bull threatening with excommunication any one who should accuse
                    of heresy either the advocates or the impugners of the doctrine, the point
                    having not yet been decided by the apostolical see. In its fifth session (1546)
                    the council of Trent, after formulating its decree on the subject of original
                    sin, sought to effect a compromise between Dominicans and Franciscans by
                    appending a declaration that it did not intend that this doctrine should be
                    applied to the blessed and immaculate Virgin Mary, but that the constitutions of
                    Sixtus IV. were still to be observed. In the beginning of the 17th century the
                    field of battle was transferred to Spain, where, under the predominant influence
                    of the Franciscans and Jesuits, medals were struck, pictures painted, statues
                    erected, and persecutions set on foot in honour of the Virgin “sin pe-cado
                    concebida”; and embassies were sent to Rome, both by Philip III. and by Philip
                    IV., to obtain more explicit recognition of the popular doctrine. The popes
                    continued for a long time, however, to maintain their attitude of reserve. Paul
                    V. (1617) forbade all public dispute on the subject, and Gregory XV. (1622)
                    extended the prohibition even to private discussions, except in the case of
                    Dominicans <hi rend="italic">“inter sef</hi> But gradually the papal sympathies
                    became in &gt;re pronounced under Jesuit influences; Clement IX. gave the feast
                    of the Conception an octave; Clement XI., in 1708, made it a festival “de
                    praecepto” for all Christendom; while Benedict XIV. endeavoured to reconcile St
                    Bernard with the more modern tendencies of Roman Catholic theology, by insisting
                    upon subtle distinctions between the “conceptio activa” and the “conceptio
                    passiva” of Mary. In the pontificate of Gregory XVI. several prelates received
                    papal permission to describe her conception as immaculate; and in 1849 Pius IX.
                    was induced to address to his bishops from Gaeta an encyclical, inviting them to
                    state how far the dogmatic definition of the dogma would meet their wishes and
                    the wishes of those under their charge. A large majority declared themselves
                    strongly in favour of the proposal, and the ultimate result was that in December
                    8, 1854, the pope, in presence of a numerous concourse of cardinals, patriarchs,
                    archbishops, and bishops assembled in St Peter’s, Rome, solemnly promulgated the
                    bull “Ineffabilis Deus,” by which the doctrine of the Immaculate Conception
                    finally became for the Roman communion an article of faith, the denial of which
                    is accounted to be heresy.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The words are “Auctoritate Domini Nostri Jesu Christi, beatorum Apostolorum
                    Petri et Pauli, ac Nostra, declaramus, pronuntiamus et definimus, doctrinam,
                    quae tenet Beatissimam Virginem Mariam in primo instanti suae Conceptionis
                    fuisse singulari Omnipotentis Dei gratia et privilegio, intuitu meritorum
                    Christi Jesu, Salvatoris humani generis, ab omni originalis culpae labe
                    praeservatam immunem, esse a Deo revelatam, atque idcirco ab omnibus fidelibus
                    firmiter constanterque credendam.</p></note></p>
                <p>The feast of the Immaculate Conception is observed in the Roman Church on
                    December 8. In the Greek Church there is a festival in honour of the conception
                    of St Anne</p>
                <p>(the mother of Mary), for which December 9 was fixed by a constitution of the
                    emperor Emanuel Comnenus in the 12 th century. Her deliverance from the reproach
                    of sterility is what is celebrated; there is no reference to anything analogous
                    to the Roman doctrine. It may be remarked that strong expressions as to the
                    absolute purity of Mary are found in the Koran (iii. 37), and still more in
                    later Mahometan writings; but the Christian doctrine of sin is so utterly
                    foreign to Islam that no precise theological construction of these expressions
                    is possible.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
