<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0583-0545-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">VALDO, or Waldo, Peter</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 545</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bd1d">Poor</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90f84">Preaching</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1071040">Poor</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1074813">Preaching</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937258">Gallicisms</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=583" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">VALDO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Waldo, Peter</hi></label>,
                    frequently described as the Lyonese reformer of the twelfth century, appears in
                    contemporary documents under the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Valdes.</hi>
                    In the earliest existing documents he is called <hi rend="italic">Valdes</hi>
                    (by W. Mapes,) and <hi rend="italic">Valdesius</hi> (by the Chronicler of Laon),
                    <hi rend="italic">Valdesius, Valdius, Valdensis, Waldius,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Walderisis.</hi> Unless he derived his name from some locality,
                    Valdes or Valdo was his right appellation. The latter is of very common
                    occurrence in Gallic and Germanic documents, from the ninth to the twelfth
                    century, and <hi rend="italic">W</hi> is the Germano-Burgundian spelling. It is
                    uncertain why or where he was first named <hi rend="italic">Peter.</hi> His
                    praenomen <hi rend="italic">Petrus</hi> occurs, we believe for the first time,
                    in a Latin book of Peter de Polichdorf, written during the last half of the
                    fourteenth century.</p><p>Contemporary and documentary history is silent as to the place and date of
                    Valdo’s birth, and the events of his earlier days; but tradition states that he
                    was born in a place which, by some, has been called Vaud, Vaux, Vaudram; by
                    others Walden and Val-Grant. There is still a village near Lyon called Vaux, and
                    another in the mountain region, between Mont Dauphiné and Briançon, called Vaux
                    de Rame. The first authentic mention of the Gallic reformer appears in the
                    Chronicle of Laon, under the year 1173. He is there introduced to our notice as
                    a citizen of Lyon, who, having amassed considerable wealth by usurious
                    practices, had his conscience alarmed in a very remarkable manner. One Sunday,
                    in the year 1173, hearing a Troubadour in the streets of the city, reciting
                    passages from the Romaunt called the “Life of Alexis,” Valdo invited him home,
                    and listened with earnest attention to the whole of the poem. Alexis, as the
                    legend tells us, was a saint of eminent piety, who was so dead to all the
                    attractions of this world, that he fled from the house of a wealthy father, and
                    left his young bride on the day of his marriage, to devote himself to a fife of
                    poverty and mortification. After seventeen years of self-imposed exile, he
                    returned to the paternal abode, in the character of a mendicant, and for many
                    years received daily relief at his father’s door, without making himself known.
                    At his death a written paper revealed his secret. The narrative made a deep
                    impression on the mind of Valdo, of which the Troubadour<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In those days, many of the jongleurs and
                    wandering troubadours often combined the several characters of pedlars, poets
                    and religious Instructors. They were a privileged order, whose harp, and song,
                    and news, obtained for them admission into the castles of the lierons, and the
                    houses of the citizens. They would oftentimes begin by diverting their hearers,
                    and. after touching some string which roused devout feelings, they would launch
                    into sacred subjects, produce transcripts of Scripture, and converse on the
                    deepest points of sacred truth.</p></note> failed not to take advantage. Moved
                    by the serious discourse of his guest, Valdo went the next morning to unburthen
                    his mind to a priest of great reputation in the city, and consulted him as to
                    what he should do for the attainment of Christian perfection. “If thou wouldest
                    be perfect,” was the answer, “Go, sell all thou hast, and give to the poor.”
                    Valdo resolved to obey the injunction to the very letter. He converted his
                    property into money; he placed his two daughters in the convent of
                    Fontevrault;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In Poitou.
                    A fraternity, called “The Poor of Christ,” was settled here in 1103, under the
                    government of a woman; an institution which has been severely attacked by
                    Bayle.</p></note> he distributed largely to the poor; he fed all who came to him
                    three days in the week; and on the festival of the assumption of the Virgin
                    Mary, he publicly proclaimed his intention of abandoning the service of mammon
                    for that or God <hi rend="smallcaps">,</hi> and invited his fellow-citizens to
                    follow his example. His wife, alarmed by these proceedings, implored the
                    archbishop of Lyon to check the imprudent zeal of her husband, and that prelate
                    and his suffragan, the bishop of Bourg-en-Bresse, gave Valdo some advice upon
                    the occasion. Nothing however could damp his ardour; he persevered in his system
                    of self-denial, and gained over a number of followers, who imitated his example,
                    by embracing voluntary poverty, and by ministering bountifully to the wants of
                    the poor.</p><p>A severe famine, which desolated the whole of Gaul at this time, gave them full
                    opportunities of exercising the virtue of almsgiving, and they did so to the
                    very utmost. Forming themselves into a fraternity, under the name of “Poor Men
                    of Lyon,” Valdo and his disciples at first made themselves conspicuous, by the
                    sanctity of their lives only, but they soon began to attract further notice, by
                    rebuking the rapaciousness and corrupt manners of the ecclesiastical and monkish
                    orders. Here indeed was ample room for complaint: the ignorance and profligacy
                    of the clergy, with some few bright exceptions, were the scandal of the church;
                    and we require not the evidence of her adversaries—that of churchmen is quite
                    sufficient—to establish this fact. It was a long course of wickedness in high
                    places, and inefficiency on the part of those who called themselves the
                    successors of the apostles, and the lawfully appointed ministers of Christ,
                    which prepared the way for such a work as Valdo had to perform. But though he
                    was one of the most eminent of early reformers, he was not the first to rouse
                    Christendom from her unholy slumbers, and to say to those who slept, “awake !”
                    Even before the scenes at Orleans in 1017, described by Glaber, voices had been
                    heard, almost simultaneously, from Germany, France, and Italy, protesting
                    against ecclesiastical corruptions; and we have the testimony of Bernard of
                    Clairvaux, Peter of Clugny, and Evervinus of Cologne, who flourished between
                    1120 and 1150, to prove that, in that age, zealous and holy men were to be
                    found, who declaimed against the vices and errors of the clergy, and proposed
                    schemes of reformation.</p><p>By degrees, Valdo and the Poor Men of Lyon took upon themselves to exhort and to
                    admonish, in fact to preach both in public and private. “Coeperunt paulatim,”
                    says the Chronicle of Laon, “tam publicis quam privatis admonitionibus sua et
                    aliena culpare peccata.” This was no slight matter of exasperation to a powerful
                    body of men, whose priesthood was disgraced by priestcraft; but another
                    proceeding of the reformer called forth their fiercest animosity. Valdo employed
                    his time and property on one of the most useful and sacred objects to which a
                    Christian could dedicate himself, the translation and circulation of Scripture
                    in the vernacular tongue of the country, and for this he has never been forgiven
                    by the successors of Hildebrand. To lock up Scripture, or to refuse the free use
                    of it, was one of the novelties of an imperious and jealous church, and a
                    disproof of the infallibility of popes and councils. In 841, the third council
                    of Tours decreed, in its seventh canon, that bishops should promote scriptural
                    instruction by translations of certain homilies and psalms in the vulgar tongue,
                    “in rusticam Romanam linguam aut Theotiscam.” In the twelfth and thirteenth
                    centuries, a new light broke in upon Christian hierarchs, or they began to
                    prefer darkness to light, and it was forbidden by councils<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=584" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0584-0546"/>
                    to turn Scripture into vernacular languages for the use of the people. The
                    manner in which Valdo set about his work, attests the soundness of his judgment,
                    as well as the devotedness of his zeal. In the first place, he obtained the
                    assistance of three eminent scholars, who had a critical acquaintance with the
                    sacred writings; Bernard of Ydros, who was afterwards held in great estimation
                    by the Dominican order; Stephen of Ansa or Empsa, eminent as a grammarian and
                    linguist, who was promoted in course of time to a benefice in the city of
                    Lyon;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Stephen de
                    Borbone, apud Echart Scrip. Ordinis Praedicatorum, vol. i. p. 192.</p></note>
                    and John of Lugio,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Reinerus de Cath. c. 6; and Polickdorf, c. 1.</p></note><hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> a biblical scholar of high reputation, who became the
                    head of a religious congregation in Lombardy. The latter was the only one of the
                    three who remained faithful to the cause of Valdo, and the silence of the two
                    former, after they deserted him, as to any spots in his moral character, is a
                    strong attestation in his favour. Stephen translated into the Gallo-Provençal
                    language, John examined authorities and corrected the translations, and Bernard
                    transcribed the version so prepared for the use of the copyists, who were to
                    multiply copies for general circulation. But not satisfied with these means for
                    procuring correct translations of the Bible, Valdo also collected sentences of
                    the ancient fathers, particularly of Ambrose, Augustin, Gregory, and Jerome<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Moneta contra Valdenses,
                    lib. v. c. 1.</p></note>? in illustration of the b∞ks of Scripture, of which
                    copies were to be made; and these, too, he put in circulation to serve as notes
                    or comments for the help of his Scripture readers. This being done, the master
                    and his disciples committed many passages of Scripture to memory, and thus armed
                    with the word of God, they went forth into the streets and the houses of Lyon,
                    and into the villages of the neighbourhood, and delivered the gospel message
                    with so much ardour and success, as largely to increase the number of their
                    adherents. In some few places the churches were open to them by consent of the
                    secular clergy; and where they could not have access to the sanctuaries, they
                    preached and expounded Scripture in the streets and highways. It is uncertain
                    how many books of the Bible were translated and circulated by the Lyonese
                    Reformer, and the Poor Men of Lyons. Walter Mapes says, that the volume of Valdo
                    which was presented to Pope Alexander, contained the text and a gloss of the <hi rend="italic">Psalms,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">of many books</hi> of the Old
                    and New Testament. Reiner leads us to believe, that the whole of the New
                    Testament was circulated by them, in the vulgar tongue. Stephen de Borbone
                    speaks only of <hi rend="italic">many books</hi> of the Bible, without
                    designating them. The effect produced by the gospel tidings, as they were
                    delivered by these new expounders, was felt like an electric spark throughout
                    the whole of the province and diocese of Lyon. The common people heard them
                    gladly, for now, for the first time in their lives, they listened to preachers
                    who spoke in the language of Scripture, and pointed to the sacred page, in
                    confirmation of every doctrine which they urged.</p><p>After persevering in this course for five years, Valdo found that the increasing
                    enmity of the monks and clergy of Lyons had become dangerous to him. In 1178, he
                    therefore took the bold and honest step of going to Rome, to make his views
                    known to the sovereign pontiff Alexander III. and to request the papal sanction
                    to his proceedings.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Chronicle of Laon. See Bouquet, vol. xiii. p. 680.</p></note> In fact, he
                    asked the pope to recognize his fraternity of the “Poor Men of Lyon” as an
                    ecclesiastical order of authorised preachers, and licensed circulators of
                    Scripture. Never did the founder of a religious community experience a better
                    reception from prince or pontiff. The pope embraced Valdo, “Valdesium amplexatus
                    est papa, approbans votum quod fuerat voluntariae paupertatis, &amp;c.” says the
                    faithful narrator whom we have before cited.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ibid.</p></note><hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> He approved
                    of the order of the “Poor Men of Lyon” as professors of voluntary poverty; but
                    while he gave them a limited license as preachers, he forbade them to exercise
                    it without the especial permission of the regular priesthood. Up to this period
                    the conduct of Valdo and his disciples had been irreproachable even at Rome, or
                    the pope would not have shown him such favour. In fact, all his proceedings
                    hitherto had been strongly characteristic of one who acted as a dutiful member
                    of the holy Catholic church. It was a church-legend which first made a serious
                    impression upon him; it was to a priest that he first went for spiritual
                    counsel, after his conscience had been awakened. The adviser whom he next
                    consulted was a bishop; so closely did he observe the canon of Ignatius, “nihil
                    sine episcopo.” He placed his daughters in a convent; an act which savoured of
                    the most rigid adherence to ecclesiastical customs. The holy book on which the
                    church builds its faith was his constant study; and his chosen fellow-labourers
                    in the work of transcribing and translating, were members of the sacerdotal
                    order. So blameless was his career, and so conscious was he himself of the
                    purity of his motives, that he sought, as we have shewn, an interview with him
                    who was called the supreme Head of the Church, and was received with indulgence
                    and honour. The childlike submission and meekness of this exemplary Christian
                    were carried to such an extent, that for a time he obeyed the pope, and forbore
                    to preach, except on the terms imposed upon him. At length however his ardent
                    zeal, sharpened by the opposition of the clergy, who hated the spirituality and
                    fervour which condemned their own negligence, could no longer be restrained, and
                    he preached without their permission. He and his disciples were commanded by
                    episcopal authority not to speak at all, nor preach in the name of Jesus; they
                    answered as Peter and John had done before the council at Jerusalem. They were
                    accused of a presumptuous usurpation of the apostolic office, and were again
                    admonished to be silent, on pain of the severest ecclesiastical censure. They
                    however persevered, and from disobedience, says one of our historical witnesses,
                    they fell into contumacy, and from contumacy, into the penalty of
                    excommunication.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Stephen
                    de Borbone, ut supra.</p></note> ® The fearful sentence, which was meant to
                    deprive them of all the ordinances of religion, to exclude them from the church
                    and the altar, to deny baptism to their children, burial to their dead, marriage
                    to their betrothed, and to banish them from Lyon, was passed by John de
                    Bellesmains, archbishop of Lyon, in 1181. Pope Lucius confirmed the
                    excommunication in 1184. In the Lateran council of 1215, the same dread sentence
                    was again fulminated against all who should embrace their doctrines, or receive
                    them into their houses. They were driven ignominiously from their homes; and
                    seeing no hope of producing a reformation in the bosom of the imperious church,
                    out of which they had been cast, or of being received back into it, without
                    doing violence to their consciences, Valdo and his followers had no other
                    alternative than to form themselves into a community, in which persons, selected
                    from their own body, were appointed to perform the offices of religion, and
                    administer the sacraments.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>From all we can collect, this was not done until after very mature
                    deliberation and consultation with religious persons in other countries, whose
                    eyes had been opened to the corruptions of the Latin church. Monets, the most
                    dispassionate of all their accusers, states that Valdo “ordinem habuit ab
                    universitate fratrum suorum,” and that a Lombard separatist was his authority
                    for this statement. Moneta contra Valdenses, lib. v. c. 1.</p></note> Thus Valdo
                    and the “Poor Men,” or “Valdenses of Lyon" were not voluntary seceders from the
                    dominant church, but they were thrust out of her, and Rome, contrary to her
                    usual policy, which is to turn enthusiasm to account <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=585" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0585-0547"/>in
                    her own favour, if not in her own way, has to thank herself for a schism, which
                    rent from her communion some of the most devout Christians of France, and of
                    several other countries, in which the doctrines of the Lyonese reformers
                    gradually found recipients.</p><p>The “Poor Men of Lyon,” exiled from their native city, found refuge in the
                    secluded parts of Provence and Lombardy, and were hospitably received there by
                    persons who held kindred opinions. The document, which states this, points to
                    religious communities on each side of the Cottian Alps, to the territorial
                    Waldenses of ecclesiastical history, whose situation providentially enabled them
                    to maintain in safety opinions at variance with those of Rome. A remarkable
                    passage in the authority which gives us this information, adds that the exiles
                    imbibed the errors of these subalpine heretics, and became, when they mingled
                    with them, the most determined enemies of the church.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Stephen de Borbone, ut
                    supra.</p></note></p><p>From this time the “Poor Men of Lyon,” and the Val-denses (territorially so
                    called) of the Cottian Alps, became mixed up in ecclesiastical history, as if
                    they were one and the same. But the former, after their exile from Lyon, were
                    never gathered together in any one district or province as a distinct people,
                    but were scattered among the nations; and those who embraced their tenets,
                    sometimes adhered to them openly, sometimes secretly, but never in sufficient
                    numbers, or local strength, to constitute a church. When or where Valdo died,
                    remains in obscurity, but his name was given to almost every sect who protested
                    against papal usurpation.</p><p>A happier destiny was reserved for the subalpine Valdenses. They were the
                    inhabitants of a mountain tract of country, where they constituted the majority
                    of the population; and at this hour the remains of them form an established
                    church, and a well known and intelligent religious community in a region of
                    Piedmont.</p><p>The persecutions which, for 200 years, swept Europe of all who were called
                    Valdenses, except in the subalpine territories, were an outrage upon humanity,
                    and have fixed an indelible stigma on the church of Rome. Her offended pride was
                    satisfied with nothing short of death, whenever she could cause it to be
                    inflicted on those who dared to dispute her authority; and Stephen de Borbone
                    relates, without a breath of compunction, that he was present when eighty of
                    Valdo’s sect were condemned to the flames. Albericus the chronicler states the
                    number to have been 182, and speaks of it as a sacrifice of a sweet-smelling
                    savour acceptable to the Lord,—“Holocaustum placabile Domino.” But with all the
                    animosity of the early persecutors of Valdo and his disciples, they have not
                    recorded one well authenticated accusation of immorality against them. It is a
                    singular attestation to the moral and religious character of Valdo, that none of
                    those calumnies, which were afterwards circulated by Roman catholic writers,
                    were advanced against him during his lifetime. The chronicle of Laon briefly
                    mentions his disobedience in preaching without permission, and the ruin and
                    scandal which it occasioned.</p><p>Walter Mapes, who was present at Rome when Valdo appealed to the pope, indulges
                    in a vein of irony against the Valdesii, who wanted to reform the church; he
                    ridiculed them as a parcel of “houseless,”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>"Ydiotas, illiterates, ineptos. Hii certa nusquam babent
                    domicilia, bini et bini circumeunt: nudi pedes, lancis induti, habentes omnia
                    sibi communia tanquam Apostoli, nudi nudum Christum sequentes.” See Gualt. Map.
                    MS. Bodl.</p></note> “bare-footed,” “indigent,” and “illiterate idiots,”
                    unworthy of notice; but utters not a word against their morality. On the
                    contrary, in one of those unguarded expressions, which truth wrings from
                    prejudice, he admitted that they preserved the faith, and were ready to die for
                    the sake of the Lord Jesus Christ.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Sunt certe temporibus nostris licet a nobis damnati et
                    densi, qui fidero servare velint et si ponantur ad rationem ut dudum, ponant
                    animas suas pro pastore suo Domino Jesu." Ibid.</p></note></p><p>The earliest calumniator of “the Poor Men of Lyon,” <hi rend="italic">Alanus
                    insignis theologus,</hi> who inveighed with the utmost severity against them,
                    said nothing worse of their founder, than that he presumed to preach without
                    inspiration or literature, to call himself an apostle without a mission, and a
                    teacher without learning.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Liber secundus Alani insig. Theol. contra Vald. p. 175. edit. Par.
                    1612.</p><p>* Moneta contra Valdenses, lib. v.</p></note></p><p>Moneta,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>· Petri Monachi
                    Hist. Albig.. p. 8. edit. Trever. 1615.</p></note> ’ who wrote a history of the
                    Valdenses of Lyon, within half a century after their first appearance, speaks of
                    a certain man named Valdesius, from whom they derived their origin, without
                    casting any stain upon his moral fame; and though Moneta was an inquisitor, the
                    bosom friend of Dominic, and condemned heretics to the flames, and wrote forty
                    folio pages in defence of persecution, yet he admits that the Valdenses still
                    respected the validity of Romish ordination, received the Old as well as the New
                    Testament, and did not give reins to licentiousness.</p><p>Peter, the monk of Vaux Sernay,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>'The Greek ritualists inform us that the sandal was a mark
                    of sacerdotal dignity. Some very curious mistakes bare occurred from the terms
                    Xabatati and Subatati applied to the followers of Valdo. The term is derived
                    from <hi rend="italic">sabot,</hi> a sandal.</p></note><hi rend="superscript">
                    β</hi> who wrote in 1217, and was clamorous for the total extinction of the
                    Albigenses by fire and sword, mentions the name of <hi rend="italic">Waldius,</hi> the founder of a sect of heretics called <hi rend="italic">Waldenses,</hi> without a syllable of reproach; and states the principal errors
                    of those schismatics to have been “an affected imitation of the apostles,
                    refusal to take an oath, denial of the power of the magistrate to inflict the
                    punishment of death, and presuming, because they were sandal-wearers,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Reinerus de Sectis Antiq.
                    Her. c. 4, 5 <hi rend="italic">.</hi> Bibliotheca Patrum, vol. iv.</p></note> to
                    celebrate the Eucharist without episcopal ordination.”</p><p>Reiner, <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> whose work bears the date of 1250, has no
                    charge to bring against Valdo, and no other against his followers than their
                    separation from, and hostility to, the church of Rome, their use of Scripture in
                    the vulgar tongue, and the estimation in which they held those of their sect who
                    embraced a life of poverty, and believed in justification by faith. We may
                    therefore consider that all the licentious tales which have been told at the
                    expense of Valdo and his disciples, were the invention of after times. That
                    individuals among them may have broached some extravagant and fanatical dogmas,
                    is not improbable; but we have no contemporary evidence in proof of their having
                    departed from the strictest rules of moral and religious purity, or of their
                    having been guilty of any other than the unpardonable offence of disobeying a
                    spiritual authority, which had become as tyrannical in the exercise of its
                    power, as it was remiss in the discharge of the sacred trusts committed to it.
                    “The worst that can be said of them,” said the inquisitor Reiner, whose business
                    it was to accuse and hunt them down, “is, that they detest the Roman church."
                    (<hi rend="smallcaps">d. f.</hi>)</p></div></body></text></TEI>