<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0743-0703-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VOSSIUS, Gerard John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 703</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:993547">Laude</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=743" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VOSSIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gerard John</hi></label>, a
                    writer of great and variegated erudition, was born near Heidelberg in the year
                    1577. His father, John Voss, and his mother, Cornelie de Bie, were both natives
                    of Roermund, a town in the Netherlands. Having embraced the doctrines of the
                    Reformation, he emigrated to the Palatinate, where he studied divinity, and in
                    1575 became a minister in the vicinity of Heidelberg; but on refusing to adopt
                    the Lutheran creed on the subject of the eucharist, he found it advisable to
                    revisit his own country. Here he successively discharged the duties of a pastor
                    in different places. His wife died at Dordrecht in 1584. He afterwards married
                    Anne de Witt, but scarcely survived for three months. His son, who was thus left
                    an orphan, received his early education at Dordrecht, and at the age of
                    eighteen, was sent to the university of Leyden, where he studied Greek under
                    Vulcanius, mathematics under Snell, and other branches of learning under other
                    able professors. At the age of twenty, he published a Latin panegyric on Maurice
                    prince of Nassau. After having taken the degrees of master of arts, and doctor
                    of philosophy, he applied himself to the study of divinity and the Hebrew
                    language under Gomarus and Trelcatius. From his father he inherited a library
                    well stored with books of divinity and ecclesiastical history; and at an early
                    period of his life, he acquired a very extensive knowledge in both
                    departments.</p>
                <p>At the age of twenty-two, he was appointed director of the College of Dordrecht.
                    In 1602 he married Elizabeth Corput, the daughter of a minister. After bearing
                    three children, she died on the 6th of February 1607; and on the 18th of August
                    ensuing, he married Elizabeth du Jon, the daughter of an eminent theologian,
                    better known by his Latinized name of Junius. By this second marriage, he had
                    five sons and two daughters, but he had the misfortune to survive all his
                    children except one son. In 1614 he was appointed director of the Theological
                    College established at Leyden; but in 1618, he relinquished this office for the
                    professorship of eloquence and of chronology. Vossius, whose sentiments were
                    moderate and peaceful, was anxious to shun the theological suite which at that
                    time agitated the Dutch republic. But his <hi rend="italic">Historia
                    Pelagiana,</hi> published in 1618, involved him in some trials and difficulties.
                    In that elaborate work, he discussed the doctrine of predestination and grace in
                    a strain which the Calvinists considered as much too favourable to the tenets of
                    Arminius. In 1620 the synod of Tergou deprived him of his professorship; but
                    another synod, held at Rotterdam in the following year, permitted him to be
                    reinstated, under the condition of his retracting the errors contained in his
                    history, and promising neither to do nor say any thing in opposition to the
                    decrees of the synod of Dordrecht. These he doubtless considered as very hard
                    terras, and for some years he declined to comply with them. In the mean time he
                    was prohibited from teaching either in public or in private; and in one of his
                    letters, he estimates his pecuniary loss at six thousand livres a-year. In 1624
                    he made such concessions or explanations as led to his reinstatement.</p>
                <p>What exposed him to persecution at home, recommended him to favour abroad.
                    Archbishop Laud, a very zealous patron of Arminianism, was so highly satisfied
                    with his work, that he procured him a prebend at Canterbury, which he was
                    permitted to hold as a mere sinecure. He proceeded to England in 1629, and was
                    installed. On paying a visit to Oxford, he was created LL. D. Here he discovered
                    and encouraged the talents of Dr Pocock, who became so eminent as an
                    orientalist. A college or Athenaeum having been founded at Amsterdam, Vossius
                    was appointed professor of history in the year 1633. Here he continued his
                    learned labours till the time of his death, and produced a variety of works,
                    distinguished by the extent and solidity of their erudition. He died on the 19th
                    of March 1649, at the age of seventy-two.</p>
                <p>He was highly esteemed by his contemporaries for his moral worth, as well as for
                    his talents and learning. He was not only an able grammarian and critic, but was
                    likewise skilled in history and theology. He has written treatises on history,
                    poetry, rhetoric, logic, and the mathematical sciences. His work entitled
                    “Aristarchus, sive de Arte Grammatica,” is not only very elaborate, but likewise
                    very able and judicious. An edition of it is now printing at Halle under the
                    superintendence of Förtsch. In this department, we must not overlook his
                    “Etymologico Linguae Latinae,”</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=744"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0744-0704"/>
                <p>and his work “De Vitiis Sermonis.” His “Institutiones Oratoriae,” are also very
                    elaborate. His “Ars Historica,” and his treatises “De Historicis Graecis,” and
                    “De Historicis Latinis,” are valuable specimens of his labours as a professor of
                    history; and the last of them is still held in much estimation. In the nine
                    books “De Idololatria,” he displays the same unlimited research that
                    characterises all his larger works. Of his theological learning he has exhibited
                    no mean specimen in his “Historiae de Controversiis quas Pelagius ejusque
                    Reliquiae moverunt, libri septem.” Of the entire works of Vossius, a great
                    treasure of erudition, a complete collection was published at Amsterdam in 1701,
                    in six volumes folio.</p>
                <p>Vossius had five sons, who were all known by their literary productions. Their
                    names were Dionysius, Francis, Gerard, Matthew, and Isaac. The last was the only
                    one who survived him.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Vossius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Isaac,</hi> the son of this
                    learned and estimable man, was born at Leyden in the year 1618. He was trained
                    under the domestic superintendence of his father, and became one of the most
                    learned men of his own age. In 1639, when he had only reached his twenty-first
                    year, he distinguished himself by an edition of the Periplus of Scylax. In 1642
                    he made a journey to Italy, and visited Rome. He became one of the literary
                    correspondents of the queen of Sweden, and, like some other scholars of
                    eminence, was invited to her court. It appears from his letters, that he was at
                    Stockholm in 1649, 1650, and 1651. His misunderstanding with Salmasius however
                    exposed him to the queen’s displeasure; and in 1652, when he returned from
                    Holland, accompanied by Bochart and Huet, he was not admitted to her presence.
                    But she soon renewed her correspondence with Vossius, and saw him during her
                    visit to Holland. On the death of his father, he was offered the professorship
                    of history at Amsterdam; but he preferred a life of studious retirement, and he
                    appears to have been sufficiently independent to follow the bent of his own
                    inclination. In 1663 he received a handsome present from Louis the Fourteenth.
                    In 1670 he came to England; and having visited Oxford during the same year, he
                    was created LL. D., and, as Wood states, was “with great humanity and friendship
                    entertained by some of the chief heads of houses, as his father had been before
                    in 1629.” He had now acquired a high reputation; and in 1673 the king bestowed
                    upon him a canonry of Windsor. Both he and his father must have held their
                    preferments as lay-sinecures. He died in Windsor Castle on the 10th of February
                    1689, in the seventy-first year of his age. On his death-bed, he was visited by
                    the dean of Windsor and one of the canons, who urged him, but in vain, to take
                    the sacrament. “Dr Vossius, if you will not do it for the love of God, at least
                    do it for the honour of the chapter.” This appeal was ineffectual; and to one of
                    the dean’s pious admonitions, he replied, “I wish you would instruct me how to
                    oblige the farmers to pay me what they owe me: that is what I would have you to
                    do for me at present.” King Charles sometimes observed, that there was nothing
                    which he refused to believe, except the Bible. Some of his works indeed display
                    sufficient credulity. Of this we find abundant evidence in his “Variarum
                    Observationum liber,” in which he avers that ancient Rome was twenty times as
                    large as Paris and London together, and estimates its population at fourteen
                    millions. Of the population of China, he has given an account still more
                    extravagant. His judgment is on most occasions greatly inferior to his learning,
                    and the spirit of paradox very seldom deserts him. In his usual strain, he wrote
                    various tracts on the Septuagint, and was opposed by Father Simon and Dr Hody.
                    On the age of the world he maintained with Hornius a controversy which involved
                    the chronology of this version. Another curious work he published, “De
                    Sibyllinis aliisque quae Christi natalem praecessere Oraculis.” Oxon. 1680, 8vo.
                    This is the second edition. One of his most able and pleasing works is entitled
                    “De Poematum Cantu, et Viribus Rythmi.” Oxon. 1683, 8vo. Among other ancient
                    authors, he published editions of Catullus and Pomponius Mela, which, if he had
                    produced no original work, would have been sufficient to recommend him to the
                    notice of posterity as a man of uncommon erudition. (x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
