<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0600-0562-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VARRO, Marcus Terentius</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 562</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:902475">Editors</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=600" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VARRO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marcus Terentius</hi></label>, a
                    very learned and very miscellaneous writer, was born at Rome about the year
                    116</p>
                <p>before the Christian era. He received what was then considered as the best
                    education that could be obtained. Having studied at Rome under Stilo, he
                    proceeded to Athens, and became the disciple of Antiochus, an Academic
                    philosopher. Returning to his native city, he began to take some share in the
                    business of the forum, but he does not appear to have acquired much reputation
                    as an orator. He successively filled the office of triumvir, and tribune of the
                    people. When he was about forty-nine years of age, Pompey entrusted him with the
                    command of a Greek fleet, employed in the war against the pirates. In a naval
                    engagement which took place near the coast of Cilicia, he acquitted himself with
                    so much courage, that he was the first that boarded one of the enemy’s ships;
                    and in honour of this exploit, Pompey presented him with a rostral crown. For
                    some time he acted as governor of Cilicia, apparently by virtue of an
                    extraordinary appointment.</p>
                <p>During the civil war which ensued, Varro adhered to Pompey, and was employed as
                    his lieutenant in farther Spain. He was however advanced in years, and,
                    according to Caesar’s account, was disposed to follow the turns of fortune. The
                    affairs of his own party having assumed a more promising aspect, he pursued
                    measures of greater decision; and having embodied two legions, with thirty
                    irregular cohorts, he made vigorous preparations for defending the province, but
                    the speedy approach of Caesar rendered all his plans abortive. One of his
                    legions revolted, and the inhabitants evinced no disposition to make the quarrel
                    their own. Varro now adopted the resolution of marching towards Italy; but
                    finding that this attempt was impracticable, he offered to deliver the remaining
                    legion to any one whom the victorious general should nominate. Having
                    accordingly delivered it to Sextus Caesar, he presented himself to Julius Caesar
                    at Corduba, and made a surrender of all his treasure, ships, and stores. After
                    this unfortunate termination of his military services, he appears to have
                    devoted himself with great ardour and perseverance to the pursuits of
                    literature; and, as his life was extended beyond the usual term, he produced a
                    great number of works, and on a great variety of subjects. He cultivated a
                    particular intimacy with Cicero, who inscribed to him his Academica, as he
                    inscribed to Cicero a portion of his treatise “De Lingua Latina.”</p>
                <p>When Caesar returned to Rome after having subdued all his enemies, Varro
                    entertained some apprehension for his personal safety, and thought it prudent to
                    withdraw from the city; but his fears were soon removed, and their hostility was
                    at length converted into friendship. Caesar committed to him the charge of
                    forming and superintending a public library; a charge for which he was eminently
                    qualified by his very extensive and variegated learning. After the death of this
                    ruler of the world, he was again exposed to danger: he was included in the same
                    proscription which proved fatal to his friend Cicero; but, even on this
                    occasion, his good fortune did not desert him. His wealth, as well as his
                    political connexions, must have contributed to mark him for destruction. He was
                    sheltered and concealed by Calenus, and his name was at length erased from the
                    list of the proscribed. He was the possessor of several villas; and in the mean
                    time one of these had been seized and plundered by Antony. The loss of his
                    valuable library, including some of his own writings, was one of the
                    contingencies to which he was exposed at this unhappy crisis. He however
                    survived for many years, and continued his studies with unabated ardour. At the
                    age of seventy-eight, as we learn from Aulus Gellius, he had composed 490 books.
                    According to Pliny, he still continued to write at the age of eighty-eight. His
                    death is referred to the year 27 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.;</hi> and, according
                    to the computation from this date and the supposed date of his birth, he must
                    have attained the age of eighty-nine. It is not however improbable<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=601" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0601-0563"/>
                    that he may have exceeded this age by a few years.</p>
                <p>Varro has very frequently been described as the most learned of the Romans; and
                    it has already been stated that he wrote on an immense variety of subjects.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Fabricii Bibliotheca
                    Latina, tom i. p. 124-132 edit. Ernesti, where very many of his lost works are
                    enumerated.</p></note> His works were partly in prose, and partly in verse. One
                    of them, a Menippean satire, consisted of an intermixture of verse with prose,
                    of Greek with Latin.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Casauboni de Satyrica Graecorum Poesi et Romanorum Satira libri duo, p. 258.
                    Paris. 1606, 8vo.</p></note> Some of them related to grammar and rhetoric,
                    others to history and philosophy, others again to politics and theology. He
                    seems indeed to have embraced almost every topic of human speculation. But of
                    all these treasures of ancient learning. It is deeply to be regretted that only
                    a very inconsiderable remnant has escaped the ravages of time. Of his
                    twenty-four books “De Lingua Latina,” the first three have all perished except a
                    few inconsiderable fragments. The fourth, fifth, and sixth, relating to the
                    origin of Latin words, and inscribed to Cicero, and the seventh, eighth, and
                    ninth, relating to the analogy of the language, are however preserved, though
                    not without some mutilations. Of the other books, scarcely a vestige remains.
                    Even in this mutilated state, the work is both curious and valuable. His editor
                    Scaliger has however shewn that his etymologies are not unfrequently erroneous;
                    and another very learned critic, Salmasius, has remarked that his reluctance to
                    admit Greek derivations often leads him very far astray.</p>
                <p>His three books “De Re Rustica,” have reached us in a better condition. It
                    appears from the exordium, that he undertook the composition of this work at the
                    age of eighty; and that his wife Fundania, to whom it is addressed, had
                    purchased a demesne which she wished him to manage in the most advantageous
                    manner. Some inconsiderable fragments of his other works, in prose and verse,
                    have been preserved, and have been collected with due care.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>His poetical fragments were very laboriously
                    collected by R. Stephanus, Fragmenta Poetanim Veterum Latinorum, quorum Opera
                    non extant, p. 305-364. Excudebat H. Stephanus, 1564, 8vo. These fragments were
                    collected by the father, and digested by the son.</p></note></p>
                <p>Of the work “De Lingua Latina,” an edition, considered as the first, is in
                    quarto, without place or date, but supposed to have been printed at Rome by G.
                    Lauer, about the year 1471. The editor was Pomponius Laetus. There arc other
                    three very early editions, likewise without dates, but conjectured to have been
                    printed, the first at Venice about 1472, the second in the same city in 1474,
                    and the third at Rome about the same time. The first two are in quarto, the
                    third is in folio. After this period, the work was inserted in various
                    collections of the Latin grammarians. Several editions of it bear the name of
                    Michael Bentinus. One of them is that of Paris, 1530, 8vo. This edition likewise
                    contains the spurious <hi rend="italic">Origines</hi> ascribed to Cato. An
                    edition was publised by Antonius Augustinus, afterwards archbishop of Tarragona,
                    Romae, 1554, 8vo. The same edition, which contains marginal emendations, but no
                    commentary, is generally to be found with the date of 1557, and it then includes
                    several additions; at the beginning of the volume, “Dubia et Varia,” “Doctorum
                    Virorum Nomina qui hujus libri emendationi operam dederunt,” and more than two
                    pages of <hi rend="italic">Emendata;</hi> and at the end, seventy-two unnumbered
                    leaves, occupied with various indices. This edition of Varro was reprinted among
                    the works of the editor, Augustini Opera, tom. vii. p. 425-524. The next edition
                    was that of Vertranius Maurus, Lugd. 1563, 8vo. It was followed by the very
                    elaborate and valuable edition of Joseph Scaliger, Paris. 1565, 8vo. And soon
                    afterwards appeared “Adriani Turnebi Commentarii et Emendationes in libros
                    Varronis de Lingua Latina.” Paris. 1566, 8vo. This was a posthumous work, and
                    laboured under the usual disadvantages of such publications. Here we must not
                    overlook another learned labour, “Ad M. Ter. Varronis Assertiones Analogiae
                    Sermonis Latini, Appendix Henrici Stephani.” Exc. H. Stephanus, 1591, 8vo. An
                    edition of Varro’s work was published by Scioppius, Ingo1stadii, 1605, 8vo.
                    Another separate edition appeared after a very long interval, Biponti, 1788, 2
                    tom. 8vo. This very useful edition, which also includes the fragments of Varro’s
                    works, is illustrated with the notes of Augustinus, Tumebus, Scaliger, and
                    Popma. It was followed by the critical edition of L. Spengel, Berolini, 1826,
                    8vo∙ And last of all appeared “M. Terentii Varronis de Lingua Latina librorum
                    quae supersunt, emendata et annotata a Carolo Odofredo Muellero.” Lipsiae, 1833,
                    8vo. This is an edition of no small value; and we add, with much regret, that
                    the editor has been prematurely arrested in the midst of a very distinguished
                    career. He died at Athens on the first of August 1840.</p>
                <p>Varro’s treatise “De Re Rustica” has been printed in the numerous editions of the
                    “Scriptores Rei Rusticae.” the earliest edition of this collection is supposed
                    to be that printed by Jenson, Venet. 1472, fol. Two editions issued from the
                    Aldine press in 1514 and 1533. A critical edition was published by Victorins,
                    Lugd. 1541-2. It consists of four parts; of which the first three contain the
                    text of the different writers, and the fourth, dated in 1542, bears the title of
                    “Petri Victorii Explicationes suarum in Catonem, Varronem, Columellam
                    Castigationum.” This part, consisting of 144 pages, is sometimes to be found as
                    a separate publication. And here we must likewise notice a learned work of
                    Fulvius Ursinus, “Notae ad M. Catonem, M. Varronem, L. Columellam de Re
                    Rustica.” Romae, 1587, 8vo. For a very elaborate and valuable edition of the
                    “Scriptores Rei Rusticae,” we are indebted to Gesner, Lipsiae, 1735, 2 tom. 4to.
                    Lips. 1773-4, 2 tom. 4to. And another edition, described as the best, was more
                    recently published by Schneider, Lips. 1794-7, 4 tom. 8vo. Of Varro’s treatise
                    on agriculture, an English translation was published by the Rev. T. Owen, Lond.
                    1800, 8vo.</p>
                <p>Of both works of Varro there are several editions, and the earliest is that of
                    Scaliger. Exc. H. Stephanus, 1569, 8vo. It was reprinted at Paris in 1573, 1581,
                    and 1585. A collective edition of these two works, and the fragments of his
                    other works, was published by Ausonius Popma, Lugd. Bat. 1601, 8vo. the same
                    editor had previously made a collection of the Fragmenta, Franequerae, 1589,
                    8vo. Another edition of all his works was published not long afterwards,
                    Durdrechti, 1619, 8vo. Some copies of the same edition exhibit the imprint of
                    Amsterdam, 1623. (x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
