<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0578-0545-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRANBERRY (9th edition, volume 6, page 545)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1802520">Pears</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056048">Pear</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204928">California</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n578/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRANBERRY</label>, the fruit of plants of the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Oxycoccus,</hi> natural order <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vacciniaceae.</hi><hi rend="italic">0.</hi><hi rend="italic">palustris,</hi>
                    the common cranberry plant, is found in marshy land in northern and central
                    Europe and North America. Its stems are wiry, creeping, and of varying length;
                    the leaves are evergreen, dark and shining above, glaucous below, revolute at
                    the margin, ovate, lanceolate, or elliptical in shape, and not more than half an
                    inch long; the flowers, which appear in May or June, are small and pedunculate,
                    and have a four-lobed, rose-tinted corolla, purplish filaments, and anther-cells
                    forming two long tubes; the berries ripen in August and September; they are
                    pear-shaped and about the size of currants, are crimson in colour, and often
                    spotted, and have an acid and astringent taste. The American species, <hi
                    rend="italic">0.</hi><hi rend="italic">macrocarpus,</hi> is found wild from
                    Maine to the Carolinas. It attains a greater size than <hi rend="italic"
                    >0.</hi><hi rend="italic">palustris,</hi> and bears bigger anâ finer berries,
                    which are of three principal sorts, the <hi rend="italic">cherry</hi> or round,
                    the <hi rend="italic">bugle</hi> or oblong, and the <hi rend="italic">pear</hi>
                    or bell-shaped, and vary in hue from light pink to dark purple, or may be
                    mottled red and white. It was first cultivated in England for the sake of its
                    fruit by Sir Joseph Banks. <hi rend="italic">0.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >erectus</hi> is a species indigenous to Virginia and California, and is
                    remarkable for the excellent flavour of its berry.</p>
                <p>Air and moisture are the chief requisites for the thriving of the cranberry
                    plant. It is cultivated in America on a soil of peat or vegetable mould, free
                    from loam and clay, and cleared of turf, and having a surface layer of clean
                    sand. The sand, which needs renewal every two or three years, is necessary for
                    the vigorous existence of the plants, and serves both to keep the underlying
                    soil cool and damp, and to check the growth of grass and weeds. The ground must
                    be thoroughly drained, and should be provided with a supply of water and a dam
                    for flooding the plants during winter to protect them from frost, and
                    occasionally at other seasons to destroy insect pests; but the use of
                    springwater should be avoided. The flavour of the fruit is found to be improved
                    by growing the plants in a soil enriched with well-rotted dung, and by supplying
                    them with less moisture than they obtain in their natural habitats. Propagation
                    is effected by means of cuttings, of which the wood should be wiry in texture,
                    and the leaves of a greenish - brown colour. In America, where, in the. vicinity
                    of Cape Cod, Massachusetts, the cultivation of the cranberry commenced early in
                    the present century, wide tracts of waste land have been utilized for that
                    purpose,—low, easily flooded, marshy ground, worth originally not more than from
                    $10 to $20 an acre, having been made to yield annually $200 or $300 worth of the
                    fruit per acre. The yield varies between 50 and 400 bushels an acre, but 100
                    bushels, or about 35 barrels, is estimated to be the average production when the
                    plants have begun to bear well. In .1871 there were in New* Jersey about 2000
                    acres in fruiting, which in the previous year had produced 150,000 bushels of
                    cranberries, and 4000 acres more had been prepared and planted. A total of
                    75,000 barrels was obtained in 1869 in the States and Territories of America.
                    Cranberries should be gathered when ripe and dry, otherwise they do not keep
                    well. The darkest-coloured berries are those which are most esteemed. The
                    picking of the fruit begins in New Jersey in October, at the close of the
                    blackberry and whortleberry season, and often lasts until the coming in of cold
                    weather. From 3 to 4 bushels a day may be collected by good workers. New York,
                    Philadelphia, Boston, and Baltimore are tho leading American markets for
                    cranberries, whence they arc exported to the West Indies, England, and France in
                    great <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n579/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0579-0546"/> quantities. England was formerly supplied by
                    Lincolnshire and Norfolk with abundance of the common cranberry, which it now
                    largely imports from Sweden and Russia. The fruit is much used for pies and
                    tarts, and also for making an acid summer beverage. The Mount Ida berry,
                    cowberry, or red whortleberry, <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium Vitis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">idaea,</hi> is sometimes sold for the cranberry. The Tasmanian and
                    the Australian cranberries are the produce respectively of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Λstroloma lιumifusum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lissantlιe saρida,</hi> plants
                    of the order <hi rend="italic">Epacridaceae.</hi></p>
                <p>See Trowbridge, <hi rend="italic">The Cranberry Culturist,</hi> Newhaven, U.S.,
                    1869; <hi rend="italic">Report of the. Commissioner of Agriculture for</hi>
                    1869, Washington, 1870; <hi rend="italic">Report of the American Institute of
                    New York for</hi> 1869-70, Albany, 1870.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
