<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0435-0406-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CORMENIN (9th edition, volume 6, page 406)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mn08">Jurists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717p75">Prizes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m3b">Moralities</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k55d">Morals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1077716">Prizes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026097">Moralities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026093">Morale</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n435/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CORMENIN</label>, Louis <hi rend="smallcaps">Marie de la
                    Haye, Viscount de</hi> (1788-1868), a French jurist and political pamphleteer,
                    was born at Paris, January 6, 1788. His father and his grandfather both held the
                    rank of lieutenant-general of the admiralty. In consequence of the suppression
                    of the colleges he received his early education at a private school at Paris,
                    and afterwards studied in the school of law. At the age of twenty he was
                    received advocate, and about the same time he gained some reputation as a writer
                    of piquant and delicate poems. In 1810 he received from Napoleon I. the
                    appointment of auditor to the council of state; and after the restoration of the
                    Bourbons he became master of requests. During the period of his connection with
                    the council he devoted himself zealously to the study of administrative law, and
                    acquired those stores of exact knowledge which afterwards furnished the material
                    for his principal work as a jurist. He was selected to prepare <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n436/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0436-0407"/> some of the most important reports of the
                    council. Among his separate publications at this time are noted,— <hi
                    rend="italic">Du</hi><hi rend="italic">Conseil d’Etat</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >envisage coìnme</hi><hi rend="italic">conseil et comme juridiction dans notre
                    monarchie constitutionelle</hi> (1818), and <hi rend="italic">De la
                    responsabilité des agents du gouvernement.</hi> In the former he claimed, for
                    the protection of the rights of private persons in the administration of
                    justice, the institution of a special court whose members should be irremovable,
                    the right of oral defence, and publicity of trial. In 1822 appeared his <hi
                    rend="italic">Questions de droit</hi><hi rend="italic">administratif,</hi> in
                    which he for the first time brought together and gave scientific shape to the
                    scattered elements of administrative law. These he arranged and stated clearly
                    in the form of aphorisms, with logical deductions, establishing them by proofs
                    drawn from the archives of the council of state. This is recognized as his most
                    important work as a jurist, and has become the chief authority on its subject.
                    It has passed through five editions, the fifth, which was published in 1840,
                    being thoroughly revised. In 1828 Cormenin entered the Chamber of Deputies as
                    member for Orleans, took his seat in the Left Centre, and began a vigorous
                    opposition to the Government of Charles X. As he was not gifted with the
                    qualifications of the orator, he seldom appeared at. the tribune; but in the
                    various committees he defended all forms of popular liberties, and at the same
                    time delivered, in a series of powerful pamphlets, under the pseudonym of
                    “Timon,” the most formidable blows against tyranny and all political and
                    administrative abuses. The ministerialists named him “Γ homme du contentieux.”
                    After the revolution of July 1830, Cormenin was one of the 221 who signed the
                    protest against the elevation of the Orleans dynasty to the throne; and he
                    resigned both his office in the council of state and his seat in the chamber. He
                    was, however, soon re-elected deputy, and now voted with the extreme Left. The
                    discussions on the budget in 1831 gave rise to the publication of his famous
                    series of <hi rend="italic">Lettres sur la liste civile,</hi> which in ten years
                    ran through twenty-five editions. In the following year he had the distinction
                    of being elected by four arrondissements; he took his seat for Belley. In 1834
                    he was elected by two arrondissements, and sat for Joigny, which he represented
                    till 1846, In this year he lost his seat in consequence of the popular prejudice
                    aroused against him by his trenchant pamphlet <hi rend="italic">Oui et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">non</hi> (1845) against attacks on religious liberty, and a second
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Feu! Feu!</hi> (1846), written in reply to those who
                    demanded a retractation of the former. In this he re-asserted his principles
                    still more relentlessly. Sixty thousand copies were rapidly sold. One inevitable
                    penalty which he had to suffer for these incisive manifestoes was exclusion from
                    the French Academy and the Academy of Moral and Political Sciences. Cormenin was
                    an earnest advocate of universal suffrage before the revolution of February
                    1848, and had remorselessly exposed the corrupt practices at elections in his
                    pamphlet— <hi rend="italic">Ordre du jour sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la
                    corruption</hi><hi rend="italic">électorale.</hi> After the revolution he was
                    elected by four departments to the constituent assembly, and became one of its
                    vice-presidents. He was also member and president of the constitutional
                    commission, and for some time took a leading part in drawing up the republican
                    constitution. But the disputes which broke out among the members led him to
                    resign the presidency. He was soon after named member of the council of state
                    and president of the <hi rend="italic">comité du contentieux,</hi> It was at
                    this period that he published two pamphlets— <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">V independence</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >V</hi><hi rend="italic">Italie.</hi> After the <hi rend="italic">coup
                    dfétat</hi> of December 2, 1851, Cormenin, who had undertaken the defence of
                    Prince Louis Napoleon after his attempt at Strasburg, accepted a place in the
                    new council of state of the empire. Four years later, by imperial ordinance, he
                    was made a member of the Institute. One of the most characteristic works of
                    Cormenin, not yet mentioned is the <hi rend="italic">Livre des orateurs,</hi> a
                    series of brilliant studies of the principal parliamentary orators of the
                    restoration and the monarchy of July, the first edition of which appeared in
                    1838, and the eighteenth in 1860. In 1846 he published his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Entretiens</hi><hi rend="italic">de village,</hi> which procured him the
                    Montyon prize, and of which six editions were called for the same year. His last
                    work was <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">droit de tonnage</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">en Algérie</hi> (1860). Cormenin was distinguished also as a
                    practical philanthropist, and is said to have established more charitable
                    institutions than any layman of his time in France. He was admitted to the
                    Legion of Honour in 1821, and was promoted commander in 1865. He died at Paris,
                    May 6, 1868.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
