<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0717-0684-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CUCA, or Coca (9th edition, volume 6, page 684)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205549">Bolivia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205578">Ecuador</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205916">Colombia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kf6q">Coca</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0659q">Endowments</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058953">Peruvians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:909854">Endowments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865972">Coca</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155558">Travel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355164">Travels</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n717/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CUCA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Coca</hi></label><hi
                    rend="italic">(Erythroxylon Coca),</hi> is a plant of the natural order <hi
                    rend="italic">Erylhroxylaceae,</hi> the leaves of which are used as a
                    masticatory in the western countries of South America. <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi> It resembles a blackthorn bush, and grows .to a height of 6 or 8 feet.
                    The branches are straight, and the leaves, which have a lively green tint, are
                    thin, opaque, oval, tapering at the extremities, and similar to tea-leaves; on
                    each side of the strong mid-rib is a longitudinal vein. Good samples of the
                    dried leaves are uncurled, are of a deep green on the upper, and a grey-green on
                    the lower surface, and have a strong tea-like odour; when chewed they produce a
                    sense of warmth in the mouth, and have a pleasant, pungent taste. Bad specimens
                    have a camphora-ceons smell and a brownish colour, and lack the pungent taste.
                    The flowers are small, and disposed in little clusters on short stalks; the
                    corolla is composed of five yellowish-white petals, the anthers are
                    heart-shaped, and the pistils are three in number. The flowers are succeeded by
                    red berries. The seeds are sown in December and January in small plots <hi
                    rend="italic">(almacigas)</hi> sheltered from the sun, and the young plants when
                    from l¾ to 2 feet in height are placed in holes <hi rend="italic">(aaepî),</hi>
                    or, if the ground is level, in furrows <hi rend="italic">(uachos)</hi> in
                    carefully-weeded soil. The plants thrive best in hot, damp situations, such as
                    the clearings of forests; but the leaves most preferred are obtained in drier
                    localities, on the sides of hills. The leaves are gathered from plants varying
                    in age from one and a half to upwards of forty years. They are considered ready
                    for plucking when they break on being bent. The first and most abundant harvest
                    is in March, after the rains; the second is at the end of June, the third in
                    October or November. The green leaves <hi rend="italic">(matu)</hi> are spread
                    in thin layers on coarse woollen cloths and dried in the sun; they are then
                    packed in sacks, which, in order to preserve the quality of the leaves, must be
                    kept from damp.</p>
                <p>It has been estimated that cuca is used by about 8,000,000 of the human race,
                    being consumed in Bolivia, Peru, Ecuador, Colombia, and Rio Negro. In Peru the
                    Indians carry a leathern pouch (the <hi rend="italic">chuspa,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">huallqui)</hi> for the leaves, and a supply of pulverized unslaked
                    lime, or a preparation of the ashes of the quinoa plant <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Chenopodium quinoa),</hi> called <hi rend="italic">lliρta</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">llucta.</hi> Three or four times a day labour is suspended for <hi
                    rend="italic">chacchar</hi> or <hi rend="italic">acullicar,</hi> as the
                    mastication of cuca is termed. The leaves, deprived of their stalks, are chewed
                    and formed into a ball <hi rend="italic">(acullico)</hi> in the mouth; a small
                    quantity of the lime or llipta is then applied to the acullico to give it a
                    proper relish. Two or three ounces of cuca are thus daily consumed by each
                    Indian.</p>
                <p>Cuca is a powerful stimulant of the nervous system; it enables fatigue to be
                    borne with less nourishment and greater ease than ordinarily, and diminishes the
                    difficulty of breathing in ascending mountains; when used externally it is said
                    to be a remedy for rheumatism and headache.</p>
                <p>The poet Cowley represents the Indian “Pachamma” as addressing Venus thus :—</p>
                <p>“Our <hi rend="italic">Varicocha</hi> first this <hi rend="italic">Coca</hi>
                    sent,</p>
                <p>Endow’d with Leaves of wondrous Nourishment, Whose Juice succ’d in, and to the
                    Stomach tak’n Long Hunger and long Labour can sustain;</p>
                <p>From which our faint and weary Bodies find More Succour, more they chear the
                    drooping Mind, Than can your <hi rend="italic">Bacchus</hi> and your <hi
                    rend="italic">Ceres</hi> join’d.</p>
                <p>Three Leaves supply for six days march afford The <hi rend="italic">Quitoita</hi>
                    with this Provision stor’d Can pass the vast and cloudy <hi rend="italic"
                    >Andes</hi> o’er.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">(Plants,</hi> bk. v. p. 121, <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> 9th
                    ed. Lond. 1700.</p>
                <p>Dr Pöppig <hi rend="italic">(Travels in Chili and Peru)</hi> considers the habit
                    of cuca-chewing to be as dangerous to the health as opium-eating, and in the
                    highest degree pernicious, and Mr J. A. Lloyd alludes to cuca as a “poisonous
                    narcotic” <hi rend="italic">(&lt;7ourn.</hi><hi rend="italic">R. Geog.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Soc.,</hi> 1854, p. 260). It does not, however, appear from the
                    writings of Garcilasso that he observed any ill results among the Peruvian
                    Indians from the practice of cuca-chewing. Von Tschudi refers to numerous
                    instances of their longevity and good health, notwithstanding the habit, almost
                    from boyhood, of masticating cuca three times a day. Markham regards cuca as the
                    least injurious, and the most soothing and invigorating of all the narcotics
                    used by man; and Dr Archibald Smith <hi rend="italic">(Peru as it is,</hi>
                    London, 1839) states that cuca when fresh and good, and used in moderate
                    quantity, increases nervous energy, removes drowsiness, enlivens the spirits,
                    and enables the Indian to bear cold, wet, great bodily exertion, and even want
                    of food, to a surprising degree, with apparent ease and impunity. Though it is
                    said, if taken to excess, to <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> Garcilasso de la
                    Vega, writing of the plant, says that it is called <hi rend="italic">cuca</hi>
                    by the Indians, <hi rend="italic">coca</hi> by the Spaniards; and Father Blas
                    Valera states that the leaves are called <hi rend="italic">cuca</hi> both by
                    Indians and Spaniards. <hi rend="italic">(The Royal Commentaries of the
                    Yncas,</hi> 1609-1617; trans, by C. R. Markham, Hakluyt Soc., 1871). See also,
                    on the name <hi rend="italic">cuca,</hi> Christison, <hi rend="italic">Brit.
                    Med. Journ.,</hi> April 29, 1876, p. 527.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n718/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0718-0685"/>
                <p>occasion tremor in the limbs, and even a gloomy sort of mania, such dire effects,
                    he considers, must be of rare occurrence, since, after living for years in
                    constant intercourse with persons accustomed to frequent cuca plantations, and
                    with Indian yanacones or labourers, all of whom, whether old or young,
                    masticated the favourite leaf, he never witnessed a single instance in which the
                    chewer was affected with mania or tremor.</p>
                <p>Cuca was used by the Peruvian Indians in the most ancient times. It was employed
                    as an offering to the sun, or to produce smoke at the great sacrifices; and the
                    priests, it was believed, must chew it during the performance of religious
                    ceremonies, otherwise the gods would not be propitiated. Cuca is still held in
                    superstitious veneration among the Peruvians, and is believed by the miners of
                    Cerro de Pasco to soften the veins of ore, if masticated and thrown upon
                    them.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cocaine,</hi> the alkaloid to which cuca owes its special
                    properties, was discovered by Niemann in 1859. Tlιe formula assigned to it is
                    Ci6H <hi rend="subscript"> 19</hi> NO4, or C1 <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 21</hi> NO4 (Lossen). It is highly poisonous, and its
                    physiological action is apparently identical with that of theine, caffeine,
                    guaraninè, and theobromine, which all, as has been shown by Dr A. Bennet,
                    “induce a series of symptoms affecting the nervous, respiratory, circulatory,
                    vaso motor, and glandular systems” <hi rend="italic">(Edin. Med.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Journ.,</hi> October 1873, p. 323).</p>
                <p>Tachudi, <hi rend="italic">Travels in Peru, fee.,</hi> 1838-42 (Lond. 1847); C.
                    R. Markham, <hi rend="italic">Travels in Peru and India,</hi> p. 232 (Lond.
                    1862).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
