<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0750-0715-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CURRANTS (9th edition, volume 6, page 715)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8br7m">Grape</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3kb0r">Vines</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c40">Shooting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885315">Currants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946524">Grapes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116836">Shooting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n750/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CURRANTS</label>, the dried seedless fruit of a variety of
                    the grape-vine, <hi rend="italic">Vitis vinifera,</hi> cultivated principally in
                    Zante, Cephalonia, and Ithaca, and near Patras, in the Morea. Currants were
                    brought originally from Corinth, whence their name; in the 13th and 14th
                    centuries they were known as <hi rend="italic">raisins de Corauntz.</hi> In the
                    Ionian Islands the currant-vine is grown on the sides of the lower hills, or in
                    the valleys, the grape-vine occupying the higher and less open and rich ground.
                    Gypseous marls, or calcareous marls containing a little gypsum, are preferred to
                    limestone soils, as they allow of the deep penetration of the roots of the
                    vines. The most favourable situations are those where a good supply of water can
                    be obtained for the irrigation of the plantations. This is carried on from the
                    end of October to the close of the year, after which all that is necessary is to
                    keep the ground moist. The vines are planted in rows 3 or 4 feet apart.
                    Propagation is effected by grafting on stocks of the grape-vine, or by planting
                    out in spring the young vigorous shoots obtained at the end of the previous year
                    from old currant-vines that have been cut away below the ground. The grafts bear
                    fruit in three years, the slips in about double that time. The vine-stock for
                    grafting is cut down to the depth of a foot below the surface of the soil; two
                    or three perpendicular incisions are made near the bark with a chisel; and into
                    these are inserted shoots of the last year’s growth. The engrafted part then
                    receives an application of moist marl, is wrapped in leaves and bound with
                    rushes, and is covered with earth, two or three eyes of the shoots being left
                    projecting above ground. In December the currant plantations are cleared of dead
                    and weak wood. In February the branches are cut back, and pruned of median
                    shoots, which are said to prevent tho lateral ones proceeding from the same bud
                    from bearing fruit. In order effectually to water the trees, the earth round
                    about them is in February and March hoed up so as to leave them in a kind of
                    basin, or is piled up against their stems. In May, when the leaves begin to
                    show, the ground is thoroughly turned, and if requisite manured, and is then
                    re-levelled. By the middle of April the leaves are fully out, and in June it is
                    necessary to break back the newly-formed shoots. The fruit begins to ripen in
                    July, and in the next month the vintage takes place. At this season rain is
                    greatly dreaded, as it always damages and may even destroy the ripe fruit. The
                    plantations, Which are commonly much exposed, are watched by dogs aħd armed men.
                    In Cephalonia the currant-grape is said to ripen at least a week earlier than in
                    Zante. To destroy the oïdium, a pest that severely injures the plantations, the
                    vines are dusted, at the time the fruit is maturing, with finely-ground brr
                    ιstone. The currants when sufficiently ripe are gathered and placed on a drying
                    ground, where they are exposed to the sun in layers half an inch thick; from
                    time to time they are turned and swept into heaps, until they become entirely
                    detached from stalk. They are then packed in large butts for exportation. The
                    wine made from the currant-grape is inferior in quality, but is said to be
                    capable of much improvement. The fresh fruit is luscious and highly flavoured,
                    but soon cloys the palate. In 1834 the duty on currants was made 22s. 2d. per
                    cwt., or one-half what it had previously been; in 1844 it was reduced to 15s.,
                    and in 1860 to 7s. per cwt. In 1874 the imports of currants into the United
                    Kingdom were :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Cwts.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Vaine.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>From Austrian territories..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 6978</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>£ 8,606</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Greece</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...963,358</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,278,974</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, other countries</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 2,119</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,994</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Total . ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...972,455</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>£1,290,574</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The currants of British kitchen-gardens are the produce of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ribes nigrum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">R.</hi><hi rend="italic">rubrum,</hi>
                    deciduous shrubs of the natural order <hi rend="italic">Grossulariaceae,</hi>
                    indigenous to Britain, Northern and Central Europe, Siberia, and Canada The
                    former species bears the black, the latter the red currant. White currants are
                    the fruit of <hi rend="italic">R. album,</hi> a cultivated variety of <hi
                    rend="italic">R. rubrum.</hi> Both red and black currants are used for making
                    tarts and pies, jams, jellies, and wine; the latter are also employed
                    medicinally in lozenges, and in the preparation of a gargle for sore throat, are
                    occasionally preserved in spirits, and in Russia are fermented with honey to
                    produce a strong liquor. The leaves as well as the roots of the black currant
                    have been recommended for their therapeutic virtues. A kind of black currant,
                    bearing poor and acid fruit, is indigenous to Tierra del Fuego. Royle mentions
                    three Himalayan species of currants; their fruit he found to contain less
                    saccharine matter than that of their cultivated European congeners</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
