<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0749-0714-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CURRAN, John Philpot (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    714)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100776">Rowan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n749/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CURRAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Philpot</hi></label>
                    (1750—1817), Master of the Rolls in Ireland, and one of the most brilliant wits
                    and orators of his day, was born on the 24th July 1750, at Newmarket, Cork,
                    where his father, a descendant of one of Cromwell’s soldiers, was seneschal to
                    the manor-court. Pleased with his bright boyish vivacity and wit, the rector of
                    his native place, the Rev. Nathaniel Boyse, first gave him lessons and then sent
                    him to school at Middleton. At the age of nineteen he became a sizar of Trinity
                    College, Dublin; and in 1773, having taken his M.A. degree, he entered the
                    Middle Temple. During his residence in London he gave some little attention to
                    the study of law, but gained far more by his assiduous attendance at the
                    students’ debating societies. In 1774 he married a lady who brought him a small
                    dowry; but the marriage proved most unhappy, not without fault on the part of
                    Curran, and Mrs Curran finally eloped from her husband.</p>
                <p>In 1775 Curran was called to the Irish bar, where he very soon obtained a
                    practice. On his first rising in court, excessive nervousness prevented him from
                    even reading distinctly the few words of a legal form, and when requested by the
                    judge to read more clearly he became so agitated as to be totally unable to
                    proceed. But, his feelings once roused, all nervousness disappeared. His
                    effective and witty attack upon a judge who had sneered at his poverty, the
                    success with which he prosecuted a nobleman for a disgraceful assault upon a
                    priest, the duel which he fought with one of the witnesses for this nobleman,
                    and other similar exploits, gained him such a reputation that he was soon the
                    most popular advocate in Ireland.</p>
                <p>In 1783 Curran was appointed king’s counsel; andin the same year he was presented
                    to a seat in the Irish House of Commons. His conduct in connection with this
                    affair displays his conduct in a most honourable light; finding that he differed
                    radically in politics from the gentleman from whom he had received his seat, he
                    offered to buy another to replace that which he occupied. In his parliamentary
                    career Curran was throughout sincere and consistent. He spoke vigorously in
                    behalf of Catholic emancipation, and strenuously attacked the ministerial
                    bribery which prevailed. His declamations against the Government party led him
                    into two duels—the first with Fitzgibbon, then attorney-general, afterwards Lord
                    Clare; the second with the secretary of state, Major Hobart, afterwards Lord
                    Buckingham. The Union caused him the bitterest disappointment; he even talked of
                    leaving Ireland, either for America or for England.</p>
                <p>Curran’s fame rests most of all upon his speeches in behalf of the accused in the
                    state trials that were so numerous between 1794 and 1803; and among them may be
                    mentioned those in defence of Hamilton Rowan, the Rev. William Jackson, the
                    brothers Shears, Finnerty, Lord Edward Fitzgerald, Tone, and Kirwan. Another of
                    his most famous and characteristic speeches is that against the marquis of
                    Headfort, who had eloped with the wife of a clergyman named Massey. On the
                    arrest of Emmett, who had formed an attachment to his daughter, Curran was
                    himself under suspicion; but, on examination before the Privy Council, nothing
                    was brought forward to implicate him in the intended rebellion.</p>
                <p>In 1806, on the death of Pitt and the formation of the Fox ministry, Curran
                    received the post of Master of the Rolls, with a seat in the Privy Council, much
                    to his disappointment, for he had desired a position of greater political
                    influence. For eight years, however, he performed the distasteful duties of this
                    office. He then retired on a pension of £3000; and the three remaining years of
                    his life were spent in London, where he became one of the most brilliant members
                    of the brilliant society which included Sheridan, Erskine, Thomas Moore, and
                    William Godwin. He died at his house in Bromptón on the 14th October 1817.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n750/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0750-0715"/>
                <p>Curran’s legal erudition was never profound; and though he was capable of the
                    most ingenious pleading, his appeal was always to the emotions of his audience.
                    His best speeches are one fiery torrent of invective, pathos, national feeling,
                    and wit. His diction was lofty and sonorous. To his personal presence he owed
                    nothing; foi he was short, slim, and boyish-looking, and his voice was thin and
                    shrill.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Curran and his Contemporaries,</hi> a most entertaining
                    work, by Charles Phillips, personal friend of Curran’s (1818), and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Curran</hi> by his son, W. H. Curran (1819, and with
                    additions by Dr Shelton Mackenzie, New York, 1855), both of which contain
                    numerous samples of Curran’s eloquence. See also <hi rend="italic">Currans
                    Speeches</hi> (1805, 1808, 1845), <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Curran,</hi> by
                    Wm. O’Regan (1817), <hi rend="italic">Letters to Rev. H. Weston</hi> (1819).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
