<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0344-0315-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CONSUL (9th edition, volume 6, page 315)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876196">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n344/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CONSUL</label>, a public officer authorized by the state
                    whose commission he bears to manage the commercial affairs of its subjects in a
                    foreign country, and formally permitted by the Government of the country wherein
                    he resides to perform the duties which are specified in his commission, or <hi
                    rend="italic">lettre</hi><hi rend="italic">de provision.</hi> A consul, as such,
                    is not invested with any diplomatic character, and he cannot enter on his
                    official duties until a rescript, termed an <hi rend="italic">exaequatur</hi>
                    (sometimes a mere countersign endorsed on the commission) has been delivered to
                    him by the authorities of the state to which his nomination has been
                    communicated by his own Government. This <hi rend="italic">exaequatur,</hi>
                    called in Turkey a <hi rend="italic">barat,</hi> may be revoked at any time at
                    the discretion of the Government where he resides. The status of consuls
                    commissioned by the Christian powers of Europe to reside in the Levant, and to
                    exercise judicial functions in civil and criminal matters between their own
                    countrymen and strangers, is exceptional to the common law, and is founded on
                    special conventions or capitulations with the Ottoman Porte. The English consuls
                    in the Levant were originally the officers of “the governor and company of
                    merchants of England trading in the Levant seas,” created by letters patent from
                    James I., which were cancelled in 1826. Besides the pure consular
                    jurisdiction—exercised under the Order in Council 30th November 1864, by a judge
                    in the Supreme Consular Court at Constantinople, and by the ordinary consuls in
                    provincial courts, subject to an appeal to Her Majesty’s Imperial Court of
                    Appeal, in cases beyond <hi rend="italic">£500</hi> in value—there is also the
                    jurisdiction of the consular court of the defender’s nation, where the parties
                    are both foreign Christians, and a Turkish tribunal for cases between Turks and
                    foreign Christians. The tendency now is to substitute mixed tribunals in both
                    these cases. The right of British consuls to be present in the native courts,
                    when one of the parties is a British subject, was conceded by the Treaty of
                    Dardanelles (1809). lt is not unusual in the case of consuls-general resident in
                    Mahometan countries that they should also be accredited as political agents, or
                    <hi rend="italic">charges d'affaires,</hi> in which case they are invested with
                    the diplomatic character, and are entitled to the privileges of public
                    ministers.</p>
                <p>The present system of consuls <hi rend="italic">d'outre mer,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">à l’étranger,</hi> was preceded by the system of domestic consuls,
                    <hi rend="italic">juges</hi> consuls, or <hi rend="italic">marchands,</hi> in
                    the chief maritime cities of the south of Europe. These constituted mere
                    tribunals of commerce which had no special concern with foreign <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n345/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0345-0316"/> shipping or trade. Later on, the need was felt of
                    a safe place of deposit and of an independent jurisdiction. Particular quarters
                    of mercantile cities were assigned to foreign traders, and disputes were decided
                    by officers variously called governors, protectors, ancients, aldermen (in the
                    Hanse towns), syndics, jurats, prévosts, capitouls, and échevins —all names
                    borrowed from municipal offices. The consul was generally a wholesale dealer,
                    named by the rector and council of the home city. He had power to fine and
                    banish from the quarter. Similar to these were the judge-conservators, elected
                    by British residents in the Portuguese ports. This privilege long cemented the
                    friendly relations of the two nations, and was formally renounced only in 1842.
                    Another singular institution, containing more than the germ of the modern
                    consulate, was “the <hi rend="italic">Cour de la Fonde,</hi> whose jurisdiction
                    had supplanted the old Court of the Reis or Baillis (established by Godfrey de
                    Bouillon at Jerusalem for the benefit of Syrian merchants), and which included a
                    cognizance of all commercial matters, its judges being a mixed body of Franks
                    and Syrians” (Kent’s <hi rend="italic">Commentaries,</hi> by Abdy, p. 137). The
                    16th century saw the introduction of foreign consuls, but the earliest treaties
                    of Great Britain with Spain and Turkey on this subject are dated in 1665 and
                    1675. The right to establish consuls is now universally recognized by Christian
                    civilized states. Jurists at one time contended that according to international
                    law a right of “extra-territoriality” attached to consuls, their persons and
                    dwellings being sacred, and themselves amenable to local authority only in cases
                    of strong suspicion on political grounds. It is now admitted that, apart from
                    treaty, cus∙ tom has established very few consular privileges; that perhaps
                    consuls may be arrested and incarcerated, not merely on criminal charges, but
                    for civil debt; and that, if they engage in trade or become the owners of
                    immovable property, their persons certainly lose protection. This question of
                    arrest has been frequently raised in Europe :— in the case of Barbuit, a
                    tallow-chandler, who from 1717 to 1735 acted as Prussian consul in London, and
                    to whom the exemption conferred by statute on ambassadors was held not to apply;
                    in the case of Cretico, the Turkish consul at London in 1808; in the case of
                    Begley, the United States consul at Genoa, arrested in Paris in 1840; and in the
                    case of De la Fuente Hermosa, Uruguayan consul, whom the <hi rend="italic">Cour
                    Royale</hi> of Paris in 1812 held liable to arrest for debt. In the same way
                    consuls, unless protected by treaty, pay local taxes, although they are
                    generally exempt from general duties on articles of personal consumption, relief
                    from income tax being often given by treaty. They are exempt from billeting and
                    military service, but are not entitled (except in the Levant, where also freedom
                    from arrest and trial is the rule) to have private chapels in their houses. The
                    exception in favour of the Levant was illustrated in 1853, when the refugee
                    Martin Koszta, who had become United States consul at Smyrna and <hi
                    rend="italic">charge d'affaires</hi> at Constantinople, was seized by the Turks.
                    This, although a case of suspicion on political grounds, called forth a protest
                    from America, and restitution was made. The right of consuls to exhibit their
                    national arms and flag over the door of the <hi rend="italic">bureau</hi> is not
                    disputed.</p>
                <p>The duty of consuls, under the “General Instructions to British Consuls,” is to
                    advise Her Majesty’s trading subjects, to quiet their differences, and to
                    conciliate as much as possible the subjects of the two countries. Treaty rights
                    he is to support in a mild and moderate spirit; and he is to check as far as
                    possible evasions by British traders of the local revenue laws. Besides
                    assisting British subjects who are tried for offences in the local courts, and
                    ascertaining the humanity of their treatment after sentence, he has to consider
                    whether home or foreign law is more appropriate to the case, having regard to
                    the convenience of witnesses and the time required for decision; and, where
                    local courts have wrongfully interfered, he puts the Home Government in motion
                    through the consul-general or ambassador. He sends in reports on the export and
                    import trade of the district in which he resides; and he reports to the
                    secretary of state when a vice-consul is required in any place, generally naming
                    an English merchant. Under the Act 12 and 13 Vict. c. 68, extended by the
                    Consular Marriage Act, 1868, consuls are empowered, on certain notices and
                    declarations being given, to celebrate marriage between persons who have resided
                    one month in the district, one of them being a British subject. They are also
                    empowered by statute to advance for the erection or maintenance of Anglican
                    churches, hospitals, and places of interment sums equal to the amount subscribed
                    for the purpose by the resident British subjects.</p>
                <p>As the powers and duties of consuls vary with the particular commercial interests
                    they have to protect, and the civilization of the state in whose territory they
                    reside, instead of abstract definition, we summarize the provisions on this
                    subject of the British Merchant Shipping Acts.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See also instructions to Consuls prepared by
                    the Board of Trade and approved by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,
                    1855, aud Supplementary Instructions, 1868.</p></note> Consuls are bound to send
                    to the Board of Trade such reports or returns on any matter relating to British
                    merchant shipping or seamen as they may think necessary. Where a consul suspects
                    that the shipping or navigation laws are being evaded, he may require the owner
                    or master to produce the log-book or other ship documents (such as the agreement
                    with the seamen, the account of the crew, the certificate of registration); he
                    may muster the crew, and order explanations with regard to the documents. Where
                    an offence has been committed on the high seas, or abroad ashore, by British
                    seamen or apprentices, the consul makes inquiry on oath, and may send home the
                    offender and witnesses by a British ship, particulars for the Board of Trade
                    being endorsed on the agreement for conveyance. He is also empowered to detain a
                    foreign ship, the master or seamen of which appear to him through their
                    misconduct or want of skill to have caused injury to a British vessel, until the
                    necessary application for satisfaction or security be made to the local
                    authorities. Every British mercantile ship, not carrying passengers, on entering
                    a port gives into the custody of the consul to be endorsed by him the seamen’s
                    agreement, the indentures, &lt;fcc.; a failure to do this is reported to the
                    registrar-general of seamen. The following five provisions are also made for the
                    protection of seamen. If a British master engage seamen at a foreign port, the
                    engagement is sanctioned by the consul, acting as a Superintendent of Mercantile
                    Marine Offices. The consul collects the property (including arrears of wages) of
                    British seamen or apprentices dying abroad, aud remits to H.M.
                    paymaster-general. He also provides for the subsistence of seamen who are
                    shipwrecked, discharged, or left behind, even if their service was with foreign
                    merchants; they are generally sent home in the first British ship that happens
                    to be in want of a complement, and the expenses thus incurred form a charge on
                    the Parliamentary fund for the relief of distressed seamen, the consul receiving
                    a commission of 2 J per cent, on the amount disbursed. Complaints by crews as to
                    the quality and quantity of the provisions on board are investigated by the
                    consul, who enters a statement in the log-book and reports to the Board of
                    Trade. Money disbursed by consuls on account of the illness or injury of seamen
                    is generally recoverable from the owner. With regard to passenger vessels, the
                    master is bound to give the consul facilities for inspection-and for
                    communication with passengers, and to exhibit his “master’s <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n346/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0346-0317"/> list,” or list of passengers, so that the consul
                    may transmit to the registrar-general, for insertion in the Marine Register
                    Book, a report of the passengers dying and children born during the voyage. The
                    consul may even defray the expenses of maintaining, and forwarding to their
                    destination, passengers taken off or picked up from wrecked or injured vessels,
                    if the master does not undertake to proceed in six weeks; these expenses
                    becoming, in terms of the Passenger Acts 1855 and 1863, a debt due to Her
                    Majesty from the owner or charterer. Where a salvor is justified in detaining a
                    British vessel, the master may obtain leave to depart by going with the salvor
                    before the consul, who after hearing evidence as to the service rendered and the
                    proportion of ship’s value and freight claimed, fixes the amount for which the
                    master is to gi ve bond and security. In the case of a foreign wreck the consul
                    is held to be the agent of the foreign owner. Much of the notarial business
                    which is imposed on consuls, partly by statute and partly by the request of
                    private parties, consists in taking the declarations as to registry, transfers,
                    &lt;fcc., mentioned in Schedules B, C, F, G, H, L of the Mercantile Shipping
                    Act. Under commercial treaties with China, British consuls in the free ports of
                    Canton, Amoy, Foo-chow-foo, Ningpo, and Shanghae have extensive judicial and
                    executive powers. The same observation applies to Japan. (See Order in Council
                    of 9th March 1865 and relative rules.)</p>
                <p>The position of United States consuls is minutely described in the Regulations,
                    Washington, 1870. Under various treaties and conventions they enjoy large
                    privileges and jurisdiction. By a treaty with Sweden in 1818 the United States
                    Government agreed that the consuls of the two states respectively should be sole
                    judges in disputes between captains and crews of vessels. By convention with
                    France in 1857 they likewise agreed that the consuls of both countries should be
                    permitted to hold real estate, and to have the “police interne des navires à
                    commerce.” In Eastern Asia an exclusive jurisdiction, civil and criminal, is
                    always stipulated in cases where United States subjects are interested.
                    Exemption from liability to appear as a witness is often stipulated. The
                    question was raised in France in 1843 by the case of the Spanish consul Soller
                    at Aix, and in America in 1854 by the case of Dillon, the French consul at San
                    Francisco, who, on being arrested by Judge Hoffmann for declining to give
                    evidence in a criminal suit, pulled down his consular flag. So, also,
                    inviolability of national archives is often stipulated. The archives of a French
                    consul in London were once seized by a collector of local taxes and sold by
                    auction, and in 1858 the flag, seal, arms, and record-book of the United States
                    consulate at Manchester were levied on for a private debt of the consul. To the
                    consuls of other nations the United States Government have always accorded the
                    privileges of arresting deserters, and of being themselves amenable only to the
                    Federal and not to the States courts. They also recognize foreign consuls as
                    representative suitors for absent foreigners.</p>
                <p>The United States commercial agents, although appointed by the president, receive
                    no <hi rend="italic">exaequatur.</hi> They form a class by themselves, and are
                    distinct from the consular agents, who are simply deputy consuls in districts
                    where there is no principal consul. France is distinguished among nations for an
                    organization of trained consuls who have intimate relations with the diplomatic
                    corps.</p>
                <p>See De Miltitz, <hi rend="italic">Manuel des Consuls,</hi> London and Berlin,
                    1837— 1843; De Cussy, <hi rend="italic">Réglements Consulaires des principaux
                    états maritimes de l'Europe et de V Amérique,</hi> 1851, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionnaire du diplomate et du Consul,</hi> Leipsic, 1846; Fynn’s <hi
                    rend="italic">British</hi><hi rend="italic">Consul</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Abroad;</hi> Report of Select Committee on Consular Service (Pari. Papers),
                    1872; Martens, <hi rend="italic">Guide diplomatique,</hi> Leipsic, 1866; and De
                    Clercq, <hi rend="italic">Guide pratique des consulats,</hi> 1858. (W. C.
                    S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
