<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0168-0143-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COLLIER, Arthur (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    143)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n168/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COLLIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Arthur</hi></label>
                    (1680-1732), metaphysician and divine, was born at the rectory of Langford
                    Magna, near Sarum, on 12th October 1680. There is no account of his childhood
                    and early youth; but it is probable that, after receiving some rudimentary
                    instruction at home, he went to one of the grammar schools at Salisbury. He
                    entered at Pembroke College, Oxford, in July 1697 and remained there till
                    October in the following year, when he and his brother William became members of
                    Balliol together. His father died in 1697, and as the family owned the advowson
                    of Langford Magna, it was arranged, after some difficulties raised by Burnet,
                    then bishop of Salisbury, that the benefice should be held by a clergyman until
                    Arthur was old enough to be inducted. » He was accordingly presented to the
                    benefice in 1704, and continued in it till his death in 1732. Although a bold
                    speculator in theology, his sermons intended for his parish show no traces of
                    his peculiar notions, and he seems to have been faithful in the discharge of his
                    duty. He was often in pecuniary difficulties, from which at last he was obliged
                    to free himself by selling the reversion of Langford rectory to Corpus Christi
                    College, Oxford, a misfortune which his biographer attributes to his “habits of
                    abstruse speculation, which seem to have unfitted him for all considerations of
                    worldly prudence.” Collier’s philosophical opinions took shape early in his
                    mind. They grew out of a diligent study of the writings of Descartes and
                    Malebranche. Norris of Bemerton, a neighbouring clergyman, also strongly
                    influenced him by his <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Ideal World.</hi> It is
                    remarkable that Collier makes no reference to Locke, nor shows the least sign of
                    having any knowledge of his works. As early as 1703 Collier seems to have become
                    convinced of the non-existence of an external world. There is among his MSS.,
                    under date January 1708, an outline of an essay in three chapters on the
                    question whether the visible world is external or not. In 1712 he wrote two
                    essays, which are still in manuscript, one on substance and accident, and the
                    other termed <hi rend="italic">Clavis</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophica.</hi>
                    The work on which his philosophical reputation depends appeared in 1713, under
                    the title <hi rend="italic">Clavis</hi><hi rend="italic">Universalis, or a New
                    Inquiry after Truth, being a Demonstration of the Non-Existence or Impossibility
                    of an External World.</hi> It has been favourably mentioned by Reid, Stewart,
                    and others, was frequently referred to by the Leibnitzians, and was translated
                    into German by Professor Eschenbach in 1756. Berkeley’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Principles of Knowledge</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Theory of Vision</hi>
                    preceded it by three and four years respectively. Although there is no evidence
                    that they were known to Collier before the publication of his book, a passage in
                    a letter written by him in March 1713-14 proves that he was acquainted in some
                    measure with Berkeley’s opinions at that date. In this letter and other four,
                    which are given in Benson’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Collier</hi> (1837),
                    there are some further remarks in defence of his philosophical views; but they
                    are merely a repetition of the arguments in the <hi rend="italic">Clavis.</hi>
                    These are grounded on two presuppositions—first, the utter aversion of common
                    sense to any theory of representative perception; and second, the opinion which
                    Collier held in common with Berkeley, and Hume afterwards, that the difference
                    between imagination and sense perception is only one of degree. The former is
                    the basis of the negative part of his argument; <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n169/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0169-0144"/> the latter supplies him with all the positive
                    account he has to give, and that is meagre enough. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Clavis</hi> consists of two parts. After some introductory remarks, iu which he
                    explains that he will use the term “external world” in the sense of absolute,
                    self-existent, independent matter, and fences the position he is to occupy
                    against sundry possible misinterpretations, he attempts in the first part to
                    prove that the visible world is not external, by showing—first, that the seeming
                    externeity of a visible object is no proof of real externeity, and second, that
                    a visible object, as such, is not external. The image of a centaur seems as much
                    external to the mind as any object of sense; and since the difference between
                    imagination and perception is only one of degree, God could so act upon the mind
                    of a person imagining a centaur, that he would perceive it as vividly as any
                    object can be seen. Descartes and his school affirm that certain objects of
                    sense, as sounds, smells, &lt;fcc., exist only in their respective faculties,
                    although no one can doubt that they <hi rend="italic">seem</hi> to exist
                    altogether without them. The same philosophers agree that light and colours,
                    which are allowed to be objects properly visible, are not external. Still they
                    seem to be so. The delusions of the insane and the visions of inspired men are
                    further instances of seeming externality which is not real. So is the familiar
                    case of objects seen in a looking-glass. A number of similar illustrations are
                    used to prove the second proposition, that a visible object, as such, is not
                    external. If we assume, for instance, that there is an external moon, it cannot
                    be the same as the visible moon, for this is ever-changing and is never bigger
                    than a trencher; but the real moon is some thousands of miles in diameter.
                    Berkeley uses the same argument in his <hi rend="italic">Álciſkhron</hi> (1732).
                    Then, too, the Aristotelian and the Cartesian forms of representative perception
                    agree in holding that the true object of vision is not the external reality. The
                    author concludes his first part by replying to objections based on the universal
                    consent of men, on the assurance given by touch of the extra existence of the
                    visible world, and on the truth and goodness of God (Descartes), which would be
                    impugned if our senses deceived us. Collier argues naively that if universal
                    consent means the consent of those who have considered the subject, it may be
                    claimed for his view. He thinks with Berkeley that objects of sight are quite
                    distinct from those of touch, and that the one therefore cannot give any
                    assurance of the other ∙ and he asks the Cartesians to consider how far God’s
                    truth and goodness are called in question by their denial of the externality of
                    the secondary qualities. The second part of the book is taken up with a number
                    of metaphysical arguments to prove the impossibility of an external world. The
                    pivot of this part is the logical principle of contradiction. From the
                    hypothesis of an external world a series of antinomies are deduced, such as that
                    the world is both finite and infinite, is movable and immovable, &amp;c.; and
                    finally, Aristotle and various other philosophers are quoted, to show that the
                    external matter they dealt with, as mere potentiality, is just nothing at all.
                    Among other uses and consequences of his treatise, Collier thinks it furnishes
                    an easy refutation of the Romish doctrine of transubstantiation. If there is no
                    external world, the distinction between substance and accidents vanishes, and
                    these become the sole essence of material objects, so that there is no room for
                    any change whilst they remain as before. Sir William Hamilton thinks that the
                    logically necessary advance from the old theory of representative perception to
                    idealism was stayed by anxiety to save this miracle of the church; and he gives
                    Collier credit for being the first to make the discovery.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discussions,</hi> pp. 198-202.</p></note> Professor Ueberweg, on the other
                    hand, is of opinion that idealism and the miracle of the eucharist may be
                    reconciled by regarding substance not as substrate supporting the accidents, but
                    as intelligible essence; so that when in the religious act the body and blood of
                    Christ are conjoined with the bread and wine, these cease to be essential and
                    become accidents, and a different substance is present.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Annotations on Berkeley's
                    Principles,</hi> p. 138.</p></note> But in that form of idealism which
                    recognizes an intelligible essence there must be such a necessary connection
                    between essence and phenomenon as would require the presence of new phenomena
                    along with the new essence. Still it must have been some deeper cause than
                    concern for the church dogma that retarded idealism. Until philosophers could be
                    broughtto reflect on the meaning of such notions as externality, cause, &lt;tc.,
                    it was inevitable that they should continue striving to justify the belief in an
                    external material world. Collier’s blank denial would not have turned the
                    stream. It needed a more subtle thinker to divert it into the course which it
                    afterwards followed.</p>
                <p>Collier’s book possesses an interest for the student of philosophy on account of
                    the resemblance between his views and those of his contemporary Berkeley.. Both
                    were impelled to philosophize by their dissatisfaction with the theory of
                    representative perception. Both have the feeling that it is inconsistent with
                    the common sense of mankind, which will insist that the very object perceived is
                    the sole reality, and both claim to substitute for the theory held in favour,
                    and vainly sought to be demonstrated by their predecessors, another that will
                    meet the demands of common sense. They equally affirm that the so-called
                    representative image is the sole reality, aud discard the unperceiving material
                    cause of the philosophers as an unthinkable monstrosity. Of objects of sense,
                    they say, their <hi rend="italic">esse</hi> is <hi rend="italic">percipi.</hi>
                    But Collier never got beyond a bald assertion of the fact, while Berkeley
                    addressed himself to an explanation of it, which gave him ever profounder matter
                    for philosophical reflection all his days. The thought of a distinction between
                    direct and indirect perception never dawned upon Collier’s mind. He could only
                    meet the doctrine of the representationists, therefore, with a flat negation. To
                    the question how all matter exists in dependence on percipient mind he could
                    only reply, “Just how my reader pleases, provided it be somehow.” As cause of
                    our sensations and ground of our belief in externality, he substituted for an
                    unintelligible material substance an equally unintelligible operation of divine
                    power. But his illustrious contemporary gave a fresh start to philosophy by his
                    exposition of the association between visual and tactual sensations; and his
                    glimpses, faint at first, gradually grew more distinct of an intelligible order
                    in the universe. Collier’s book exhibits no traces of a scientific development.
                    In the first part, which may be compared with Berkeley’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theory oj Vision,</hi> he merely brings together a few instances of visual
                    experience, which throw discredit upon the popular opinion. . The most that can
                    be said about him is that he was an intelligent student of Descartes and
                    Malebranche, and had the ability to apply the results of his reading to the
                    facts of his experience. He starts no original conception, contributes nothing
                    to the development of philosophy. The latter half of his book reads like the
                    ingenious quibbling of the schoolmen. In philosophy he is a curiosity, and
                    nothing more. His biographer tries to make out that the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Clavis</hi> fell flat on the English public in comparison with the reception
                    accorded to Berkeley’s writings, on account of its inferiority in point of
                    style. No doubt it is immensely inferior in that respect; but the crudeness of
                    Collier’s thought had quite as much to do with his failure to gain a hearing.
                    Hamilton<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Discussions,</hi> p. 197.</p></note> allows greater sagacity to
                    Collier than to Berkeley, for not vainly attempting to enlist men’s natural
                    belief against the hypothetical realism of the philosophers. But Collier did so
                    as far as his light enabled him. He appealed to the popular conviction that the
                    proper object of sense is the sole reality, although he despaired of getting men
                    to give up their belief in its externality. He moreover distinctly asserted that
                    nothing but prejudice prevented them from doing so; and there is little doubt
                    that if it had ever occurred to him, as it did to Berkeley, to explain the
                    genesis of the notion of externality, he would have been more hopeful of
                    commending his theory to the popular mind. What.Collier simply denied Berkeley
                    tried to explain, and therein lies that real difference between the two writers
                    which accounts for the comparative oblivion that has been the fate of the one,
                    and justifies the place assigned to the other in the history of philosophy.</p>
                <p>In a curious discourse on Genesis i. 1, which Collier published in 1730, under
                    the modest title, <hi rend="italic">A Specimen of a True Philosophy,</hi> we
                    have a jumble of his theological views and his philosophical opinions. Inasmuch
                    as we are often told in Scripture that God created all <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0170-0145"/> things in and by the Son, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >aρχ∙f</hi> ∣ of the passage commented on must refer to the only begotten Son of
                    God. If then we exist in God, because we are made by Him, as St Paul says, “in
                    him we live, and move, and have our being,” we must believe that we exist mor,e
                    immediately in the Son, being told, as in the text, that God made us and all
                    things by and in His Son. Christ, the <hi rend="italic">aρχh</hi> of the whole
                    creation, must needs be in some sense the subject or object of all that is
                    called science. Things, however, do not exist immediately in Christ, but at
                    various distances and projections from II im. Everything in particular is in its
                    own proper or immediate <hi rend="italic">apχh</hi> or substance; but all these
                    terminate in one, the Son of God, the substance of the whole creation. This
                    interpretation.of the passage is corroborated by the conclusion reached in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Glavis Universalis;</hi> for it is there proved that the
                    visible or material world exists immediately in the mind of the percipient, and
                    hence the meaning of the text must be that mind or spirit is the αρχ⅛ in which
                    God created the heaven and the earth. As the objects of sense exist immediately
                    in the mind, so the mind exists immediately in the Son of God; and thus the
                    ladder of being is completed in this <hi rend="italic">Specimen of a True
                    Philosophy.</hi><hi rend="italic">TheLogology, oraTreatise on the Logos, in
                    Seven Sermons on John</hi> i. 1, 2, 3, and 14, was published in 1732, the year
                    of Collier’s death. It further applies his theory of inexistence to the Son, who
                    is said to be in the Father, as men are in Him, and material objects are in
                    them. The Son is the “mean proportional” between God and us. Collier was
                    heterodox in regard to the incarnation, as well as the Trinity, maintaining
                    “that the pre-existent Word, or Son of God, was not united to a created human
                    soul or spirit, but was himself the man called Jesus and the Christ. ’ '</p>
                <p>See Benson’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Arthur
                    Collier,</hi> 1837; Parr’s <hi rend="italic">Metaphysical Tracts by English
                    Philosophers of the Eighteenth, Century,</hi> 1837; <hi rend="italic">T
                    ennem.a.nn’a History of Philosophy;</hi> Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discussions;</hi> Professor Fraser’s edition of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Berkeley</hi><hi rend="italic">s</hi><hi rend="italic">Works.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
