<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0102-0083-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COBBETT, William (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    83)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639k84f">Farms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qp5f">Farming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921422">Farms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353199">Grammar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n102/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COBBETT, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>
                    (1766-1835), one of the most vigorous of English political writers, was born
                    near Farnham in Surrey, according to his own statement, on the 9th March 1766.
                    He was the grandson of a farm-labourer, and the son of a small farmer; and
                    during his early life he worked on his father’s farm. At the age of sixteen,
                    inspired with patriotic feeling by the sight of the men· of - war in Portsmouth
                    harbour, he offered himself as a sailor; and at seventeen (May 1783) having,
                    while on his way to Guildford fair, met the London coach, he suddenly resolved
                    to accompany it to its destination. He arrived at Ludgate Hill with exactly
                    half-a-crown in his pocket, but an old gentleman who had travelled with him
                    invited him to his house, and obtained for him the situation of copying clerk in
                    an attorney’s office. He greatly disliked his new occupation; and rejecting all
                    his father's entreaties that he would return home, he went down to Chatham early
                    in 1784 with the intention of joining the marines. By some mistake, however, he
                    was enlisted in a regiment of the line, which rather more than a year after
                    proceeded to St John’s, New Brunswick. All his leisure time during the months he
                    remained at Chatham was devoted to reading the contents of the circulating
                    library of the town, and getting up by heart· Lowth’s <hi rend="italic">English
                    Grammar.</hi> His uniform good conduct, and the power of writing correctly which
                    he had acquired, quickly raised him to the rank of corporal, from which, without
                    passing through the intermediate grade of sergeant, he was promoted to that of
                    sergeant-major. In November 1791 he was discharged at his own request, and
                    received the official thanks of the major and the general who signed his
                    discharge. But Cobbett’s connection with the regiment did not end in this
                    agreeable manner. He brought a serious charge against some of its officers, and
                    instead of appearing at the trial fled to France (March 1792). The inquiry which
                    was held in his absence resulted in a complete acquittal of the accused.</p>
                <p>In the previous February Cobbett had married the daughter of a sergeant-major of
                    artillery; he had met her some years before in New Brunswick, and had proved her
                    to be endowed with energy and self-control equal to his own. In September of the
                    same year (1792) he crossed to the United States, and for a time supported
                    himself at Wilmington by teaching English to French emigrants. Among these was
                    Talleyrand, who employed him, according to Cobbett’s story, not because he was
                    ignorant of English, but because he wished to purchase his pen. Cobbett made his
                    first literary sensation by his <hi rend="italic">Observations on the Emigration
                    of a Martyr to the Cause of Liberty,</hi> a clever retort en Dr Priestley, who
                    had just landed in America complaining of the treatment he had received in
                    England. This pamphlet was followed by a number of papers, signed “Peter
                    Porcupine,” and entitled <hi rend="italic">Prospect from the Congress
                    Gallery,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Political Censor,</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Porcupine's</hi><hi rend="italic">Gazette.</hi> In the spring of
                    1796, having quarrelled with his publisher, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n103/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0103-0084"/> he set up in Philadelphia as bookseller and
                    publisher of his own works. On the day of opening, his windows were filled with
                    prints of the most extravagant of the French Revolutionists and of the founders
                    of the American Republic placed side by side, along with portraits of George
                    III., the British ministers,and any one else he could find likely to be
                    obnoxious to the people; and he continued to pour forth praises of Great Britain
                    and scorn of the institutions of the United States, with special abuse of the
                    French party. Abuse and threats were of course in turn showered upon him, and in
                    August, for one of his attacks on Spain, he was prosecuted, though
                    unsuccessfully, by the Spanish ambassador. Immediately on this he was taken up
                    for libels upon American statesmen, and bound in recognizances to the amount of
                    $4000, and shortly after he was prosecuted a third time for saying that a
                    certain Dr Rush, who was much addicted to bleeding, killed nearly all the
                    patients he attended. The trial was repeatedly deferred, and was not settled
                    till the end of 1799, when he was fined $5000. After this last misfortune, for a
                    few months Cobbett carried on a newspaper called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rushlight;</hi> but in June 1800 he set sail for England.</p>
                <p>At home he found himself regarded as the champion of order and monarchy. Windham
                    invited him to dinner, introduced him to Pitt, and begged him to accept a share
                    in the <hi rend="italic">True Briton.</hi> He refused the offer and joined an
                    old friend, John Morgan, in opening a book shop in Pall Mall. For some time he
                    published the <hi rend="italic">Porcupine's Gazette,</hi> which was followed in
                    January 1802 by the <hi rend="italic">Weekly Political Register.</hi> In 1801
                    appeared his Letters to Lord Hawkesbury (afterwards earl of Liverpool) and Mr
                    Addington, in opposition to the peace of Amiens, the terms of which had been
                    agreed to by the former on behalf of Great Britain in the October of that year,
                    but which was not finally concluded till 1802. On the conclusion of the peace
                    Cobbett made a still bolder protest; he determined to take no part in the
                    general illumination, and— assisted by the sympathy of his wife, who, being in
                    delicate health, removed to the house of a friend—he carried out his resolve,
                    allowing his windows to be smashed and his door broken open by the angry mob.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Letters to the Rt. Hon. Henry Addington</hi> are among the
                    most polished and dignified of Cobbett’s writings; but by 1803 he was once more
                    revelling in personalities. The government of Ireland was singled out for
                    wholesale attack; and a letter published in the <hi rend="italic">Register</hi>
                    remarked of Hardwicke, the lordlieutenant, that the appointment was like setting
                    the surgeon’s apprentice to bleed the pauper patients. For this, though not a
                    word had been uttered against Hardwicke’s character, Cobbett was fined £500; and
                    two days after the conclusion of this trial a second commenced, at the suit <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> of Plunkett, the solicitor-general for Ireland, which
                    resulted in a similar fine. About this time he began to write in support of
                    Radical views; and to cultivate the friendship of Sir Francis Burdett, from whom
                    he received considerable sums of money, and. other favours, for which he gave no
                    very grateful return. In 1809 he was once more in the most serious trouble. He
                    had bitterly commented on the flogging of some militia, because their mutiny had
                    been repressed and their sentence carried out by the aid of a body of German
                    troops, and in consequence he was fined £1000 and imprisoned for two years. His
                    indomitable vigour was never better displayed. He still continued to publish the
                    <hi rend="italic">Register,</hi> and to superintend the affairs of his farm; a
                    hamper containing specimens of its produce and other provisions came to him
                    every week; and he amused himself with the company of some of his children and
                    with weekly letters from the rest. On his release a public dinner, presided over
                    by Sir F. Burdett, was held in honour of the event. He returned to his farm at
                    Botley in Hampshire, and continued in his old course, extending his influence by
                    the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Twopenny Trash,</hi> which, not being
                    periodical, escaped the newspaper stamp tax. Meanwhile, however, he had
                    contracted debts to the amount of £34,000 (for it is said that, notwithstanding
                    the aversion he publicly expressed to paper currency, he had carried on his
                    business by the aid of accommodation bills to a very large amount); and in March
                    1817 he fled to the United States. But his pen was as active as ever; from Long
                    Island the <hi rend="italic">Register</hi> was regularly despatched to England;
                    and it was here that he wrote his clear and interesting <hi rend="italic"
                    >English Grammar,</hi> of which 10,000 copies were sold in a month.</p>
                <p>His return to England was accompanied by his weakest exhibition—the exhuming and
                    bringing over of the bones of Tom Paine, whom he had once heartily abused, but
                    on whom he now wrote a panegyrical ode. Nobody paid any attention to the affair;
                    the relics he offered were not purchased; and the bones were reinterred.</p>
                <p>Cobbett’s great aim was now to obtain a seat in the House of Commons. He calmly
                    suggested that his friends should assist him by raising the sum of £5000; it
                    would be much better, he said, than a meeting of 50,000 persons. He first
                    offered himself for Coventry, but failed; in 1826 he was by a large number of
                    votes last of the candidates for Preston; and in 1828 he could find no one to
                    propose him for the office of common councillor. In 1830, that year of
                    revolutions, he was prosecuted for inciting to rebellion, but the jury
                    disagreed, and soon after, through the influence of one of his admirers, Mr
                    Fielden, who was himself a candidate for Oldham, he was returned for that town.
                    In the House his speeches were listened to with amused attention. His position
                    is sufficiently marked by the sneer of Peel that he would attend to Mr Cobbett’s
                    observations exactly as if they had been those of a “respectable member ;” and
                    the only striking part of his career was his absurd motion that the king should
                    be prayed to remove Sir Robert Peel’s name from the list of the privy council,
                    because of the change he had proposed in the currency in 1819. In 1834 Cobbett
                    was again member for Oldham, but his health now began to give way, and in June
                    1835 he left London for his farm, where he died on the 16 th of that month.</p>
                <p>Cobbett’s account of his home-life makes him appear singularly happy; his love
                    and admiration of his wife never failed; and his education of his children seems
                    to have been distinguished by great kindliness, and by a good deal of healthy
                    wisdom, mingled with the prejudices due to the peculiarities of his temper and
                    circumstances. Cobbett’s ruling characteristic was a sturdy egotism, which had
                    in it something of the nobler element of self-respect. A firm will, a strong
                    brain, feelings not over-sensitive, an intense love of fighting, a resolve to
                    get on, in the sense of making himself a power in the world—these are the
                    principal qualities which account for the success of his career. His opinions
                    were the fruits of his emotions. It was enough for him to get a thorough grasp
                    of one side of a question, about the other side he did not trouble himself; but
                    he always firmly seizes the facts which make for his view, and expresses them
                    with unfailing clearness. His argument, which is never subtle, has always the
                    appearance of weight, however flimsy it may be in fact. His sarcasm is seldom
                    polished or delicate, but usually rough, and often abusive, while coarse
                    nicknames were his special delight. His style is always extremely forcible, and
                    marked by unusual grammatical correctness.</p>
                <p>Cobbett’s contributions to periodical literature occupy 10C volumes, twelve of
                    which consist of the papers published at Philadelphia between 1794 and 1800, and
                    the rest of the <hi rend="italic">Weekly Political Register,</hi> which ended
                    only with Cobbett’s life (June 1835). An abridgment of these works, with notes,
                    has been published by his sons, John Μ. Cobbett and James P. Cobbett. Besides
                    this ha <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n104/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0104-0085"/> published— <hi rend="italic">An Account of the
                    Horrors of the French Revolution,</hi> and a work tracing all these horrors to
                    “the licentious politics and infidel philosophy of the presentage” (both 1798);
                    <hi rend="italic">A Year's Residence in the United States; Parliamentary History
                    of England from the Norman Conquest to</hi> 1800 (1806); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cottage Economy; Roman History; French Grammar,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >English Grammar,</hi> both in the form of letters; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geographical Dictionary of England and Wales; History of the Regency and Reign
                    of George IV.,</hi> containing a defence of Queen Caroline, whose cause he
                    warmly advocated (1830-4); <hi rend="italic">Life of Andrew Jackson, President
                    of the United States</hi> (1834); <hi rend="italic">Legacy to Labourers; Legacy
                    to Peel; Legacy to Parsons,</hi> an attack on the secular claims of the
                    Established Church; <hi rend="italic">Doom of Tithes; Rural Rides; Advice to
                    Young Men and Women;</hi><hi rend="italic">Cobbett'</hi><hi rend="italic">s
                    Corn;</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> λvΛ</hi><hi rend="italic">History of the
                    Protestant Reformation in England and Ireland,</hi> in which he defends the
                    monasteries, Queen Mary, and Bonner, and attacks the Reformation, Henry VIII.,
                    Elizabeth, and all who helped to bring it about, with such vehemence that the
                    work was translated into French and Italian, and extensively circulated among
                    Roman Catholics.</p>
                <p>In 1798 Cobbett published in America an account of his early life, under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">The Life and Adventures of Peter Porcupine;</hi> and
                    he left papers relating to his subsequent career. These materials were embodied
                    in an anonymous <hi rend="italic">Life of Cobbett</hi> which appeared soon after
                    his death. See also Sir Henry Bulwer’s <hi rend="italic">Historical Characters;
                    Biographies of John Wilkes and William Cobbett</hi> by Rev. John Watson; and the
                    abridged and annotated edition of the <hi rend="italic">Register.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
