<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0713-5986-0351-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">LINCOLNSHIRE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 351</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:922931">Fens</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:832970">Birds</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:922098">Feathers</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:794216">Abbeys</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:955625">Herons</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sh7p">Fens</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t08d">Dykes</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz97">Herons</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193205986" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">LINCOLNSHIRE</label>, an English maritime county. It is
                    bounded on the north by Yorkshire, on the east by the German Ocean and Norfolk,
                    on the south by Cambridge, Northampton, and Rutland shires, and on the west by
                    Nottinghamshire and Leicestershire. Its greatest length is seventy-three miles,
                    and its greatest breadth forty-eight. The area is 2814 square miles, or about
                    1,800,000 acres.</p><p>The county is divided into three districts or provinces. The largest of these,
                    Lindsey, is more extensive than the other two, containing more than 1,000,000
                    acres, and stretching from the shores of the German Ocean to Nottinghamshire. It
                    is rather an elevated tract of country, but the whole is so level as scarcely to
                    contain a single hill. The north-eastern part of this division is a very
                    extensive district of heathy land, generally very poor, especially the northern
                    part of it, and denominated the Wolds. Though some parts of it have recently
                    been brought into cultivation, yet a great portion has scarcely any other live
                    stock than the numerous rabbits, which multiply in extended warrens. A small
                    part, however, of this division, contains a rich tract of low land, formed by
                    the rivers Trent, Dun, and Idle, where horned cattle are pastured, and some
                    excellent flax is produced. The province of Lindsey is subdivided into fifteen
                    hundreds and two sokes.</p><p>The province of Kcsteven extends along the western side of the county, from its
                    middle to its southern extremity; in which latter part is a portion of the fens.
                    Notwithstanding there arc many extensive heaths, especially near Lincoln and
                    Ancaster; and though the soil and elevation are various, yet on the whole it may
                    properly be described as a fertile country. Towards the west a ridge of hills,
                    which forms an abrupt boundary, extends from Grantham nearly to Lincoln; but
                    none of the points attains a great elevation. This province is subdivided into
                    nine hundreds and three sokes.</p><p>The third province, Holland, contains the greater part of that unhealthy division
                    of Lincolnshire usually called the <hi rend="italic">Fens.</hi> It is subdivided
                    into three hundreds, sometimes denominated sokes, sometimes wapentakes. The
                    character of this province is similar to that of the province of the same name
                    in the Netherlands, after which it has been called. Nearly the whole of it
                    appears, at a remote period, to have been covered by the sea, and only brought
                    into its present state of productiveness by the active and persevering labour of
                    the inhabitants. The embankments and the draining have been expensive,
                    perpetual, and progressive, and the soil that has been redeemed has conferred a
                    most abundant remuneration. Excellent pasture land has been formed out of the
                    swamps and bogs, and some of it produces extraordinary crops of corn, especially
                    oats. Even in those parts that have not been reclaimed, the reeds, which abound,
                    are converted into good covering for houses and barns, and they are well stocked
                    with aquatic wild fowl. The taking of them is a profitable employment to many
                    persons, and the markets of London are principally supplied from thence with
                    those delicacies. The decoys in this district are more numerous than in any
                    other part of England. They are commonly formed around quiet pools, to which
                    pipes made of bent willows, and covered with nets, gradually enlarging as they
                    approach the water, are conducted. Into the large orifice of the pipes the wild
                    birds are enticed by tame ones trained for that business, and who conduct them
                    into the funnel, when the appearance of a man or his dog behind drives them to
                    the most contracted part, where they are taken. The quantity of birds taken in
                    some seasons is prodigious, amounting to some hundreds of thousands. They
                    usually consist of teal, widgeon, and wild ducks; but occasionally wild geese,
                    godwits, coots, ruffs, and reeves and whimbrels, are caught. In these otherwise
                    unproductive fens, the keeping of geese, principally for the sake of the
                    feathers, is a considerable branch of rural industry, and supplies a large part
                    of the demands of the kingdom, both for beds and for pens. The feathers are
                    plucked from the birds at three, four, sometimes five different periods in the
                    course of a year. This is thought a barbarous custom; but the charge of cruelty
                    is denied by the breeders, who assert that, for their own profit, they pluck
                    only those feathers which are so near falling off as to occasion little pain;
                    those more firmly fixed, and which have some portion of blood at their end,
                    being of very inferior value. The young ones are plucked as well as the old
                    ones; experience having taught that, when plucked early, the future growth of
                    the feathers becomes greater. During the breeding season, the birds are lodged
                    in the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193205999" xml:id="kp-eb0713-5999-0352"/>same houses as their owners, in wicker pens, which
                    are arranged in rows, frequently in the bed chambers. A gooseherd in attendance
                    on the flock leads them daily to water, and assists them, on their return, to
                    get into their several cells. The attendants are acquainted with each individual
                    goose in the flock, and can commonly distinguish them by the tones of their
                    voices. Near Spalding there is a considerable heronry, and a smaller one near
                    Surflet, where the herons, like rooks, build their nests on high trees.</p><p>The air in the fens is generally insalubrious, and the inhabitants suffer much
                    from the nature of the water, which is generally of a brackish quality; and
                    though they make reservoirs to preserve rain water, in dry summers they
                    experience very great distress. In warm weather, vast swarms of insects add to
                    the annoyances peculiar to this district.</p><p>The population, according to the returns at the four decennial enumerations,
                    appear to have amounted in 1801 to 208,557, in 1811 to 237,891, in 1821 to
                    283,053, and in 1831 to 317,400. The annual value of the real property, as taken
                    in 1815, amounted to L.2,061,830.</p><p>The burials, including both the registered and the unregistered, in the period
                    from 1821 to 1831, appear to have been one in 53 of the whole number of
                    inhabitants then living. The illegitimate births were one in nineteen of the
                    whole born.</p><p>The occupations of the inhabitants, according to the returns arranged by Mr
                    Rickman in 1831, were as follow:</p><p>Occupiers of land employing labourers 6,901 ∙</p><p>Occupiers of land not employing labourers 6,204</p><p>Labourers employed in agriculture 32,167</p><p>Labourers employed in manufactures 167</p><p>Employed in retail trade or handicraft 20,490</p><p>Capitalists, bankers, &amp;c 2,734</p><p>Labourers not agricultural 5,855</p><p>Other males twenty years of age 3,886</p><p>Male servants 1,848</p><p>Female servants 16,011</p><p>The towns containing more than 2000 inhabitants, and their population in 1831,
                    were—</p><p>Lincoln, city 11,892</p><p>Boston, town .' 11,240</p><p>Lowth 6,927</p><p>Gainsborough 6,658</p><p>Stamford 5,837</p><p>Grantham 4,590</p><p>Grimsby 4,225</p><p>Horncastle 3,988</p><p>FIolbeach 3,890</p><p>Long Sutton 3,510</p><p>Sleaford 2,450</p><p>Bourn 2,355</p><p>Crowland 2,268</p><p>The reform bill has left the city of Lincoln, and the boroughs of Boston,
                    Stamford, and Grantham, with two members each, as before. It has left Grimsby
                    with only one; and has divided the county into two districts, one called the
                    Part of Lindsey, and the other the Part of Kesteven and Holland. The polling
                    places for the former are Lincoln, Gainsborough, Epworth, Barton, Brigg, Market
                    Rosin, Louth, Spilsby, and Horncastle; and for the latter, Sleaford, Boston,
                    Holbeach, Bourn, Donington, Navenby, Spalding, and Grantham.</p><p>The capital of this pounty is the see of a bishop, whose jurisdiction is the
                    largest of any in England, extending over the counties of Lincoln, Leicester,
                    Huntingdon, Bedford, and Buckingham; over one half of Hertfordshire, and several
                    portions of Oxfordshire, Berkshire, Rutlandshire, Northamptonshire, and
                    Warwickshire; and including 1517 parishes, under the superintendence of six
                    archdeacons.</p><p>The fens of Lincolnshire have running through them wide ditches, which serve to
                    drain the water from the land, and which, when united and extended, become
                    navigable, and highly beneficial as means of conveying the productions to the
                    various markets. The Foss Dyke, the earliest canal made in Britain, was
                    constructed in the year 1121, to form a connection between the city of Lincoln
                    and the river Trent; and though, from the nature of the soil, it has been often
                    obstructed, and the expense of keeping it in order has been great, it has
                    continued to be used from that time to the present day. The river Trent, though
                    rising in Staffordshire, may be considered as a Lincolnshire river, from the
                    principal navigation upon it belonging to this county. It receives the Dun and
                    the Ouse, and, before reaching the sea, unites with the Humber. It is navigable
                    for large barges to Gainsborough. It has, upon the influx of the tide, a most
                    extraordinary <hi rend="italic">bore,</hi> or, as it is provincially termed, <hi rend="italic">eager,</hi> when the waters run up resembling a wall with a
                    rapidity that has no equal in any of our English rivers, except the Wye at
                    Cĥipstow. The Witham rises within the county, about ten miles from Stamford. The
                    early part of its course is through a beautiful district till it reaches the fen
                    country, when its course becomes sluggish; but being navigable to Boston, it is
                    highly beneficial both for draining and for commerce. The other rivers are the
                    Ancholme, the Welland, the Glen, the Grant, and the Ouse. The Humber, indeed, is
                    its boundary on part of the northern side; but is more commonly and properly
                    considered as a Yorkshire than a Lincolnshire river, from Hull, its principal
                    port, being in that county. Two small canals communicate with the river Witham,
                    one from Horncastle, and the other from Sleaford.</p><p>The great bay or estuary into which the different rivers and dykes that drain the
                    fens are disembogued, is very shallow, and filled with drifting sands, which
                    render the approach to the shore highly dangerous. The rivers are constantly
                    loaded with mud, and, in times of flood, encounter the tide, equally charged
                    with its floating silt, which causes a stagnation and deposit that is constantly
                    shifting its position, as the strength of the rivers or of the tides happens to
                    be the more powerful.</p><p>The face of the country in the fens is generally uninteresting, exhibiting
                    extensive plains, with nothing to break the continuity of the line of vision,
                    and only rendered less monotonous by the vast numbers of cattle with which the
                    green meadows are covered. On the wolds a more bleak and dreary prospect
                    presents itself; but the western division of the country near Stamford and
                    Grantham is variegated, woody, and undulating, and presents generally pleasing
                    pictures.</p><p>The agriculture of the fens is of the simplest kind; for where nature has created
                    such a productive soil, little remains to be done by the operations of man. In
                    the more elevated parts of the county the cultivation is conducted with various,
                    but, on the whole, good judgment; and the land produces ample crops of wheat,
                    oats, barley, and beans, and in some parts hemp and flax. The attention,
                    however, of the whole county is more turned to derive profit from cattle than
                    from the use of the plough.</p><p><hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> ~ The oxen of Lincolnshire are proverbial for their
                    goodness. The original race were of a great size, with large heads and short
                    horns, thick in the bone, deep in the belly, short on the neck, high on the
                    rump, and bare en the shoulders; but these have been improved by such various
                    and judicious crossings of breeds, that their symmetry and excellent qualities
                    render them the best in the island. Many cattle bred in other countries are
                    fattened here on the rich natural pastures; but a portion of oil-cake is very
                    commonly given, to fit them earlier for <pb break="no" facs="nls:193206012" xml:id="kp-eb0713-6012-0353"/>the market of
                    Smithfield, to which numerous droves are weekly despatched. This fattening of
                    cattle for the supply of London is so advantageous that the dairy is almost
                    everywhere considered as a secondary object.</p><p>The sheep of this county are almost peculiar to it. They are of a large size,
                    have horns, and produce heavy fleeces of long wool, highly prized in the
                    manufacture of stuffs and some kinds of baizes. The flesh is, however, rank in
                    flavour, and, unless the animals are improved by crossing with other races, is
                    not generally relished. As the foundation of an excellent breed, they were
                    selected by the late judicious Mr Bakewell, who, from mixing them with other
                    races, produced those excellent sheep known by the name of the new Leicesters.
                    The fleeces of the pure Lincolnshire sheep in general weigh from ten to twelve
                    pounds; but extraordinary instances have been known in which they have attained
                    more than twenty pounds.</p><p>The live stock, in which this county exceeds every other, is rabbits, which the
                    numerous warrens on the wolds produce in vast numbers. From their prodigious
                    quantity, the flesh is of small value, and the sale of the skins for the use of
                    the furriers and hatters is the principal source of profit. The number of
                    warrens has considerably diminished of late years, and the land they occupied
                    has been appropriated to tillage; but they are still very extensive.</p><p>Lincolnshire is not a manufacturing county. Before the extension <hi rend="italic">of</hi> machinery, the spinning of their native wool gave
                    occupation to the female part of the population; but that employment has been
                    nearly discontinued of late years, and no other has yet been substituted in its
                    place. In some parts the flax is spun for domestic use. The nature of its
                    sea-shores operates to prevent foreign commerce; and there is little or no
                    intercourse between Lincolnshire and the ports even of Holland and Germany,
                    which are opposite to it. The county produces neither minerals nor coals.</p><p>The antiquities of Lincolnshire are numerous, Almost all the churches are fine
                    specimens of ancient architecture, a singularity which distinguishes them from
                    those in every other county of England. The remains of Crowland, founded in 716,
                    the seat of a mitred abbot, and anciently a place of great fame, are still
                    visited by every antiquary; and near them is the triangular bridge over three
                    streams, in good preservation. It is, however, so lofty and precipitous, that it
                    is only useful to horse and foot travellers, as carriages usually pass under it.
                    The other most prominent antiquities are, Torksey Castle, at the junction of the
                    Foss Dyke with the Trent; Thornton Abbey, near the Humber; Bardney Abbey, on the
                    banks of the Witham; Tattershall Castle, on the same river; and Somerton Castle,
                    in the parish of Boothby.</p><p>Sir Isaac Newton, Lord Burghley, Lord Bolingbroke, Stukeley the antiquarian, and
                    Wesley, the founder of Methodism, were, amongst many other eminent men, natives
                    of this county.</p><p>The most remarkable seats of noblemen and gentlemen are, Blankney, Charles
                    Chaplin, Esq.; Brocklesby Park, Lord Yarborough; Coleby Hall, Earl Lindsey;
                    Gautby, Robert Vener, Esq.; Grinsthorpe Castle, Lord Gwydir; Hanby Hall, Sir
                    William Manners; Harmston, Samuel Thorold, Esq.; Hainton Park, G. Heneage, Esq.;
                    Noc-ton Park, Earl of Ripon; Belton House, Lord Brownlow; Normanby Hall, Sir J.
                    Sheffield; Reevesby Abbey, late Sir Joseph Banks; Subton, Sir Robert Heron;
                    Summer Castle, Lady Wrey; Syston, Sir John Thorold; Thur-gunby, Lord
                    Middleton.</p></div></body></text></TEI>