<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0713-4361-0226-07" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">LEMONNIER, Peter (Claude)
                    Charles</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 226</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:998476">Light</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:832970">Birds</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0743s">Winds</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67d46">Quadrant</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193204361" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">LEMONNIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter (Claude)
                    Charles</hi></label>, a diligent and accurate astronomer, born at Paris, on the
                    23d of November 1715, was the son of Peter Lemonnier, of St Sever, in
                    Normandy.</p><p>His father was a professor of philosophy in the College d’Harcourt, and member of
                    the Academy of Sciences. He distinguished himself, as a teacher, by his activity
                    in promoting the introduction of mathematical reasoning into the Cartesian
                    philosophy. Under such auspices, the son might have enjoyed facilities for the
                    cultivation of any of the sciences; but he soon showed a decided preference for
                    astronomy, and began to be a practical observer before he was sixteen. In the
                    month of November 1732, Mr Fouchy procured him the use of a mural quadrant of
                    three feet radius, and he soon applied himself with diligence to the
                    determination of the sun’s greatest equation, an investigation which he
                    continued for many years; and in 1741, he found the equation to amount to 1° 55'
                    3ľ'; a quantity differing only by 7" from Delambre’s latest determination.</p><p>He presented to the Academy of Sciences, in 1735, an elaborate map of the moon,
                    accompanied by some remarks; and in the month of April of the following year,
                    before he was twenty-one years old, he was made a member of the Academy, in the
                    character of Adjunct Geometrician. He continued to be a constant contributor to
                    its Memoirs for more than fifty years. The winter of 1736 and 1737 he passed at
                    Torneo, with Clairaut and Maupertuis, as a member of a committee appointed by
                    the Academy for measuring a degree in Lapland; and he was not less zealous than
                    any of his colleagues in the execution of that arduous undertaking.</p><p>He is considered as having effected, in conjunction with Lacaille, a complete
                    reformation in the practical astronomy of France. He entered very early into
                    correspondence with the English astronomers of the day; they had carried their
                    instruments and modes of observation to a higher degree of perfection than their
                    neighbours; and Lemonnier was of great use to the science, in making known to
                    his countrymen the practical methods of Flamsteed, and in introducing the
                    instruments of Graham and Bird.' In April 1739, he was made a foreign member of
                    the Royal Society of London, and for the last twelve or fourteen years of his
                    life he is said to have been the senior member of the society. He was the first
                    that introduced the effects of nutation, then lately discovered by Bradley, into
                    the solar tables; and he complained bitterly of Lacaille’s injustice, in not
                    giving him due credit for the improvement.</p><p>The Due de Noailles made him known to the king of France, who was fond of his
                    company, and showed him many kindnesses. In 1742, he gave him apartments at the
                    Capucins in the Rue St Honoré, where he continued to live till the Revolution.
                    On another occasion, when he had taken great pains to fix an accurate meridian
                    at St Sulpice, the king made him a present of 15,000 livres, which he expended
                    in the purchase of instruments, as the greatest luxury that be was capable of
                    enjoying.</p><p>The places of the stars, which he determined in 1740, served Lalande for the
                    purpose of computing their proper motions, though they differed a little from
                    the results of Bradley’s observations. About 1746, he was much engaged in
                    examining the inequalities of Saturn, produced by the attraction of Jupiter; and
                    Euler employed his computations in the theory which obtained a prize in 1748;
                    each confirming the accuracy of the other. He continued to observe the moon,
                    without intermission, for fifty years, though a small part only of his
                    observations was published.</p><p>In the year 1748 he went to England, partly for the purpose of obtaining further
                    information from a personal acquaintance with the astronomers and opticians
                    resident in London, and partly in order to observe the solar eclipse <pb break="no" facs="nls:193204374" xml:id="kp-eb0713-4374-0227"/> of
                    that year, in a situation where it would be very nearly annular. He proceeded
                    accordingly to Scotland with the Earl of Morton, accompanied by Short the
                    optician, and they observed the eclipse together at Aberdour, an ancient
                    residence of Lord Morton’s, in Fifeshire. They obtained their time from the
                    College at Edinburgh, where there was a transit instrument, by means of the
                    flash of a cannon fired from the castle at twelve, and another five minutes
                    after. “The eclipse was so nearly annular, that, at the nearest approach, the
                    cusps seemed to want about one-seventh of the moon’s circumference to be joined;
                    yet a brown light was plainly observed, both by Lord Morton and myself,” says Mr
                    Short, “to proceed or stretch along the circumference of the moon, from each of
                    the cusps, about one third of the whole distance of the cusps from each cusp;
                    and there remained about one third of the whole distance of the cusps not
                    enlightened by this brown light, so that we were for some time in suspense
                    whether or not we were to have the eclipse annular with us. During the greatest
                    darkness, the planet Venus was seen at Edinburgh, and other places, by a great
                    number of people, but I did not hear of any other stars being seen. The darkness
                    was not great, but th© sky appeared of a faint languid colour.” In fact, our
                    mornings and evenings are always illuminated by a light, which has acquired more
                    or less of a red tinge in its oblique passage through the atmosphere; and when
                    we have a similar light without the redness, the contrast between the sensation
                    and the memory makes it appear “faint,” that is, greenish or grey, instead of
                    white. Mr Lemonnier was particularly anxious to measure the moon’s diameter,
                    which “he found 29'47∣", ’ ' agreeing precisely with the computed diameter, and
                    not requiring any correction for the supposed effects of irradiation. A similar
                    remark was made by a very accurate practical astronomer in the eclipse of
                    1820.</p><p>In order to verify the position of his mural quadrant, which was of eight feet
                    radius, and made by Bird, Lemonnier felt the advantage of having a moveable one
                    to compare with it, and he procured a block of marble eight feet by six, and
                    fifteen inches thick, turning on an axis, to which he fixed his smaller
                    instrument, of five feet radius, in order to be able to reverse its position. He
                    devoted a considerable portion of his time to the investigation of the laws of
                    magnetism, and especially to the variation of the compass; and he endeavoured to
                    ascertain the effect of the moon’s influence on the winds, and on the atmosphere
                    in general.</p><p>Lemonnier had long disputed the accuracy of the Parisian base, measured by
                    Cassini and Maraldi, but he was at last convinced that his objections were
                    groundless. He was originally a most zealous friend and patron of Lalande; but
                    afterwards, having taken offence at some slight cause, he refused to see him for
                    many years. In fact, he appears to have been somewhat obstinate and irritable;
                    but he is said to have had genius, zeal, activity, and intelligence, as well as
                    credit in the world, and reputation among men of science. He was a voluminous
                    writer; he had much learning and sagacity, but he often wanted precision in his
                    language and his reasoning. In November 1(91, he had a paralytic attack, which
                    terminated his scientific career, though he survived it till the 2d of April
                    1799, when a second stroke carried him off, at Héril, near Baieux. He was made,
                    in the mean time, one of the 14+ original members of the National Institute, as
                    a testimony to the merit of his past labours.</p><p>He had married, in 1763, Mlle, de Cussy, a lady of very respectable family in
                    Normandy. He had three daughters; the first married Mr de Parfouru, who was an
                    early victim of the Revolution; the second the celebrated Lagrange; and the
                    third her uncle, Lemonnier the physician, who was also a man of considerable
                    science, and a member of the Royal Society of London.</p><p>From 1735 to 1790, there are very few volumes of the Memoirs of the Academy
                    without one or more of Lemonnier’s papers; but though not unimportant in the
                    aggregate, they are somewhat uninteresting in the detail. They relate almost
                    exclusively to astronomical observations; eclipses, occultations, appulses,
                    oppositions, and conjunctions; solstices, longitudes and latitudes; with some
                    accounts of astronomical instruments and apparatus. There are also some memoirs
                    relating to the sun’s equation and diameter, and on his place, as compared with
                    Arcturus; on the motion of Saturn, and on his fifth satellite; on the expansion
                    of wooden measures; on the transit of Venus, and on the diameter and the tables
                    of that planet; on Euler’s formula for parallax; on the variation of the needle;
                    on lunar altitudes; on the tides; on horizontal refraction; on Saturn’s ring;
                    and on some currents of wind. He also published separately some extensive works,
                    which acquired considerable celebrity.</p><p>1. The first was his Histoire Celeste, 4to, 1741, comprehending the interval from
                    1666 to 1685, and containing an account of a transit instrument of Graham’s
                    construction.</p><p>2. Théorie des Comètes, 1743, in 8vo, including a translation of Halley’s work on
                    comets, together with a method of computing the orbit from three
                    observations.</p><p>3. Institutions Astronomiques, 4to, 1746; an improved translation of Keill’s
                    Astronomy, which long continued to be the best elementary treatise in the French
                    language. It contains also solar tables, and a variety of other additions
                    derived from observation.</p><p>4. Observations Astronomiques, part i. 1751; ii. 1754; iii. 1759; iv. 1775.</p><p>5. A Letter on the Theory of the Winds, in Halley’s Tables, published by
                    Chappe.</p><p>6. Nouveau Zodiaque, réduit à 1755, Paris, 1755, in 8vo, containing thirty-one
                    pages of charts, much more complete than those of Senex, and superseded by some
                    very late publications only.</p><p>7. A History of Astronomy in the Traité d’Aberration of Fontaine des Crutes.</p><p>8. Observations pour la Mesure du degré entre Paris et Amiens, 8vo, 1757.</p><p>9. Abrégé du Pilotage, par Goubert, 1766, in 4to, with additions.</p><p>10. Astronomie Nautique Lunaire, 8vo, 1771.</p><p>11. Exposition des Moyens les plus faciles de résoudre plusieurs questions dans
                    l’Art de la Navigation, 1772, in 8vo, employing very generally a table of verse
                    sines, and greatly recommending the use of Gunter’s scale for nautical
                    computations.</p><p>12. Essai sur les Marées, 1774, in 8vo, particularly describing the effects of
                    the tides at Mont St Michel, and on the neighbouring flat sands, and including
                    also some considerations on refraction, and on magnetism.</p><p>13. Description et Usage des principaux Instrumens d’Astronomie, 1774, folio,
                    forming part of the collection of Arts et Metiers.</p><p>14. Atlas celeste de Flamsteed, 1776, in 4to, revised.</p><p>15. Lois du Magnétisme, 2 parts, 8vo, 1776-8, with an elaborate chart.</p><p>16. Traité de la Construction de Vaisseaux, par Chapman, 1779, folio, from the
                    Swedish, and said to be less perfect than the translation of Vial du
                    Clairbois.</p><p>17. Mémoires concernant diverses questions d’Astronomie et de Physique, 4 parts,
                    1781-4-6-8, in 4to.</p><p>18. De la Correction introduite pour accourcir la Ligne sèche du Lock de dix-huit
                    pieds, 8vo, 1790.</p><p>19. Lettre au sujet d’une Eclipse, Par. 1791; together with some remarks on
                    navigation, and on the cur <pb break="no" facs="nls:193204387" xml:id="kp-eb0713-4387-0228"/>rents of the South Seas, all apparently from the
                    Memoirs of the Academy. The eclipse, which was observed as annular in China,
                    should have been total, according to the computed distance of the luminaries
                    concerned.</p></div></body></text></TEI>