<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0713-8768-0565-08" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">LOO-CHOO Islands</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 565</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn10">Loo</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039481">Norwegians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193208768" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">LOO-CHOO <hi rend="smallcaps">Islands</hi></label>, called
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lewchew</hi> by Mr Macleod, and by others <hi rend="smallcaps">Liqueo,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Lieoukiou.</hi> This group
                    of islands is situated in the Eastern Ocean, to the south of Japan, about 400 or
                    500 miles east of the Chinese coast. They were little known to Europeans until
                    they were visited by Captains Maxwell and Hall in the Alceste and Lyra in 1816,
                    on their return from conveying Lord Amherst to China. Very full accounts have
                    been published by Captain Hall and M$ Macleod of these islands, and of the
                    climate and soil, as well as of the inhabitants, who appeared to these gentlemen
                    to be extremely simple and interesting in their manners. These islands are in
                    number thirty-six; but the only one of any great extent is the</p><p>Great Loo-choo, which is thirty miles in length, and from twelve to fifteen in
                    breadth. The climate is here a happy medium between the opposite extremes of
                    heat and cold. Being situated in the middle of a vast ocean, these islands are
                    refreshed by the sea breezes, which, blowing continually over them, produce an
                    agreeable coolness. They are also well watered by small rivers and streamlets,
                    which, rising in the central eminences, flow in different directions to the sea,
                    and afford an abundant supply of excellent water. Being in the latitude of 26.
                    N., the scenery, though not quite so rich, is, according to Captain Hall, even
                    more pleasing to the eye than in countries nearer to the equator; the vegetation
                    not being so luxuriant as to overload the landscape with foliage. The style of
                    the landscape is on the whole decidedly tropical, though there is much variety;
                    and the groves of pine trees 'give some parts of the country quite a European
                    character. The orange and lime, the banyan of India, and the Norwegian fir, all
                    thrive in Loo-choo. The mode of dressing the ground at Loo-choo is very neat,
                    and resembles that of China, particularly in the process of manuring and
                    irrigation. Tobacco, wheat, rice, Indian corn, millet, sweet potatoes, brinjals,
                    and many other tropical vegetables, grow in great perfection at Loo-choo. Along
                    the sides of the hills, and around the villages, the bamboo and rattan grow to a
                    considerable size. But Captain Hall mentions that the pine was the most
                    conspicuous tree which they observed on the island, rising to a great height and
                    size. Some are forty feet in height, and three or four in girth. The cattle on
                    this island are of a small black breed, and invariably used instead of horses
                    for agricultural purposes. Hogs, goats, and poultry, with rice and a great
                    variety of vegetables, form the chief food of the inhabitants, milk being seldom
                    used. The English saw no geese on the island, nor sheep; but their horses,
                    though very small and slender, were sufficiently strong for the natives. Their
                    goats and pigs were also diminutive; but the poultry were large and excellent.
                    These islands are not infested by any wild animals. They had no carts or wheeled
                    carriages of any kind, all loads being carried by horses; and the roads, which
                    are numerous, and generally kept in excellent order, measure generally from six
                    to ten feet across.</p><p>The whole coast of Loo-choo, as well as of the other islands, is encircled with
                    coral reefs, which do not appear above water; and when the weather is calm, and
                    their situation is not pointed out by breakers, they are exceedingly dangerous
                    to mariners. The Alceste, Captain Maxwell’s ship, was several times in danger
                    from these hidden rocks. This singular formation, which appears to be extending
                    itself over the Pacific, was minutely examined by Captain Hall. After the sea
                    has left it for some time, it becomes dry, and appears to be a compact rock; but
                    no sooner does the tide rise again, and the waves begin to wash over it, than
                    millions of coral worms, protruding themselves from holes in the surface, begin
                    their operations; so that, from their prodigious numbers, the whole surface of
                    the rock appears to be alive and in motion. These insects or worms cannot raise
                    the rock above the surface of the water, and the level of the highest tide is
                    accordingly the limit of the rock upwards, after which a horizontal field comes
                    to be formed coincident with that plane, and perpendicular on all sides; and
                    thus the reef, extending itself perpendicularly, and in all directions, becomes
                    extremely dangerous to navigators. On the coast of Loo-choo there are several
                    excellent harbours, particularly one, which is capacious and safe, and affords
                    everywhere depth of water for the largest ships, with secure anchorage. Its
                    banks consist of high rocks, overgrown with climbing plants and flowers.</p><p>These islands are inhabited by a singular and apparently amiable people. They are
                    of a diminutive stature, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193208781" xml:id="kp-eb0713-8781-0566"/>not exceeding in their average height above five
                    feet two inches. But they are strong, well-made, and athletic; and in complexion
                    they are quite as fair as the natives of Spain and Portugal. They invariably
                    manifested towards their English visitors the most gentle, polite, and humane
                    dispositions, but with that jealousy of them as strangers which is peculiar to
                    China, Japan, and all the neighbouring countries. They were at first extremely
                    averse to the landing of their visitors, and it was only after long
                    deliberations that they were induced to concede the liberty of doing §o. But our
                    people were confined to a small space on the sea-shore, under a burning sun; and
                    it was only by renewed entreaties that they were allowed to extend their walks
                    into the country. The’natives, however, very freely visited the English ships,
                    and examined them carefully in all their equipmentsand detail. They accepted
                    readily the hospitality of the strangers, and conformed to their manners in
                    every thing. In their interviews they always showed a natural good breeding,
                    bowing whenever they spoke to the English, uncovering their heads in their
                    presence, and, in drinking, bowing to all around. After they had permitted the
                    English to land, many visits were paid; but they never admitted the strangers
                    into the interior of their town, and even limited their walks within a certain
                    space. Any attempt to pass these bounds was always resisted by the sentinels;
                    not, however, by force, but by a polite request, and by representing, that if
                    the orders of the court were transgressed, blame would fall upon them. Some
                    overtures were made by Captain Maxwell for an interview with the king; but these
                    were always steadily resisted, on the ground or pretence that no embassy or
                    letters were brought from the king of Eng-Iand, to whom, however, the king of
                    Loo-choo wrote a letter, which was unfortunately lost in the wreck of the
                    Alceste. It was extremely difficult to bring about any intercourse with this
                    people. Ordinary requests were made the subject of tedious negociations; and the
                    most ungracious feature in their character was their uniform aversion to any
                    intimate communication with their visitors. In one particular they manifested a
                    rigid adherence to Chinese manners; namely, in carefully withholding from the
                    view of the Europeans their women, though the latter did not appear otherwise to
                    be very closely confined. The practice of polygamy, which prevails in China, has
                    no place here, and, the English were told, was even held in abhorrence. From the
                    free intercourse also of the different sexes, the parties had opportunities of
                    being acquainted before marriage.</p><p>One of the most remarkable facts mentioned by Captain Hall is, that the natives
                    of these islands were unacquainted with the use of fire-arms. From all that the
                    English could observe, they were even ignorant of the use of money; and though
                    those amongst the natives who had visited China must have seen the currency of
                    that country, yet none of them showed any desire to possess Spanish dollars or
                    gold coins, nor could it ever be learned whether they were in possession of any
                    common medium of exchange. With regard to their want of arms, it is supposed by
                    Mr Macleod, that the Chinese, after conquering, had disarmed them. The musketry
                    and cannon of the English were objects of great wonder to them; and when they
                    saw Captain Maxwell bring down a bird on the wing, they were shocked and
                    terrified, and requested that fire-arms should not be again brought into the
                    island. When Napoleon was informed, at St Helena, that these people had neither
                    arms nor money, he ridiculed the idea as incredible and absurd, and affirmed
                    that the English had been imposed on. The result justified his penetration.
                    These people are well acquainted with both; and it is now known that,
                    notwithstanding all their fair seeming, they are about the most remorseless
                    pirates in the Yellow Sea. In their intercourse with our people, however, they
                    were remarked for their honesty; insomuch, that though they were freely admitted
                    on board of the English ships, and many valuable articles were often in their
                    way, yet nothing was ever missed.</p><p>They appear to live on social and friendly terms with one another, and have
                    frequently pic-nic parties in the fields, the dinner being carried about in
                    little japanned boxes, with sliding drawers, fastened to the end of a bamboo.
                    They entertained the English at dinner; and the meal consisted of hard-boiled
                    eggs coloured and sliced, fish dried in butter, sliced junk smoked, sliced pig’s
                    liver; then came tea, which was succeeded by an unpalatable dish of coarse,
                    soft, black sugar, wrapped up in unbaked dough. Cakes in various shapes, with
                    something like cheese, completed the entertainment; the intervals being filled
                    up with drinking sackee, and with smoking.</p><p>The Loo∙chooans appear to have made no progress in science or literature, though
                    several individuals amongst them were distinguished by the English for their
                    intelligence, and turn for inquiry. Their language is a dialect of the Japanese;
                    but they have Chinese books, which are studied by the learned. Their religion
                    seems to resemble the superstition of China; but it is remarkable that the order
                    of priests, who are generally objects of veneration in all countries, are here
                    considered as an inferior caste. All the science of these islanders is derived
                    from the Chinese. Their practice of medicine is also Chinese; and they
                    generally*administer to their patients roots, seeds, and dried flowers of the
                    country. The capital of Great Loo-choo, and of the archipelago, is situated five
                    miles from its port of Napakiang. The English were not allowed to approach it,
                    but saw it from a distance, beautifully situated on the top of a hill; the
                    houses, intermingled with the trees, rising above one another, and the royal
                    palace above the whole. When the English left these islands, the natives
                    professed the most affectionate regard for them, and expressed (with what
                    sincerity the reader may judge) the deepest regret at their departure. Long, of
                    the capital of the Great Loo-choo, 127. 52. 1. E. Lat. 26. 14. N.</p></div></body></text></TEI>