<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0713-8989-0582-03" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">LUBECK</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 582</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:950757">Hamburgers</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:958978">Holsteiners</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k675">Freedom</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193208989" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">LUBECK</label>, an independent republic in the north of
                    Germany, consisting of the city of that name, a part of the town of Bergedorf,
                    divided between Hamburg and Lubeck, and sixty-eight villages and hamlets. It
                    extends over 148 square miles, and contains 6437 houses, and 46,508 inhabitants,
                    who all profess the Lutheran religion, except 300 Calvinists, 400 Catholics, and
                    300 Jews. The income of the state amounts to L.40,000 a year, but is burdened
                    with a heavy debt of near L.300,000. It is governed by a senate of four
                    burgomasters and sixteen counsellors, with two syndics and a procurator, who,
                    though the executive power, have no votes in the senate. The lower house of
                    assembly is chosen by the twelve guilds or companies of the free burgesses. The
                    military force amounts to about 600 men of horse and foot.</p><p>The city of Lubeck, the capital of the republic, is situated in latitude 53. 50.
                    22. north, and longitude 10. 4L 32, east. It stands on a gentle elevation
                    between the rivers Trave and Wakenitz, the former of which is navigable to the
                    Baltic Sea, which it enters at Travemund, about twelve miles below the city. It
                    has good wide streets, with massive houses, built in a very antique style. At
                    present it displays a picture of decay when compared with the evident signs
                    which remain of its former prosperity. After the battle of Jena in the year
                    1806, Blucher, with the wreck of the Prussian army, took refuge within the
                    walls, and were followed by the French. A battle was fought in every street,
                    which spread horror and a degree of suffering which has never been effaced.</p><p>The French, during their possession, robbed it of all that was moveable, and the
                    trade on which it depended disappeared in the absence of the capital with which
                    it had been carried on. The number of dwelling-houses is 3070, but that of
                    inhabitants does not now exceed 23,000, a striking disproportion when the size
                    of the houses is taken into consideration. The most prominent public building is
                    the church of the holy virgin, with a magnificent altar of black marble, a most
                    curious astronomical clock, and two towers 400 feet in height. The Rathshouse,
                    in which the representatives of the Hans Towns assembled, with its extensive
                    cellars, in better times stocked with many hundred pipes of the oldest Rhenish
                    wine, all taken away by the French, is a fine old building. There is little
                    trade, the chief part of which consists in the conveyance of goods from Hamburg
                    to the ports of Sweden and Russia, and bringing back the products of those
                    countries, <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> There are some shipowners, and about
                    ninety vessels, great and small, belonging to the port of Lubeck. There are some
                    small establishments for making snuff’ and tobacco, for refining sugar, and for
                    other smaller manufactures.</p><p>Lubeck is remarkable for what it has been, rather than for what it now is. It was
                    once the head of a confederacy of cities, in which the spirit of freedom and of
                    active commerce was carried on, whilst the rest of Europe was deeply sunk in
                    military despotism and in disgraceful indolence. At that time it was respected,
                    feared, and its alliance courted, by the monarchs of the most powerful states;
                    and its powerful fleets overawed the whole of the shores of the Baltic Sea. As
                    the history of this place is curious, a few lines may be devoted to it.</p><p>It appears that in the beginning of the ninth century a tribe of Sclavonians
                    built on the little river Schwartau a fortified place to protect themselves
                    against another tribe called the Obotrittens. This was the ancient Lubeck. It
                    was, however, taken and made the residence of Henry <hi rend="underline">kin</hi> g of the Obotrittens, who continued there till 1139, when it was
                    captured and demolished, and the present city founded on the river Trave, by
                    Rudolph of Holstein, and peopled by fugitives from Westphalia and the
                    Netherlands. In the year 1158 it was transferred to Henry the Lion, duke of
                    Saxony, who granted to the city those privileges which it long enjoyed, and
                    which were gradually assumed by the other cities which had acquired
                    independence. Their naval power then rose rapidly; and a war having broke out
                    between the emperor of Germany and Henry, the citizens maintained the cause of
                    the latter with so much resolution, that, though attacked, they only submitted
                    in consequence of a treaty which insured to them all the rights and privileges
                    they had previously enjoyed. The possession of the city then became an object of
                    contest between Saxony, Holstein, and Denmark, by the last of which, in 1201,
                    Lubeck was captured; but at length, in 1226, it threw itself under the
                    protection of the empire, when Frederick the Second affirmed its freedom, and
                    instated it as an imperial city, with all the privileges of an independent
                    member of the Germanic body.</p><p>In 1241 the first alliance was formed with Hamburg, and in 1260 Bremen and other
                    free cities had become members of the confederacy, of which Lubeck was declared
                    the head, and the place of assembly of the whole representatives. This commenced
                    the flourishing period of its existence, which long continued, till all the
                    cities, excepting Lubeck, Hamburg, Bremen, and Frankfort, had been one after
                    another subjugated, and united to the dominions of the several princes by whom
                    they were surrounded. This had taken place towards the end of the sixteenth
                    century, when the trade of Lubeck took another direction; and this place, though
                    nominally the head of the remaining confederacy, was the poorest and least
                    populous of any of them. In 1802, when so many German states lost their
                    independence, Lubeck still nominally retained hers, till she fell under the
                    French yoke in the year 1806. In 1810 Lubeck was formed into a portion of the
                    French department of the Mouths of the Elbe, of which Hamburg was declared the
                    capital. After the victory of Leipzig in 1813 its freedom was restored, and
                    afterwards secured by the congress of Vienna in 1815. The restoration of its
                    ancient power is now hopeless.</p></div></body></text></TEI>