<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0862-0822-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WEATHER (7th edition, volume 21, page 822)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1213323">Aden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d278">Weather</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vc0z">Globes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864856">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173186">Weathering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173087">Weather</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=862" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WEATHER</label>. The term <hi rend="italic">weather</hi> is
                    used, in the popular sense which is commonly attached to the word, to express
                    the general condition of the atmosphere resulting from heat or cold,
                    tranquillity or commotion, dryness or humidity, in all its modifications of
                    visible and invisible vapour, together with the other variable phenomena
                    accompanying the meteorological changes which are exhibited in ceaseless
                    rotation by that great mass of attenuated matter. There being no department of
                    physical inquiry where the desire of knowledge and the gratification of a
                    rational curiosity is so constantly and inseparably connected with our personal
                    comfort, the state of the weather has, in all ages and in every country,
                    occupied a large share of the attention of naturalists, as well as of ordinary
                    observers. It is not a little remarkable, however, that notwithstanding the
                    general interest which the subject is fitted to excite, and the constant
                    attention that has been devoted to it, there is no branch of science in which,
                    with all the advantages of accurate instruments and accumulated observations,
                    there is less of systematic and well-established principles, or more of arrogant
                    and unfounded pretension. This must be ascribed, not so much to the defective
                    state of our knowledge concerning the actual condition of that portion of the
                    atmosphere which is within the immediate sphere of our observation, as to the
                    fact that the causes which contribute to produce changes in the meteorological
                    phenomena which it exhibits in some particular geographical situation,
                    frequently have their origin in regions far beyond the reach of the observer;
                    and hence predictions respecting the state of the weather must be founded more
                    upon conjectures suggested by a cautious induction than upon the indications of
                    instruments which, however well fitted to give precise and accurate information
                    respecting the condition of the surrounding air with regard to pressure,
                    temperature, or humidity, furnish no means of discovering the remote causes by
                    which that condition was produced, or may be afterwards affected and even
                    entirely subverted.</p>
                <p>It may be hoped, however, that the efforts which have been lately made for the
                    erection of magnetic and meteorological observatories in almost every important
                    station of the globe, and the liberal encouragement which has been granted by
                    the various governments of Europe for supplying these establishments with
                    suitable instruments, under the superintendence of skilful observers, will, at
                    no distant period, furnish precise and accurate data for determining the
                    simultaneous condition of the atmosphere over an extensive portion of the
                    surface of the earth, and thus enabling us to ascertain whether the
                    meteorological appearances which distinguish different seasons are altogether of
                    an anomalous character; or, otherwise, to what extent they are, like other
                    physical phenomena, the result of fixed and invariable laws, which, though
                    involved in obscurity as to their mode of action, do not fail, after a certain
                    lapse of time, to display their operation by the periodical revolutions in the
                    weather, to which they give birth.</p>
                <p>Though this country can scarcely claim the honour of having first set the example
                    to other states, of engaging with zeal and alacrity in this great and important
                    undertaking, it must be admitted that the British Association for the
                    Advancement of Science has contributed in no small degree to draw the attention
                    of other learned bodies to the subject, while it has annually devoted a
                    considerable portion of its funds to the investigation of objects which are
                    calculated to throw great light upon the leading principles of meteorology. At
                    the recommendation of that institution, the British government has established
                    magnetic and meteorological observatories at various places in the empire, as
                    well as in the colonies, particularly at Greenwich, Dublin, Plymouth, the Cape
                    of Good Hope, Van Diemen’s Land, Madras, Sincapore, Simla in the Himalaya range,
                    Aden in the Arabian Gulf, and Toronto in Canada. It has also furnished
                    instruments to the observatories established at Breslau in Prussia, at
                    Hammerfest in Norway, as well as to those established at Cairo and at Algiers.
                    The liberal and enlightened views evinced by the British government for the
                    support of these institutions have been followed by corresponding efforts on the
                    part of other civilized states; and accordingly we learn that establishments for
                    similar purposes are now fixed at St Petersburg, Kasan, Catherinehourg,
                    Barnaoul, Nicolaieff, and various other places in the Russian empire, as well as
                    at Berlin, Brussels, Copenhagen, Göttingen, Gotha, Hanover, Heidelberg, Leipzig,
                    Milan, Munich, Philadelphia, Prague, Upsala, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>It is only by the co-operation of numerous observers pursuing with regularity and
                    perseverance a system of judicious observations, at stations so remote from each
                    other, that we can obtain, in the first place, an accurate register of the
                    meteorological phenomena which are connected with geographical position, and be
                    afterwards enabled to apply suitable equations to the general laws by which
                    these phenomena are regulated, for the purpose of adapting them to the local
                    peculiarities which distinguish the climates of particular places. Many years
                    may be necessary for the full development of these laws; but already have the
                    magnetic observations recorded at stations separated widely by distance
                    indicated the existence and operation of a diffusive principle, probably of a
                    thermo-electric character, which, exerting its influence in the bowels of the
                    earth, is capable of producing contemporaneous magnetic effects of the most
                    palpable kind at the surface. The relation subsisting between caloric and the
                    distribution of the electric fluid may lead us to expect from these observations
                    new discoveries respecting the mysterious laws which govern the periodical and
                    secular changes of terrestrial temperature that have so long perplexed
                    geologists, and may thus authorize us to anticipate some of the great thermal
                    revolutions to which our globe is from time to time exposed. For further
                    information on this subject, the reader may consult the articles <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Barometer, Climate, Clouds, Colo, Evaporation, Hygrometry,
                    Meteorology, Temperature, (v. v. v.</hi>)</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=863"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0863-0823"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
