<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0823-0783-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WASHINGTON, George (7th edition, volume 21, page
                    783)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09w92">Addresses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874582">Conducting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=823" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WASHINGTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>, the
                    first president of the United States, was born in the year 1732, in the parish
                    of Washington, in Virginia. He was descended from an ancient family in Cheshire,
                    of which a branch was established in Virginia about the middle of the
                    seventeenth century. Little is known concerning his education, or the early
                    years of his life. Before he was twenty years of age, he was appointed a major
                    in the colonial militia, and had then an opportunity of displaying those
                    military and political talents which have since rendered his name so famous
                    throughout the world. In the disputes which arose between the French and English
                    officers, about settling the limits of Canada and Louisiana, Major Washington
                    was employed by the governor of Virginia as a negotiator, and he succeeded in
                    preventing a threatened invasion of the English frontiers by tire French and
                    their Indian allies; but in the following year, when hostilities seemed
                    inevitable, he was appointed lieutenant-colonel, and soon after to the command
                    of a regiment raised by the colony for its own defence. In 1755, Colonel
                    Washington served as a volunteer in the unfortunate expedition of General
                    Braddock; and in that expedition, which was attended with great difficulty, he
                    exhibited so much calmness and intrepidity, that the utmost confidence was
                    reposed in his talents, and perfect obedience paid to his commands, by the whole
                    army. After having been employed in a different and more successful expedition,
                    to the river Ohio, the state of his health required him, about the year 1758, to
                    resign his military situation; and in the sixteen following years, durring which
                    period he married Mrs Custis, a Virginian lady of amiable character and
                    respectable connections, it would appear that he resided chiefly at his
                    beautiful seat of Mount Vernon, and was occupied in the cultivation of his
                    estate.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=824"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0824-0784"/>
                <p>When the disaffection of the Americans to the British government had become
                    pretty general, and had at last spread to the colony of Virginia, Colonel
                    Washington was appointed a delegate from that state to the congress which met at
                    Philadelphia on the 26th October 1774; and soon after he was appointed to the
                    command of the American army, which had assembled in the provinces of New
                    England. The conduct of Washington during the whole of the war, as well as
                    during the period when he presided in the government of the United States, has
                    been so fully detailed in other parts of this work, that it would be unnecessary
                    repetition even to give a general outline of it in this place.</p>
                <p>Washington resigned the presidency in 1796, after having published a farewell
                    address to his countrymen. This address was remarkably distinguished for the
                    simplicity and ingenuousness, moderation and sobriety, the good sense, prudence,
                    and honesty, as well as sincere affection for his country and for mankind, which
                    the author of it had always exhibited. It seemed to be a perfect picture of his
                    whole life. From the time of his resignation till the month of July 1798, he
                    lived in retirement at his seat of Mount Vernon. At this period, when the
                    unprincipled actors in the French revolution were carrying on their wicked
                    machinations in every part of the world to which their influence extended, the
                    United States resolved to arm by land and sea in their own defence. General
                    Washington was called from his retirement, and the command of the army was
                    bestowed upon him. This he accepted, because he considered, as he himself
                    expressed it, “every thing we hold dear and sacred was seriously threatened,
                    although he had flattered himself that he had quitted for ever the boundless
                    field of public action, incessant trouble, and high responsibility, in which he
                    had long acted so conspicuous a part.” In this situation he continued during the
                    remaining short period of his life. On Thursday the 12th of December 1799, he
                    was seized with an inflammation in the throat, and was carried off on Saturday
                    the 14th of the same month, in the sixty-eighth year of his age. In his dying
                    moments he displayed the same calmness, simplicity, and regularity, which had
                    uniformly marked his conduct through life. He saw the approaches of death
                    without fear, and he met them without parade. The well-ordered state of his
                    private affairs bore the stamp of that constant authority of prudence and
                    practical reason over his actions which was always the most prominent feature of
                    his character. His name will ever be remembered by, and precious to, all
                    wellwishers of mankind and of liberty, as that of the most prudent commander and
                    the most virtuous ruler that history has recorded. His life has been written by
                    Marshall, chief justice of America, and by Mr Sparks; and his state-papers have
                    been published, with an eloquent eloge, by Μ. Guizot.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
