<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0458-0428-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TURNING</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066737">Plate</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066824">Plating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1083789">Pulleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1894461">Mandrill</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829528">Beds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn8h">Plate</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n3s">Pulleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0648s">Chucks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=458" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">TURNING</label>, the art of giving circular and
                    other forms to objects, by making them revolve in various manners in a machine
                    called a lathe, and applying cutting instruments so as to produce the form
                    required; or by making the cutting instrument revolve, when the object to be
                    operated upon is fixed.</p>
                <p part="N">This art is of great antiquity, and is of immense importance to the
                    practical mechanic. It embraces many varieties requiring varied machinery for
                    their proper performance, from the simple throwing wheel of the potter to the
                    complicated and nearly automatic slide-lathe, in which, almost independent of
                    manual dexterity, an indefinite number of copies of an article can be produced
                    with unerring accuracy.</p>
                <p part="N">There is probably, in the range of mechanical operation, none
                    susceptible of greater accuracy than the art of turning, and there is none which
                    has so much conduced to the improvement of our machinery. The extent of the
                    applications of this art may be learned by the four following conditions, which
                    comprise the most important of its varieties. A knowledge of the manipulations
                    no mere description can convey; and as, in the limits here assigned us, it would
                    be impossible to describe all the varieties of the art, and the machines made
                    use of, we shall content ourselves with such a selection as may appear to us to
                    possess the greatest interest for the general reader.</p>
                <p part="N">1st. The article to be turned may be made to revolve round its own axis,
                    and the cutting tool applied to its surface, so as to produce the requisite
                    form, as in simple turning, performed in the ordinary lathe used by
                    cabinet-turners; the more powerful lathe used for turning metal of large
                    diameter; and the self-acting slide-lathe.</p>
                <p part="N">2d. The article may remain stationary, while the cutting instrument
                    either merely revolves, or, while revolving, has at the same time some other
                    motion given to it.</p>
                <p part="N">3d. The article may be made to move in some curve derived from circular
                    motion, and the cutting tool applied as before.</p>
                <p part="N">4th. The article may be made to revolve, and at the same time to have a
                    reciprocating motion in the direction of its axis, the cutting instrument being
                    only applied, however, while the article is either in the course of its forward
                    or backward motion, but its application not continued through both; and all
                    these motions may be more or less combined, thus producing almost infinite
                    variety.</p>
                <p part="N">The self-acting slide-lathe being the most perfect of the machines of
                    the first class, we have preferred giving a drawing and description of it; from
                    these, the other lathes referred to will be more easily understood than if we
                    had described a less perfect machine. The lathe, when of large size, is
                    generally driven by steam or other power; but when small it is driven by a
                    treadle put in motion by the foot of the workman. The treadle acts on a cranked
                    axle, on which is fixed a fly-wheel; and a band from the fly-wheel passes over
                    the pulley of the mandril or spindle, to which the article to be turned is
                    attached. This is generally the arrangement of the common lathe, which differs
                    from the slide-lathe only in wanting the slide and its moving apparatus, which
                    we are about to describe, and has in place of it a simple rest to work by
                    hand.</p>
                <p part="N">The following figures represent the slide-lathe as constructed by Messrs
                    Whitworth &amp; Company of Manchester, and exhibit certain contrivances which
                    have been patented by these gentlemen.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=459"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0459-0429"/>
                <p part="N">the same parts in all the figures. A A is a strong framing, which
                    supports the bed of the lathe B B. At the left-hand extremity of the bed is
                    fixed the head C C, and through steel bushes in the tiprights, or puppets as
                    they are termed, the spindle or mandril D works; the projecting right hand end
                    of the mandril is screwed, so that chucks and other apparatus for holding the
                    work to be turned may be attached to it. One of these, the double driver, will
                    be found figured and described afterwards. In brackets projecting backwards from
                    the uprights another spindle E works. One of the brackets and the end of the
                    spindle are seen in fig. 2. On the main spindle D there is a conical pulley F,
                    carrying a pinion on its smaller end; the pulley with its pinion turns on the
                    spindle, hut independently of it. To the right of the pulley is a spur-wheel H,
                    keyed on the spindle; to this spur-wheel the pulley can be locked at pleasure,
                    so as to be carried round along with it. On the spindle E is a spur-wheel G and
                    a pinion, which cannot be seen in the drawing. These are fitted respectively to
                    gear with the spur-wheel and pulley-pinion of the main spindle. Different
                    materials require to pass the cutting tool with different degrees of rapidity,
                    in order to be efficiently operated upon. Cast iron requires to revolve slowly,
                    so that it may come in contact with the cutting tool at the rate of about 100
                    feet per minute; wrought iron and steel about twice as quick; and brass is
                    better cut at a still higher velocity. Thus, it is required that provision be
                    made in the lathe for altering the speed, independently of the velocity of the
                    prime mover. It is obvious, too, that the same material must require a change in
                    the speed of the lathe, according to its diameter, that a uniform rate of speed
                    may be maintained by its surface. This alteration in the velocity of the spindle
                    or mandril is produced by the pulley and wheels we have just described, in the
                    following manner :—When the belt from the prime mover, acting on the pulley F,
                    causes it to revolve, if a slow motion be required, the pinion of the pulley is
                    made to gear with the spur-wheel I of the spindle E; and the pinion fixed on the
                    same spindle gearing into the spur-wheel H of the main spindle D, causes it to
                    revolve with a motion slow as compared with the speed of the pulley. If a higher
                    velocity be required, the wheel and pinion of the spindle E are put out of gear
                    with the pinion and wheel of the main spindle by sliding the spindle E a little
                    to the left hand, and then locking together the pulley and spur-wheel H, so as
                    to cause the main spindle to turn directly by the pulley.</p>
                <p part="N">The face of the spur-wheel H has drawn on it a great number of
                    concentric circles. The circumference of each circle is divided into equal
                    parts, and such numbers are chosen for the division as are multiples of the
                    greatest variety of measures; at each division of the circles there is pierced a
                    hole, into which a point is pressed by a spring. By means of this apparatus, an
                    object in the lathe can have its surface divided into any number of equal parts.
                    On the end of the main spindle is fixed a pinion K, which, by the intervention
                    of the stud-wheels and pinion L, drives the spur-wheel M, fixed on the end of a
                    screw N, which extends along the whole length of the lathe, and is called the
                    leading screw. The ends of the leading screws and main spindle are made
                    accurately of the same size, so that the wheels and pinions which have for
                    different purposes to be fixed on them may be exchangeable. On the right hand
                    side of the lathe is seen the shifting-head or puppet O, which is capable of
                    being shifted along to any part of the bed, and fixed there, and which carries
                    the centre pin. This is adjusted more nicely to its work by means of a screw
                    turned by the wheel P, and it is fixed by the clamping screw Q. The slide-rest
                    consists of an upper and an under slide: the latter lies across the bed, and is
                    moved along it lengthways by means of the leading screw. The upper slide can
                    move at right angles to the under one, and carries the cutting tools: the manner
                    in which the slides are moved by the leading screw is, in this lathe, very
                    ingenious. From the under slide there descends a short vertical spindle,
                    carrying on its lower extremity a peculiarly-formed pinion β, which is
                    constantly in gear with the leading screw. When the leading screw is in motion
                    and the pinion fixed, the latter serves as a nut or female screw, and the slide
                    is moved along the bed of the lathe to the right or to the left as the screw may
                    be turned. On the upper end of the vertical spindle there is fixed a mitred
                    wheel <hi rend="italic">b</hi>: into this a pinion <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                    works, whose spindle crosses the slide, and has a handle <hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi> fixed to it. On the slide having reached one or other extremity of
                    the bed of the lathe, it may be carried to the other by reversing the motion of
                    the screw; but it is more speedily done by turning the handle <hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi> which turns the pinion <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> and so the slide is
                    carried along very rapidly.</p>
                <p part="N">The upper slide is moved across the bed of the lathe as follows: A
                    pinion <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> which works into the mitred wheel of the
                    vertical spindle, is fixed on the end of a shaft <hi rend="italic">f</hi>, on
                    whose other end is fixed the wheel <hi rend="italic">g</hi>; this gears into
                    another wheel Λ, fixed on the end of a leading screw, which crosses the main
                    leading screw, and, by means of an apparatus similar to that above described,
                    causes the upper slide to move at right angles to the under one. In fig. 3 the
                    under slide is represented as fixed in its position by means of a clamp, whose
                    handle is seen at <hi rend="italic">k</hi> in fig. 1, and the main leading screw
                    is, by means of the pinion <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> the mitred wheel <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi>, and the pinion and wheels <hi rend="italic">e</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">g, h</hi>, working the cross leading screw of the upper
                    slide, by which it is moved across the bed of the lathe.</p>
                <p part="N">In plain cylindrical turning, the motion of the slide is so adjusted in
                    relation to the motion of the article operated upon, that the cutter carried by
                    the slide shall not move over a space greater than the breadth of its point in
                    the lime that the article makes one revolution. In screw-turning, the cutter
                    again is made to travel over a space as much greater than the breadth of its
                    point during one revolution of the spindle, as the pitch of the screw requires.
                    The requisite changes in the motion are effected by changing the wheels on the
                    ends of the main spindle and the leading screw.</p>
                <p part="N">On the mandril nose there is represented, in fig. 1, what is called a
                    double driver, and we here give the details of an excellent apparatus of this
                    kind, invented by Mr Joseph Clement of London, by which an article can be fixed
                    perfectly true between the centres of the lathe. The figures and description are
                    from the Transactions of the Society of Arts of London, vol. xlvii.</p>
                <p part="N">“Fig. 4 is a side or edge view of the chuck; and fig. 5 is a face or
                    front view. The same letters refer to the same part in both views.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">“a a</hi> is a circular plate or chuck, on the back of
                    which is formed a boss <hi rend="italic">b</hi>: the boss ⅛ contains a female
                    screw for screwing it on the nose of the lathe-mandril. On the face of the chuck
                    or plate <hi rend="italic">a a,</hi> and in the middle, is screwed a conical
                    centre <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> on which is supported one end of the thing to
                    be turned, as shewn at <hi rend="italic">d</hi> in fig. 4. <hi rend="italic">e
                        e</hi> is a parallel plate in the form of a cross, one side of which is
                    fitted to the face of the chuck <hi rend="italic">a a;</hi> in the middle of the
                    horizontal arms of the plate <hi rend="italic">e e</hi> are two oblong holes <hi
                        rend="italic">f f,</hi> as represented by the dotted lines in fig. δ; <hi
                        rend="italic">g g</hi> are two screws which pass through the holes <hi
                        rend="italic">ff,</hi> and screw into the face of the chuck <hi
                        rend="italic">a a;</hi> the necks of the screws <hi rend="italic">g g</hi>
                    are made to fit the holes <hi rend="italic">f f</hi> in one direction, but the
                    plate <hi rend="italic">e e</hi> is at liberty to slide to and fro beneath the
                    heads of the screws <hi rend="italic">g g</hi> in the contrary direction: there
                    are also thin washers beneath the heads of the screws <hi rend="italic">g
                        g,</hi> which act as springs, and tend to hold the plate <hi rend="italic">e
                        e</hi> in the situation wherever it may be slid to; there is also an oblong
                    hole in the middle of the plate <hi rend="italic">e e</hi>, through which
                    projects the centre <hi rend="italic">c:</hi> in the vertical arms of the cross
                    or plate <hi rend="italic">e e</hi> are six screwed holes; <hi rend="italic"
                        >h</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i</hi> are two studs or drivers, which may be
                    screwed into any of the holes marked <hi rend="italic">j</hi>, so as to
                    accommodate the length of the ends of the carrier <hi rend="italic">k.</hi>
                    There is a face view of the carrier *, represented in its place (by dotted lines
                    on the face of the plate, <hi rend="italic">e e,</hi> fig. 5). The ends of the
                    carrier are acting against the studs Λ and ».</p>
                <p part="N">“Supposing a piece of metal d, to be supported between the centre <hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi> of the chuck <hi rend="italic">a a</hi> and the centre
                    of the puppet-head of the lathe, and the carrier <hi rend="italic">k</hi> to be
                    fixed on one end of it, as shewn in fig. 4: let the plate <hi rend="italic">e
                        e</hi> (see fig, 5) be slid on the face of the chuck <hi rend="italic">a
                        a.</hi> a little towards the left hand; then the stud <hi rend="italic"
                        >h</hi> will cause the upper end of the carrier <hi rend="italic">k</hi> to
                    move or turn in the same direction upon the centre <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> But
                    the stud <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, and the lower end of the carrier <hi
                        rend="italic">k,</hi> will be moved in contrary directions, and will be
                    separated from each other double the distance that the plate <hi rend="italic">e
                        c</hi> lias slid on the face of the chuck <hi rend="italic">a a;</hi>
                    therefore, should the plate <hi rend="italic">c e</hi> be in the above position,
                    and the lathe put in motion, so as to turn the plate <hi rend="italic">a a</hi>
                    round to. wards the left hand, the stud or driver <hi rend="italic">h</hi> would
                    be the first that would come in contact with the carrier <hi rend="italic"
                        >k</hi>. But when the turning-tool is applied to the thing to be turned, or
                    any resistance which tends to prevent it from turning round, the carrier <hi
                        rend="italic">k</hi> will cause the upper stud Λ and the plate <hi
                        rend="italic">e e,</hi> together with the stud <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, to
                    be slid towards the left hand till the stud <hi rend="italic">i</hi> comes in
                    contact with the lower end of the carrier <hi rend="italic">k;</hi> then the
                    studs or drivers <hi rend="italic">h</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i</hi> will be
                    acting with equal force against the ends of the carrier <hi rend="italic"
                        >k,</hi> which will remove the greatest part of the twist or strain from the
                    centre <hi rend="italic">e</hi> of the chuck <hi rend="italic">a a,</hi> by
                    which means any slender cylinder, &amp;c. may be turned more perfectly than can
                    be done by a single driver. If another stud be screwed into one of the holes
                    opposite the drivers <hi rend="italic">h</hi> or <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, it
                    will prevent the thing to be turned from overrunning itself, or back-lashing,
                    when it has got a heavyside. The drivers <hi rend="italic">h</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">i</hi> may be made of different lengths, as may be found most
                    convenient.”</p>
                <p part="N">When it is required to replace in the lathe an article whose <pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=460"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0460-0430"/>centres have been lost, a simple apparatus,
                    called a boring collar, is made use of. It consists of a puppet, capable of
                    being fixed on the bed of the lathe, in the same manner as the puppet O, fig. 1,
                    and as a substitute for it. On the right hand side of this is fixed, by a bolt
                    through its centre, a disc of cast iron, which has been turned perfectly flat,
                    and which is of as large diameter as the height of the puppet above the bed will
                    admit. On this disc a circle is traced, the highest point of it being exactly
                    level with the centre of the mandril; and all round the circle are bored holes,
                    varying in their dimensions, to suit the different sizes of the objects which
                    require to be centred. The disc moving round on the bolt by which it is attached
                    to the puppet, the hole suitable for the article to be centred is turned
                    uppermost, so as to be on a line with the mandril, and the disc is then fixed in
                    that position by another bolt or pin, which is passed into a hole in the puppet
                    below the centre, through one of another inner series of holes in the plale,
                    which correspond to those above described.</p>
                <p part="N">The slide-lathe which we have described is one well adapted for the
                    machinist; but for particular uses, certain modifications are made in the
                    apparatus: of these we shall immediately speak. In the mean time we may observe,
                    that a very useful arrangement of the slide-lathe has been made by Mr C. D. May
                    of Edinburgh. In his lathe the slide works, not on the top of the bed, but along
                    its face: it thus can pass from end to end clear of the puppets, and the lathe
                    can at once be converted into an ordinary one to work by hand, by moving the
                    slide to the right hand extremity of the lathe, clear of the shifting puppet,
                    and applying the ordinary rest to work by hand. This lathe is very neat, is
                    simple in construction, and occupies little space</p>
                <p part="N">The modifications in the slide-rest are as follows: The upper slide, in
                    place of being able to move at right angles only to the lower rest, may have
                    other motions given to it. It may be made to turn round on a centre, and, by an
                    index and graduated arc, may be set at any angle to the axis of the mandril. In
                    this way it is used for turning conical work. The rest may be made, too, to
                    receive cutting instruments, to which circular motion may be given, while the
                    article operated upon remains stationary, as mentioned in the second division of
                    the subject.</p>
                <p part="N">In this case a frame is added to the lathe, consisting of two uprights,
                    one at each end, carrying a series of pulleys put in motion by bells from the
                    fly-wheel, and which again, by means of a band, give motion to a pulley fixed on
                    the end of a revolving cutter, carried by the slide. It will at once be seen,
                    that when an article is held in a chuck on the end of the mandril, and turned
                    round, so as, by means of the divided circles on the spur-wheel face, to present
                    any number of sides to the action of the revolving cutter, and when the cutter
                    itself can, by means of the double slides and turning motion, be set in almost
                    any position relative to the work, the variety of uses of which this arrangement
                    is susceptible is almost infinite. Holes may be bored with it radiating from the
                    axis of a cylinder, as for the spokes of a wheel: they may be bored in a
                    straight line, or in a helical line; continuous grooves may be formed in any
                    direction. By using proper cutters, any of the geometrical solids may be formed
                    in the lathe. A very obvious application of this apparatus is to the cutting of
                    the teeth of wheels, either direct or oblique. Suppose that it is required to
                    cut a wheel of ninety teeth: a circle in the dividing plate on the face of the
                    spur-wheel, containing ninety holes, or any multiple of that number, is
                    selected, and the spring pointer being fixed in the first hole, a proper cutter,
                    fixed on a vertical spindle, is made to act on the wheel, and to cut out the
                    first tooth to the proper depth: it is then withdrawn, and the mandril is turned
                    round until the pointer falls into the second hole of the dividing plate; the
                    cutter is again applied for the second tooth, and so on successively for all of
                    them In what we have described we have supposed the work to be fixed to the
                    mandril of the lathe, and the cutting instruments attached to the slide; but the
                    case may be reversed, and thence arises a new variety of applications. A
                    circular saw being fixed on the mandril, an article held in the slide-rest may
                    be presented to it, so as to be cut in any plane. Large drills, too, may be
                    carried by the mandril, and the work to be bored fixed to the slide.</p>
                <p part="N">To the other varieties of the art the term of ornamental turning or
                    engine-turning is generally applied. Among these are rosette turning, eccentric
                    turning, elliptic turning, epicycloidal turning, and spiral turning. The lathe
                    for the first of these has this peculiarity. The head on the left, in place of
                    being fixed firm on the bed, stands between centres parallel to the spindle at
                    the level of the bed. It is kept in its proper position by the adjusted pressure
                    of four springs, one of which is fixed at each side of the front and back
                    puppet. On the spindles are fixed the rosettes, from which the lathe derives its
                    peculiar motion. These rosettes consist of wheels, discs, or portions of
                    cylinders, having their surface indented in various forms. Fixed parallel to the
                    spindle, but at a lower level, is the bar on which the rubbing apparatus is
                    fixed; the rubber, being placed in contact with one of the rosettes, and
                    incapable of yielding to the inequalities of its surface, forces the spindle on
                    which the rosettes are placed, and consequently the article operated on, to move
                    in various regular curves, as the indentations on the rosette guide them. The
                    rosette may be applied to elliptical turning by using a proper chuck, as
                    described under that head. For vertical waved lines, a pinion is fixed on the
                    head of the spindle, working a rack attached to a vertical slide fixed in the
                    front puppet; to counterbalance the slide, a cord is attached to its top, passed
                    over a pulley above, and attached to a weight at its other extremity; thus the
                    pinion is relieved from unnecessary friction.</p>
                <p part="N">In eccentric turning, an eccentric chuck is used. This consists of a
                    solid circular plate, which is fixed to the mandril of the lathe. On the face of
                    the plate are fixed two guides, so as to form a dovetailed slide for another
                    plate, which is moved by a screw sunk in a slot in the under plate. On the upper
                    plate is a circular toothed plate, which is capable of being turned round its
                    centre, and is retained in any position by a catch, which falls between its
                    teeth, and is held by a spring. On the centre of this wheel is fixed a screw
                    similar to that on the nose of the mandril, and to this is chucked the work to
                    be turned. The first plate moves, of course, concentric with the s indie of the
                    lathe; but the slide, with its circular plate, can be moved so that the work
                    revolves with any degree of eccentricity required.</p>
                <p part="N">Epicycloidal turning is another beautiful variety of the art. Like
                    eccentric turning, this is performed by a chuck peculiarly formed, but so
                    complicated as to be totally unintelligible without the aid of numerous figures;
                    we are under the necessity, therefore, of referring the reader to the works
                    quoted at the end of the article for a full explanation of it. In Bergeron’s
                    work, he will find beautiful engravings of the apparatus for this and the other
                    varieties of ornamental turning, with minute descriptions.</p>
                <p part="N">Elliptic turning will be found described under that title.</p>
                <p part="N">The lathe for spiral turning is constructed as follows. On a shaft lying
                    above the bed are three drums, or large wheels, with broad rims, that on the
                    extreme left being smaller than the other two. To the circumference of the
                    latter is attached a cord, which is stretched tight to the end of a strong
                    elastic beam or spring fixed at the roof. On the bed, beneath this drum, is the
                    fixed head, which consists of two puppets fixed at about two and a half feet
                    asunder. In the top of each puppet is fixed a brass bush, in which the spindle,
                    which is perfectly cylindrical, moves as directed by the leading screw,
                    consisting of a cylinder of wood, firmly fixed on the spindle between the two
                    puppets, on which is grooved out a screw of the same pitch as that required to
                    be made. This is effected by placing beneath, and close to the cylinder, a wheel
                    having a thin, round, or pointed edge, and turning on centres in a forked frame,
                    after the manner of a framed pulley. The frame of this wheel is fixed on a stiff
                    centre, so as to be capable of being set to any angle. If the spindle be then
                    caused to revolve, it will also move in a longitudinal direction, in exact
                    proportion to the divergence from a right angle, at which the wheel is set. and
                    there will be traced on the cylinder a screw, which, when cut to fit the edge of
                    the wheel, is a leading screw. These leading screws may be multiplied
                    indefinitely, by shifting the wheel to different angles, to mark a y number of
                    cylinders or leading screws that may be required. On the spindle at the front of
                    the leading screw is a wooden pulley, round which passes the cord which conies
                    down from the large drum on the left; it then passes down and is fixed to the
                    left corner of the treadle, the other end of which is raised by a cord passing
                    straight from its extremity to the large drum on the other end of the shaft. By
                    pressing down the treadle, the cord, which. as before remarked, passes round the
                    pulley on the spindle, causes it to revolve; it also, by unwinding from the
                    drums, causes them and their shaft to revolve, and the smaller drum, as it
                    revolves, warps round it the cord attached to the spring in the roof, thereby
                    bending it. It is evident that, whenever the pressure of the foot on the treadle
                    is removed, the elasticity of the spring will cause it to pull off the cord
                    which held it down, and cause the small drum round which the cord was wound, and
                    the other drums, and the spindle, to revolve in the opposite direction to that
                    caused by the descent of the treadle.</p>
                <p part="N">The shift ng head consists of two puppets and a spin&lt;lle. the same as
                    that just described for the fixed head. Solid on the head of each spindle is a
                    socket or hollow cylinder, in which is fixed, by means of a side-screw or
                    otherwise, a strong taper screw: one of these screws is inserted into each end
                    of the piece of wood to be turned. The rest has a groove, through which the tool
                    passes, in order to prevent the longitudinal motion from displacing it. It is
                    evident that no more length of twisted work can be produced at once than the
                    length of the leading screw: but by shilling the rest, and taking care that the
                    cuts join accurately, the twist or <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=461" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0461-0431"
                    />screw may be continued to any desired length. By means of this lathe, every
                    variety of twisted work can be produced.</p>
                <p part="N">The reciprocating motion of the spindle may be varied by the
                    introduction of other apparatus for its introduction than the screw we have
                    described. By means of elliptical or other rubbers placed at the extremity of
                    the spindle, singular compound motions are produced; and when with these are
                    combined rubbers to cause lateral motion, as in the rosette lathe, an immense
                    variety of beautiful and fanciful figures is the result.</p>
                <p part="N">For full information on lathes and turning, the reader may consult the
                    Transactions of the various societies, and the following works: L’Art de
                    Tourner, par Charles Plumier, Lyons, 1701: L’Art de Tourner, par Paulin
                    Desormeux, Paris, 1824; Manuel du Tourneur, par Bergeron, Paris, 1816;
                    Ibbetson’s Specimens of Eccentric Circular Turning.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
