<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0112-0094-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAWING</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1164604">Vats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837824">Bran</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=112" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">TAWING</label>, the art of dressing skins in white,
                    so as to render them fit for divers manufactures, particularly gloves, &amp;c.
                    All skins may be tawed; but those chiefly used for this purpose are lamb, sheep,
                    kid, and goat skins. The method of tawing is this. The skins having been cleared
                    of wool or hair by means of lime, are laid in a large vat of wood or stone, set
                    on the ground, full of water, in which quicklime has been slaked; where they are
                    allowed to lie a month or six weeks, according as the weather is more or less
                    hot, or as the skins are required to be more or less soft and pliant. While they
                    are in the vat, the water and lime are changed twice, and the skins arc taken
                    out and put in again every day; and when they are taken out for the last time,
                    they are laid all night to soak in a running water, that the greatest part of
                    the lime may be removed; and in the morning are laid together by sixes one upon
                    another, upon a wooden leg, and are scraped stoutly one after another, to get
                    the flesh off from the fleshy side, with a cutting two-handled instrument called
                    a knife; and then they cut off the legs and other superfluous parts about the
                    extremes. They are afterwards laid in a vat or pit with a little water, where
                    they are fulled with wooden pestles for the space of a quarter of an hour; and
                    then the vat is filled up with water, with which they are rinsed.</p>
                <p part="N">In the next place, they are thrown on a clean pavement to drain, and
                    afterwards cast into a fresh pit of water, out of which they rinse them well;
                    and they are again laid on the wooden leg, six at a time, with the hair side
                    outermost: after which they rub a kind of whetstone very briskly, to soften and
                    fit them to receive four or five more preparations, given them on the leg both
                    on the flesh side and hair side, with the knife, after the manner above
                    mentioned. After this they are put into a pit of water and wheaten bran, and
                    stirred about in it with wooden poles till the bran is perceived to stick to
                    them, and then they are left. As they rise of themselves to the top of the water
                    by a kind of fermentation, they are plunged down again to the bottom; and at the
                    same time fire is set to the liquor, which bums as easily as if it were brandy,
                    but goes out the moment the skins are all covered. They repeat this operation as
                    often as the skins rise above the water; and when they have done with rising
                    they take them out, lay them on the wooden leg, the fleshy side outwards, and
                    pass the knife over them to scrape off the bran.</p>
                <p part="N">Having thus cleared them of the bran, they lay the skins in a large
                    basket, and load them with huge stones to promote the draining; and when they
                    are drained sufficiently, they give them their feeding, which is performed after
                    the manner following. For 100 of large sheep-skins, and for smaller in
                    proportion, they take eight pounds of alum and three of sea-salt, and melt the
                    whole with water in a vessel over the fire, pouring the solution out, while yet
                    lukewarm, into a kind of trough, in which are twenty pounds of the finest
                    wheat-flour, with the yolks of eight dozen of eggs; of all which is formed a
                    kind of paste, a little thicker than children’s pap. This, when prepared, is put
                    into another vessel to be used in the following manner. They pour a quantity of
                    hot water into the trough in which the paste was made, mixing two spoonfuls of
                    the paste with it; to do which they use a wooden spoon that contains just as
                    much as is required for a dozen of skins; and when the whole is well diluted,
                    two dozen of the skins are plunged into it; but they take care that the water be
                    not too hot, which would spoil the paste and burn the skins. After they have
                    lain some time in the trough, they are taken out, one after another, with the
                    hand, and are stretched out. This they do twice; and after they have given them
                    all their paste, they put them into tubs, and there full them afresh with wooden
                    pestles. They then put them into a vat, where they are suffered to lie for five
                    or six days, or more; after which they take them out in fair weather, and hang
                    them to dry on cords or racks; and the quicker they are dried the better; for if
                    they are too long in drying the salt and alum within them are apt to make them
                    rise in a grain, which is an essential fault in this kind of dressing.</p>
                <p part="N">When the skins are dry, they are made up into bundles, and just dipt in
                    fair water, and taken out and drained: they are then thrown into an empty tub;
                    and after having lain some time are taken out and trampled under foot. They then
                    draw them over a flat iron instrument, the top of which is round like a
                    battledore, and the bottom fixed into a wooden block, to stretch and open them;
                    and having been opened, they are hung in the air upon cords to dry; and being
                    dry, they are opened a second time, by passing them again over the same
                    instrument. In the last place, they are laid on a table, pulled out, and laid
                    smooth, and are then fit for sale.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=113"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0113-0095"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
