<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-3176-0258-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARRIAGE (7th edition, volume 14, page 258)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002186">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026687">Mosaics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026685">Mosaicism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876969">Contracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd88">Contractions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795945">Contracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c21">Mosaics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m3337r">Civilization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194203176?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARRIAGE</label> is a contract entered into between two
                    persons of different sexes, with a view to one undivided state or society for
                    life. It has its origin in the constitution, and is nearly coeval with the
                    history, of man; and the first occasion of its occurrence is represented to us
                    in holy writ as having taken place under the immediate direction of the All-wise
                    Creator. It is, therefore, in a peculiar sense, an institution of divine
                    providence; and all the positive laws of man for the regulation of marriage
                    should intend and operate its maintenance and protection.</p>
                <p>To constitute a valid marriage with us, it is necessary that the parties should
                    lie under no disability preventing them from entering into the contract; that
                    they should be willing to contract; and that the contract should actually be
                    completed.</p>
                <p>Consent is obviously essential to marriage. Those, therefore, who are incapable
                    of consent are of course incapable of marriage; and so idiots are incapable of
                    marriage, and lunatics, except during a lueid interval. With regard to the
                    employment of force to effectuate a union, it is utterly subversive of society,
                    and must be everywhere regarded as a high crime. The language itself bears
                    testimony to the same fact, license and desire being pre-eminently sexual
                    license and sexual desire, as if licentiousness and lust were the parents of all
                    moral and social disorder.</p>
                <p>Incapacity to consent may be conceived to include under it another disability,
                    namely, want of age and immaturity of judgment, the usual attendant on early
                    years. But this has another foundation, namely, physical immaturity; and upon
                    these two grounds it has been the policy of most nations to disallow the
                    marriage of infants. Eighteen and twenty were the usual ages of marriage for
                    males with those northern nations amongst whom the Roman laws had not been
                    introduced; but amongst the Lombards the age of marriage was fourteen for males
                    and twelve for females, as in the Roman law; and such is also the law of this
                    country. The framers of the Code Civil, however, justly conceive those ages
                    unsuited to our customs and climate, and accordingly fix the age at eighteen for
                    males and fifteen for females, but with a power in the government to dispense
                    with the age upon cause shown. The canon law, on the other hand, attends only to
                    physical considerations and allows persons of every age to marry, provided onlj
                    they are <hi rend="italic">habiles</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">matrimonium.</hi> In the Mosaic law there was no restraint on
                    marriage merely in respect of age but then it is to be remembered here, that
                    amongst the Jews the parental influence and authority were perfectly sufficient
                    to prevent premature marriage; whilst yet, on the other hand, the importance of
                    marriage was, from circumstances peculiar to that people, perfectly sufficient
                    to prevent undue obstruction.</p>
                <p>Another disability is a prior marriage subsisting, or the having another husband
                    or wife living at the same time: polygamy, though practised by many nations,
                    both ancient and modern, being expressly condemned by Scripture, and contrary to
                    all sound policy.</p>
                <p>A further disability is relationship by birth or by affinity. Amongst the
                    Athenians, no other relationship but that of parent and child formed a bar to
                    marriage, with the exception of brothers and sisters, the intermarriage of whom
                    was forbidden, in order to prevent the union of inheritances. But in this the
                    Athenians were singular; and in the law of Scotland, where the Levitical law of
                    marriage is adopted, the intermarriage of ascendants and descendants is
                    forbidden to the remotest degree, as is likewise that of collaterals <hi
                    rend="italic">in loco parentis,</hi> and also of the whole or half blood who are
                    within the second degree, thus allowing cousins-german, and all of more remote
                    degree, to intermarry. In the case of affinity or of relationship by marriage,
                    the husband and wife being in law but one person, the blood relations of either
                    are held as related by affinity in the same degree to the one spouse as by
                    consanguinity to the other. With regarďto illegitimate kindred, it is held that
                    the impediments of consanguinity and affinity apply no less to such persons than
                    to those lawfully related; on this principle, that the state and condition of
                    bastardy, or rather the forms of marriage, are but of civil institution
                    only.</p>
                <p>There is a still further disability, the disability <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>
                    before alluded to, namely, physical incapacity; but this is only a ground on
                    which a marriage may be declared void at the instance of either of the parties,
                    and not itself a nullity pleadable by others.</p>
                <p>By an act of the parliament of Scotland, 1600, c. 20, it was further declared
                    that all marriages contracted by persons divorced for adultery, with the person
                    with whom they had been judicially found to have committed the crime, should be
                    null and unlawful, and the issue born thereof be incapable to succeed as heirs
                    to their parents. But it does not appear that this statute has ever been acted
                    on by the courts.</p>
                <p>The next particular we noticed as requisite to marriage was, that the parties
                    should be willing to contract; on which particular we need not dwell, the will
                    of the parties being <pb break="no" facs="nls:194203189?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-3189-0259"/> clearly, from what we have already stated, of the
                    essence of the contract. Indeed we have adopted, from the civil law, the maxim,
                    <hi rend="italic">Consensus non</hi><hi rend="italic">concubitus facit
                    nuptias.</hi></p>
                <p>The last requisite on this head is, that the parties do actually contract, or
                    that effect be given to their declared intentions.</p>
                <p>To give a distinct origin to the important relation of husband and wife, and also
                    solemnity to the engagement, it has been the practice of most countries to enter
                    on marriage with a ceremony in which the ministers of religion have commonly
                    assisted. In Scotland, as early as the middle of the thirteenth century, we find
                    it enacted by one of the canons of a provincial council held at Perth, that no
                    faith should be given to any one regarding a marriage not eelebrated before a
                    priest, and three or four witnesses specially called for the occasion. Whether
                    these canons were ever ratified by the civil power is not clear; but a
                    distinction exists, and has long done so, between marriages celebrated in <hi
                    rend="subscript"> t</hi> ∕h&lt;fie <hi rend="italic">ecclesiae,</hi> and what
                    are called clandestine marriages. Both kinds, however (as came also to be the
                    doctrine of the canon law), are valid; and, moreover, the deliberate consent of
                    parties entering into a present agreement to take each other for husband and
                    wife, or their solemn acknowledgment, written or verbal, of their having done
                    so,constitutes a marriage in law, whether proof of formal celebration be offered
                    or not. By a statute of the Scottish parliament, also, passed upwards of fifty
                    years before the Reformation, 1503, c. 77, it was enacted, that where <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> marriage has not been disputed in the lifetime of the
                    parties, the widow, being reputed and holden the lawful wife of the deceased in
                    her lifetime, shall have the dower, or <hi rend="italic">tierce as</hi> it is
                    called, and enjoy the same without hindrance, “aye and quhil it be clearly
                    decerned, and sentence given, that she was not his lawful wife.” The law
                    ofEngland is altogether different; the mode of contracting marriage having been
                    regulated there by special statute since the middle of the last century,
                    previous to which time, however, the marriage law of both countries appears to
                    have been, generally speaking, the same. But in Scotland there is this
                    remarkable peculiarity, that, in the absenee of a special provision to the
                    contrary, marriage is held incomplete to many purposes, till it has subsisted
                    for a year and day, or living issue be born thereof. This is said by Lord Stair
                    to have been derived from the Roman law; and certainly we find there, that if a
                    woman who had no parent, by the consent of her guardians, after espousal, lived
                    with a man as his wife for one year, without being absent for three nights, she
                    became the lawful wife of such man by what was termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >usucaption.</hi> But this is plainly different from the custom of Scotland,
                    which we rather think had its origin in the practice of <hi rend="italic"
                    >hand-fastening,</hi> once prevalent in that country. (See Lindsay’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicles of Scotland,</hi> p. 66; Martin’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Western Isles,</hi> p. 114; Forsyth’s <hi rend="italic">Scotland,</hi> vol. ii.
                    p. 284.) According to the law as it now stands, if a marriage have not subsisted
                    for year and day, or produced a living child, all rights granted in
                    consideration of the marriage become void, and things return to the same
                    condition in which they stood before the marriage, unless special stipulation be
                    made to the contrary. The husband has no right to courtesy, nor the widow to her
                    dower; the tocher is paid back, and the moveable funds still extant are restored
                    to the party to whom they originally belonged.</p>
                <p>Let us now attend to some of the chief consequences resulting from the
                    matrimonial engagement. By marriage, the husband and wife become one person in
                    law; and on this unity depend almost all the rights and disabilities which
                    cither of them acquires or incurs by their intermarriage. This unity, however,
                    does not operate in the same way as in the case of the contract of partnership,
                    where every member of the company represents all, and may bind all, but upon the
                    principle of the subjection of the wife to the husband. Whilst, therefore, the
                    moveable property of the parties is <hi rend="italic">ipso jure</hi> formed into
                    a common fund, the husband is also <hi rend="italic">ipso jure</hi> the
                    administrator of that fund. He is the head of the family, and the proper curator
                    of his wife, over whom also he is invested with a large marital authority; and
                    her very management as head of the domestic economy’· of his house is not in
                    virtue of any' inherent or independent power of her own, but of delegation from
                    him. She has, however, her own peculiar property of paraphernalia, customary
                    gifts, and exclusive provisions; the law will protect her against the cruelty of
                    her husband; and without his consent she may execute a testament or dispose of
                    her property by a <hi rend="italic">mortis causa</hi> conveyance. In the case of
                    donations also between husband and wife, either party may recall their gifts, in
                    as far as they are not reasonable, either tacitly or expressly.</p>
                <p>We have already alluded to the dissolution of marriage by death. This is its
                    natural termination; and in England it is the only way in which a valid marriage
                    can end, except by the power of an act of parliament. It is otherwise in
                    Scotland; for here a marriage may be dissolved not only by the death of either
                    party, but also by judicial sentence of divorce for adultery or desertion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Jactitation of</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Marriage,</hi>
                    in English law, one of the first and principal matrimonial causes, when one of
                    the parties gives out that he or she is married to the other, whereby a common
                    reputation of their matrimony may ensue. On this ground the party injured may
                    libel the other in the spiritual court; and unless the defendant undertakes and
                    makes out a proof of the actual marriage, he or she is enjoined perpetual
                    silence on that head; which is the only remedy the ecclesiastical courts can
                    give for this injury.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
