<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0020-0010-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SUTHERLAND</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 10</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=20" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SUTHERLAND</label>, an extensive county in the north of
                    Scotland, situated between 57° 53' and 58° 36' north latitude, and between 3°
                    39' and 5° 15' west longitude from Greenwich; having the sea on the south-east,
                    west, and north, Caithness on the north-east, and Ross-shire on the south. From
                    north to south it extends from 35 to 50 miles, and from west to east from 45 to
                    50, and contains, according to the latest authorities, 1754 square miles, or
                    1,112,560 English acres divided into thirteen parishes, which belong to the
                    synod of Sutherland and Caithness. Of the other divisions, the principal are,
                    Assynt and Edderachylis on the west, and Strathnaver on the east; names
                    recognised by the inhabitants, and which still serve to designate the locality
                    of the natural objects and other circumstances of the country.</p>
                <p>The coast of Sutherland, like that of the other Highland counties of Scotland,
                    presents a succession of inlets of the sea, and bold promontories, with a number
                    of rocks and islets. The principal arms of the sea are Lochs Assynt, Laxford,
                    and Inchard, on the west; Durness Bay, Loch Eriboll, the Kyle of Tongue, and the
                    bays of Torrisdale and Strathy, on the north; and Loch Fleet in the Frith of
                    Dornoch, on the south-east: and the more remarkable promontories are, Ru Stoir,
                    on the south side of Loch Assynt; Cape Wrath, on the north-west extremity of the
                    county; Far-out Head and Whitten Head, on the north; and Strathy Head, on the
                    north-east. The interior consists of mountains, mosses, lakes, and streams,
                    presenting great variety in form, but almost all having the same general
                    character of being barren, rugged, and dismal, more especially on the western
                    side; and so closely thrown together, that there is no valley of any extent, and
                    seldom a tree or a shrub, to relieve the eye. The Assynt mountains have not even
                    heath to cover their nakedness, except in patches among the rocks near their
                    base. Exceptions to this general character occur on the eastern coast, along the
                    Dornoch Frith, and on the banks of a few of the lakes and rivulets. From its
                    latitude, and exposure to the winds of the German and Northern Ocean, the
                    climate of Sutherland is sharp and cold. On the east coast, however, it is not
                    so severe as to prevent the growth of wheat, which sometimes ripens as early
                    here as in many parts of England.</p>
                <p>The principal streams are, Oickel, Fleet, Brora, and Helmsdale, which fall into
                    the Dornoch Frith on the southeast. The tide renders the Oickel navigable by
                    vessels of fifty tons for about twelve miles, and for boats for about eight
                    miles farther; and they have all good salmon fisheries. These rivulets have
                    their sources among the mountains in the centre of the district, and flow
                    south-east-In the same quarter various streams take their rise, and flow in a
                    northerly direction; such as Strathy, the Naver, which gives its name to the
                    tract called Strathnaver, the Dinart, &amp;c., most of them containing salmon.
                    The most considerable lake is Loch Shin, about twenty miles long and one broad,
                    situated on the southern side of the county, through which flows a stream of the
                    same name, which falls into the Oickel. There are several others of considerable
                    extent in different parts, the whole occupying about fifty-three square miles,
                    or nearly 34,000 acres. On the north coast the sea has formed some remarkable
                    caves in the limestone rock, particularly one at Smow, to the east of Balnakeel
                    of Durness, thirty-two yards wide and twenty yards high; and another at
                    Fraisgill, fifty feet high, and twenty feet wide at its entrance, but
                    contracting by degress till its termination, more than half a mile under
                    ground.</p>
                <p>The oldest formation of rocks in Sutherland is gneiss, which extends over the
                    whole county, and affords a great diversity of aspect in the stratification.
                    This formation is traversed by granite veins, which abound in various places in
                    the south-east part of the county, as also in the upper part of the parishes of
                    Reay and Edderachylis. The gneiss is also traversed by veins of greenstone and
                    porphyry. Those of the greenstone are found in great abundance in the south-east
                    district of Assynt, and in the country around Scourie in Edderachylis parish.
                    Porphyry veins are of rare occurrence. Mica-slate is developed to a considerable
                    extent in two parts of the county; in that portion of the district of Moin which
                    stretches southwards, and constitutes the whole of the mountains of Ben-Hope,
                    Ben-Hee, and Meal-Rynies; and that part of the county between Loch Fleet and
                    Bonar Bridge. Granite fields prevail in the lower part of the parish of Reay,
                    and in the parishes of Loth and Kogart. Syenite is to be met with in several
                    places. It is most abundant in the mountain of Ben-Laoghal, and that
                    considerable tract of hilly country which intervenes between the head of Loch
                    Fleet and Lairg, at the foot of Loch Shin. The quartz series of rocks occurs
                    principally in greater or less fields in the west part of the county, from Loch
                    Eriboll on the north, to Loch Vattie on the south. This series is connected with
                    sandstone and limestone. The latter is divided into four great fields connected
                    with each other, and running in the same direction as the quartz. There is also
                    a portion of nearly six miles in length at Durness, between Loch Eriboll and
                    Cape Wrath. Red stone and conglomerate are extensively displayed on the east
                    side, and at several points on the north coast and the interior. The oolite
                    series of rocks, consisting of white sandstone, sandstone flag, slate-clay,
                    limestone, and coal, forms the coast between Golspie and the Ord of Caithness,
                    and has a breadth at the river Brora of three miles. At Brora, coal occurs at
                    several points, but it has been found not to be worth the working. Calcareous
                    sinter and bog iron ore are the only chemical alluvial deposits to be found in
                    the county.</p>
                <p>This county, which is valued in the cess-books at L.26,193. 9s. 7d. Scots, is
                    almost entirely the property of the duke of Sutherland. In 1812 the gross rental
                    of the lands and houses, as returned under the property-tax act, was L.28,458.
                    8s. 4d. including about L.1700 as the rent of the salmon and other fisheries.
                    Since that period, the great and extensive improvements effected by the spirited
                    proprietors must have augmented the rental in a corresponding degree. More than
                    half the valuation is held under entail. The principal seats are, Dunrobin
                    Castle, duke of Sutherland, on the coast of the Dornoch Frith, in the parish of
                    Golspie; Skibo, Dempster, on an inlet of the same frith, near the south-eastern
                    corner of the county; and Tongue Castle, on the Kyle of Tongue, on the north
                    coast. Most of the other proprietors have good modern houses, all of which are
                    situated near the coast. In no part of Britain has a greater change been
                    effected in so short at period as in Sutherland, and this chiefly by the spirit
                    and liberality of its greatest proprietor, the duke of Sutherland. Within these
                    twenty or thirty years, roads, bridges, harbours, and villages, have been
                    constructed wherever they seemed to be required; and both the natural and moral
                    obstructions to the improvement of this extensive territory have, as far as it
                    appears practicable, been in a great measure overcome. Before the beginning of
                    the present century, Sutherland was almost in a state of nature, excluded from
                    the benefits of that civilization which had spread over<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=21" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0021-0011"/>
                    the rest of Britain; and this exclusion was principally owing to the want of
                    roads and other means of communication.</p>
                <p>During the last twenty years the greatest changes have taken place. “Before that
                    period, the injurious system of sub-letting prevailed, and both the knowledge
                    and the practice of farming were exceedingly defective. The place of Dunrobin
                    excepted, there was neither draining, trenching, nor fallow, and very little
                    green crop, besides potatoes and a little pease. There were few fences, and
                    these few bad. The plough, which was rudely constructed, had no part of it iron
                    but the coulter, the sock, and the hook at the end of the beam. Four country
                    garrans, or highland ponies, were yoked to the plough abreast, and the driver
                    walked in front of them backwards. There were few wheeled vehicles that deserved
                    the name. Corn, fuel, &amp;c. were carried in a kind of frame called crubags,
                    fastened on horseback to a wooden saddle, that rested on a straw-mat. The public
                    road was the only one, and that itself indifferent. The dwellings of the
                    subtenants were wooden frames, thatched with turf; and of these, one end
                    accommodated cattle, horses, and. sometimes pigs. One end also of the
                    turf-coverings of these huts, saturated as it was with soot, was annually stript
                    off and converted into manure. With such dwellings the dress of their tenants
                    corresponded. The state of things is now very different. Farming is brought to
                    the highest degree of excellence that industry, skill, and expense, can bring
                    it. Nor is it too much to say, that the system of farming at present followed in
                    the county does not fall short of the best modes of farming in any part of the
                    kingdom. The farmers have very good houses, with two public rooms; and they have
                    their wheeled carriages for personal and family use. Sub-letting is abolished.
                    The small tenants or cottars live in decent cottages, built with stone and lime,
                    or clay, with glass windows; and their fare is correspondingly better; and the
                    tradesmen and ploughmen wear good clothes. In no county of Scotland was there
                    ever, in so short a time, the same length of road made, as there has been within
                    the last twenty years in the county of Sutherland, In former times the internal
                    communication was by mere paths or tracks, and many parts of it were all but
                    inaccessible. Now, several hundred miles of good road, unchecked by tolls,
                    intersect the county in every direction; and there is free and easy access to
                    every part of it. These roads were made, partly by the parliamentary
                    commissioners and the county, but chiefly at the expense of the noble
                    proprietors, and under the able management of James Loch, Esq. M. P. their
                    commissioner.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Statistical Account of Scotland.</p></note></p>
                <p>Sutherland is eminently adapted by nature for sheepgrazing; and the plans of
                    converting it into extensive sheep-walks, which have been for some years
                    carrying into execution, have greatly augmented the revenue of the proprietors,
                    and added to the commercial wealth of the nation; but they have doubtless been
                    attended with much suffering to the small tenants whom it was necessary to
                    dispossess. The people who had been removed from the interior in 1818 and 1819,
                    when these great changes took place, are densely settled along the sea-coast; in
                    some instances about thirty cottagers occupying the land formerly in the
                    possession of twelve. They have likewise been obliged to make a' violent change
                    in their occupations and habits: instead of tending flocks, and following other
                    rural occupations, they have been forced to encounter the hardships and dangers
                    of the sea, and occupy themselves with the fisheries; and many families have
                    preferred emigration from their native country, to engaging in occupations so
                    entirely foreign to their previous habits.</p>
                <p>The ordinary system of husbandry adopted is the five-course shift rotation of
                    crops; and trenching and draining have been executed to a great extent. The rent
                    of arable land is from 20s. to 30s. per acre. The corn-farms are generally of
                    such an extent as yield from L.50 to L.200 of annual rent; few exceed L.300. The
                    average rate of grazing is L.1. 10s. per ox or cow grazed, and 2s. per sheep.
                    The leases of farms are generally for nineteen years; but the cottagers on the
                    coast are almost always tenants at will, which is evidently a bar to the
                    improvement of their cots. But the greater part of the county is laid out in
                    extensive sheep-farms, yielding about L.500 of yearly rent each. The Cheviot or
                    white-faced breed of sheep is that which is generally kept. The Dunrobin breed
                    of cattle, originally from Argyleshire, is excellent. Some Ayrshire cows are
                    kept for dairy use. On some farms the breed of Galloway black-polled cattle, and
                    highland black cattle, are chiefly reared. Goats were once a part of the stock
                    of the farmers, but they have now nearly disappeared.</p>
                <p>Until the recent establishments of the duke of Sutherland, there was no
                    manufacture in this county, if we except that of kelp, of which the quantity
                    used to be 250 tons. A cotton-mill had been erected at Spinningdale, on a branch
                    of the Dornoch Frith, by a Glasgow company; but the building having been burnt
                    down in 1806, the undertaking was abandoned. A good many boats are employed in
                    the fisheries on the west and north coast for cod, ling, haddock, and herring;
                    and lobsters and mussels are found in considerable quantities. At Helmsdale, on
                    the east coast, many of those small tenants who were removed by the introduction
                    of sheep-farming, have also embarked in the fisheries with considerable success;
                    and large sums have been expended within these few years by the noble proprietor
                    of the Sutherland estate in erecting the necessary buildings. The principal
                    exports are sheep, wool, cattle, horses, salmon, and cod. Their butter and
                    cheese are nearly all consumed at home; and besides the usual imports of cloths,
                    groceries, &amp;c., they require some corn, chiefly oatmeal, especially on the
                    west and north sides of the county, where they have very little corn-land.</p>
                <p>Dornoch, a royal borough, situated on the south-eastern extremity, on the frith
                    of that name, is the only town, and contains little more than 500 inhabitants.
                    Golspie, Helmsdale, and Brora, are the principal villages. With these
                    exceptions, the inhabitants are scattered along the coast, and in some of the
                    principal straths, passing much of their time in idleness; a healthy, robust,
                    and simple, though not ill-informed race, who have contributed largely to the
                    public service. For the last half century, the Sutherland family have raised
                    among them, at the commencement of every war, a corps of a thousand men, well
                    known by the name of the Sutherland Fencibles; but this military spirit, founded
                    in attachment to their chiefs, has now become much weaker than formerly.</p>
                <p>The schools in the county are the parish schools, and those of the Society for
                    propagating Christian Knowledge and the Gaelic School Society. According to the
                    last parliamentary returns, there was neither printer nor bookseller in the
                    whole county; a circumstance indicating either great poverty or little literary
                    taste among the inhabitants. Sutherland is distinguished from every other county
                    in the kingdom in being undisturbed by religious dissent; there is not a single
                    dissenting place of worship within its limits. Savings banks have been
                    established in some of the parishes. The only prison in the county is at
                    Dornoch. The number of prisoners during the year 1833 was twenty, of whom six
                    were committed for smuggling, and ten for assaults.</p>
                <p>In various districts along the coast, there are some remains of antiquity. The
                    most interesting are two circular buildings, called Dun Domadil, or Dornadilla’s
                    Tower, and<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=22"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0022-0012"/> Castle Coll, both reared of large stones, nicely
                    fitted, but without cement, and of which considerable portions are still entire,
                    after the lapse of probably 1000 years. Castle Coll, which is situated on the
                    east side of the county, on a stream that falls into the Brora, has an exterior
                    circumference of fifty-four yards, with walls four yards and a half thick at the
                    base, inclining inwards nine inches in every three feet in height; and two small
                    apartments on each side of the door-way, as if intended for guard-rooms. The
                    highest part of the wall is now only eleven feet high, but old people remember
                    it twice that height. Dun Dornadil is in the parish of Durness, on the northern
                    side of the county. It is a building of the same character with the former, but
                    still more dilapidated, and is celebrated in the ancient Gaelic ballads as a
                    place of renown at a very early period. The ruins of Dornoch cathedral still
                    display the original grandeur of that edifice, which is said to have been built
                    in the eleventh century, and repaired and enlarged in the thirteenth. Circular
                    cairns with subterraneous passages, tumuli, and some small forts, may yet be
                    traced in various situations along the coast.</p>
                <p>The county sends one member to parliament; and the town of Dornoch joins with
                    Cromarty, Dingwall, Tain, Wick, and Kirkwall, in electing one for the Scotish
                    burghs.</p>
                <p>The population, according to the census of 1801, was 23,117, in 1811 it amounted
                    to 23,629, in 1821 to 23,840, and in 1831 to 25,518, of which 12,090 were males,
                    and 13,428 were females. The families employed in agriculture were 3567, in
                    trade and manufactures 409, in all other occupations 1029.</p>
                <p>New Statistical Account of Scotland; Henderson’s General View of the County of
                    Sutherland; Loch’s Account of the Improvements of the Marquis of Stafford in
                    Sutherland; and Cunningham’s Essay on the Geology of the County, in Quarterly
                    Journal of Agriculture, No. xlvi.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
