<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0781-0736-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">YELLOWSTONE NATIONAL PARK (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    736)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xd69">Canonization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207555">Montana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211709">Idaho</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204724">Missouri</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210251">Colorado</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053705">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845944">Canonization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139579">Surveying</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n781/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YELLOWSTONE NATIONAL PARK</label>, an area situated mainly in
                    north-western Wyoming, United States, which has been withdrawn from settlement
                    by the United States Government and dedicated to the purposes of a public park.
                    It is a region of hot springs and geysers, mountains and canons, lakes and
                    waterfalls. While it is almost entirely comprised in Wyoming, a narrow strip 2
                    miles wide projects on the north into Montana, and on the west a strip about 5
                    miles in width projects into the same Territory and into Idaho. Its boundaries,
                    which were defined at a time when the country was little known, are as follows.
                    The northern boundary is a parallel of latitude running through the mouth of
                    Gardiner river, a branch of the Yellowstone, 2 miles north of 45° N. The eastern
                    boundary is a meridian 10 miles east of the most easterly point of Yellowstone
                    Lake, which places it almost on the 110th meridian. The southern boundary is a
                    parallel 10 miles south of the most southerly portion of the same body of water,
                    in lat. 44° 10' N. The western boundary is a meridian 15 miles west of the most
                    westerly portion of Madison (now Shoshone) Lake, this meridian being
                    approximately that of 111° 6'. The Park is therefore very nearly a rectangle in
                    shape, its length north and south being 61∙8 miles and its breadth 53∙6. Its
                    area is 3312 square miles.</p>
                <p>Its surface is mainly an undulating plateau, with a mean <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n782/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0782-0737"/> elevation above the sea of about 8000 feet, upon
                    the surface of which the minor streams flow, while the larger ones have cut
                    canons for themselves, several of them being of great depth. The eastern
                    portion, however, is occupied by an extremely rugged mountain chain, known as
                    the Absaroka Range, peaks of which rise to heights exceeding 11,000 feet. These
                    mountains, which separate the waters of the Yellowstone from those of the Big
                    Horn, are unsurpassed in the United States for sublimity and grandeur of
                    scenery. The Gallatin Range, which separates the Yellowstone from the Gallatin
                    river, enters the Park near the north-western corner and extends southwards some
                    20 miles within it. It reaches its culminating point in Electric Peak, 11,050
                    feet high, just within the Park boundary. Another group of mountains, in the
                    form of a horseshoe, occurs near the middle of the Park, known as the Washburne
                    Mountains, the highest summit of which, Mount Washburne, has an elevation of
                    10,346 feet. The Red Mountains are in the southern part, their culminating peak
                    being Mount Sheridan, 10,385 feet in height. In this part of the Park the
                    plateau is more elevated and broken, and just beyond its southern limits it
                    rises into a confused maze of mountains.</p>
                <p>The Park has an abundant rainfall, and its streams are numerous and bold. It
                    contains many beautiful lakes and ponds. Within its area are the sources of the
                    Yellowstone and the Madison, which go to make up the Missouri, and of the Snake,
                    one of the forks of the Columbia. This last stream, which drains the
                    south-western part, takes its rise in several branches, among them being Lewis
                    Fork, which has its origin in the beautiful Shoshone Lake, and Heart river,
                    which rises in Heart Lake, under the shadow of Mount Sheridan. The Yellowstone
                    drains the eastern part. Rising just beyond its southern limits, it flows into
                    and through Yellowstone Lake, a magnificent sheet of water, of very irregular
                    shape, having an area of 150 square miles. A few miles below the lake, the
                    river, after a succession of rapids, leaps over a cliff, making the Upper Fall,
                    112 feet in height. Half a mile lower down it rolls over the Lower Fall, which
                    has a clear descent of 300 feet. The river at this point carries, at the average
                    stage of water, about 1200 cubic feet per second. With this fall the river
                    enters the Grand Canon, which in many scenic effects has not its equal on the
                    globe. Its depth is not great, at least as compared with the canons upon the
                    Colorado river system, ranging from 600 feet at its head to 1200 near the
                    middle, where it passes the Washburne Mountains. Its length to the mouth of
                    Lamar river is 24 miles. It is cut in a volcanic plateau, and its ragged broken
                    walls, which are inclined at very steep angles, are of a barbaric richness of
                    colouring that almost defies description. Reds, yellows, and purples
                    predominate, and are set off very effectively against the dark green of the
                    forests upon the plateau, and the white foam oi the rushing river which fills
                    the bottom of the chasm. Near the foot of the Grand Canon, Tower creek, which
                    drains the concavity of the horseshoe formed by the Washburne Mountains, enters
                    the Yellowstone. Just above its mouth this stream makes a beautiful fall of 132
                    feet into the gorge in which it joins the river. A few miles farther down the
                    Yellowstone is joined by an eastern branch, Lamar river, which drains a large
                    part of the Absaroka Range. Then it enters the Third Canon, from which it
                    emerges at the mouth of Gardiner river. The latter stream drains an area of
                    elevated land by means of its three forks, and upon each of them occurs a fine
                    fall in its descent toward the Yellowstone. The Madison rises in the western
                    part of the Park and flows in a generally northward and then westward course out
                    of the Park. Its waters are mainly collected from the rainfall upon the
                    plateaus, and from the hot springs and geysers, most of which are within its
                    drainage area. Upon this river and its affluents are several fine falls. Indeed
                    all the streams of this region show evidence, in the character of their courses,
                    of a recent change of level in the surface of the country.</p>
                <p>The climate is characterized by a considerable degree of humidity and a heavy
                    rainfall, as compared with adjacent portions of the West. The temperature is
                    that of a semi-arctic region. Frost may occur in midsummer and snow begins to
                    fall in September.</p>
                <p>The native fauna is abundant and varied. The policy of the Government, which
                    protects game within this reservation, has induced it to take shelter here
                    against the sportsman and pot-hunter, so that elk, deer, antelope, mountain
                    sheep, bear, and numerous smaller game animals are very abundant and tame. The
                    only herd of wild bisons left in the United States is upon this reservation; and
                    in some parts moose are occasionally seen.</p>
                <p>The flora is very varied. With the exception of a few limited areas in the
                    northern part, the region is covered with forests, generally so dense that
                    landmarks are invisible and the traveller is forced to guide himself by the sun
                    or by compass. The trees are mainly the Douglas spruce and the yellow pine, and
                    are not of large size or great commercial value.</p>
                <p>The surface of the park is almost entirely covered with volcanic rocks. The
                    Gallatin Range, however, in the north-western corner, is made up of stratified
                    beds ranging from the Silurian system up to the Cretaceous. In a few localities
                    also Tertiary lake beds and local drift are found. The plateaus generally are
                    composed of rhyolite, while the mountain ranges are made up of later volcanic
                    deposits, mainly conglomerates. In this region the ancient volcanic fires, which
                    formerly extended far and wide, especially to the south and west, are still in
                    existence, as is shown by the vast numbers of hot springs and geysers. The
                    number of the former is by a close estimate not less than 3000, varying in size
                    from a few inches in diameter to an area of many acres. The number of active
                    geysers is 71. These phenomena are found in groups in numerous localities, the
                    most important of which—for they contain most of the great geysers—are the Upper
                    and the Lower Geyser basins, near the head of the Madison, here known as the
                    Firehole, river. The former contains 26 geysers, several of which are of such
                    power as to throw water to heights exceeding 200 feet, and the amount of water
                    thrown out is so great as to raise the temperature of the river water many
                    degrees. The Lower basin contains 16 geysers. The Norris basin, upon Gibbon
                    river, a branch of the Madison, contains 9 geysers, and the Shoshone basin, upon
                    the shore of Shoshone Lake, contains 8 active spouters. Others are found at
                    Heart Lake, upon Pelican creek, in Hayden’s valley, and in Monument basin. In
                    all these localities the water holds silica in solution in considerable
                    quantities, so that as it cools and evaporates it deposits siliceous matter,
                    which has covered with a hard white floor many square miles of these valleys,
                    and has built up craters around the springs and geysers of considerable size and
                    great beauty of form. Besides silica, the water of many of the springs contains
                    sulphur, iron, alum, and other materials in solution, which in places stain the
                    pure white of the siliceous deposits with bright bands of colour. Upon Gardiner
                    river, near the northern boundary of the Park, there is a large group of
                    springs, known as the Mammoth Hot Springs, which differ from the others in
                    holding carbonate of lime in solution. These springs have deposited so freely as
                    to build up a hill 200 feet in height, from the top of which the springs boil
                    out. The slopes of this mound have been built in the form of a succession of
                    basins rising one above another, and the water from the springs overflows from
                    one into another, growing gradually cooler as it descends. Upon the bank of
                    Yellowstone river, between the falls and the lake, there was, when the region
                    was first explored, a geyser which at intervals of about 4 hours threw up a
                    column of mud to a height of 40 or 50 feet. In more recent times this geyser has
                    ceased action. These phenomena have been under observation since 1871; and,
                    while there have been changes in them, certain geysers having ceased and others
                    having been formed, no evidence of a diminution of power has been observed.</p>
                <p>The Park is accessible by means of the Northern Pacific Railroad, by a branch
                    which extends up the valley of the Yellowstone within a few miles of the
                    northern boundary; and with this a line of stage coaches is connected.</p>
                <p>The most stringent laws have been enacted in regard to the killing of game, the
                    starting of forest fires, and the removal of the deposits of the springs.</p>
                <p>Although exploring parties had at various times passed on all sides of this
                    strange region, its wonders remained undiscovered until so late a period as
                    1870. This fact is all the more remarkable because at that time the frontier of
                    settlement was in the Gallatin valley, not a hundred miles from the great geyser
                    region. Some rumours of hot springs and geysers, coming from stray trappers and
                    Indians, had been received, however, and these were sufficient to start a party
                    from the Montana settlements in 1870, to investigate the strange tales. The
                    discoveries made by this, the Washburne party, induced Dr F. V. Hayden, then in
                    charge of a Government survey, to turn his explorations in this direction. The
                    reports <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n783/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0783-0738"/> brought back by him induced Congress to reserve
                    this area from settlement, which was done in the spring of 1872. In that year
                    further explorations were made, and in subsequent years army expeditions carried
                    the work of exploration still farther. In 1878 a map of the Park, based upon
                    triangulation, was drawn up by the Hayden survey, and in 1883-85 a more detailed
                    map was made by the United States Geological Survey, and a systematic study of
                    its geological phenomena was instituted. (H. G*.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
