<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0805-0756-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">YOUNG, Edward (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    756)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:883881">Crofts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952109">Hay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t316">Hay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n805/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YOUNG, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi></label> (1681-1765),
                    author of <hi rend="italic">Night Thoughts,</hi> was born at Upham, near
                    Winchester, in 1681. The minute facts of his life are to be found in the
                    biography contributed to Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Poets</hi> by
                    Herbert Croft. The son of the dean of Sarum, educated at Winchester and Oxford
                    (New College and Corpus), Young obtained a law fellowship at All Souls in 1708,
                    and proceeded to use it as a base of operations for gratifying his “ruling
                    passion,” the love of fame. There was at the time an open career for young men
                    of talent who showed ability to recommend the policy and the persons of
                    statesmen in their struggle for power, and Young, full of unbounded energy and
                    eloquence, exuberant to eccentricity, joined in the race with a vigour that soon
                    raised him to distinction. He seems to have been for a time in the family of the
                    earl of Exeter as tutor; but the notorious marquis of Wharton (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Wharton)</hi> took a fancy to him, bribed him away from this
                    post with liberal promises of maintenance and patronage, settled two annuities
                    on him, and tried to get him into Parliament. Meantime Young began to publish
                    and to dedicate, the poems and the dedications taken together <hi rend="italic"
                    >(The Last Hay,</hi> 1713, and <hi rend="italic">The Force of Religion,</hi>
                    1714) showing the simple mixture of piety and worldliness that is one of the
                    notes of his character. He essayed tragedy, writing at mid-day with closed
                    shutters, by the light of a candle fixed in a human skull. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Busiris</hi> was performed at Drury Lane in 1719, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Revenge</hi> in 1721. Far from gloomy in the company of Wharton and his friends,
                    he had a decided bent for gloomy themes when alone, and a most copious and
                    lofty— often extravagantly lofty—eloquence in the treatment of them; a
                    paraphrase of the book of Job was one of his productions about this time. But he
                    showed equal facility in dashing and effective satire: his first great literary
                    success was made with the series of satires published between 1725 and 1728, and
                    collected in the latter year under the title <hi rend="italic">Love of Fame, the
                    Universal Passion.</hi> These satires do not bear comparison with Pope’s, to
                    which they pointed the way, but they have a charm of exuberant vitality and
                    power, an irregular abundance of wit and bold imagery, a frequent felicity of
                    diction, that entitle them to Johnson’s praise—“a very great performance”—and
                    enable us to understand the impression produced by Young in conversation. One of
                    the features in Young’s character that disarms resentment of his fulsome
                    adulation, and other extravagances and eccentricities, is his humorous
                    Falstaffian consciousness of his own faults. “Who can write the true absurd like
                    me ?” he cries in one of his satires. He abundantly proved this in <hi
                    rend="italic">Ocean: an Ode,</hi> with which he hailed the accession of George
                    II. Soon after, when nearly fifty, he took orders, was appointed a royal
                    chaplain, and presented by his college to the rectory of Welwyn. He was
                    disappointed in his desire of further promotion in the church; he had succeeded
                    some time before in extracting a pension of £200 from Walpole, and this favour
                    was cynically treated as a satisfaction in full of his claims on the Government.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Night Thoughts</hi> were published in separate “Nights”
                    between 1742 and 1744. In the preface Young said that “the occasion of this poem
                    was real, not fictitious, and that the facts mentioned did naturally force these
                    moral reflexions on the mind of the writer.” Croft has shown that this
                    statement, though justifiable in the main, has to be taken with some
                    qualifications, and that a common belief that Lorenzo was meant for the author’s
                    own son was undoubtedly a mistake. Still, it is true that Young’s wife, her
                    daughter, and her daughter’s husband died in rapid succession, and the poem —a
                    great work in spite of all its inequalities—was, like <hi rend="italic">In
                    Memoriam,</hi> the expression of a real sorrow and search for consolation. Young
                    continued to write occasionally even after he had passed his eightieth year. His
                    death took place on 12th April 1765.</p>
                <p>Besides Croft’s <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> there are interesting references to
                    Young in Boswell’s <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi> (see Birkbeck’s ed., iv. 119,
                    v. 270).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
