<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0061-0050-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MURCHISON, Sir Roderick Impey (9th edition, volume 17,
                    page 50)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1013537">Medals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086358z">Medals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n61/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MURCHISON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Roderick
                        Impey</hi></label> (1792-1871), geologist, was descended from a small clan
                    or sept which for many generations lived in the west of Ross-shire, furnishing
                    factors for some of the greater lairds, occupants of farms among the western
                    sea-lochs, and even occasionally a parish minister. His father, educated as a
                    medical man, acquired a competent fortune in India, and while still in the prime
                    of life returned to Scotland, where, marrying one of the Mackenzies of Fairburn,
                    he purchased the estate of Tarradale in eastern Ross and settled for a few years
                    as a resident Highland landlord. At Tarradale his eldest son, the subject of
                    this notice, was born on 19th February 1792. Young Murchison left the Highlands
                    when only three years old, and at the age of seven was sent to the grammar
                    school of Durham, where during six years he received the only connected general
                    education he ever obtained. He was then placed at the military college, Great
                    Marlow, to be trained for the army. With some difficulty he succeeded in passing
                    the not very stringent examinations of the time, and at the age of fifteen was
                    gazetted ensign in the 36th regiment. A year later (1808) he landed with
                    Wellesley in Galicia, and was present at the actions of Roriça and Vimiera.
                    Subsequently under Sir John Moore he took part in the retreat to Corunna and the
                    final battle there. These six months of active service formed the only part of
                    his military career in which he was exposed to the hardships and dangers of
                    actual warfare. The defeat of Napoleon at Waterloo seeming to close the prospect
                    of advancement in the military profession, Murchison, after eight years of
                    service, quitted the army, and married the daughter of General Hugonin, of
                    Nursted House, Hampshire. With her he then spent rather more than two years on
                    the Continent, particularly in Italy, where her cultivated tastes were of signal
                    influence in guiding his pursuits. He threw himself with all the enthusiasm of
                    his character into the study of art and antiquities, and for the first time in
                    his life tasted the pleasures of truly intellectual pursuits.</p>
                <p>Returning to England in 1818, he sold his paternal property in Ross-shire and
                    settled in England, where, finding art studies no longer practicable, he took
                    heart and soul to field-sports. He soon became one of the greatest fox-hunters
                    in the northern counties; but at last, getting weary of such pursuits and
                    meeting Sir Humphrey Davy, who urged him to turn his energy to science, he was
                    induced to attend lectures at the Royal Institution. This change in the current
                    of his occupations was much helped by the sympathy of his wife, who, besides her
                    artistic acquirements, took much interest in some branches of natural history.
                    Eager and enthusiastic in whatever he undertook, he was soon fascinated by the
                    young science of geology, and threw himself heartily into its prosecution. He
                    joined the Geological Society of London and soon showed himself one of its most
                    active members, having as his colleagues there such men as Sedgwick, Lyell,
                    Buckland, Herschel, Whewell, and Babbage. Exploring with his wife the geology of
                    the south of England, he devoted special attention to the rocks of the
                    north-west of Sussex and the adjoining parts of Hants and Surrey, on which he
                    wrote his first scientific paper, read to the Society towards the close of 1825.
                    From that early period on to the end of his long life his industry and
                    enthusiasm remained preeminent. Though he had reached the age of thirty-two
                    before he took any interest in science, he developed his taste and increased his
                    knowledge so rapidly by unwearied diligence that in the first three years of his
                    scientific career he had explored large parts of England and Scotland, had
                    obtained materials for three important memoirs, as well as for two more written
                    in conjunction with Sedgwick, and from the position of a mere beginner had risen
                    to be a prominent member of the Geological Society and one of its two
                    secretaries.</p>
                <p>Turning his attention for a little to Continental geology, he explored with Lyell
                    the volcanic region of Auvergne, parts of southern France, northern Italy,
                    Tyrol, and Switzerland. A little later, with Sedgwick as his companion, he
                    attacked the difficult problem of the geological structure of the Alps, and
                    their joint paper giving the results of their study will always be regarded as
                    one of the classics in the literature of Alpine geology.</p>
                <p>It was in the year 1831 that Murchison found the field in which the chief work of
                    his life was to be accomplished. Acting on a suggestion made to him by Buckland
                    he betook himself to the borders of Wales, with the view of endeavouring to
                    discover whether the greywacke rocks underlying the Old Red Sandstone could be
                    grouped <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n62/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0062-0051"/> into a definite order of succession, as the
                    Secondary rocks of England had been made to tell their story by William Smith.
                    For several years he continued to work vigorously in that region. The result was
                    the establishment of the Silurian system,—a definite section of the geological
                    record, bringing into notice for the first time a remarkable series of
                    formations, each replete with distinctive organic remains older than and very
                    different from those of the other rocks of England. The full import of his
                        discoveries<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                            results of these researches were embodied in a massive quarto volume
                            entitled <hi rend="italic">The Silurian System</hi> (London,
                        1839).</p></note> was not at first perceived; but as years passed on the
                    types of existence brought to light by him from the rocks of the border counties
                    of England and Wales were ascertained to belong to a geological period of which
                    there are recognizable traces in almost all parts of the globe. Thus the term
                    “Silurian,” derived from the name of the old British tribe Silures, soon passed
                    into the familiar vocabulary of geologists in every country.</p>
                <p>The establishment of the Silurian system was followed by that of the Devonian
                    system, an investigation in which Sedgwick and Murchison were fellow-labourers,
                    both in the south-west of England and in the Rhinelands. Soon afterwards
                    Murchison projected an important geological campaign in Russia with the view of
                    extending to that part of the Continent the classification he had succeeded in
                    elaborating for the older rocks of western Europe. He was accompanied by De
                    Verneuil and Keyserling, in conjunction with whom he produced a magnificent work
                    on <hi rend="italic">Russia and the Ural Mountains.</hi> The publication of this
                    monograph in 1845 completes the first and most active half of Murchison’s
                    scientific career.</p>
                <p>In 1846 he was knighted, and later in the same year he presided over the meeting
                    of the British Association at Southampton. During the later years of his life a
                    large part of his time was devoted to the affairs of the Royal Geographical
                    Society, of which he became president. So constant and active were his exertions
                    on behalf of geographical exploration that to a large section of the
                    contemporary public he was known rather as a geographer than as a geologist. He
                    particularly identified himself with the fortunes of David Livingstone in
                    Africa, and did much to raise and keep alive the sympathy of his
                    fellow-countrymen in the fate of that great explorer. The chief geological
                    investigation of the last decade of his life was devoted to the Highlands of
                    Scotland, where he succeeded in showing that the vast masses of crystalline
                    schists, previously supposed to be part of what used to be termed the Primitive
                    formations, were really not older than the Silurian period, for that underneath
                    them lay beds of limestone and quartzite containing Lower Silurian fossils. By
                    this important discovery he not only changed at once the accepted views of the
                    structure of half a kingdom but furnished a gigantic example of regional
                    metamorphism, the true significance of which in regard to theories of
                    metamorphism is not yet adequately appreciated.</p>
                <p>In the year 1855 Murchison was appointed director-general of the geological
                    survey and director of the Royal School of Mines and Geological Museum, Jermyn
                    Street, London, in succession to Sir Henry de la Beche, who had been the first
                    to hold these offices. Official routine now occupied much of his time, but he
                    found opportunity for the Highland researches just alluded to, and also for
                    preparing successive editions of his work <hi rend="italic">Siluria,</hi> which
                    was meant to present the main features of the original <hi rend="italic"
                        >Silurian System</hi> together with a digest of subsequent discoveries,
                    particularly of those which showed the extension of the Silurian classification
                    into other countries. His official position gave him still further opportunity
                    for the exercise of those social functions for which he had always been
                    distinguished, and which a considerable fortune inherited from near relatives on
                    his mother’s side enabled him to display on a greater scale. His house was one
                    of the great centres where science, art, literature, politics, and social
                    eminence were brought together in friendly intercourse. In 1863 he was made a
                    K.C.B., and three years later was raised to the dignity of a baronet. The
                    learned societies of his own country bestowed their highest rewards upon him:
                    the Royal Society gave him the Copley medal, the Geological Society its
                    Wollaston medal, and the Royal Society of Edinburgh its Brisbane medal. There
                    was hardly a foreign scientific society of note which had not his name enrolled
                    among its honorary members. The French Academy of Sciences awarded to him the
                    Prix Cuvier, and elected him one of its eight foreign members in succession to
                    Faraday.</p>
                <p>One of the closing public acts of Murchison’s life was the founding of a chair of
                    geology and mineralogy in the university of Edinburgh, for which he gave the sum
                    of £6000, an annual sum of £200 being likewise provided by a vote in parliament
                    for the endowment of the professorship. While the negotiations with the
                    Government in regard to this subject were still in progress, Murchison was
                    seized with a paralytic affection on 21st November 1870. At first his life was
                    in danger, but he eventually rallied, and was able to see his friends, read, and
                    take interest in current affairs until the early autumn of the following year,
                    when his malady began to make rapid progress. At last after a brief attack of
                    bronchitis he died on 22d October 1871.</p>
                <p>The chief work for which Murchison will always hold a high place in the annals of
                    geology is the investigation of the older Palaeozoic rocks, which culminated in
                    the establishment and subsequent development of the Silurian system of
                    formations. He added a new chapter to geological history, and one of peculiar
                    interest, because it contains the story of almost the earliest appearance of
                    living things upon this planet. From the year 1825, when his first paper was
                    read, down to the year of his death he continued to augment the literature of
                    his favourite science with papers and memoirs. These, upwards of 150 in number,
                    were published in the transactions of scientific societies at home and abroad.
                    His <hi rend="italic">Silurian System, Russia and the Ural Mountains,</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Siluria</hi> were the most voluminous and important of his
                    independent works. As a careful original observer, a sympathetic and liberal
                    friend of scientific progress, and a man of wealth and good social position
                    Murchison enjoyed a peculiar eminence among the scientific men of his day, and
                    occupied a place which none of his surviving compeers could wholly fill. See
                    Murchison’s <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by A. Geikie, 1875. (A. GE.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
