<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0121-0110-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MUSSEL (9th edition, volume 17, page 110)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k47x">Mussels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h9v">Pearls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t12">Bait</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1031088">Mussels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1161386">Unio</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056116">Pearls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n121/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MUSSEL</label>, a term applied in England to two families of
                    Lamellibranch Molluscs,—the marine <hi rend="italic">Mytilacea,</hi> of which
                    the Edible Mussel, <hi rend="italic">Mytilus edulis,</hi> is the representative,
                    and the fresh-water <hi rend="italic">Unionacea,</hi> of which the River Mussel,
                        <hi rend="italic">Unio pictorum,</hi> and the Swan Mussel, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anodon cygneus,</hi> are the common British examples. It is not obvious why
                    these fresh-water forms have been associated popularly with the <hi
                        rend="italic">Mytilacea</hi> under the name Mussel, unless it be on account
                    of the frequently very dark colour of their shells. They are somewhat remote
                    from the sea mussels in structure, and have not even a common economic
                    importance.</p>
                <p>The Sea Mussel <hi rend="italic">(Mytilus edulis)</hi> belongs to the second
                    order of the class <hi rend="italic">Lamellibranchia</hi> (see vol. xvi. pp. 685
                        <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> namely, the <hi rend="italic">Heteromya,</hi>
                    in which the anterior or palliai adductor is much smaller than the pedal or
                    posterior adductor. It and the other <hi rend="italic">Mytilacea</hi> are
                    remarkable for the comparatively free condition of the gill-filaments, which,
                    whilst adhering to one another to form gill-plates (vol. xvi. p. 689, fig. 133),
                    are yet not fused to one another by concrescence. It is also remarkable for the
                    small size of its foot and the large development of two glands in the foot— the
                    byssus-forming and the byssus-cementing glands.</p>
                <p>The byssus is a collection of horny threads by which the Sea Mussel (like many
                    other Lamellibranch or Bivalve Molluscs) fixes itself to stones, rocks, or
                    submerged wood, but is not a permanent means of attachment, since it can be
                    discarded by the animal, which, after a certain amount of locomotion, again
                    fixes itself by new secretion of byssus from the foot. Such movement is,
                    however, very rare. <hi rend="italic">Mytilus</hi> possesses no siphonal
                    tube-like productions öf the margin of the mantle-skirt, nor any notching of the
                    same, representative of the siphons which are found in its freshwater ally, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Dreissena</hi><hi rend="italic">polymorpha.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Mytilus edulis</hi> is an exceedingly abundant and widely
                    distributed form. It occurs on both sides of the northern Atlantic and in the
                    Mediterranean basin. It presents varieties of form and colour according to the
                    depth of water and other circumstances of its habitat. Usually it is found on
                    the British coast encrusting rocks exposed at low tides, or on the flat surfaces
                    formed by sandbanks overlying clay, the latter kind of colonies being known
                    locally as “scalps.” Under these conditions it forms continuous masses of
                    individuals closely packed together, sometimes extending over many acres of
                    surface and numbering millions. The readiness with which the young <hi
                        rend="italic">Mytilus</hi> attaches itself to wicker-work is made the means
                    of artificially cultivating and securing these molluscs for the market both in
                    the bay of Kiel in North Germany and at the mouth of the Somme and other spots
                    on the coast of France.</p>
                <p>Natural scalps are subject to extreme vicissitudes: an area of many acres may be
                    destroyed by a local change of current producing a deposit of sand or shingle
                    over the scalp, or by exposure to frost at low tide in winter, or by
                    accumulation of decomposing vegetable matter. The chief localities of natural
                    scalps on the British coast are Morecambe Bay in Lancashire and the flat eastern
                    shores, especially that of the Wash of Lincoln, and similar shallow bays. These
                    scalps are in some cases in the hands of private owners, but the English
                    Government has not granted sufficiently definite rights to such individuals to
                    enable them to protect their property from marauders, and to justify them in
                    undertaking artificial cultivation.</p>
                <p>The Sea Mussel is scarcely inferior in commercial value to the oyster. In 1873
                    the value of mussels exported from Antwerp alone to Paris to be used as human
                    food was £280,000. In Britain their chief consumption is in the deep-sea line
                    fishery, where they are held to be the most killing of all baits. Twenty-eight
                    boats engaged in haddock-fishing at Eyemouth used between October 1882 and May
                    1883 920 tons of mussels (about 47 million individuals), costing nearly £1800 to
                    the fishermen, about one-half of which sum was expended on the carriage of the
                    mussels. It is quite impossible to calculate the number of tons of mussels
                    annually used in this way by British fishermen, but it amounts to some hundreds
                    of thousands, and the supplying of the market would offer a lucrative investment
                    for capital did the Government grant definite proprietary rights over the
                    fore-shore and sea-bottom to those ready to enter upon such enterprise. Many
                    thousand tons of mussels are wastefully employed as manure by the farmers on
                    lands adjoining scalp-producing coast, as in Lancashire and Norfolk, three
                    half-pence a bushel being the price quoted in such cases. It is a curious fact,
                    illustrative of the ignorant procedure and arbitrary fashions of fisher-folk,
                    that on the Atlantic seaboard of the United States the Sea Mussel, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mytilus edulis,</hi> though common, is not used as bait nor as
                    food. Instead, the Soft Clam, <hi rend="italic">Mya</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >arenaria,</hi> a Lamellibranch not used by English or Norwegian fishermen,
                    though abundant on their shores, is employed as bait by the fishermen to the
                    extent of 1⅛ million bushels per annum, valued at £120,000. At the mouth of the
                    river Conway in North Wales the Sea Mussel is crushed in large quantities in
                    order to extract pearls of an inferior quality which are occasionally found in
                    these as in other Lamellibranch Molluscs (Gwyn Jeffreys).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mytilus edulis</hi> is considered of fair size for eating when
                    it is 2 inches in length, which size is attained in three years after the spat
                    or young mussel has fixed itself. Under favourable circumstances it will grow
                    much larger than this, specimens being recorded of 9 inches in length. It is
                    very tolerant of fresh water, fattening best, as does the oyster, in water of
                    density 1014 (the density of the water of the North Sea being 1026). Experiments
                    made by removing mussels from salt water to brackish, and finally to quite fresh
                    water show that it is even mote tolerant of fresh water than the oyster; of
                    thirty mussels so transferred all were alive after fifteen days. <hi
                        rend="italic">Mytilus edulis</hi> is occasionally poisonous, owing to
                    conditions not satisfactorily determined.</p>
                <p>The fresh-water Mussels, <hi rend="italic">Anodon cygneus,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Unio pictorum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">TJnio margaritiferus</hi> belong
                    to the order Isomya of Lamellibranch Molluscs, in which the anterior and
                    posterior adductor muscles are equally developed. An account of the anatomy of
                        <hi rend="italic">Anodon</hi> is given in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Mollusca.</hi><hi rend="italic">Unio</hi> differs in no important point
                    from <hi rend="italic">Anodon</hi> in internal structure. The family <hi
                        rend="italic">Unionacea,</hi> to which these genera belong, is of world-wide
                    distribution, and its species occur only in ponds and rivers. A vast number of
                    species arranged in several genera and sub-genera have been distinguished, but
                    in the British Islands the three species above named are the only claimants to
                    the title of “fresh-water mussel.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Anodon cygneus,</hi> the Pond Mussel or Swan Mussel, appears to
                    be entirely without economic importance. <hi rend="italic">Unio pictorum,</hi>
                    the common Biver Mussel (Thames), appears to owe its name to the fact that the
                    shells were used at one time for holding water-colour paints as now shells of
                    this species and of the Sea Mussel are used for holding gold and silver paint
                    sold by artists’ colourmen, but it has no other economic value. <hi
                        rend="italic">Unio margaritiferas,</hi> the Pearl Mussel, was at one time of
                    considerable importance as a source of pearls, and the pearl mussel fishery is
                    to this day carried on under peculiar state regulations in Sweden and Saxony,
                    and other parts of the Continent. In Scotland and Ireland the pearl mussel
                    fishery was also of importance, but has altogether dwindled into insignificance
                    since the opening up of commercial intercourse with the East and with the
                    islands of the Pacific Ocean, whence finer and more abundant pearls than those
                    of <hi rend="italic">Unio</hi><hi rend="italic">margaritiferus</hi> arè
                    derived.</p>
                <p>In the last forty years of the last century pearls were exported from the Scotch
                    fisheries to Paris to the value of £100,000; round pearls, the size of a pea,
                    perfect in every respect, were worth £3 or £4. The Pearl Mussel is still used as
                    bait in the Aberdeen cod fishery.</p>
                <p>For an account of the anatomy of <hi rend="italic">Mytilus edulis</hi> the reader
                    is referred to the treatise by Sabatier on that subject (Paris, 1875). Its
                    development from the egg has not been fully studied, but some very important
                    facts as to the structure of the free-swimming young or spat are to be found in
                    the memoir by Lacaze Duthiers, <hi rend="italic">Annules</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >des Sciences</hi><hi rend="italic">Naturelles,</hi> 1856. The essayby Mr
                    Charles Harding on <hi rend="italic">Molluscs used for Food or Bait,</hi>
                    published by the committee of the London International Fisheries Exhibition,
                    1883, may be consulted as to the economic questions connected with the Sea
                    Mussel. (E. R. I..)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
