<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0057-0048-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MURAT, Joachim</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 48</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864856">Clouds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1138503">Summer</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:844959">Camps</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150446">Thrones</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n57/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MURAT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joachim</hi></label> (1768-1815),
                    king of Naples and a celebrated French cavalry leader, was, according to most
                    accounts, the younger son of an innkeeper at Bastide For-tunière in the
                    department of Lot, France, and was born in 1768, but by his own account his
                    father was a well-to-do farmer in that village. This is most probably the truth,
                    as after being educated at a seminary at Cahors he was entered at the university
                    of Toulouse, where he studied canon law. He was intended for the priesthood, but
                    led a reckless life; and after spending all his money he enlisted in a cavalry
                    regiment. He had attained the rank of “maréchal des logis” in 1789, and was the
                    recognized leader of the young soldiers from his great prowess in all athletics
                    and feats of daring. His influence was so great and so prejudicial to authority
                    that he received unlimited leave of absence in 1790. In November 1791 he was
                    elected by the department of Lot a member of the garde <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n60/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0060-0049"/> constitutionelle of the king. In May 1792 the
                    garde was disbanded, but Murat had shown such military qualities and such
                    advanced principles that he was at once appointed a sub-lieutenant in the
                    chasseurs-à-cheval, and on the outbreak of war aide-de-camp to General Hué. He
                    was rapidly promoted to be captain and major in the 21st chasseurs, but after
                    Thermidor found himself looked upon with suspicion on account of his former
                    advanced republican sentiments. He was recalled from the front, and happened to
                    be wandering about Paris in the spring and summer of 1795, like another
                    unemployed officer, Napoleon Bonaparte, whose acquaintance he made, and whose
                    friendship he won. When Bonaparte was requested by Barras to undertake the
                    defence of the convention in Vendémiaire 1795 he at once called Murat to his
                    side and commissioned him to bring up from Sèvres the artillery with which the
                    sections were shot down. His services on this occasion were recognized by his
                    receiving the lieutenant-colonelcy of the 21st chasseurs and the appointment of
                    first aide-de-camp to General Bonaparte in Italy. In the first battles of the
                    famous campaign of 1796, Montenotte, Ceva, Dego, and Mondovi, Murat so greatly
                    distinguished himself that he was chosen to carry the flags taken from the enemy
                    to Paris. He was promoted to be general of brigade, and returned to Italy in
                    time to be of essential service to Bonaparte at Bassano and Corona and Fort St
                    Georges, where he was wounded. He then was sent on a diplomatic mission to
                    Genoa, but returned in time to be present at Rivoli. In the advance into Tyrol
                    in the summer of 1797 he commanded the vanguard, and by his passage of the
                    Tagliamento hurried on the preliminaries of Leoben. In 1798 he was for a short
                    time commandant at Rome, and then accompanied Bonaparte to Egypt. At the battle
                    of the Pyramids he led his first famous cavalry charge, and so distinguished
                    himself in Syria that he was made general of division. He returned to France
                    with Bonaparte, and on the 18th Brumaire led into the orangery of Saint Cloud
                    the sixty grenadiers whose appearance broke up the Council of Five Hundred. He
                    was, after the success of the coup d’état, made commandant of the consular
                    guard, and in January 1800 married Marie Annonciade Caroline Bonaparte, the
                    youngest sister of the first consul. He commanded the French cavalry at the
                    battle of Marengo, and was afterwards made governor in the Cisalpine Republic.
                    He was made a marshal of France in 1804; he was titular governor of Paris, was
                    invested with the grand eagle of the Legion of Honour, and appointed grand
                    admiral of France with the title of prince in 1805. He commanded the cavalry of
                    the grand army in the German campaign of 1805, and was so conspicuous at
                    Austerlitz that Napoleon made him grand-duke of Berg and Cleves. He commanded
                    the cavalry at Jena, Eylau, and Friedland, and in 1808 was made general-in-chief
                    of the French armies in Spain. He entered Madrid on 25th March, and did much to
                    hurry on the Spanish policy of Napoleon. The inhabitants of Madrid showed their
                    hatred for the French by murdering on 2d May all the isolated or wounded
                    Frenchmen they could find. Murat vigorously put down the riot, but not cruelly,
                    for only 158 Spaniards fell to 500 Frenchmen; and he hoped for the throne of
                    Spain as his reward. But the throne of Spain was given to Joseph Bonaparte, and
                    Murat received Joseph’s former kingdom of Naples.</p>
                <p>King Joachim Napoleon, as he called himself, entered Naples in September 1808,
                    and soon won great popularity by his handsome presence and his gaiety of manner.
                    He took Capri from the English, and organized a Neapolitan army of 80,000
                    infantry and 10,000 cavalry. But his attention was not confined to military
                    matters; he effected other great reforms in finally abolishing all relics of
                    feudalism and putting down brigandism. Unfortunately much injustice was done by
                    General Manhès in this last reform, which seriously affected Murat’s popularity
                    in Calabria. He was not present at Aspern or Wagram, but once more commanded the
                    cavalry of the grand army in the Russian campaign of 1812. He manifested his
                    usual headlong valour in the disastrous retreat, but, being offended by
                    Napoleon, he suddenly threw up. his command and left for Naples. He then began
                    an intrigue with Austria. Whether it was that he hoped to escape from a doubtful
                    cause or that he was really offended by Napoleon’s preference for Eugène
                    Beauharnais is not known, but in March 1813 he sent Prince Cariati to Vienna to
                    declare that he would surrender his claims to Sicily if Austria would guarantee
                    Naples to him. In January 1814 the alliance with Austria was declared by Murat’s
                    seizing the principality of Benevento, while Austria promised him Ancona for a
                    force of 30,000 men. At the congress of Vienna his independence was attacked by
                    Talleyrand, who was his personal enemy, and it was as much from distrust of
                    Austria as anything else that he declared in March 1815 that he intended to
                    restore the unity and independence of Italy. He had hoped that Lord William
                    Bentinck, the English general, would have supported him, but in vain. The
                    Austrians steadily advanced, and on 2d May he suffered a disastrous defeat at
                    the battle of Tolentino. With difficulty he escaped, and reached France on 27th
                    May. He offered his sword to Napoleon, who indignantly refused his offer, and he
                    then hid in seclusion near Toulon with a price upon hi ’ s head. After Waterloo
                    he was refused an asylum in England, and went to Corsica, where he was joined by
                    a few rash spirits, who urged him to strike another blow for his kingdom of
                    Naples. He refused an offer of asylum from Metternich, and started with six
                    ships. By a great mistake he landed in Calabria, where he was hated for the
                    cruelty of Manhès, on 6th October; his ships deserted him, and he was taken
                    prisoner by a captain named Trenta-Capilli, whose brother had been executed by
                    Manhès. He was imprisoned in the fort of Pizzo, and on 13th October 1815 was
                    tried by court-martial, under a law of his own, for disturbing the public peace
                    and was sentenced to be shot in half an hour. After writing a touching letter of
                    farewell to his wife and children, he bravely met his fate, and was buried at
                    Pizzo.</p>
                <p>As a king much good can be said of him; by his valour he had risen from nothing
                    to royalty, and instead of being careless of the good of his adopted country he
                    showed himself a truly wise king. As a general he was the most dashing cavalry
                    leader of the age, and, as he himself said, his presence at Waterloo would have
                    given more concentrated power to the French cavalry charges, and possibly
                    success. As a man he was rash, hot-tempered, and impetuously brave; he was
                    adored by his troopers, who followed their idol, the “golden eagle,” into the
                    most terrible fire and against the most terrible odds.</p>
                <p>For the life of Murat and his rule in Naples consult <hi rend="italic">Vie de
                    Joachim Murat,</hi> by Μ* * *, 1815; <hi rend="italic">Memorie sulla
                    condotta</hi><hi rend="italic">politica e militare</hi><hi rend="italic">tenuta
                    da Gioacchino Murat,</hi> 1815; <hi rend="italic">Gioacchino Murat, o</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">del Reame di Napoli dal</hi> 1800 <hi
                    rend="italic">al</hi> 1815, Milan, 1839; <hi rend="italic">Campagnes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Aιdrichiens</hi><hi rend="italic">contre</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Murat</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi> 1815, by V* * C* * de Br., Brussels, 1821;
                    and particularly Freiherr von Helfert, <hi rend="italic">Joachim Murat,
                    seine</hi><hi rend="italic">letzten Kämpfe und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >seine</hi><hi rend="italic">Ende,</hi> Vienna, 1878. For his daring attempt in
                    1815 and his death see A. de Beauchamp, <hi rend="italic">Catastrophe de
                    Murat,</hi> 1815; Francis Macirone, <hi rend="italic">Interesting^ facts
                    relating to the fall and death of Joachim Murat, King of Naples,</hi> London,
                    1817; P. Colletta, <hi rend="italic">Pochi fatti</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >su</hi><hi rend="italic">Gioacchino Murat,</hi> Naples, 1820, correcting
                    Macirone, and translated by I.. Gallois, Paris, 1823; Galvani, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires sur les Événements gui</hi><hi rend="italic">out</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >précédé la· mort de Joachim, roi des Deux</hi><hi rend="italic">Sidles,</hi>
                    Paris, 1843; and Jean de la Rocca, <hi rend="italic">Le Roi Murat et ses
                    derniers jours,</hi> from the papers of Multedo, who accompanied the king,
                    Paris, 1868. (H. Μ. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
