<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0066-0055-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MURILLO, Bartolomé</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 55</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:926650">Fishing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MURILLO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bartolomé</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Esteban</hi> (1617-1682), the greatest ecclesiastical painter
                    of Spain, was the son of Gaspar Esteban Murillo and Maria Perez, and was born at
                    Seville in 1617, probably at the very end of the year, as he was baptized on 1st
                    January 1618. Esteban-Murillo appears to have been the compound surname of the
                    father, but some inquirers consider that, in accordance with a frequent
                    Andalusian custom, the painter assumed the surname of his maternal grandmother,
                    Elvira Murillo, in addition to that of his father. His parents (of whom nothing
                    distinct is known, save that they were of a humble class), having been struck
                    with the precocious sketches with which the unlettered boy was accustomed to
                    adorn whatever available surface came in his way, wisely resolved to place him
                    under the care of their distant relative, Juan del Castillo, the painter. Juan,
                    a correct draughtsman and dry colourist, taught him all the mechanical parts of
                    his profession with extreme care, and Murillo proved himself an apt and docile
                    pupil. The artistic appliances of his master’s studio were by no means abundant,
                    and were often of the simplest kind. A few casts, some stray fragments of
                    sculpture, and a lay figure formed the principal aids available in those days
                    for the Sevillian student of art. A living model was a luxury generally beyond
                    the means of the school, but on great occasions the youths would strip in turn
                    and proffer an arm or a leg to be studied by their fellows. Objects of still
                    life, however, were much studied by Murillo, and he early learned to hit off the
                    ragged urchins of Seville pursuing their adventures in the market-place. Murillo
                    in a few years painted as well as his master, and as stiffly. His two pictures
                    of the Virgin, executed during this period, show how thoroughly he had mastered
                    the style, with all its defects. Castillo was a very kind man, but his removal
                    to Cadiz in 1639-40 threw his favourite pupil entirely upon his own resources.
                    The fine school of Zurbaran was too expensive for the poor lad; his parents were
                    either dead or too poor to help him, and he was compelled to earn his bread by
                    painting rough pictures for the “feria” or public fair of Seville. The religious
                    daubs exposed at that mart were generally of as low an order as the prices paid
                    for them by their rude purchasers. A “pintura de la feria” (a picture for the
                    fair) was a proverbial expression for an execrably bad one; yet the street
                    painters who thronged the market-place with their “clumsy saints and unripe
                    Madonnas” not unfrequently rose to be able and even famous artists. This
                    rough-and-ready practice, partly for the market-place, partly for converts in
                    Mexico and Peru, for whom Madonnas and popular saints -were produced and shipped
                    off by the dozen, doubtless increased Murillo’s manual dexterity; but, if we may
                    judge from the picture of the Virgin and Child still shown in the Murillo-room
                    at Seville as belonging to this period, he made but little improvement in
                    colouring or in general strength of design. Struck by the favourable change
                    which travel had wrought upon the style of his brother artist Pedro de Moya,
                    Murillo in 1642 resolved to make a journey to Flanders or Italy in quest of
                    further insight into art. But how was he, already struggling for existence and
                    with a poor sister dependent on him, to raise the means necessary for such an
                    expedition? Having bought a large quantity of canvas, he cut it into squares of
                    different sizes, which he converted into pictures of a kind likely to sell. The
                    American traders at once bought up his pieces, and he now found himself
                    sufficiently rich to carry out his much-cherished design. He placed his sister
                    under the care of some friends, and without divulging his plans to any one set
                    out for Madrid. On reaching the capital he waited on Velazquez, his
                    fellowtownsman, the great court-painter, then at the summit of his fortune, and,
                    communicating to him his simple story, asked for some introduction to friends in
                    Rome. The master liked what he saw of the manly youth, and in the noblest manner
                    offered him lodging in his own house, and proposed to procure him admission to
                    the royal galleries of the capital. Murillo accepted the offer, and here enjoyed
                    the masterpieces of Italy and Flanders without travelling beyond the walls of
                    Madrid. The next two years were chiefly spent in copying from Ribera, Vandyck,
                    and Velazquez; and in 1644 he so greatly astonished the latter with some of his
                    efforts that they were submitted to the inspection of the king and the court.
                    His patron now urged him to go to Rome, and offered him letters to smooth his
                    way; but Murillo, from whatever cause, preferred returning to his sister and his
                    native Seville.</p>
                <p>The friars of the convent of San Francisco in Seville had about this time piously
                    determined to adorn the walls of their small cloister in a manner worthy of
                    their patron saint. But the brotherhood had no money; and after endless begging
                    they still found themselves incapable of employing an artist of name to execute
                    the task. Murillo was needy, and offered his services; after balancing their own
                    poverty against his obscurity the friars bade him begin. Murillo covered the
                    walls with eleven large pictures of remarkable power and beauty,—displaying by
                    turns the strong colouring of Ribera, the life-like truthfulness of Velazquez,
                    and the sweetness of Vandyck. Among them were to be found representations of San
                    Francisco, of San Diego, of Santa Clara, and of San Gil. These pictures were
                    executed in his earliest style, commonly called his <hi rend="italic">frio</hi>
                    or cold style. It was based chiefly on Ribera and Caravaggio, and was dark with
                    a decided outline. This rich collection is no longer to be met with in Seville;
                    Marshal Soult carried off ten of the works. The fame of these striking
                    productions soon got abroad, and “El Claustro Chico” swarmed daily with artists
                    and critics. Murillo was no longer friendless and unknown. The rich and the
                    noble of Seville overwhelmed him with their commissions and their praises.</p>
                <p>In 1648 Murillo married a wealthy lady of rank, Dona Beatriz de Cabrera y
                    Sotomayor, of the neighbourhood of Seville, and his house soon became the
                    favourite resort of artists and connoisseurs. About this time he was associated
                    with the landscape-painter Yriarte—the two artists interchanging figures and
                    landscapes for their respective works; but they did not finally agree, and the
                    co-operation came to an end. Murillo now painted the well-known Flight into
                    Egypt, and shortly afterwards changed his earliest style of painting for his <hi
                    rend="italic">calido</hi> or warm style. His drawing was still well defined, but
                    his outlines became softer and his figures rounder, and his colouring gained in
                    warmth and transparency. His first picture of this style, according to Cean
                    Bermudez, was a representation of Our Lady of the Conception, and was painted in
                    1652 for the brotherhood of the True Cross; he received for it 2500 reals (£26).
                    In 1655 he executed his two famous paintings of San Leandro and San Isidoro at
                    the order of Don Juan Federigo, archdeacon of Carmona, which are now to be seen
                    in the cathedral of Seville. These are two noble <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n67/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0067-0056"/> portraits, finished with great care and admirable
                    effect, but the critics complain of the figures being rather short. His next
                    picture, the Nativity of the Virgin, painted for the chapter, is regarded as one
                    of the most delightful specimens of his <hi rend="italic">calido</hi> style. In
                    the following year (1656) the same body gave him an order for a vast picture of
                    San Antonio de Padua, for which he received 10,000 reals (£104). This is one of
                    his most celebrated performances, and still hangs in the baptistery of the
                    cathedral. It was “repaired” in 1833; the grandeur of the design, however, and
                    the singular richness of the colouring may still be traced. The same year saw
                    him engaged on four large pictures of a semicircular form, designed by his fast
                    friend and patron Don Justino Neve y Yevenes, to adorn the walls of the church
                    of Santa Maria la Blanca. The first two were meant to illustrate the history of
                    the festival of Our Lady of the Snow, or the foundation of the Roman basilica of
                    Santa Maria Maggiore. The one represents the wealthy but childless Roman senator
                    and his lady asleep and dreaming; the other exhibits the devout pair relating
                    their dream to Pope Liberius. Of these two noble paintings the Dream is the
                    finer, and in it is to be noticed the commencement of Murillo’s third and last
                    style, known as the <hi rend="italic">vaporoso</hi><hi rend="italic">or</hi>
                    vapoury. It should be noted, however, that the three styles are not strictly
                    separable into dateperiods; for the painter alternated the styles according to
                    his subject-matter or the mood of his inspiration, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >calido</hi> being the most frequent. In the <hi rend="italic">vaporoso</hi>
                    method the well - marked outlines and careful drawing of his former styles
                    disappear, the outlines are lost in the misty blending of the light and shade,
                    and the general finish betrays more haste than was usual with Murillo. After
                    many changes of fortune, these two pictures now hang in the Academy of San
                    Fernando at Madrid. The remaining pieces executed for this small church were a
                    Virgin of the Conception and a figure of Faith. Soult laid his hands on these
                    also, and they have not been recovered.</p>
                <p>In 1658 Murillo undertook and consummated a task which had hitherto baffled all
                    the artists of Spain, and even royalty itself. This was the establishing of a
                    public academy of art. By superior tact and good temper he overcame the vanity
                    of Valdes Leal and the presumption of the younger Herrera, and secured their
                    co-operation. The Academy of Seville was accordingly opened for the first time
                    in January 1660, and Murillo and the second Herrera were chosen presidents. The
                    former continued to direct it during the following year; but the calls of his
                    studio induced him to leave it, now flourishing and prosperous, in other
                    hands.</p>
                <p>Passing over some half-length pictures of saints and a dark-haired Madonna,
                    painted in 1668 for the chapterroom of the cathedral of his native city, we
                    enter upon the most splendid period of Murillo’s career. In 1661 Don Miguel
                    Manara Vicentelo de Leca, who had recently turned to a life of sanctity from one
                    of the wildest profligacy, resolved to raise money for the restoration of the
                    dilapidated Hospital de la Caridad, of whose pious guild he was himself a
                    member. Manara commissioned his friend Murillo to paint eleven pictures for this
                    edifice of San Jorge. Three of these pieces represented the Annunciation of the
                    Blessed Virgin, the Infant Saviour, and the Infant St John. The remaining eight
                    are considered Murillo’s masterpieces. They consist of Moses striking the Rock,
                    the Return of the Prodigal, Abraham receiving the Three Angels, the Charity of
                    San Juan de Dios, the Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes, Our Lord healing the
                    Paralytic, St Peter released from Prison by the Angel, and St Elizabeth of
                    Hungary. These works occupied the artist four years, and in 1674 he received for
                    his eight great pictures 78,115 reals or about £800. The Moses, the Loaves
                    and</p>
                <p>Fishes, and the San Juan are still to be found at Seville; but the French carried
                    off the rest. On these pictures Murillo evidently expended all his strength, and
                    he has left in them an enduring monument of his genius. For compass and vigour
                    the Moses stands first; but the Prodigal’s Return and the St Elizabeth were
                    considered by Bermudez the most perfect of all as works of art. The front of
                    this famous hospital was also indebted to the genius of Murillo <hi
                    rend="italic">; five</hi> large designs in blue glazed tiles were executed from
                    his drawings. He had scarcely completed the undertakings for this edifice when
                    his favourite Franciscans again solicited the aid of his pencil. He accordingly
                    executed some twenty paintings for the humble little church known as the Convent
                    de los Capucinos. Seventeen of these Capuchin pictures are still preserved in
                    the Museum of Seville. Of these the Charity of St Thomas of Villanueva is
                    reckoned the best. Murillo himself was wont to call it “su lienzo” (his own
                    picture). Another little piece of extraordinary merit, which once hung in this
                    church, is the Virgin of the Napkin, believed to have been painted on a
                    “servilleta” and presented to the cook of the Capuchin brotherhood as a memorial
                    of the artist’s pencil.</p>
                <p>In 1670 Murillo is said to have declined an invitation to court, preferring to
                    labour among the brown coats of Seville. Eight years afterwards his friend the
                    canon Justino again employed him to paint three pieces for the Hospital de los
                    Venerables: the Mystery of the Immaculate Conception, St Peter Weeping, and the
                    Blessed Virgin. As a mark of esteem, Murillo next painted a full-length portrait
                    of the canon, in which all the artist’s skill is visible. The sleek spaniel
                    reposing at the feet of the priest has been known before now to call forth a
                    snarl from a living dog as he approached it. His portraits generally, though
                    few, are of great beauty. Towards the close of his life Murillo executed a
                    series of pictures illustrative of the life of “the glorious doctor” for the
                    Augustinian convent at Seville. This brings us to the last work of the artist.
                    Mounting a scaffolding one day at Cadiz (whither he had gone in 1681) to execute
                    the higher parts of a large picture of the Espousal of St Catherine, on which he
                    was engaged for the Capuchins of that town, he stumbled, and fell so violently
                    that he received a hurt from which he never recovered. The great picture was
                    left unfinished, and the artist returned to his beloved Seville only to die. He
                    died as he had lived, a humble, pious, brave man, on the 3d of April 1682 in the
                    arms of the chevalier Pedro Nunez de Villavicencio, an intimate friend and one
                    of his best pupils. Another of his numerous pupils was Sebastian Gomez, named
                    “Murillo’s Mulatto.” Murillo left behind him two sons (one of them at first an
                    indifferent painter, afterwards a priest) and a daughter,—his wife having died
                    before him. His body was laid in the church of Santa Cruz, which he had greatly
                    frequented during his last illness; and by his own desire it was covered with a
                    stone slab bearing his name, a skeleton, and the words “<hi rend="italic"
                    >Vive</hi><hi rend="italic">moriturus."</hi> Soult sacked this church, and
                    nothing is to be seen of it now but a heap of rubbish.</p>
                <p>Murillo has always been one of the most popular of painters—not in Spain alone.
                    His works show great technical attainment without much style, and a strong
                    feeling for ordinary nature and for truthful or sentimental expression without
                    lofty beauty or ideal elevation. His ecstasies of Madonnas and Saints, the
                    themes of some of his most celebrated achievements, neither raise the mind nor
                    seize upon the imagination; but they stimulate sluggish perceptions and lukewarm
                    devoteeism, and are accepted as ravishingly pious by mobs of the fashionable and
                    the unfashionable. Take as an example the Immaculate Conception (or Assumption
                    of the Virgin, for the titles may, with reference to Murillo’s treatments of
                    this subject, almost be interchanged) in the Louvre, a picture for which, on its
                    sale from the Soult collection, perhaps the largest <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n68/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0068-0057"/> price on record was given in 1852, some £24,600.
                    His subjects may be broadly divided into two great groups—the scenes from low
                    life (which were a new kind of experiment in Spanish art, so far as the subjects
                    of children are concerned), and the Scriptural, legendary, and religious works.
                    The former, of which some salient specimens are in the Dulwich Gallery, are,
                    although undoubtedly truthful, neither ingenious nor sympathetic; sordid
                    unsightliness and roguish squalor are their foundation. The children have little
                    of the charm of childhood, and none of its auroral promise. The embodiments are
                    accurate and knowing studies of ungainliness. Works of this class belong mostly
                    to the earlier years of Murillo’s practice. The subjects in which the painter
                    most eminently excels are crowded compositions in which some act of saintliness,
                    involving the ascetic or self-mortifying element, is being performed,—subjects
                    which, while obtrusively repulsive in some of their details, emphasize at once
                    the broadly human and the expressly Catholic conceptions of life. A famous
                    example is the picture, now in the Madrid academy, of St Elizabeth of Hungary
                    washing patients afflicted with the scab or itch, and hence commonly named El
                    Tinoso. Technically considered, it unites his three styles of painting, more
                    especially the cold and the warm. His power of giving atmosphere to combined
                    groups of figures is one of the marked characteristics of Murillo’s art; and he
                    may be said to have excelled in this respect all his predecessors or
                    contemporaries of whatever school.</p>
                <p>Seville must still be visited by persons who wish to study Murillo thoroughly,
                    and to relish the full and native flavour of his art. A large number of the
                    works which used to adorn this city have, however, been transported elsewhither.
                    In the Royal Gallery at Madrid are forty-five specimens of Murillo—the Infant
                    Christ and the Baptist (named Los Ninos della Concha), St Ildefonso vested with
                    a Chasuble by the Madonna, &amp;c.; in the Museo della Trinidad, Christ and the
                    Virgin appearing to St Francis in a Cavern, an immense composition, and various
                    others. In the London National Gallery the chief example is the Holy Family;
                    this was one of the master’s latest works, painted in Cadiz. Murillo, who was
                    the last pre-eminent painter of Seville, was an indefatigable and most prolific
                    worker, hardly leaving his painting-room save for his assiduous devotions in
                    church; he realized large prices according to the standard of his time, and made
                    a great fortune. His character is recorded as very amiable and soft, yet not the
                    less independent, subject also to sudden impulses, not unmixed with gusts of
                    passion.</p>
                <p>For further information see, especially, Stirling, <hi rend="italic">Annals of
                    the Artists of Spain,</hi> 3 vols., London, 1848; Richard Ford, <hi
                    rend="italic">Handbook for Spain,</hi> London, 1855; and Curtis, <hi
                    rend="italic">Catalogue of the Works of Velazquez and Murillo</hi> (1883). (W.
                    Μ. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
