<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0010-0001-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MOTHER-OF-PEARL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 1</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1056116">Pearls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821509">Australianisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1052751">Papuans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205585">Panama</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p24h">Papuans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h9v">Pearls</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n10/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MOTHER-OF-PEARL</label>. The shells of many molluscous
                    animals display a brilliant pearly and iridescent lustre, resulting from the
                    peculiar manner in which the layers of calcareous matter of which they are
                    composed have been successively formed. Such shells, even when small in size,
                    form bright and, specially to the untutored eye, attractive ornaments, and as
                    such are used for necklaces and similar purposes. When the shells are of
                    sufficient size to cut and shape for purposes of utility, they become an article
                    of some commercial importance under the name of Mother-of-Pearl. This term,
                    though applicable to all pearly shells, is in commerce principally applied to
                    the shells of the bivalve pearl-mussel <hi rend="italic">Afeleagrina</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">margaritifera,</hi> which is <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0011-0002"/> the principal source of the commercial product.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Meleagrina</hi><hi rend="italic">margaritifera</hi> is a
                    native of tropical seas, and is found around the coasts of all the lands within
                    the tropics. The shells vary in size, the largest reaching to about the
                    dimensions of a dessert plate, with a weight of from 1 to 1∣ tt&gt;. They also
                    vary in colour to a considerable extent, some being dark and smoky round the
                    outer edge with little iridescence, others dark but possessing a rich play of
                    colours, and the greater part pearly white with varying iridescence. The
                    principal sources of supply are the islands of the East Indian archipelago, the
                    Pacific islands, the north-west Australian coast, the Persian and Red Seas, and
                    the Gulf of Panama. The largest and steadiest consumption of mother-of-pearl is
                    in the button trade, and much is also consumed by cutlers for handles of fruit
                    and dessert knives and forks, pocket-knives, &amp;c. It is also used in the
                    inlaying of Japanese and Chinese lacquers, European lacquered papier-mâché work,
                    trays, &amp;c., and as an ornamental inlay generally. In an innumerable variety
                    of small and fancy articles mother-of-pearl is also employed, its use being
                    limited only by the moderate dimensions and thickness of material obtainable,
                    and its rather brittle nature. The carving of pilgrim shells and the elaboration
                    of crucifixes and ornamental work in mother-of-pearl is a distinctive industry
                    of the monks and other inhabitants of Bethlehem. Among the South Sea Islands the
                    shell is largely fashioned into fishing-hooks, a purpose for which its brilliant
                    conspicuous appearance appears to render it suitable without the addition of any
                    bait or other lure. Among shells other than those of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Meleagrina</hi><hi rend="italic">margaritifera</hi> used as mother-of-pearl may
                    be mentioned the Green Ear or Ormer shell <hi rend="italic">(Haliotis
                    tubercu-latd)</hi> and several other species of Haliotis, besides various
                    species of Turbo.</p>
                <p>The pearl-shell fishery is an important industry on the north and north-west
                    coasts of Australia, producing about 800 tons yearly, valued at over £100,000,
                    the Papuan islanders of Torres Straits being employed as divers under European
                    supervision, with skilled appliances. The shell of the golden-tipped variety of
                    Avicula found here is much more valuable than the dark-edged one of the South
                    Seas. The value of the fisheries depends much more on the shell than on the
                    occasional pearls found, which indeed are sometimes, along with the “fish,” a
                    perquisite of the diver; but on the west coast, about Shark’s Bay, a smaller
                    variety of the same mollusc produces valuable pearls, their exciting cause being
                    possibly present there in greater abundance. That the pearl itself is not due to
                    disease, or to the presence of any irritating cause, seems clear from the fact
                    that the mollusc can reject it at will, and often does so when taken (for which
                    reason the diver, in seizing him, at once places his hand over the opening so as
                    to close the shell); but it is believed now that the pearl is secreted and held
                    ready to be dissolved by the powerful acid of the sac, and spread in nacreous
                    layers over the spot irritated by the borer <hi rend="italic">(Pholax sp.
                    ).</hi> Accordingly pearls are seldom found in the young “fish,” whose shells
                    are much harder outside, and not susceptible to such attacks. A mass of nacreous
                    layers formed round a point of irritation or “blister” can sometimes be cut out
                    of the shell, and might easily be mistaken for (and sold as) a pearl, but it is
                    never quite perfect all round and is always hollow. Sometimes, after having
                    secured the loose pearls, the fishermen deposit the mollusc again, unharmed, in
                    a secure and accessible locality, and repeat the process for three and four
                    years successively.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
