<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0780-0757-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOLDEN BULL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 757</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110280">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1115918">Shields</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:896108">Documentation</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:893284">Diet</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nj3s">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fx74153">Documents</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n780/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOLDEN BULL</label> (Latin, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Bulla</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Aurea)</hi> is, in general, the designation of
                    any charter decorated with a golden seal or <hi rend="italic">bulla,</hi> either
                    from the intrinsic importance of its contents, or from the rank and dignity of
                    the bestower or the recipient. The custom of thus giving distinction to certain
                    documents is said to be of Byzantine origin, though if this be the case it is
                    somewhat strange that the word employed as an equivalent for golden bull in
                    Byzantine Greek should be the hybrid <hi rend="italic">χρνσόβουλλον</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">{cf</hi> Codinus Curopalates, ό μ,eγας <hi rend="italic">λογοθέτης
                    διατάττει το. παρά του βασιλέως</hi><hi rend="italic">aπoστeλλoμeνa</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">προστάγματα</hi> και <hi rend="italic">χρυσό βουλλα προς</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">τe</hi><hi rend="italic">'Ρήγας,</hi> 2οΰλτανα?, καί <hi
                    rend="italic">τοπάρχονς;</hi> and Anna Comnena, <hi rend="italic">Alexiad,</hi>
                    lib. iii., διά <hi rend="italic">^χpυσoβoυλloυ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >λόγου</hi><hi rend="italic">j</hi> lib. viii., <hi rend="italic">χρυσόβουλον
                    λόγον).</hi> In Germany a Golden Bull is mentioned under the reign of Henry I.
                    in <hi rend="italic">Chronica C assin.,</hi> ii. 31, and the oldest German
                    example, if it be genuine, dates from 983. At first the golden seal was formed
                    after the type of a solid coin, but at a later date, while the golden surface
                    presented to the eye was greatly increased, the seal was really composed of two
                    thin metal plates filled in with wax. The number of golden bulls issued by the
                    imperial chancery must have been very large; the town of Frankfort, for example,
                    still preserves no fewer than eight. But the name has become practically
                    restricted to a few documents of unusual political importance, the golden bull
                    of the Empire, the golden bull of Brabant, the golden bull of Hungary, and the
                    golden bull of Milan—and of these the first is undoubtedly <hi rend="italic"
                    >the</hi> golden bull <hi rend="italic">par excellence.</hi></p>
                <p>It was drawn up under the direction of the emperor Charles IV., and it was
                    formally ratified in 1356,—the first twenty-three chapters by the diet of
                    Nuremberg (10th January), and the remaining seven by the diet of Metz (25th
                    December). The actual redaction has been assigned to Bartolus de Saxoferrato, to
                    Rudolf of Friedberg the imperial secretary, and even to the emperor himself; but
                    there is no distinct authority for any of the three hypotheses as opposed to the
                    others. A brief statement of the general purpose of its enactments has already
                    been given at page 495 of the present volume. The exordium is a strangely
                    rhetorical lamentation over the miseries of division, and more especially of a
                    kingdom divided against itself; and the body of the document gives a survey of
                    the duties, privileges, and relations of the various dignitaries of the empire,
                    the emperor, the electors ecclesiastical and secular, the electoral
                    plenipotentiaries, and the officers of the court. As might almost be expected, a
                    large place is given to rules of ceremony and etiquette. At first the document
                    was known simply as the Lex Carolina; but by and by the name of the Book with
                    the Golden Bull came into use, and the present elliptical title was sufficiently
                    established by 1417 to be officially employed in a charter by King Sigismund.
                    The original autograph was committed to the care of the electoral prince of
                    Mainz, as chancellor-in-chief of the empire, and it was preserved in the
                    imperial archives at Mainz till 1789. Official transcripts were probably
                    furnished to each of the seven electors at the time of the promulgation, and
                    before long many of the other members of the empire secured copies for
                    themselves. The transcript which belonged to the elector of Treves is preserved
                    in the state archives at Stuttgart, that of the elector of Cologne in the court
                    library at Darmstadt, and that of the elector of Bohemia in the imperial
                    archives at Vienna. Berlin, Munich, and Dresden also boast the possession of an
                    electoral transcript; and the town of Kitzingen has a contemporary copy in its
                    municipal archives. There appears, however, to be good reason to doubt the
                    genuineness of most of these so-called original transcripts. But perhaps the
                    best known example is that of Frankfort-on-the-Main, which was procured from the
                    imperial chancery in 1366, and is adorned with a golden seal like the original.
                    Not only was it regularly quoted as the indubitable authority in regard to the
                    election of the emperors in Frankfort itself, but it was from time to time
                    officially consulted by members of the empire.</p>
                <p>The manuscript consists of 43 leaves of parchment of medium quality, each
                    measuring about 10∣ inches in height by 7⅛ in breadth. The seal is of the plate
                    and wax type. On the obverse appears a figure of the emperor seated on his
                    throne, with the sceptre in his right hand and the globe in his left; a shield,
                    with the crowned imperial eagle, occupies the space on the one side of the
                    throne, and a corresponding shield, with the crowned Bohemian lion with two
                    tails, occupies the space on the other side; and round the margin runs the
                    legend, <hi rend="italic">Kαrolus</hi><hi rend="italic">quartus divina favente
                    clementia, Romanorum imperator</hi><hi rend="italic">semper</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Augustus</hi><hi rend="italic">et Boemiae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >rex.</hi> On the reverse is a castle, with the words <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aurea</hi><hi rend="italic">Roma</hi> on the gate, and the circumscription
                    reads, <hi rend="italic">Roma caput Mundi</hi><hi rend="italic">Regit orbis
                    frena rotundi.</hi> The original Latin text of the bull was printed at Nuremberg
                    by Creussner in 1474, and a second edition by Kobergen appeared at the same
                    place in 1477. Since that time it has been frequently reprinted from various
                    manuscripts and collections. Goldastus gave the Palatine text, compared with
                    those of Bohemia and Frankfort, in his <hi rend="italic">Collectio
                    Constitutionum Imperialium,</hi> tom. i. Another is to be found in Onuphrius
                    Panvinius, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Comitiis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Imperii,</hi> and as an appendix to Cujacius, <hi rend="italic">De
                    feudis∙,</hi> and a third, of unknown history, is prefixed to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Codex</hi><hi rend="italic">Recessuum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Imperii,</hi> printed at Mainz in 1599, and again in 1615. The Frankfort text
                    appeared in 1742— <hi rend="italic">Aurca Bulla secundum exemplar</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">originale</hi><hi rend="italic">Frankfurtense</hi> —from the pen
                    of Wolfgang Ch. Multz. German translations, none of which, however, had any
                    official authority, were published at Nuremberg, 1474(?); at Venice, Johannus
                    Jenson, 1476; and at Strasburg, Joh. Preussen, 1485. Among the earlier
                    commentators· of the document are Buxtorf, Dominicus Arumaeus, Martinus
                    Rumelius, H. Caninius, G. T. Dietrich, Ostermann, Speidelius, and Limnaeus <hi
                    rend="italic">{In</hi><hi rend="italic">Auream bullam,</hi> Strasburg, 1662).
                    The student will find a good account of the older literature of the subject in
                    Biener, <hi rend="italic">Commentarii</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">origine</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">progressu
                    legum Germanicarum,</hi> 1787 (vol. ii.); and, besides the important work of
                    Ohlen-schlager, <hi rend="italic">Neue Erläuterungen der Güldener Bulla,</hi>
                    Frankfort and Leipsic, 1766, he may consult H. G. Thülemarius, <hi rend="italic"
                    >De bulla</hi><hi rend="italic">aurea argentea,</hi> &amp;c., Heidelberg, 1682
                    (which gives the Frankfort text of the bull of Charles IV., a golden bull of
                    Andronicus of Constantinople, the Bulla Brabantina, and the capitulation of
                    Maximilian II.); Pütters, <hi rend="italic">Staatsverfassung des deutschen
                    Reichs,</hi> Gottingen, 1788; Pfister, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                    Deutschen,</hi> Hamburg, 1831 (vol. iii.); and Stobbe, <hi rend="italic">Gcsch.
                    der Deutschen Rechtsquellen,</hi> Brunswick, 1860. A learned article on “Goldene
                    Bulle,” by H. Brandes, will be found in Erseh and Gmber <hi rend="superscript">
                    -</hi> s <hi rend="italic">Encyclopädie,</hi> 1861.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
