<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0162-0151-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GENEVA, The Lake of (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    151)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996964">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211573">Anguilla</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775v4s">Bible</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n162/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GENEVA, <hi rend="smallcaps">The Lake of</hi></label> (the
                    Latin <hi rend="italic">Lacus Lemanus</hi><hi rend="italic">or</hi> Lake Leman,
                    also known in the Middle Ages as Lac Losannete or Lake of Lausanne, and as Mer
                    du Rhône or Sea of the Rhone), is the largest of the Swiss lakes, having an area
                    of 578 sq. kil. or 223 sq. miles. Its general form is that of a crescent, the
                    northern shore being almost the arc of a circle, with a radius of 21 ⅛ miles.
                    The eastern end of the crescent is broad and rounded, while the western tapers
                    towards Geneva. Its maximum breadth, between Morges and Amphion, is 8∣ miles. It
                    is divided into two portions, the Great and Little Lake, by the strait of
                    Promonthoux, which is not much more than 2 miles across. The Great Lake is 39
                    miles long, with a mean breadth of 6 miles, and the Little or Western Lake is 14
                    miles long, with a mean breadth of rather more than 2 miles. The bottom of the
                    larger basin forms a wide valley, which gradually deepens from 200 to 325 feet
                    at the foot of the slopes to a maximum of 1095 feet, which it attains between
                    Ouclιy and Évian. The mean level of the surface of the lake is 1230 feet above
                    the level of the sea. According to the elaborate soundings made in 1873 by M.
                    Gosset, engineer of the Federal Topographic Department, the bottom is remarkably
                    free from inequalities, almost all traces of rocks, erratic blocks, or moraines,
                    having been covered over by a regular bed of extremely fine argillo-calcareous
                    mud, which can be moulded and baked like potter’s clay. Between the basin of the
                    Great Lake and that of the Little Lake there runs a ridge or bar not very
                    strongly marked, 200 feet from the surface. The maximum depth of the lesser
                    basin is only 71 metres or 233 feet. The bottom is apparently level, but it
                    presents numerous erratic blocks, and in one place rises to a considerable
                    eminence, known to the Genevese fishers as the Hauts Monts.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Further details on the conformation of
                            the lake will be found in De la Beche’s letter to Professor Pictet,
                            published in <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque Universelle:</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Sciences</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Arts,</hi> t. xii., 1817; in Μ. Gosset’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Carte ∏ydrogr.</hi><hi rend="italic">du Lac
                                Léman,</hi> issued as part of the <hi rend="italic">Topog.
                                Atlas</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">Schweiz,</hi>
                            and described in <hi rend="italic">Bibl. Un.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >(Sei.</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Arts),</hi> t.
                            lii., 1875, and in a <hi rend="italic">Note</hi><hi
                                rend="italic superscript"> stl</hi><hi rend="italic">r la Carte du
                                Lac,</hi> by Ed. Pictet, in the same number.</p></note> The unusual
                    blueness of the waters of the Leman has long been remarked. According to Μ.
                        Forel,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“Et ’.des sur
                            les variations de la transparence des eaux du lac Léman,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Βibl. Un. (Sc.</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Arts),</hi> 1877.</p></note> the transparency is very
                    much greater in winter than summer, the extreme limit of visibility of a white
                    disk on an average for the seven winter months from October to April being 41
                    feet, and for the five summer months 21 ’ 6. This arises from the thermal
                    stratification of the water keeping in suspension a greater quantity of dust and
                    organic particles during summer. It is generally in August that the level of the
                    lake reaches its highest limit, between 4 and 5 feet on an average above its
                    lowest limit, which is usually reached in March. Besides this seasonal change,
                    due to differences of influx and removal of water, several disturbances of level
                    of a less obvious kind have attracted the attention of the Swiss physicists.
                    Most remarkable are the <hi rend="italic">seiches,</hi> or “movements of steady
                    uninodal oscillation,” in which the whole mass of water in the lake rhythmically
                    swings from shore to shore. According to Μ. Forel,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Μ. Forel’s numerous studies on the
                            subject will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque
                                Universelle,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin de la soc.
                                τaud.</hi> (Lausanne).</p></note> there are both longitudinal and
                    transverse <hi rend="italic">seiches.</hi> Their effect is most distinctly seen
                    at Geneva, where they sometimes raise the level of the water from 4 to 5 feet.
                    They are not improbably due to several distinct causes, but the most efficient
                    would appear to be a difference of barometric pressure in different parts of the
                    lake. In the eastern portion of the lake there is an irregular but violent
                    current during spring and autumn, called Lardeyre or La Dière, which is supposed
                    to be due to subterranean affluents. The principal winds are the Bise from the
                    north-east, the stormy Bornand that rushes from the ravines of Savoy, and the
                    dry south wind, known as the Séchard. Less use is made of the lake as a means of
                    communication since the opening of the railway along the Swiss shore, but the
                    lateen sails of the minor craft still brighten the landscape, and an excellent
                    steam service is maintained by a company formed in 1873. The first steamboat,
                    the “William Tell,” was introduced on the lake in 1823; and the first saloon
                    steamboat, the “Mont Blanc,” dates only from 1876.</p>
                <p>The Lake of Geneva is not so rich in fish as many of the smaller lakes of
                        Switzerland.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>According to G. Lunel, whose <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                                naturelle</hi><hi rend="italic">des p&gt;oissons</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">du bassin du Léman,</hi> (Geneva, 1874) has superseded
                            the valuable memoir of Professor Jurine in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Mémoires de la Sociétié</hi><hi rend="italic">de physique,</hi>
                            tome iii. (1825), there are 21 species:— <hi rend="italic">Perca
                                fluviatilis,</hi> L.; <hi rend="italic">Coitus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >gobio,</hi> L.; <hi rend="italic">Lota vulgaris,</hi> Cuv.; <hi
                                rend="italic">Cyprinus</hi><hi rend="italic">carpio,</hi> L.; <hi
                                rend="italic">Cyρrinoρsis</hi><hi rend="italic">auratus,</hi> L.;
                                <hi rend="italic">Tinea vulgaris,</hi> Cuv.; <hi rend="italic">Gobio
                                fluviatilis,</hi> Cuv.; <hi rend="italic">Alburnus lucidus,</hi>
                            Heckel; <hi rend="italic">Alb. bipunctatus,</hi> L.; <hi rend="italic"
                                >Scardinius erythrophthalmus,</hi> Bonap.; <hi rend="italic"
                                >Leuciscus</hi><hi rend="italic">rutilus,</hi> L.; <hi rend="italic"
                                >Squalius</hi><hi rend="italic">cephalus,</hi> Bonap.; <hi
                                rend="italic">Phoxinus</hi><hi rend="italic">lavis,</hi> Ag.; <hi
                                rend="italic">Cobitis</hi><hi rend="italic">barbatula,</hi> Lin.;
                                <hi rend="italic">Coregonus</hi><hi rend="italic">fera,</hi> Jurine;
                                <hi rend="italic">Coregonus</hi><hi rend="italic">hiemalis,</hi>
                            Jurine; <hi rend="italic">Thymallus vulgaris,</hi> Nilsson; <hi
                                rend="italic">Salmo</hi><hi rend="italic">umbla,</hi> L.; <hi
                                rend="italic">Tnata, variabilis,</hi> G. L.; <hi rend="italic">Esox
                                lucius,</hi> L.; <hi rend="italic">Anguilla vulgaris,</hi>
                            Fleming.</p></note> Comparatively small success has attended the
                    attempts of Professor Chavannes of Lausanne to introduce the salmon, which, like
                    many other fishes, finds the Perte du Rhône a barrier between <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n163/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0163-0152"/> the sea and the lake. The “fera” <hi
                        rend="italic">(Coregonus</hi><hi rend="italic">ferai)</hi> is economically
                    the most important species. In the mud at the bottom of the lake there exists an
                    interesting fauna, of about 40 species, mainly belonging to the lower orders.
                    Several of the species, as <hi rend="italic">Gammarus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >coecus,</hi> are found 1000 feet below the surface, in the reign of
                    perpetual darkness. Two species of gastropods of the genus <hi rend="italic"
                        >Limnceus</hi> are worthy of special note as possessing developed lungs,
                    though they live at a depth of from 150 to 300 feet.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For details see Forel’s contributions to
                            the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin de la soc. vau-doise des s^. nat.,</hi> t
                            xiii., &amp;c.</p></note></p>
                <p>See Rodolphe Rey, <hi rend="italic">Genève et les rives du Léman,</hi> 3d ed.
                    (Geneva, 1875); Egli, <hi rend="italic">Taschenbuch Schweizerischen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">statistics</hi> (Zurich, 1875); Herbst, <hi rend="italic">Der
                        Genfer See und seine Umgebung</hi> (Weimar, 1877).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
